<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>Mar. Drugs 2009, 7, 355-360; doi:10.3390/md7030355 <lb/>Marine Drugs <lb/>ISSN 1660-3397 <lb/>www.mdpi.com/journal/marinedrugs <lb/>Article <lb/>Brominated Selinane Sesquiterpenes from the Marine Brown <lb/>Alga Dictyopteris divaricata <lb/>Nai-Yun Ji 1, *, Wei Wen 1 , Xiao-Ming Li 2 , Qin-Zhao Xue 1 , Hua-Ling Xiao 3 and <lb/>Bin-Gui Wang 2, * <lb/>1 Yantai Institute of Coastal Zone Research for Sustainable Development, Chinese Academy of <lb/>Sciences, Yantai 264003, China; E-Mails: wenwei_500@sina.com (W.W.); <lb/>qzxue@yic.ac.cn (Q-Z.X.) <lb/>2 Institute of Oceanology, Chinese Academy of Sciences, Qingdao 266071, China; <lb/>E-Mail: lixmqd@yahoo.com.cn (X-M.L.) <lb/>3 Ocean University of China, Qingdao 266003, China; E-Mail: backofangel@hotmail.com <lb/>* Authors to whom correspondence should be addressed; E-Mails: nyji@yic.ac.cn (N-Y.J.); <lb/>wangbg@ms.qdio.ac.cn (B-G.W.) <lb/>Received: 29 June 2009; in revised form: 13 July 2009 / Accepted: 21 July 2009 / <lb/>Published: 22 July 2009 <lb/>Abstract: Two new brominated selinane sesquiterpenes, 1-bromoselin-4(14),11-diene (1) <lb/>and 9-bromoselin-4(14),11-diene (2), one known cadinane sesquiterpene, cadalene (3), and <lb/>four known selinane sesquiterpenes, α-selinene (4), β-selinene (5), β-dictyopterol (6), and <lb/>cyperusol C (7), were isolated from a sample of marine brown alga Dictyopteris divaricata <lb/>collected off the coast of Yantai (China). Their structures were established by detailed MS <lb/>and NMR spectroscopic analysis, as well as comparison with literature data. <lb/>Keywords: Dictyopteris divaricata; sesquiterpene; selinane <lb/></front>

			<body>1. Introduction <lb/>The marine brown alga Dictyopteris divaricata, found widely spread along the coasts of China, has <lb/>provided many structurally interesting sesquiterpenes and norsesquiterpenes [1-4]. However, to date <lb/>there have been no reports of halogenated structures isolated from this species. Our continuing <lb/> </body>
			
			<note place="headnote">OPEN ACCESS <lb/>Mar. Drugs 2009, 7 <lb/></note>

			<page>356 <lb/></page>

			<body>investigation of the secondary metabolites of D. divaricata collected off the coast of Yantai has <lb/>revealed two new brominated sesquiterpenes, 1-bromoselin-4(14),11-diene (1) and <lb/>9-bromoselin-4(14),11-diene (2), one known cadinane sesquiterpene, cadalene (3) [5], and four known <lb/>selinane sesquiterpenes, α-selinene (4) [6], β-selinene (5) [6], β-dictyopterol (6) [7], and <lb/>cyperusol C (7) [8]. The isolation and structural determination of compounds 1-7 are the subject of <lb/>this paper. <lb/>2. Results and Discussion <lb/>The dried and powdered alga D. divaricata was extracted with the mixture of CHCl 3 and MeOH <lb/>(1:1, v/v). The concentrated extracts were partitioned between H 2 O and EtOAc. The EtOAc-soluble <lb/>fraction was purified by a combination of silica gel, reversed-phase silica gel, and Sephadex LH-20 <lb/>column chromatography, as well as preparative TLC procedure, to yield compounds 1-7 (Figure 1). <lb/>Figure 1. Structures of compounds 1-7. <lb/>H <lb/>H <lb/>Br <lb/>Br <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>3 <lb/>15 <lb/>14 <lb/>13 <lb/>12 <lb/>11 <lb/>10 <lb/>9 <lb/>7 <lb/>5 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>15 <lb/>14 <lb/>13 <lb/>12 <lb/>11 <lb/>10 <lb/>9 <lb/>7 <lb/>5 <lb/>3 <lb/>H <lb/>H <lb/>H <lb/>OH <lb/>HO <lb/>H <lb/>OH <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>6 <lb/>7 <lb/>Compounds 1-3 were obtained as a colorless oily mixture. They displayed one spot by TLC <lb/>analysis (Rf 0.65, petroleum ether), and all attempts to separate them failed due to their low polarity. <lb/>The IR spectrum showed absorptions of vinyl and phenyl groups at v max 1643, 1604, 1512, and <lb/>1450 cm -1 and no absorption of hydroxyl groups. The GC-EIMS gave three peaks with molecular ion <lb/>peaks at m/z 198, 282/284 (1:1) and 282/284 (1:1) [M] + , which indicated that the mixture was <lb/>composed of three compounds. The 1 H-and 13 C-NMR data of these three compounds 1-3 could be <lb/>distinguished with the aid of the NMR data shown in Table 1. <lb/>The compound with the molecular ion peak at m/z 198 was tentatively identified as cadalene (3) by <lb/>comparison with the EIMS database [5]. Fortunately, the 1 H and 13 C-NMR peaks of 3 could be found <lb/>in NMR spectra (Table 1). H-2 was ortho to H-3 and H-8 was ortho to H-9 according to their large <lb/>coupling constants (J &gt; 7 Hz). The coupling constant 1.7 Hz between H-6 and H-8 indicated H-6 was <lb/>meta to H-8. The above connections were corroborated by the 1 H-1 H COSY correlations between <lb/>H-2/H-3, H-6/H-8, H-8/H-9. The presence of 3 was further confirmed by the observed HMBC <lb/>correlations from H-11 to C-3, C-4, C-12, and C-13, from H-12 to C-4, C-11, and C-13, from H-13 to <lb/>C-4, C-11, and C-12, from H-14 to C-1, C-2, and C-10, and from H-15 to C-6, C-7, and C-8. It is <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Mar. Drugs 2009, 7 <lb/></note>

			<page>357 <lb/></page>

			<body>obvious then that the molecular ion clusters at m/z 282/284 (1:1) [M] + correspond to the other two <lb/>compounds 1-2, whose molecular formulae were determined as C 15 H 23 Br on the basis of HRESIMS <lb/>(m/z 203.1784 [M-Br] + , calcd. for C 15 H 23 Br, 203.1799). <lb/>The 1 H-NMR spectrum of 1 displayed two methyl singlets, one double-doublet assignable to a <lb/>halogenated/oxygenated methine, and four broad characteristic olefinic protons singlets. The 13 C-NMR <lb/>spectrum along with the DEPT and HSQC experiments revealed the presence of two methyls, seven <lb/>methylenes, three methines, and three quaternary carbon atoms. A detailed comparison of the NMR <lb/>data with those reported for β-selinene (5) and β-dictyopterol (6) revealed the similarity between <lb/>them [6,7], although n contrast to β-selinene (5) and β-dictyopterol (6), C-1 in 1 was brominated [δ C <lb/>67.9 (d)], as established by comparison with the reported data for 1-bromo-4-hydroxyselin-7-ene [9]; <lb/>this was corroborated by the molecular ion cluster at m/z 282/284 (1:1) [M] + and fragment ion peak at <lb/>m/z 203 [M-Br] + in the EIMS and the molecular formula C 15 H 23 Br. The observed HMBC correlations <lb/>from H-12 to C-7 and C-13, from H-13 to C-7, C-11, and C-12, from H-14a and H-14b to C-3 and C-5, <lb/>and from H-15 to C-1, C-5, C-9, and C-10 confirmed the planar structure of 1. <lb/>Table 1. 1 H and 13 C-NMR data of compounds 1-3 (in CDCl 3 , δ in ppm, J in Hz). <lb/>No. <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>δ C <lb/>δ H <lb/>δ C <lb/>δ H <lb/>δ C <lb/>δ H <lb/>1a <lb/>67.9 d <lb/>4.09 (dd, 11.8, 4.4) <lb/>42.8 t <lb/>1.14 (m) <lb/>131.8 s <lb/>1b <lb/>1.91 (m) <lb/>2a <lb/>35.0 t <lb/>2.15 (m) <lb/>27.1 t <lb/>1.43 (m) <lb/>125.6 d <lb/>7.22 (d, 7.2) <lb/>2b <lb/>2.21 (m) <lb/>1.61 (m) <lb/>3a <lb/>37.2 t <lb/>2.15 (m) <lb/>39.1 t <lb/>2.17 (m) <lb/>121.4 d <lb/>7.28 (d, 7.2) <lb/>3b <lb/>2.32 (m) <lb/>2.17 (m) <lb/>4 <lb/>147.5 s <lb/>147.8 s <lb/>142.1 s <lb/>5 <lb/>49.7 d <lb/>1.91 (m) <lb/>49.1 d <lb/>1.99 (m) <lb/>131.6 s <lb/>6a <lb/>30.1 t <lb/>1.41 (m) <lb/>30.7 t <lb/>1.35 (m) <lb/>122.9 d <lb/>7.92 (d, 1.7) <lb/>6b <lb/>1.63 (m) <lb/>1.62 (m) <lb/>7 <lb/>45.4 d <lb/>1.95 (m) <lb/>45.7 d <lb/>1.95 (m) <lb/>134.7 s <lb/>8a <lb/>26.8 t <lb/>1.40 (m) <lb/>37.7 t <lb/>2.39 (m) <lb/>127.2 d <lb/>7.35 (dd, 8.5, 1.7) <lb/>8b <lb/>1.66 (m) <lb/>2.39 (m) <lb/>9a <lb/>39.8 t <lb/>1.18 (m) <lb/>52.2 d <lb/>4.30 (dd, 12.0, 4.0) <lb/>124.8 d <lb/>7.92 (d, 8.5) <lb/>9b <lb/>2.04 (m) <lb/>10 <lb/>41.2 s <lb/>41.0 s <lb/>131.2 s <lb/>11 <lb/>150.0 s <lb/>149.9 s <lb/>28.3 d <lb/>3.72 (h, 7.0) <lb/>12a <lb/>108.6 t <lb/>4.73 (br s) <lb/>108.6 t <lb/>4.73 (br s) <lb/>23.6 q <lb/>1.27 (d, 7.0) <lb/>12b <lb/>4.73 (br s) <lb/>4.73 (br s) <lb/>13 <lb/>21.0 q <lb/>1.75 (s) <lb/>21.0 q <lb/>1.75 (s) <lb/>23.6 q <lb/>1.27 (d, 7.0) <lb/>14a <lb/>107.7 t <lb/>4.55 (br s) <lb/>107.6 t <lb/>4.56 (br s) <lb/>19.4 q <lb/>2.65 (s) <lb/>14b <lb/>4.78 (br s) <lb/>4.73 (br s) <lb/>15 <lb/>12.0 q <lb/>0.85 (s) <lb/>14.1 q <lb/>0.86 (s) <lb/>22.0 q <lb/>2.56 (s) <lb/>The relative configuration of 1 was determined by analysis of coupling constants and NOESY <lb/>correlations, as well as by comparison with literature data. H-1 was axial, as indicated by its large <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Mar. Drugs 2009, 7 <lb/></note>

			<page>358 <lb/></page>

			<body>coupling constant (11.8 Hz), and located on the same face of H-5 from the NOESY correlation <lb/>between them. The NOESY correlations between H-15/H-2a, H-6a, H-8a indicated C-15, H-2a, H-6a, <lb/>and H-8a to be axial and the decalin ring to be trans-fused. C-11 was equatorial and the configuration <lb/>at C-7 was the same as in 4-7 based on their identical NMR data and the observed NOESY correlation <lb/>between H-7/H-9a [6-8]. The above evidence established the structure of 1 as <lb/>1-bromoselin-4(14),11-diene. Compound 1 has also been isolated in pure form from Laurencia pinnata, <lb/>collected off the coast of Nanji Island (China), and its structure was confirmed unambiguously by <lb/>1D/2D NMR and HRAPPIMS (high-resolution atmospheric pressure photoionization mass <lb/>spectroscopy), and this data was used to deconvolute the spectra of the 1-3 mixture [10]. <lb/>The 1 H-NMR spectrum of 2 also displayed two methyl singlets, one double-doublet attributed to a <lb/>halogenated/oxygenated methine, and four broad singlets ascribable to olefinic protons. The 13 C-NMR <lb/>spectrum, along with the DEPT and HSQC experiments, revealed the presence of two methyls, seven <lb/>methylenes, three methines, and three quaternary carbon atoms. Based on their identical molecular ion <lb/>clusters at m/z 282/284 (1:1) [M] + and fragment ion peaks at m/z 203 [M-Br] + in the EIMS and the <lb/>molecular formulae C 15 H 23 Br, compound 2 should be an isomer of 1, a fact conformed by analysis of <lb/>their NMR data. The NMR data were also compared with those reported for β-selinene (5), showing <lb/>the similarity between them [6]. In contrast to β-selinene (5), C-9 at δ C 52.2 (d) was brominated in 2, <lb/>as indicated by the HMBC correlation from H-15 to C-9. The other HMBC correlations from H-12 to <lb/>C-7 and C-13, from H-13 to C-7, C-11, and C-12, from H-14a and H-14b to C-3 and C-5, and from <lb/>H-15 to C-1, C-5, and C-10 confirmed the structure of 2. The relative configuration of 2 was <lb/>determined by analysis of coupling constants and NOESY correlations, as well as by comparison with <lb/>literature data. H-9 was axial, as suggested by its large coupling constant (12.0 Hz), and, based on the <lb/>NOESY correlation between them, located on the same face as H-5. The decalin ring was trans-fused <lb/>based on the identical chemical shifts of C-5 and C-10 in 2 and 1. The C-11 was equatorial and the <lb/>configuration at C-7 was identical with those of 1, 4-7 according to their similar NMR data [6-8]. The <lb/>above evidence established the structure of 2 to be 9-bromoselin-4(14),11-diene. <lb/>The structures of known compounds 4-7 were confirmed by detailed NMR data comparison with <lb/>those in the literature [6-8]. To the best of our knowledge, compounds 1 and 2 represent the first <lb/>example of halogenated terpenes from the genus Dictyopteris, and are new additions to the molecular <lb/>diversity of this genus. Compounds 1 and 2 may act as effective chemical defenses against marine <lb/>herbivores by comparison with similar brominated structures [11]. <lb/>3. Experimental Section <lb/>3.1. General <lb/>NMR spectra were recorded in CDCl 3 at 500 and 125 MHz for 1 H and 13 C, respectively, on a <lb/>Bruker Avance 500 MHz NMR spectrometer with TMS as internal standard. GC-EIMS spectra were <lb/>determined on a Thermo Scientific ITQ 900 spectrometer. High resolution mass spectra were <lb/>measured on a VG Autospec 3000 mass spectrometer. IR spectra were obtained on a JASCO <lb/>FT/IR-4100 Fourier Transform Infrared spectrometer. Column chromatography was performed with <lb/>silica gel (200-300 mesh, Qingdao Haiyang Chemical Co., Qingdao, P.R. China), RP-18 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Mar. Drugs 2009, 7 <lb/></note>

			<page>359 <lb/></page>

			<body>reversed-phase silica gel (ODS-A, YMC), and Sephadex LH-20 (Pharmacia). TLC was carried out <lb/>with precoated silica gel plates (GF-254, Qingdao Haiyang Chemical Co., Qingdao, P.R. China). All <lb/>solvents were of analytical grade. <lb/>3.2. Algal Material <lb/>The brown alga Dictyopteris divaricata was collected off the coast of Yantai (lat. 37°31&apos;15&quot;N, long. <lb/>121°26&apos;59&quot;E), Shandong Province, P. R. China, in July 2008, and a voucher specimen (MBA0807) <lb/>has been deposited at the Bio-Resource Laboratory of Yantai Institute of Coastal Zone Research for <lb/>Sustainable Development, Chinese Academy of Sciences. <lb/>3.3. Extraction and Isolation <lb/>Dried and powdered alga D. divaricata (2 kg) was extracted with a 1:1 (v/v) mixture of CHCl 3 and <lb/>MeOH. The concentrated extract was partitioned between H 2 O and EtOAc. The EtOAc-soluble <lb/>fraction (90 g) was fractioned by silica gel column chromatography [petroleum ether (PE)/EtOAc <lb/>gradient] to give ten fractions, I-X. Fraction I, eluted with PE, was further purified by silica gel column <lb/>chromatography (PE) to afford a mixture of 1-3 (10.0 mg) and a mixture of 4 and 5 (40.9 mg). <lb/>Fraction VII, eluted with PE/EtOAc (2:1), was further purified by Sephadex LH-20 (CHCl 3 /CH 3 OH) <lb/>and RP-18 (CH 3 OH/H 2 O 3:1) column chromatography and preparative TLC (PE/EtOAc 3:1) to afford <lb/>6 (5.1 mg). Fraction IX, eluted with EtOAc, was further purified by Sephadex LH-20 (CHCl 3 /CH 3 OH) <lb/>and RP-18 (CH 3 OH/H 2 O 9:1) column chromatography and preparative TLC (EtOAc) to afford 7 <lb/>(5.5 mg). <lb/>1-Bromoselin-4(14),11-diene (1). Colorless oil; 1 H-NMR and 13 C-NMR: see Table 1; EIMS m/z <lb/>(relative intensity): 284/282 [M] + (3), 203 [M-Br] + (98), 161 (26), 159 (28), 147 (88), 133 (36), <lb/>119 (52), 105 (89), 91 (100), 79 (54), 77 (46), 67 (37) <lb/>9-Bromoselin-4(14),11-diene (2). Colorless oil; 1 H-NMR and 13 C-NMR: see Table 1; EIMS m/z <lb/>(relative intensity): 284/282 [M] + (2), 203 [M-Br] + (59), 161 (26), 159 (11), 147 (61), 133 (28), <lb/>119 (44), 105 (78), 91 (100), 79 (56), 77 (52), 67 (46). <lb/>Cadalene (3). Colorless oil; 1 H-NMR and 13 C-NMR: see Table 1; EIMS m/z (relative intensity): <lb/>198 (59), 183 (100), 168 (48), 153 (16). <lb/>IR (KBr) of 1-3: 3,074, 2,931, 2866, 1,643, 1,604, 1,512, 1,450, 1,377, 887 and 829 cm -1 . <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgements <lb/>This work was financially supported by the Foundation of the National Natural Science Foundation <lb/>of China (30530080), National High-Tech R &amp; D Project (2007AA09Z403), a Chinese Academy of <lb/>Sciences President&apos;s Scholarship (awarded to N-Y. J.), Open Foundation of Shandong Oriental Ocean <lb/></div>

			<note place="headnote">Mar. Drugs 2009, 7 <lb/></note>

			<page>360 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>Sci-Tech Co., Ltd, Chinese Academy of Sciences for Key Topics in Innovation Engineering <lb/>(kcx2-yw-225), and Key Technology Research and Development Program of Shandong Province <lb/>(2007GG2QT06020). <lb/>References and Notes <lb/>1. Song, F.; Fan, X.; Xu, X.; Zhao, J.; Yang, Y.; Shi, J. Cadinane sesquiterpenes from the brown <lb/>alga Dictyopteris divaricata. J. Nat. Prod. 2004, 67, 1644-1649. <lb/>2. Song, F.; Xu, X.; Li, S.; Wang, S.; Zhao, J.; Cao, P.; Yang, Y.; Fan, X.; Shi, J.; He, L.; Lü, Y. <lb/>Norsesquiterpenes from the brown alga Dictyopteris divaricata. J. Nat. Prod. 2005, 68, <lb/>1309-1313. <lb/>3. Song, F.; Xu, X.; Li, S.; Wang, S.; Zhao, J.; Yang, Y.; Fan, X.; Shi, J.; He, L. Minor <lb/>sesquiterpenes with new carbon skeleton from the brown alga Dictyopteris divaricata. J. Nat. <lb/>Prod. 2006, 69, 1261-1266. <lb/>4. Wen, W.; Li, F.; Ji, N.Y.; Li, X.M.; Cui, C.M.; Li, X.D.; Zhang, L.N.; Xue, Q.Z.; Wang, B.G. A <lb/>new cadinane sesquiterpene from the marine brown alga Dictyopteris divaricata. Molecules 2009, <lb/>14, 2273-2277. <lb/>5. Takahashi, K.; Takani, M. Studies on constituents of medical plants. XVII. Constituents of <lb/>Schizandra nigra Max. and their carbon-13 nuclear magnetic resonance spectra. Chem. Pharm. <lb/>Bull. 1976, 24, 2000-2006. <lb/>6. Williams, H.J.; Sattler, I.; Moyna, G.; Scott, A.I.; Bell, A.A.; Vinson, S.B. Diversity in cyclic <lb/>sesquiterpene production by Gossypium hirsutum. Phytochemistry 1995, 40, 1633-1636. <lb/>7. Hu, L.; Chen, Z. Sesquiterpenoid alcohols from Chrysanthemum morifolium. Phytochemistry <lb/>1997, 44, 1287-1290. <lb/>8. Xu, F.; Morikawa, T.; Matsuda, H.; Ninomiya, K.; Yoshikawa, M. Structures of new <lb/>sesquiterpenes and hepatoprotective constituents from the Egyptian herbal medicine Cyperus <lb/>longus. J. Nat. Prod. 2004, 67, 569-576. <lb/>9. Howard, B.M.; Fenical, W. Structure, chemistry, and absolute configuration of <lb/>1(S)-bromo-4(R)-hydroxy-(-)-selin-7-ene from a marine red alga Laurencia sp. J. Org. Chem. <lb/>1977, 42, 2518-2520. <lb/>10. Ji, N.Y.; Li, X.M.; Wang, B.G. Unpublished data. <lb/>11. Paul, V.J.; Cronan Jr., J.M. Cardellina II, J.H. Isolation of new brominated sesquiterpene feeding <lb/>deterrents from tropical green alga Neomeris annulata (Dasycladaceae: Chlorophyta). J. Chem. <lb/>Ecol. 1993, 19, 1847-1860. <lb/></listBibl>

			<front>Sample Availability: Samples of compounds 1-7 are available from the authors. <lb/>© 2009 by the authors; licensee Molecular Diversity Preservation International, Basel, Switzerland. <lb/>This article is an open-access article distributed under the terms and conditions of the Creative <lb/>Commons Attribution license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/). </front>


	</text>
</tei>