<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>Anti-Tumor Effects of Novel 5-O-Acyl Plumbagins Based <lb/>on the Inhibition of Mammalian DNA Replicative <lb/>Polymerase Activity <lb/>Moe Kawamura 1 , Isoko Kuriyama 2 , Sayako Maruo 1 , Kouji Kuramochi 1 *, Kazunori Tsubaki 1 , <lb/>Hiromi Yoshida 2 , Yoshiyuki Mizushina 2,3 * <lb/>1 Graduate School of Life and Environmental Sciences, Kyoto Prefectural University, Kyoto, Kyoto, Japan, 2 Laboratory of Food &amp; Nutritional Sciences, Faculty of Nutrition, <lb/>Kobe Gakuin University, Kobe, Hyogo, Japan, 3 Cooperative Research Center of Life Sciences, Kobe Gakuin University, Kobe, Hyogo, Japan <lb/>Abstract <lb/>We previously found that vitamin K 3 (menadione, 2-methyl-1,4-naphthoquinone) inhibits the activity of human <lb/>mitochondrial DNA polymerase c (pol c). In this study, we focused on plumbagin (5-hydroxy-2-methyl-1,4-naphthoquinone), <lb/>and chemically synthesized novel plumbagins conjugated with C2:0 to C22:6 fatty acids (5-O-acyl plumbagins). These <lb/>chemically modified plumbagins enhanced mammalian pol inhibition and their cytotoxic activity. Plumbagin conjugated <lb/>with chains consisting of more than C18-unsaturated fatty acids strongly inhibited the activities of calf pol a and human pol <lb/>c. Plumbagin conjugated with oleic acid (C18:1-acyl plumbagin) showed the strongest suppression of human colon <lb/>carcinoma (HCT116) cell proliferation among the ten synthesized 5-O-acyl plumbagins. The inhibitory activity on pol a, a <lb/>DNA replicative pol, by these compounds showed high correlation with their cancer cell proliferation suppressive activity. <lb/>C18:1-Acyl plumbagin selectively inhibited the activities of mammalian pol species, but did not influence the activities of <lb/>other pols and DNA metabolic enzymes tested. This compound inhibited the proliferation of various human cancer cell <lb/>lines, and was the cytotoxic inhibitor showing strongest inhibition towards HT-29 colon cancer cells (LD 50 = 2.9 mM) among <lb/>the nine cell lines tested. In an in vivo anti-tumor assay conducted on nude mice bearing solid tumors of HT-29 cells, C18:1-<lb/>acyl plumbagin was shown to be a promising tumor suppressor. These data indicate that novel 5-O-acyl plumbagins act as <lb/>anti-cancer agents based on mammalian DNA replicative pol a inhibition. Moreover, the results suggest that acylation of <lb/>plumbagin is an effective chemical modification to improve the anti-cancer activity of vitamin K 3 derivatives, such as <lb/>plumbagin. <lb/>Citation: Kawamura M, Kuriyama I, Maruo S, Kuramochi K, Tsubaki K, et al. (2014) Anti-Tumor Effects of Novel 5-O-Acyl Plumbagins Based on the Inhibition of <lb/>Mammalian DNA Replicative Polymerase Activity. PLoS ONE 9(2): e88736. doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0088736 <lb/>Editor: Hitoshi Ashida, Kobe University, Japan <lb/>Received November 1, 2013; Accepted January 10, 2014; Published February 10, 2014 <lb/>Copyright: ß 2014 Kawamura et al. This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits <lb/>unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited. <lb/>Funding: This study was supported in part by the MEXT (Ministry of Education, Culture, Sports, Science and Technology, Japan)-Supported Program for the <lb/>Strategic Research Foundation at Private Universities, 2012-2016. Y.M. acknowledges Grant-in-Aids for Scientific Research (C) (No. 24580205) from MEXT, and the <lb/>Hyogo Science and Technology Association (Japan). I.K. acknowledges a Grant-in-Aid for Young Scientists (B) (No. 23710262) from MEXT. K.K and Y.M. <lb/>acknowledge a Grant-in-Aid for A-STEP (Adaptable and Seamless Technology Transfer Program through target-driven R&amp;D) (Exploratory Research) from JST (Japan <lb/>Science and Technology Agency). The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript. <lb/>Competing Interests: The authors declare that there are no conflicts of interest. <lb/>* E-mail: kuramoch@kpu.ac.jp (KK); mizushin@nutr.kobegakuin.ac.jp (YM) <lb/></front>

			<body>Introduction <lb/>Cancer is a major global public health problem. Epidemiolog-<lb/>ical and animal studies have indicated that chemopreventive <lb/>natural products are associated with a reduced risk of cancer <lb/>development [1,2]. Furthermore, selective inhibitors of DNA <lb/>polymerases (pols) are considered potentially useful anti-cancer, <lb/>anti-viral, anti-parasitic, and anti-pregnancy agents because some <lb/>are known to suppress human cancer and normal cell prolifera-<lb/>tion, and are cytotoxic [3,4]. <lb/>Pol (DNA-dependent DNA polymerase, E.C. 2.7.7.7) catalyzes <lb/>deoxyribonucleotide addition to the 39-hydroxyl terminus of <lb/>primed double-stranded DNA (dsDNA) molecules [5]. The human <lb/>genome encodes at least 15 DNA pols, which function in cellular <lb/>DNA synthesis [6,7]. Eukaryotic cells contain three replicative pols <lb/>(a, d, and e), one mitochondrial pol (c), and at least 11 non-<lb/>replicative pols [b, f, g, h, i, k, l, m, n, terminal deoxynucleotidyl <lb/>transferase (TdT), and REV1] [8,9]. Pols have a highly conserved <lb/>structure, with their overall catalytic subunits showing little <lb/>variation among species; conserved enzyme structures are usually <lb/>preserved over time as they perform important cellular functions <lb/>that confer evolutionary advantages. Based on sequence homol-<lb/>ogy, eukaryotic pols can be divided into four main families, termed <lb/>A, B, X, and Y [8]. Family A includes mitochondrial pol c as well <lb/>as pols h and n; family B includes the three replicative pols a, d, <lb/>and e and also pol f; family X comprises pols b, l, and m as well as <lb/>TdT; and family Y includes pols g, i, and k in addition to REV1 <lb/>[9]. We have studied selective inhibitors of each pol derived from <lb/>natural products including food materials and nutrients for more <lb/>than 18 years [10,11]. We have found that vitamin K 3 , but not K 1 <lb/>or K 2 , is a potent inhibitor of human pol c [12,13]. <lb/>Vitamin K 3 (menadione, 2-methyl-1,4-naphthoquinone, 3 of <lb/>Fig. 1) is a fat-soluble compound that contains quinone as its <lb/>principal chemical feature. Quinones are a class of organic <lb/>compounds that are derived from aromatic compounds via the <lb/>exchange of an even number of -CH = groups for -C( = O)-<lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | www.plosone.org <lb/></note>

			<page>1 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">February 2014 | Volume 9 | Issue 2 | e88736 <lb/></note>

			<body>groups and any necessary rearrangement of double bonds, <lb/>resulting in a fully conjugated cyclic dione structure. The <lb/>toxicological properties of quinones, which act as alkylating <lb/>agents, have also been examined. For example, quinones are <lb/>known to interact with flavoproteins to generate reactive oxygen <lb/>species (ROS) that can induce biological injury [14-17]. In this <lb/>study, we focused on 5-hydroxy-2-methyl-1,4-naphthoquinone <lb/>(plumbagin, 1 of Fig. 1), which has the common naphthoquinone <lb/>skeleton and a hydroxyl group and a methyl group at the C-5 and <lb/>C-2 positions, respectively. Plumbagin (1) is found in the plants of <lb/>the Plumbaginaceae, Droseraceae, Ancestrocladaceae, and Dion-<lb/>cophyllaceae families. The chief source of plumbagin (1) is the root <lb/>of Plumbago zeylanica L. (also known as &apos;&apos;Chitrak&apos;&apos;). Plumbagin (1) <lb/>has been shown to exert anti-carcinogenic, anti-atherosclerotic, <lb/>and anti-microbial effects [18-21]. The root of P. zeylanica L. has <lb/>been used in Indian medicine for approximately 2,750 years and <lb/>its components possess anti-atherogenic, cardiotonic, hepatopro-<lb/>tective, and neuroprotective properties [19]. Plumbagin (1) has <lb/>potent anti-proliferative and apoptotic activities in various types of <lb/>human cancers, and its mechanism of cytotoxicity is by inhibition <lb/>of a PI-5 kinase for ROS generation [22]. <lb/>We previously found that a vitamin K 3 (3) derivative, juglone (5-<lb/>hydroxy-1,4-naphthoquinone, 4 of Fig. 1), conjugated with fatty <lb/>acids such as 5-O-acyl juglones (5a-j of Fig. 1) were stronger pol <lb/>inhibitors than juglone alone (4) [23], therefore, ten 5-O-acylated <lb/>derivatives of plumbagin (2a-j of Fig. 1) were chemically <lb/>synthesized from plumbagin (1) and fatty acids to compare with <lb/>5-O-acyl juglones (5a-j). In this study, we first investigated the <lb/>stability of 5-O-acyl plumbagins (2) and 5-O-acyl juglones (5). We <lb/>also assayed the inhibitory effects of ten 5-O-acyl plumbagins (2a-<lb/>j) on mammalian pol activity, cytotoxicity in human cancer cell <lb/>lines and in vivo anti-tumor activity compared with plumbagin (1) <lb/>and 5-O-acyl juglones (5). The relationship between the pol <lb/>inhibitory and anti-tumor effects of vitamin K 3 -based acylated <lb/>derivatives is discussed. <lb/>Materials and Methods <lb/>Materials <lb/>A chemically synthesized DNA template, poly(dA), was <lb/>purchased from Sigma-Aldrich Inc. and a customized oligo(dT) 18 <lb/>DNA primer was produced by Sigma-Aldrich Japan K.K. <lb/>(Hokkaido, Japan). Radioactive nucleotide [ 3 H]-labeled 29-deox-<lb/>ythymidine-59-triphosphate (dTTP; 43 Ci/mmol) was obtained <lb/>from Moravek Biochemicals Inc. (Brea, CA, USA). All other <lb/>reagents were of analytical grade from Nacalai Tesque Inc. <lb/>(Kyoto, Japan). <lb/>Enzymes <lb/>Pol a was purified from calf thymus by immunoaffinity column <lb/>chromatography as described by Tamai et al. [24]. Recombinant <lb/>rat pol b was purified from Escherichia coli JMpb5 as described by <lb/>Date et al. [25]. The human pol c catalytic gene was cloned into <lb/>pFastBac. Histidine-tagged enzyme was expressed using the <lb/>BACTO-BAC HT Baculovirus Expression System according to <lb/>the manufacturer&apos;s instructions (Life Technologies, Frederick, <lb/>MD, USA) and purified using ProBound resin (Invitrogen Japan, <lb/>Tokyo Japan) [26]. Human pols d and e were purified by nuclear <lb/>fractionation of human peripheral blood cancer cells (Molt-4) <lb/>using the second subunit of pol d and e-conjugated affinity column <lb/>chromatography, respectively [27]. A truncated form of human <lb/>pol g (residues 1-511) tagged with His 6 at its C-terminal was <lb/>expressed in E. coli cells and purified as described by Kusumoto et <lb/>al. [28]. A recombinant mouse pol i tagged with His 6 at its C-<lb/>terminal was expressed and purified by Ni-NTA column <lb/>chromatography [29]. A truncated form of pol k (residues 1-<lb/>560) with 66 His-tags attached at the C-terminus was overex-<lb/>pressed in E. coli and purified as described by Ohashi et al. [30]. <lb/>Recombinant human His-pol l was overexpressed and purified <lb/>according to a method described by Shimazaki et al. [31]. <lb/>Recombinant human His-pol m was overexpressed in E. coli BL21 <lb/>and purified using Glutathione Sepharose 4B (GE Healthcare Bio-<lb/>Science Corp., Piscataway, NJ, USA) column chromatography <lb/>according to the method for pol l preparation by Shimazaki et al. <lb/>[31]. Pol a from a higher plant, cauliflower, was purified from the <lb/>inflorescence structure according to the methods outlined by <lb/>Sakaguchi et al. [32]. Recombinant rice (Oryza sativa L. cv. <lb/>Nipponbare) pol l tagged with His 6 at the C-terminus was <lb/>expressed in E. coli and purified as described by Uchiyama et al. <lb/>[33]. Calf TdT, Taq pol, T4 pol, T7 RNA polymerase, and T4 <lb/>polynucleotide kinase were purchased from Takara Bio Inc. <lb/>(Kyoto, Japan). The Klenow fragment of pol I from E. coli was <lb/>purchased from Worthington Biochemical Corp. (Freehold, NJ, <lb/>USA). Bovine pancreas deoxyribonuclease I was obtained from <lb/>Stratagene Cloning Systems (La Jolla, CA, USA). <lb/>Measurement of pol activity <lb/>The reaction mixtures for calf pol a, rat pol b, plant pol a, and <lb/>prokaryotic pols have been described previously [34,35]; those for <lb/>pol c as well as pols d and e were previously described by Umeda <lb/>et al. [26] and Ogawa et al. [36], respectively. Those for pols g, i, <lb/>and k were the same as for pol a, and those for pols l and m were <lb/>the same as for pol b. For the pol reactions, poly(dA)/oligo(dT) 18 <lb/>(A/T, 2/1) and dTTP were used as the DNA template-primer <lb/>substrate and nucleotide (dNTP; 29-deoxynucleoside-59-triphos-<lb/>phate) substrate, respectively. For the TdT reactions, oligo(dT) 18 <lb/>Figure 1. Structure of plumbagin (1), 5-O-acyl plumbagins (2), <lb/>vitamin K 3 (3), juglone (4), and 5-O-acyl juglones (5). &apos;&apos;R&apos;&apos; <lb/>represents a saturated or unsaturated alkyl group in 5-O-acyl <lb/>plumbagins (2) and 5-O-acyl juglones (5). <lb/>doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0088736.g001 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Anti-Tumor Activity by C18:1-Acyl Plumbagin <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | www.plosone.org <lb/></note>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">February 2014 | Volume 9 | Issue 2 | e88736 <lb/></note>

			<body>(39-OH) and dTTP were used as the DNA primer substrate and <lb/>nucleotide substrate, respectively. <lb/>The chemically synthesized 5-O-acyl plumbagins (2a-j) were <lb/>dissolved in distilled dimethyl sulfoxide (DMSO) to various <lb/>concentrations and sonicated for 30 s. Subsequently, 4 mL aliquots <lb/>were mixed with 16 mL of each enzyme (0.05 units) in 50 mM <lb/>Tris-HCl at pH 7.5, containing 1 mM dithiothreitol, 50% glycerol <lb/>(by vol), and 0.1 mM ethylenediaminetetraacetic acid and held at <lb/>0uC for 10 min. These inhibitor-enzyme mixtures in 8 mL volumes <lb/>were next added to 16 mL of enzyme standard reaction mixture <lb/>and incubated at 37uC for 60 min, except for Taq pol, which was <lb/>incubated at 74uC for 60 min. Activity without inhibitor was <lb/>considered 100%, and the relative activity was determined for <lb/>each inhibitor concentration. One unit of pol activity was defined <lb/>as the amount of each enzyme that catalyzed the incorporation of <lb/>1 nmol dTTP into synthetic DNA template primers in 60 min, at <lb/>37uC, and under standard reaction conditions [34,35]. <lb/>Other enzyme assays <lb/>The activities of calf primase of pol a, T7 RNA polymerase, <lb/>mouse inosine-59-triphosphate (IMP) dehydrogenase (type II), T4 <lb/>polynucleotide kinase, and bovine deoxyribonuclease I were <lb/>measured in standard assays according to the manufacturer&apos;s <lb/>specifications, as described by Tamiya-Koizumi et al. [37], <lb/>Nakayama and Saneyoshi [38], Mizushina et al. [39], Soltis et <lb/>al. [40], and Lu and Sakaguchi [41], respectively. <lb/>Thermal transition of DNA <lb/>Thermal transition profiles of dsDNA to single-stranded DNA <lb/>with or without test compound were obtained with a spectropho-<lb/>tometer (UV-2500; Shimadzu Corp., Kyoto, Japan) equipped with <lb/>a thermoelectric cell holder according to previous methods [42]. <lb/>Calf thymus DNA (6 mg/mL) was dissolved in 0.1 M sodium <lb/>phosphate buffer (pH 7.0) containing 1% DMSO. The solution <lb/>temperature was equilibrated to 75uC for 10 min, and then <lb/>increased by 1uC at 2-min intervals for each measurement point. <lb/>Any change in the absorbance (260 nm) of the compound itself at <lb/>each temperature point was automatically subtracted from that of <lb/>DNA plus the compound in the spectrophotometer. <lb/>Cell culture and measurement of cancer cell viability <lb/>The following human cancer cell lines were obtained from the <lb/>American Type Culture Collection (Manassas, VA, USA): lung <lb/>(A549), prostate (DU145 and PC3), colon (HCT116 and HT-29), <lb/>cervix (HeLa), hepatocellular liver (HepG2), breast (MCF-7), and <lb/>pancreatic cancer (PANC-1). These cells were cultured in RPMI <lb/>1640 medium supplemented with 10% fetal bovine serum, <lb/>penicillin (100 units/mL), streptomycin (100 mg/mL), and <lb/>1.6 mg/mL NaHCO 3 at 37uC in a humid atmosphere of 5% <lb/>CO 2 /95% air. For the cell viability assay, cells were seeded at <lb/>1610 3 cells/well in a 96-well microplate with various concentra-<lb/>tions of the test compounds, and incubated for 48 h. MTT (3-(4,5-<lb/>dimethylthiazol-2-yl)-2,5-diphenyl tetrazolium bromide) solution <lb/>was added to a final concentration 0.6 mg/mL in Milli-Q purified <lb/>water for 2 h [43], after which time the medium was discarded <lb/>and the cells lysed in DMSO. A 540 was then measured in a <lb/>microplate reader (Model 680, Bio-Rad Laboratories, Hercules, <lb/>CA, USA). <lb/>In vivo assessment of anti-tumor assay <lb/>Male BALB/c nu/nu mice at 5 week of age (18 g) were <lb/>purchased from Japan SLC, Inc. (Shizuoka, Japan). Mice receiving <lb/>standard laboratory chow and water ad libitum were acclimatized <lb/>for 1 week before inoculation with cancer cells. For in vivo <lb/>experiments, human colon HT-29 cells (1610 7 cells/mouse) were <lb/>subcutaneously injected into nude mice. Mice bearing solid tumors <lb/>that had grown to approximately 100 mm 3 in volume (tumor <lb/>volume = length6width6height) at 12 days after implantation <lb/>were used for the assessment of anti-tumor effects. They were <lb/>divided randomly into five groups (n = 6/group). One of the five <lb/>groups was a control group injected with 0.1 mL of phosphate <lb/>buffered saline (PBS) alone, and other groups were injected with <lb/>vitamin K 3 (3), juglone (4), C18:1-acyl juglone (5f), and C18:1-acyl <lb/>plumbagin (2f) dissolved in PBS at a dose of 5 mg/kg. The above <lb/>administrations all took place between days 12-39 subsequent to <lb/>implantation. All mice were injected subcutaneously 14 times at 1-<lb/>day intervals with the compound and PBS alone (control). Tumor <lb/>growth was measured at 1-day intervals for 40 days after <lb/>implantation. At the end of the in vivo anti-tumor assay, some <lb/>mice treated with the test compounds and PBS were indepen-<lb/>dently examined to observe major organs such as lung, heart, <lb/>spleen, stomach, liver, pancreas, kidney, intestine, and brain. <lb/>This animal study was approved by the Institutional Animal <lb/>Care and Use Committee of Kobe Gakuin University, and was <lb/>performed according to the guidelines outlined in the Care and <lb/>Use of Laboratory Animals of Kobe Gakuin University. The <lb/>animals were anesthetized with pentobarbital before undergoing <lb/>cervical dislocation. The mice that had been bred in-house with <lb/>free access to food and water were used for all experiments. All of <lb/>the mice were maintained under a 12-h light/dark cycle and <lb/>housed at a room temperature of 25uC. <lb/>Analytical instruments for synthetic 5-O-acyl plumbagins <lb/>(2a-j) <lb/>Melting points, determined on a Yanaco Micro Melting Point <lb/>apparatus, are uncorrected. NMR spectra were recorded on a <lb/>Bruker spectrometer (Avance 400). Chemical shifts are expressed <lb/>in d (ppm) relative to Me 4 Si or the residual solvent resonance, and <lb/>coupling constants (J) are expressed in Hz. The following <lb/>abbreviations are used for spin multiplicity: s = singlet, d = doublet, <lb/>t = triplet, q = quartet, quin = quintet, m = multiplet, br = broad. <lb/>Infrared spectra (IR) were recorded on a HORIBA FT-720, using <lb/>NaCl (neat) or KBr pellets (solid) and are reported in wavenum-<lb/>bers (cm 21 ). High resolution mass spectra (HRMS) were obtained <lb/>on a JEOL mass spectrometer (JMS-700 MStaion) using fast atom <lb/>bombardment (FAB), or a Fourier transformation-ion cyclotron <lb/>resonance-mass spectrometer, Bruker solariX (FT-ICR-MS) by <lb/>using electrospray ionization (ESI) and laser desorption ionization <lb/>(LDI) techniques. Analytical thin-layer chromatography (TLC) <lb/>was performed on Silica Gel 60 F 254 plates (Merck). Flash <lb/>chromatography was carried out on SiliaFlash F60 (Silicycle). <lb/>Synthesis and characterization of 5-O-acetoxy-2-methyl-<lb/>1,4-naphthoquinone (C2:0-Acyl plumbagin, 2a) <lb/>Acetic anhydride (0.5 mL) was added to a solution of plumbagin <lb/>(1) (107 mg, 0.57 mmol) in pyridine (1.0 mL), and the mixture was <lb/>stirred at room temperature for 4 h. After the solvent was <lb/>removed, the residue was purified by silica gel chromatography <lb/>(EtOAc/hexanes 1:3, v/v) to yield 2a (118 mg, 90%) as a yellow <lb/>solid [44]. Mp 118-124uC; IR (KBr) 3049, 2987, 2966, 2927, <lb/>1761, 1662, 1593, 1431, 1375, 1365, 1271, 1203, 1024, 910, <lb/>785 cm 21 ; 1 H NMR (400 MHz, CDCl 3 ) d 8.06 (dd, J = 8.0 Hz, <lb/>0.8 Hz, 1H), 7.73 (t, J = 8.0 Hz, 1H), 7.36 (dd, J = 8.0 Hz, <lb/>0.8 Hz, 1H), 6.71 (q, J = 1.2 Hz, 1H), 2.45 (s, 3H), 2.17 (d, <lb/>J = 1.2 Hz, 3H); 13 C NMR (100 MHz, CDCl 3 ) d 184.8, 183.6, <lb/>169.4, 149.2, 146.9, 136.8, 134.4, 133.8, 129.4, 125.1, 123.4, 21.1, <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Anti-Tumor Activity by C18:1-Acyl Plumbagin <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | www.plosone.org <lb/></note>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">February 2014 | Volume 9 | Issue 2 | e88736 <lb/></note>

			<body>16.0; HRMS (FAB) calcd for C 13 H 10 O 4 Na ([M+Na] + ) 253.0477, <lb/>found 253.0482 <lb/>General procedure for the preparation of 5-O-acyl <lb/>plumbagins (2b-f) using MNBA <lb/>Et 3 N (2.5-2.6 equiv.), 2-methyl-6-nitrobenzoic anhydride <lb/>(MNBA) (1.5 equiv.) and N,N-dimethyl-4-aminopyridine (DMAP) <lb/>(0.1 equiv.) were added to a solution of plumbagin (1) (1.0 equiv.) <lb/>and carboxylic acid (1.5 equiv.) in CH 2 Cl 2 at room temperature. <lb/>The mixture was stirred at room temperature under a N 2 <lb/>atmosphere until no further TLC changes were observed. The <lb/>reaction was quenched by the addition of H 2 O, and the mixture <lb/>was extracted with CHCl 3 . The combined extracts were washed <lb/>with brine, dried over Na 2 SO 4 , and concentrated. The residue was <lb/>purified by silica gel chromatography using EtOAc/hexanes as <lb/>eluent. <lb/>Synthesis and characterization of 5-O-propanolyloxy-2-<lb/>methyl-1,4-naphthoquinone (C3:0-Acyl plumbagin, 2b) <lb/>Following the general procedure, the reaction of plumbagin (1) <lb/>(52 mg, 0.28 mmol) with propionic acid (30 mL, 0.41 mmol) using <lb/>MNBA (143 mg, 0.41 mmol), Et 3 N (96 mL, 0.69 mmol), and <lb/>DMAP (3.4 mg, 0.03 mmol) for 2 h gave the crude product. The <lb/>crude product was purified by silica gel column chromatography <lb/>(EtOAc/hexanes = 1/5, v/v) to give 2b (60 mg, 89%) as a yellow <lb/>solid [44]. Mp = 108-112uC; IR (KBr) 3076, 3043, 2981, 2937, <lb/>1766, 1662, 1630, 1591, 1358, 1265, 1194, 1132, 1080, 1024, 904, <lb/>881, 781 cm 21 ; 1 H NMR (400 MHz, CDCl 3 ) d 8.06 (dd, <lb/>J = 8.0 Hz, 1.2 Hz, 1H), 7.73 (t, J = 8.0 Hz, 1H), 7.36 (dd, <lb/>Figure 2. Synthesis of 5-O-acyl plumbagins (2a-j). (A) Synthesis of 5-O-acyl plumbagin (2a). (B) Synthesis of 5-O-acyl plumbagins (2b-f). (C) <lb/>Synthesis of 5-O-acyl plumbagins (2g-j). <lb/>doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0088736.g002 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Anti-Tumor Activity by C18:1-Acyl Plumbagin <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | www.plosone.org <lb/></note>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">February 2014 | Volume 9 | Issue 2 | e88736 <lb/></note>

			<body>J = 8.0 Hz, 1.2 Hz, 1H), 6.71 (q, J = 1.2 Hz, 1H), 2.77 (q, <lb/>J = 7.6 Hz, 2H), 2.16 (d, J = 1.2 Hz, 3H), 1.32 (t, J = 7.6 Hz, <lb/>3H); 13 C NMR (100 MHz, CDCl 3 ) d 184.8, 183.6, 172.8, 149.3, <lb/>146.8, 136.9, 134.4, 133.8, 129.4, 125.0, 123.5, 27.6, 16.0, 8.7; <lb/>HRMS (FAB) calcd for C 14 H 12 O 4 Na ([M+Na] + ) 267.0633, found <lb/>267.0639. <lb/>Synthesis and characterization of 5-O-hexanoyloxy-2-<lb/>methyl-1,4-naphthoquinone (C6:0-Acyl plumbagin, 2c) <lb/>Following the general procedure, the reaction of plumbagin (1) <lb/>(100 mg, 0.53 mmol) with caproic acid (100 mL, 0.80 mmol) using <lb/>MNBA (274 mg, 0.80 mmol), Et 3 N (185 mL, 1.33 mmol), and <lb/>DMAP (6.7 mg, 0.05 mmol) for 2 h gave the crude product. The <lb/>crude product was purified by silica gel column chromatography <lb/>(EtOAc/hexanes = 1/6, v/v) to give 2c (102 mg, 68%) as a yellow <lb/>solid. Mp = 45-47uC; IR (KBr) 3086, 2958, 2929, 2871, 1766, <lb/>1664, 1631, 1595, 1454, 1362, 1267, 1234, 1138, 1105, 912, 891, <lb/>791 cm 21 ; 1 H NMR (400 MHz, CDCl 3 ) d 7.99 (dd, J = 8.0 Hz, <lb/>1.2 Hz, 1H), 7.65 (t, J = 8.0 Hz, 1H), 7.28 (dd, J = 8.0 Hz, <lb/>1.2 Hz, 1H), 6.64 (q, J = 1.2 Hz, 1H), 2.66 (t, J = 7.6 Hz, 2H), <lb/>2.09 (d, J = 1.2 Hz, 3H), 1.75 (quin, J = 7.6 Hz, 2H), 1.41-1.28 <lb/>(m, 4H), 0.87 (t, J = 7.6 Hz, 3H); 13 C NMR (100 MHz, CDCl 3 ) d <lb/>184.9, 183.6, 172.2, 149.4, 146.8, 136.9, 134.4, 133.8, 129.5, <lb/>125.0, 123.6, 34.2, 31.3, 24.1, 22.4, 16.1, 14.0; HRMS (FAB) <lb/>calcd for C 17 H 18 O 4 Na ([M+Na] + ) 309.1103, found 309.1099. <lb/>Synthesis and characterization of 5-O-dodecanoyloxy-2-<lb/>methyl-1,4-naphthoquinone (C12:0-Acyl plumbagin, 2d) <lb/>Following the general procedure, the reaction of plumbagin (1) <lb/>(53 mg, 0.28 mmol) with lauric acid (85 mg, 0.43 mmol) using <lb/>MNBA (147 mg, 0.43 mmol), Et 3 N (100 mL, 0.72 mmol), and <lb/>DMAP (3.5 mg, 0.03 mmol) for 19 h gave the crude product. The <lb/>crude product was purified by silica gel column chromatography <lb/>(EtOAc/hexanes = 1/9, v/v) to give 2d (90 mg, 86%) as a yellow <lb/>crystal; Mp 41-42uC; IR (KBr) 2922, 2850, 1755, 1654, 1632, <lb/>1593, 1464, 1358, 1271, 1230, 1188, 1144, 939, 918, 893, <lb/>787 cm 21 ; 1 H NMR (400 MHz, CDCl 3 ) d 8.06 (dd, J = 8.0 Hz, <lb/>1.2 Hz, 1H), 7.73 (t, J = 8.0 Hz, 1H), 7.35 (dd, J = 8.0 Hz, <lb/>1.2 Hz, 1H), 6.71 (q, J = 1.2 Hz, 1H), 2.73 (t, J = 7.6 Hz, 2H), <lb/>2.16 (d, J = 1.2 Hz, 3H), 1.81 (quin, J = 7.6 Hz, 2H), 1.38-1.27 <lb/>(brm, 16H), 0.88 (t, J = 7.6 Hz, 3H); 13 C NMR (100 MHz, <lb/>CDCl 3 ) d 184.9, 183.6, 172.2, 149.4, 146.8, 136.9, 134.4, 133.8, <lb/>129.5, 125.0, 123.6, 34.2, 31.9, 29.6 (2C), 29.5, 29.3, 29.3, 29.2, <lb/>24.4, 22.7, 16.1, 14.1; HRMS (ESI-LDI) calcd for C 23 H 30 O 4 Na <lb/>([M+Na] + ) 393.2036, found 393.2032. <lb/>Synthesis and characterization of 5-O-octadecanoyloxy-<lb/>2-methyl-1,4-naphthoquinone (C18:0-Acyl plumbagin, <lb/>2e) <lb/>Following the general procedure, the reaction of plumbagin (1) <lb/>(102 mg, 0.54 mmol) with stearic acid (231 mg, 0.81 mmol) using <lb/>MNBA (280 mg, 0.81 mmol), Et 3 N (189 mL, 1.36 mmol), and <lb/>DMAP (6.6 mg, 0.05 mmol) for 19 h gave the crude product. The <lb/>Figure 3. Stability of C18:1-acyl plumbagin (2f) and C18:1-acyl juglone (5f) under basic conditions. C18:1-acyl plumbagin (2f) (A) and <lb/>C18:1-acyl juglone (5f) (B) were treated with 1 equivalent of Triton B in 1,4-dioxane and MeOH. The mixtures were monitored by UV-vis spectroscopy <lb/>over time. Conditions: 1.1610 23 M, 25uC, light path length = 1 mm. <lb/>doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0088736.g003 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Anti-Tumor Activity by C18:1-Acyl Plumbagin <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | www.plosone.org <lb/></note>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">February 2014 | Volume 9 | Issue 2 | e88736 <lb/></note>

			<body>crude product was purified by silica gel column chromatography <lb/>(EtOAc/hexanes = 1/10, v/v) to give 2e (139 mg, 56%) as a <lb/>yellow solid. Mp = 67-70uC; IR (KBr) 2922, 2850, 1759, 1660, <lb/>1593, 1541, 1514, 1471, 1273, 1142, 1105, 893, 789 cm 21 ; 1 H <lb/>NMR (400 MHz, CDCl 3 ) d 7.99 (dd, J = 8.0 Hz, 1.2 Hz, 1H), <lb/>7.65 (t, J = 8.0 Hz, 1H), 7.27 (dd, J = 8.0 Hz, 1.2 Hz, 1H), 6.63 (q, <lb/>J = 1.2 Hz, 1H), 2.66 (t, J = 7.6 Hz, 2H), 2.09 (d, J = 1.2 Hz, 3H), <lb/>1.74 (quin, J = 7.6 Hz, 2H), 1.31-1.19 (brm, 28H), 0.81 (t, <lb/>J = 7.6 Hz, 3H); 13 C NMR (100 MHz, CDCl 3 ) d 184.9, 183,6, <lb/>172.2, 149.4, 146.8, 136.9, 134.4, 133.8, 129.5, 125.0, 123.6, 34.2, <lb/>31.9, 29.7 (5C), 29.6 (2C), 29.6, 29.5, 29.3, 29.2, 29.2, 24.4, 22.7, <lb/>16.0, 14.1; HRMS (FAB) calcd for C 29 H 42 O 4 Na ([M+Na] + ) <lb/>477.2981, found 447.2988. <lb/>Synthesis and characterization of 5-O-oleoyl-2-methyl-<lb/>1,4-naphthoquinone (C18:1-Acyl plumbagin, 2f) <lb/>Following the general procedure, the reaction of plumbagin (1) <lb/>(100 mg, 0.53 mmol) with oleic acid (0.25 mL, 0.79 mmol) using <lb/>MNBA (275 mg, 0.80 mmol), Et 3 N (186 mL, 1.33 mmol), and <lb/>DMAP (6.5 mg, 0.05 mmol) for 24 h gave the crude product. The <lb/>crude product was purified by silica gel column chromatography <lb/>(EtOAc/hexanes = 1/20, v/v) to give 2f (166 mg, 69%) as yellow <lb/>oil. IR (neat) 3005, 2925, 2854, 1770, 1664, 1595, 1462, 1356, <lb/>1271, 1190, 1107, 895, 783 cm 21 ; 1 H NMR (400 MHz, CDCl 3 ) d <lb/>8.06 (dd, J = 8.0 Hz, 1.2 Hz, 1H), 7.72 (t, J = 8.0 Hz, 1H), 7.34 <lb/>(dd, J = 8.0 Hz, 1.2 Hz, 1H), 6.70 (q, J = 1.2 Hz, 1H), 5.40-5.35 <lb/>(m, 2H), 2.73 (t, J = 7.6 Hz, 2H), 2.16 (d, J = 1.2 Hz, 3H), 2.06-<lb/>1.97 (brm, 4H), 1.81 (quin, J = 7.6 Hz, 2H), 1.47-1.27 (brm, 20H), <lb/>0.88 (t, J = 7.6 Hz, 3H); 13 C NMR (100 MHz, CDCl 3 ) d 184.9, <lb/>183.6, 172.1, 149.3, 146.8, 136.9, 134.4, 133.8, 130.0, 129.7, <lb/>129.5, 125.0, 123.5, 34.2, 31.9, 29.8, 29.7, 29.6, 29.6, 29.5, 29.3, <lb/>29.2, 29.1, 27.2, 27.2, 24.4, 22.7, 16.1, 14.1; HRMS (FAB) calcd <lb/>for C 29 H 40 O 4 Na ([M+Na] + ) 475.2824, found 475.2821. <lb/>General procedure for the preparation of acyl <lb/>plumbagins (2g-j) via acyl chlorides <lb/>Oxalyl chloride (3.0-3.6 equiv.) was added to a solution of <lb/>carboxylic acid (1 equiv.) in CH 2 Cl 2 at 0uC. The mixture was <lb/>stirred at room temperature for 3-4.5 h. The solvent was removed <lb/>to yield crude acyl chloride. A solution of the acyl chloride (2.2-5.8 <lb/>equiv.), plumbagin (1) (1 equiv.) and DMAP (0.1 equiv.) in <lb/>pyridine was stirred at room temperature. The mixture was stirred <lb/>at room temperature under a N 2 atmosphere until no further TLC <lb/>changes were observed. The reaction was quenched by the <lb/>addition of H 2 O, and the mixture was extracted with CHCl 3 . The <lb/>extracts were washed with brine, dried over Na 2 SO 4 , and <lb/>concentrated. The residue was purified by silica gel chromatog-<lb/>raphy using hexanes/ethyl acetate as eluent. <lb/>Synthesis and characterization of 5-O-linoleoyloxy-2-<lb/>methyl-1,4-naphthoquinone (C18:2-Acyl plumbagin, 2g) <lb/>Following the general procedure, linoleoyl chloride was <lb/>prepared by treatment of linoleic acid (110 mg, 0.39 mmol) with <lb/>oxalyl chloride (100 mL, 1.16 mmol) for 4 h. The reaction of <lb/>Figure 4. Inhibitory effects of plumbagin (1) and 5-O-acyl plumbagins (2a-j) on the activity of mammalian pols. Each compound <lb/>(10 mM) was incubated with calf pol a (B-family pol), human pol c (A-family pol), human pol k (Y-family pol), and human pol l (X-family pol) (0.05 <lb/>units each). Pol activity in the absence of the compound (control) was taken as 100%, and the relative activity is shown. Data are shown as the mean <lb/>6 SD (n = 3). ** P,0.01 and * P,0.05 vs. controls. <lb/>doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0088736.g004 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Anti-Tumor Activity by C18:1-Acyl Plumbagin <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | www.plosone.org <lb/></note>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">February 2014 | Volume 9 | Issue 2 | e88736 <lb/></note>

			<body>plumbagin (1) (34 mg, 0.18 mmol) with the crude linoleoyl <lb/>chloride using DMAP (2.2 mg, 0.02 mmol) in pyridine for 2 h <lb/>gave the crude product. The crude product was purified by silica <lb/>gel column chromatography (toluene/hexanes = 1/10, v/v) to give <lb/>2g (31.9 mg, 39%) as yellow oil. IR (neat) 3008, 2927, 2854, 1768, <lb/>1664, 1595, 1462, 1358, 1271, 1190, 1009, 1026, 982, 895, <lb/>783 cm 21 ; 1 H NMR (400 MHz, CDCl 3 ) d 8.06 (dd, J = 8.0 Hz, <lb/>1.2 Hz, 1H), 7.73 (t, J = 8.0 Hz, 1H), 7.35 (dd, J = 8.0 Hz, <lb/>1.2 Hz, 1H), 6.71 (q, J = 1.2 Hz, 1H), 5.42-5.33 (m, 4H), 2.78 (t, <lb/>J = 7.6 Hz, 2H), 2.73 (t, J = 7.6 Hz, 2H), 2.16 (d, J = 1.2 Hz, 3H), <lb/>2.08-2.03 (m, 4H), 1.81 (quin, J = 7.6 Hz, 2H), 1.36-1.26 (m, <lb/>14H), 0.94-0.86 (m, 3H); 13 C NMR (100 MHz, CDCl 3 ) d 184.9, <lb/>183.6, 172.2, 149.3, 146.8, 136.9, 134.4, 133.8, 130.2, 130.1, <lb/>129.5, 128.0, 127.9, 125.0, 123.5, 34.2, 32.5, 31.5, 29.6, 29.5, <lb/>29.3, 29.2, 29.1, 27.2, 25.6, 24.4, 22.6, 16.1, 14.1; HRMS (FAB) <lb/>calcd for C 29 H 38 O 4 Na ([M+Na] + ) 473.2668, found 473.2666. <lb/>Synthesis and characterization of 5-O-linolenoyloxy-2-<lb/>metyl-1,4-naphthoquinone (C18:3-Acyl plumbagin, 2h) <lb/>Following the general procedure, a-linolenoyl chloride was <lb/>prepared by treatment of a-linolenic acid (200 mg, 0.72 mmol) <lb/>with oxalyl chloride (200 mL, 2.33 mmol) for 4.5 h. The reaction <lb/>of plumbagin (1) (25 mg, 0.13 mmol) with the crude a-linolenoyl <lb/>chloride using DMAP (1.6 mg, 0.01 mmol) in pyridine for 18 h <lb/>gave the crude product. The crude product was purified by silica <lb/>gel column chromatography (EtOAc/hexanes = 1/20, v/v) to give <lb/>2h (32 mg, 54%) as yellow oil; IR (neat) 3010, 2927, 2856, 1768, <lb/>1664, 1595, 1462, 1358, 1271, 1107, 974, 912, 783 cm 21 ; 1 H <lb/>NMR (400 MHz, CDCl 3 ) d 8.05 (dd, J = 7.6 Hz, 1.2 Hz, 1H), <lb/>7.71 (t, J = 7.6 Hz, 1H), 7.34 (dd, J = 7.6 Hz, 1.2 Hz, 1H), 6.70 (q, <lb/>J = 1.2 Hz, 1H), 5.41-5.33 (m, 6H), 2.83-2.71 (m, 6H), 2.16 (d, <lb/>J = 1.2 Hz, 3H), 2.12-2.00 (m, 4H), 1.81 (quin, 2H), 1.48-1.30 <lb/>(brm, 8H), 0.98 (t, J = 7.6 Hz, 3H); 13 C NMR (100 MHz, CDCl 3 ) <lb/>d 184.9, 183.6, 172.2, 149.4, 146.8, 136.9, 134.4, 133.8, 132.0, <lb/>Figure 5. Effect of plumbagin (1) and 5-O-acyl plumbagins (2a-j) on the proliferation of HCT116 human colon carcinoma cells. Each <lb/>compound (10 and 100 mM) was added to cultured HCT116 cells. The cells were incubated for 48 h, and the rate of proliferation inhibition was <lb/>determined by MTT assay. Cell proliferation inhibition of the cancer cells in the absence of the compound (control) was taken as 100%. Data are <lb/>shown as the mean 6 SD (n = 5). ** P,0.01 and * P,0.05 vs. controls. <lb/>doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0088736.g005 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Anti-Tumor Activity by C18:1-Acyl Plumbagin <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | www.plosone.org <lb/></note>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">February 2014 | Volume 9 | Issue 2 | e88736 <lb/></note>

			<body>130.3, 130.0, 128.2 (2C), 127.7, 127.1, 125.0, 123.6, 34.2, 29.6, <lb/>29.2, 29.1, 27.2, 25.6, 25.5, 25.5, 24.4, 20.5, 16.1, 14.3; HRMS <lb/>(FAB) calcd for C 29 H 37 O 4 ([M+H] + ) 449.2692, found 449.2694. <lb/>Synthesis and characterization of 5-O-<lb/>eicosapentaenoyloxy-2-methyl-1,4-naphthoquinone <lb/>(C20:5-Acyl plumbagin, 2i) <lb/>Following the general procedure, eicosapentaenoyl chloride was <lb/>prepared by treatment of eicosapentaenoic acid (194 mg, <lb/>0.64 mmol) with oxalyl chloride (200 mL, 2.33 mmol) for 3 h. <lb/>The reaction of plumbagin (1) (20 mg, 0.10 mmol) with the crude <lb/>eicosapentaenoyl chloride using DMAP (1.3 mg, 0.01 mmol) in <lb/>pyridine for 4 h gave the crude product. The crude product was <lb/>purified by silica gel column chromatography (EtOAc/hex-<lb/>anes = 1/20, v/v) to give 4i (40 80%) as yellow oil. IR (neat) <lb/>3012, 2962, 1768, 1664, 1595, 1446, 1358, 1271, 1190, 1126, 897, <lb/>783, 717 cm 21 ; 1 H NMR (400 MHz, CDCl 3 ) d 8.06 (dd, <lb/>J = 7.6 Hz, 1.2 Hz, 1H), 7.72 (t, J = 7.6 Hz, 1H), 7.34 (dd, <lb/>J = 7.6 Hz, 1.2 Hz, 1H), 6.70 (q, J = 1.2 Hz, 1H), 5.50-5.35 (m, <lb/>10H), 2.90-2.72 (m, 10H), 2.27 (q, J = 7.6 Hz, 2H), 2.16 (d, <lb/>J = 1.2 Hz, 3H), 2.08 (quin, J = 7.6 Hz, 2H), 1.90 (quin, <lb/>J = 7.6 Hz, 2H), 0.97 (t, J = 7.6 Hz, 3H); 13 C NMR (100 MHz, <lb/>CDCl 3 ) d 184.8, 183.6, 171.9, 149.3, 146.8, 136.9, 134.4, 133.8, <lb/>132.0, 129.4, 129.0, 128.9, 128.5, 128.3, 128.2, 128.1, 128.1, <lb/>127.8, 127.0, 125.0, 123.5, 33.6, 26.6, 25.6, 25.6, 25.6, 25.5, 24.3, <lb/>20.5, 16.1, 14.3; HRMS (ESI-LDI) calcd for C 31 H 36 O 4 Na <lb/>([M+Na] + ) 495.2506, found 495.2505. <lb/>Synthesis and characterization of 5-O-<lb/>docosahexaenoyloxy-2-methyl-1,4-naphthoquinone <lb/>(C22:6-Acyl plumbagin, 2j) <lb/>Following the general procedure, docosahexaenoyl chloride was <lb/>prepared by treatment of docosahexaenoic acid (210 mg, <lb/>0.64 mmol) with oxalyl chloride (200 mL, 2.33 mmol) for 3 h. <lb/>The reaction of plumbagin (1) (20 mg, 0.11 mmol) with the crude <lb/>docosahexaenoyl chloride using DMAP (1.3 mg, 0.01 mmol) in <lb/>pyridine for 3 h gave the crude product. The crude product was <lb/>purified by silica gel column chromatography (EtOAc/hex-<lb/>Figure 6. Relationship between mammalian pol inhibitory activities versus human cancer cell proliferation inhibition by plumbagin <lb/>(1) and 5-O-acyl plumbagins (2a-j). X-axis indicates mammalian pol relative activity at 10 mM compound. (A) Calf pol a, (B) human pol c, (C) <lb/>human pol k, and (D) human pol l. Y-axis indicates rate of HCT116 human colon carcinoma cell proliferation at 100 mM compound. These data are <lb/>based on Figs. 4 and 5; correlation coefficient values are shown in each panel. <lb/>doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0088736.g006 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Anti-Tumor Activity by C18:1-Acyl Plumbagin <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | www.plosone.org <lb/></note>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">February 2014 | Volume 9 | Issue 2 | e88736 <lb/></note>

			<body>anes = 1/20, v/v) to give 2j (39 mg, 70%) as yellow oil; IR (neat) <lb/>3012, 2964, 2927, 2875, 1768, 1662, 1595, 1358, 1271, 1190, <lb/>1128, 1026, 980, 897, 783, 714 cm 21 ; 1 H NMR (400 MHz, <lb/>CDCl 3 ) d 8.06 (dd, J = 8.0 Hz, 1.2 Hz, 1H), 7.73 (t, J = 8.0 Hz, <lb/>1H), 7.35 (dd, J = 8.0 Hz, 1.2 Hz, 1H), 6.71 (q, J = 1.2 Hz, 1H), <lb/>5.34 (m, 12H), 2.92-2.73 (m, 12H), 2.60 (q, J = 7.2 Hz, 2H), 2.16 <lb/>(d, J = 1.2 Hz, 3H), 2.07 (quin, J = 7.2 Hz, 2H), 0.97 (t, <lb/>J = 0.4 Hz, 3H); 13 C NMR (100 MHz, CDCl 3 ) d 184.8, 183.6, <lb/>171.5, 149.3, 146.8, 136.9, 134.4, 133.8, 132.0, 129.5, 129.4, <lb/>128.5, 128.2 (2C), 128.2, 128.1, 128.1, 128.1, 127.8, 127.8, 127.0, <lb/>125.1, 123.5, 34.1, 25.6, 25.6, 25.6, 25.6, 25.5, 22.4, 20.5, 16.1, <lb/>14.3; HRMS (ESI-LDI) calcd for C 33 H 38 O 4 Na ([M+Na] + ) <lb/>521.2662, found 521.2661. <lb/>Stability of C18:1-acyl plumbagin (2f) and C18:1-acyl <lb/>juglone (5f) under basic conditions <lb/>A 2.2610 22 M solution of Triton B in MeOH was added to a <lb/>2.2610 22 M solution of each sample in 1,4-dioxane. Then, the <lb/>mixture was diluted with 1,4-dioxane to a concentration of <lb/>1.1610 23 M. Then, the stability of each compound was <lb/>monitored by UV-vis spectroscopy. UV-vis spectra were measured <lb/>at 25uC on a UV-vis spectrophotometer (JASCO V-650, Tokyo, <lb/>Japan). For comparison, UV-vis spectra of 1.1610 23 M solution <lb/>of C18:1-acyl plumbagin (2f), and C18:1-acyl juglone (5f) in 1,4-<lb/>dioxane and MeOH (19/1, v/v) were measured. <lb/>Statistical analysis <lb/>All data are expressed as the mean value 6 the standard <lb/>deviation (SD) of at least three independent determinations for <lb/>each experiment. Statistical significance between each experimen-<lb/>tal group was analyzed using Student&apos;s t-test, and a probability <lb/>level of 0.01 and 0.05 was used as the criterion of significance. <lb/>Results and Discussion <lb/>Synthesis of 5-O-acyl plumbagins (2a-j) <lb/>Synthesis of 5-O-acyl plumbagins (2a-j) is summarized in Fig. 2. <lb/>C2:0-Acyl plumbagin (2a) was prepared by treatment of <lb/>plumbagin (1) with acetic anhydride in pyridine in 90% yield <lb/>(Fig. 2A). 5-O-Acyl plumbagins 2b-f were prepared by conden-<lb/>sation of plumbagin (1) with the corresponding carboxylic acids, <lb/>using MNBA with triethylamine and DMAP in CH 2 Cl 2 (Fig. 2B). <lb/>5-O-Acyl plumbagins 2g-j were prepared by acylation of <lb/>plumbagin (1) with acyl chlorides in the presence of DMAP in <lb/>pyridine (Fig. 2C). <lb/>Stability of C18:1-acyl plumbagin (2f) and C18:1-acyl <lb/>juglone (5f) under basic conditions <lb/>We have found that C18:1-acyl plumbagin (2f) is more stable <lb/>than C18:1-acyl juglone (5f) [23] under basic conditions. C18:1-<lb/>acyl plumbagin (2f) and C18:1-acyl juglone (5f) were treated with <lb/>Triton B (benzyltrimethylammonium hydroxide) in 1,4-dioxane <lb/>and MeOH. As shown in Fig. 3, UV spectra of the mixture were <lb/>recorded at different reaction times. Almost no changes in UV <lb/>spectra of C18:1-acyl plumbagin (2f) were observed before and <lb/>after treatment of Triton B (Fig. 3A). UV spectra of the mixture of <lb/>C18:1-acyl plumbagin (2f) and Triton B rarely changed during the <lb/>reaction. In contrast, the changes in UV absorption of C18:1-acyl <lb/>juglone (5f) were clearly observed (Fig. 3B). UV absorption at <lb/>675 nm and 400 nm was observed soon after the addition of <lb/>Triton B. The absorption at 675 nm suggests the formation of an <lb/>extended aromatic compound by the reaction of C18:1-acyl <lb/>juglone with Triton B in 1,4-dioxane and MeOH. The absorption <lb/>at 675 nm became smaller during the reaction, suggesting that the <lb/>extended aromatic compound had decomposed. The absorption at <lb/>400 nm increased with reaction time. We observed weak and <lb/>broad absorption in the wavelength range 300-700 nm. These <lb/>results suggest that C18:1-acyl juglone (5f) readily decomposes <lb/>under basic conditions. <lb/>Effect of synthesized 5-O-acyl plumbagins (2a-j) on the <lb/>activities of mammalian pols <lb/>Initially, the inhibitory activity of each 5-O-acyl plumbagin (2a-<lb/>j) toward mammalian pols was investigated using calf pol a, and <lb/>human pols c, k, and l. In mammalian pols, pols a, c, k, and l <lb/>were used as the representative pols for families B, A, Y, and X, <lb/>respectively [8,9]. Assessment of the relative activity of each pol at <lb/>Table 1. IC 50 of C18:1-acyl plumbagin (2f) on the activities of <lb/>mammalian pols, other species pols, and various DNA <lb/>metabolic enzymes. <lb/>Enzyme <lb/>IC 50 values (mM) <lb/>-Mammalian pols -<lb/>[A family of pol] <lb/>Human pol c <lb/>4.560.40 ** <lb/>[B family of pols] <lb/>Calf pol a <lb/>4.860.38 ** <lb/>Human pol d <lb/>5.360.41 ** <lb/>Human pol e <lb/>4.960.40 ** <lb/>[X family of pols] <lb/>Rat pol b <lb/>10.360.46 ** <lb/>Human pol l <lb/>9.260.43 ** <lb/>Human pol m <lb/>9.560.48 ** <lb/>Calf TdT <lb/>10.660.50 ** <lb/>[Y family of pols] <lb/>Human pol g <lb/>7.960.42 ** <lb/>Mouse pol i <lb/>8.260.43 ** <lb/>Human pol k <lb/>7.660.41 ** <lb/>-Plant pol -<lb/>Cauliflower pol a <lb/>.100 <lb/>Rice pol l <lb/>.100 <lb/>-Prokaryotic pols -<lb/>E. coli pol I <lb/>.100 <lb/>Taq pol <lb/>.100 <lb/>T4 pol <lb/>.100 <lb/>-Other DNA metabolic enzymes -<lb/>Calf primase of pol a <lb/>.100 <lb/>T7 RNA polymerase <lb/>.100 <lb/>Mouse IMP dehydrogenase (type II) <lb/>.100 <lb/>T4 polynucleotide kinase <lb/>.100 <lb/>Bovine deoxyribonuclease I <lb/>.100 <lb/>Compounds were incubated with each enzyme (0.05 units). Enzyme activity in <lb/>the absence of an inhibitor (control) was taken as 100%; data, mean 6 SD <lb/>(n = 3). <lb/>**P,0.01 vs. controls. <lb/>doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0088736.t001 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Anti-Tumor Activity by C18:1-Acyl Plumbagin <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | www.plosone.org <lb/></note>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">February 2014 | Volume 9 | Issue 2 | e88736 <lb/></note>

			<body>a set concentration (10 mM) of plumbagin (1) and the ten <lb/>chemically synthesized compounds showed that some 5-O-acyl <lb/>plumbagins were stronger inhibitors of these four mammalian pols <lb/>than plumbagin (1) (Fig. 4). The plumbagins conjugated with C18 <lb/>and longer chain unsaturated fatty acids (i.e., C18:1 to C22:6-acyl <lb/>plumbagins 2f-j) strongly inhibited the activities of pols a and c, <lb/>suggesting that the group of unsaturated longer acyl side chains <lb/>might be an important structural characteristic of 5-O-acyl <lb/>plumbagin for pol inhibition. C22:6-acyl plumbagin (2j) was the <lb/>strongest inhibitor of human pols k and l among the compounds <lb/>tested. In contrast, C2:0-acyl plumbagin (2a) hardly inhibited the <lb/>activities of human pols k and l, and C18:0-acyl plumbagin (2e) <lb/>did not inhibit pol a activity. When activated DNA (bovine <lb/>deoxyribonuclease I-treated DNA) was used as the DNA template-<lb/>primer substrate instead of synthesized DNA [poly(dA)/oli-<lb/>go(dT) 18 (A/T = 2/1)] and dNTP was used as the nucleotide <lb/>substrate instead of dTTP, the inhibitory effects of these <lb/>compounds did not differ (data not shown). <lb/>Effect of synthesized 5-O-acyl plumbagins (2a-j) on <lb/>cultured human cancer cells <lb/>Pols have emerged as important cellular targets for chemical <lb/>intervention in the development of anti-cancer agents [2]. <lb/>Therefore, the synthesized 5-O-acyl plumbagins (2a-j) could be <lb/>useful in chemotherapy. Hence, we investigated the cytotoxic <lb/>effect of these compounds against HCT116 human colon <lb/>carcinoma cells. As shown in Fig. 5, 100 mM plumbagin (1) <lb/>approximately 50% suppressed cell proliferation, but 10 mM of <lb/>this compound did not. Of the ten synthesized compounds, the <lb/>nine 5-O-acyl plumbagins except for C18:0-acyl plumbagin (2e) <lb/>were stronger cell proliferation inhibitors than plumbagin (1). <lb/>C18:1-Acyl plumbagin (2f) and C18:2-acyl plumbagin (2g) had <lb/>the first and second strongest proliferation inhibitory effect on <lb/>HCT116 cells among the compounds tested, and at 10 mM <lb/>compound these cells showed less than 40 and 60% of the cell <lb/>proliferation rate, respectively. <lb/>Relationship of mammalian pol inhibition and human <lb/>cancer cell proliferation suppression by 5-O-acyl <lb/>(2a-j) <lb/>The possible relationship between the observed inhibition of <lb/>four mammalian pol families and HCT116 human colon cancer <lb/>cell proliferation inhibitory activity was confirmed by comparing <lb/>the effects of plumbagin (1) and the ten synthesized 5-O-acyl <lb/>Figure 7. Effect of C18:1-acyl plumbagin (2f) on the thermal transition of dsDNA. Control (open-square), C18:1-acyl plumbagin (2f) <lb/>(100 mM, closed-circle), and EtBr (15 mM, open-diamond) were incubated with 6 mg/mL of calf thymus dsDNA in 0.1 M Na-phosphate buffer (pH 7.0). <lb/>Data are shown as the mean 6 SD (n = 3). ** P,0.01 and * P,0.05 vs. controls. <lb/>doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0088736.g007 <lb/>Table 2. LD 50 values of C18:1-acyl plumbagin (2f) on the <lb/>proliferation of human cancer cells. <lb/>Human cancer cell line <lb/>LD 50 values (mM) <lb/>A549 (lung cancer) <lb/>15.461.7 ** <lb/>DU145 (prostate cancer) <lb/>8.860.9 ** <lb/>HCT116 (colon cancer) <lb/>6.560.6 ** <lb/>HeLa (cervical cancer) <lb/>21.062.5 ** <lb/>HepG2 (hepatocellular liver cancer) <lb/>7.460.8 ** <lb/>HT-29 cells (colon cancer) <lb/>2.960.4 ** <lb/>MCF-7 (breast cancer) <lb/>7.260.7 ** <lb/>PANC-1 (pancreatic cancer) <lb/>16.161.8 ** <lb/>PC3 (prostate cancer) <lb/>10.061.1 ** <lb/>The nine human cancer cell lines were incubated with C18:1-acyl plumbagin <lb/>(2f) for 48 h. Cell viability was determined by MTT assay, and this viability in the <lb/>absence of an inhibitor (control) was taken as 100%; data, mean 6 SD (n = 5). <lb/>**P,0.01 vs. controls. <lb/>doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0088736.t002 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Anti-Tumor Activity by C18:1-Acyl Plumbagin <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | www.plosone.org <lb/></note>

			<page>10 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">February 2014 | Volume 9 | Issue 2 | e88736 <lb/></note>

			<body>plumbagins (2a-j) on these biological activities (Fig. 6). The effect <lb/>of 10 mM of these compounds on the relative activity of pol a, <lb/>which is a DNA replicative pol of the B family, showed the highest <lb/>correlation with the effect of 100 mM of these compounds on the <lb/>cancer cell proliferation among those mammalian pol families <lb/>tested, with a correlation coefficient of 0.844. The relative activity <lb/>of pol c, a mitochondrial DNA replicative pol of the A family, <lb/>showed a moderate correlation (R 2 = 0.545) with the cancer cell <lb/>proliferation rate. Conversely, neither the activities of pols k and l, <lb/>which are DNA repair-related pols of the Y and X families <lb/>Figure 8. In vivo anti-tumor effects of C18:1-acyl plumbagin (2f). Nude mice bearing HT-29 solid tumors were administered with PBS <lb/>(control), vitamin K 3 (3), juglone (4), C18:1-acyl juglone (5f), and C18:1-acyl plumbagin (2f) at a dose of 5 mg/kg. (A) Inhibitory effect on tumor <lb/>volume in nude mice. (B) Body weight changes of nude mice; data, means 6 SE (n = 6). * P,0.05 vs. controls. <lb/>doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0088736.g008 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Anti-Tumor Activity by C18:1-Acyl Plumbagin <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | www.plosone.org <lb/></note>

			<page>11 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">February 2014 | Volume 9 | Issue 2 | e88736 <lb/></note>

			<body>respectively, were related to cytotoxicity, with a correlation <lb/>coefficient between these activities and cytotoxicity of ,0.25. <lb/>These results led to the speculation that the inhibition of the <lb/>activities of DNA replicative pols, such as pols a and c; in <lb/>particular, inhibition of both the A and B families of pols by <lb/>compounds 1 and 2a-j might cause the suppression of human <lb/>cancer cell proliferation. <lb/>In particular, C18:1-acyl plumbagin (2f) showed the strongest <lb/>inhibition of pol c of the ten synthesized 5-O-acyl plumbagins (2a-<lb/>j) tested. This compound also exhibited the strongest effects on <lb/>cancer cell proliferation suppression (Fig. 5). Therefore, C18:1-<lb/>acyl plumbagin (2f) was used in the latter part of this study. <lb/>Effects of C18:1-acyl plumbagin (2f) on the activities of <lb/>various pols and other DNA metabolic enzymes <lb/>As described briefly in the Introduction, we succeeded in <lb/>obtaining eleven mammalian pol species, including pols a, b, c, d, <lb/>e, g, i, k, l, and m, and TdT; however, pols f, h and n, and REV1 <lb/>were not yet available at the time of the study. Currently, <lb/>eukaryotes are thought to express at least 15 species of pols [6,7], <lb/>and we are still in an era when most pols are very difficult to obtain <lb/>in their purified form in a laboratory. Table 1 shows the inhibitory <lb/>effect (50% inhibitory concentration; IC 50 value) of C18:1-acyl <lb/>plumbagin (2f) against various pol species including the 11 <lb/>mammalian pols that could be obtained. This compound inhibited <lb/>the activity of all of the mammalian pols with IC 50 values of 4.5-<lb/>10.6 mM, and 50% inhibition of the A, B, X, and Y families of pols <lb/>was observed at doses of 4.5, 4.8-5.3, 9.2-10.6, and 7.6-8.2 mM, <lb/>respectively; therefore, the inhibitory effect of this compound on <lb/>the A and B families of pols was 1.5-to 2-fold stronger than that on <lb/>the X and Y families of pols. Because the IC 50 values of <lb/>aphidicolin, a known eukaryotic DNA replicative pol a, d, and e <lb/>inhibitor, were 20, 13, and 16 mM, respectively [45], the pol <lb/>inhibitory activity of C18:1-acyl plumbagin (2f) was .2-fold more <lb/>potent than that of aphidicolin. <lb/>In contrast, C18:1-acyl plumbagin (2f) had no effect on plant <lb/>pols such as cauliflower pol a or rice pol l, or prokaryotic pols, <lb/>such as E. coli pol I, Taq pol, or T4 pol (Table 1). The three-<lb/>dimensional structures of eukaryotic pols are likely to differ greatly <lb/>from those of prokaryotic pols. This compound did not inhibit the <lb/>activity of other DNA metabolic enzymes, such as calf primase pol <lb/>a, 7 RNA polymerase, mouse IMP dehydrogenase (type II), T4 <lb/>polynucleotide kinase, or bovine deoxyribonuclease I. These <lb/>results suggest that 5-O-acyl plumbagins (2) may be selective <lb/>inhibitors of mammalian pols; in particular, plumbagin (1) <lb/>conjugated with unsaturated fatty acids, such as C18:1-acyl <lb/>plumbagin (2f), potently inhibited the activities of the A and B <lb/>families of pols. <lb/>Influence of C18:1-acyl plumbagin (2f) on the <lb/>hyperchromicity of dsDNA <lb/>Specific assays were performed to determine whether C18:1-<lb/>acyl plumbagin (2f)-induced inhibition resulted from the ability of <lb/>the compound to bind to DNA or the enzyme. The interaction of <lb/>C18:1-acyl plumbagin (2f) with dsDNA was investigated by <lb/>studying its thermal transition. For this, the melting temperature <lb/>(T m ) of dsDNA in the presence of an excess of C18:1-acyl <lb/>plumbagin (2f) (100 mM) was observed using a spectrophotometer <lb/>equipped with a thermoelectric cell holder. As shown in Fig. 7, a <lb/>thermal transition (i.e., T m ) from 75 to 90uC was not observed <lb/>within the concentration range used in the assay, whereas when a <lb/>typical intercalating compound, such as ethidium bromide (EtBr, <lb/>15 mM), was used as a positive control, an obvious thermal <lb/>transition was observed. <lb/>The question of whether the inhibitory effect of C18:1-acyl <lb/>plumbagin (2f) resulted from nonspecific adhesion to mammalian <lb/>pols or from its binding to these enzymes was investigated by <lb/>determining if an excessive amount of nucleic acid [poly(rC)] or <lb/>protein (BSA; bovine serum albumin) prevented the inhibitory <lb/>effect of C18:1-acyl plumbagin (2f). Poly(rC) and BSA had little or <lb/>no influence on pol inhibition by C18:1-acyl plumbagin (2f) (data <lb/>not shown), suggesting that this compound selectively bound to the <lb/>pol molecule. These observations indicated that C18:1-acyl <lb/>plumbagin (2f) did not act as a DNA intercalating agent or as a <lb/>template-primer substrate. <lb/>Collectively, these results suggested that C18:1-acyl plumbagin <lb/>(2f) might be a potent and specific inhibitor of mammalian pols. <lb/>Subsequently, we investigated whether pol inhibition by C18:1-<lb/>acyl plumbagin (2f) resulted in reduced human cancer cell <lb/>proliferation. <lb/>Effect of C18:1-acyl plumbagin (2f) on cultured human <lb/>cancer cell lines <lb/>C18:1-Acyl plumbagin (2f) treatment for 48 h suppressed the <lb/>proliferation of various human cancer cells in a dose-dependent <lb/>manner. As shown in Table 2, C18:1-acyl plumbagin (2f) <lb/>prevented the proliferation of nine human cancer cell lines, such <lb/>as A549, DU145, HCT116, HeLa, HepG2, HT-29, MCF-7, <lb/>PANC-1, and PC3 cells, with LD 50 values of 2.9-21.0 mM. These <lb/>results suggested that this compound could have suppressive <lb/>activity against the different type of cancer cell lines. In particular, <lb/>this compound showed the strongest cell proliferation suppression <lb/>in the colon cancer cell lines, HCT116 and HT-29, with LD 50 <lb/>values of 6.5 and 2.9 mM, respectively. These dose-response curves <lb/>by MTT detection were the same as that obtained by trypan blue <lb/>staining (data not shown), suggesting that C18:1-acyl plumbagin <lb/>(2f) might cause a direct toxic effect on the cells. Because these <lb/>LD 50 s were similar to the IC 50 s for pols (Table 1), this inhibition <lb/>must be mostly led by the function of pols, such as DNA replicative <lb/>pol a. C18:1-Acyl plumbagin (2f) more strongly suppressed the <lb/>proliferation of these human cancer cell lines than aphidicolin, <lb/>which is an inhibitor of eukaryotic DNA replicative pols (data not <lb/>shown). <lb/>Effect of C18:1-acyl plumbagin (2f) on in vivo anti-tumor <lb/>activity <lb/>Because the cell proliferation inhibitory effect of C18:1-acyl <lb/>plumbagin (2f) was the strongest on HT-29 cells among the nine <lb/>human cancer cell lines tested (Table 2), this cell line was used in <lb/>vivo anti-tumor assays. In this assay, we investigated whether <lb/>C18:1-acyl plumbagin (2f) was more stable and/or had stronger <lb/>bioactivity than C18:1-acyl juglone (5f) in vivo; thus, C18:1-acyl <lb/>plumbagin (2f) was compared with vitamin K 3 (3), juglone (4), and <lb/>C18:1-acyl juglone (5f). <lb/>HT-29 cells were subcutaneously injected into 40 nude mice. At <lb/>12 days after the implantation, these nude mice were sorted five <lb/>groups (one control group and four treatment groups) and each <lb/>mouse group contained 6 mice bearing solid tumor volume of 96-<lb/>102 mm 3 . The sorted nude mice were injected with each test <lb/>compound dissolved in PBS (5 mg/kg) at 1-day intervals until 40 <lb/>days. As shown in Fig. 8A, these compounds suppressed tumor <lb/>growth as compared with the control (PBS) group, and the <lb/>decreased rates of tumor volume at 40 days following injection <lb/>with vitamin K 3 (3), juglone (4), C18:1-acyl juglone (5f), and <lb/>C18:1-acyl plumbagin (2f) were 7.0, 9.2, 10.3, and 30.5%, <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Anti-Tumor Activity by C18:1-Acyl Plumbagin <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | www.plosone.org <lb/></note>

			<page>12 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">February 2014 | Volume 9 | Issue 2 | e88736 <lb/></note>

			<body>respectively. C18:1-acyl plumbagin (2f) showed more than a 3-fold <lb/>stronger anti-tumor effect than the other compounds tested, <lb/>suggesting that C18:1-acyl plumbagin (2f) must be stable in vivo, <lb/>but C18:1-acyl juglone (5f) did not. A significant correlation was <lb/>found between 5-O-acyl plumbagins (2) and the inhibition of <lb/>mammalian pols, especially DNA replicative pol a (Fig. 6A). <lb/>C18:1-Acyl plumbagin (2f) may be able to penetrate cancer cells of <lb/>tumor in mouse and reach the nucleus, inhibiting the activities of <lb/>pols and then the inhibition of pol activity by this compound may <lb/>lead to cell proliferative suppression and prevent tumor growth. <lb/>None of the nude mice showed any significant loss of body <lb/>weight throughout the experimental period (Fig. 8B). It was also <lb/>noted that the main visceral organs, such as the liver, lung, kidney, <lb/>spleen, heart, stomach, small intestine, large intestine, pancreas, <lb/>and testis of all the groups showed no toxic or degenerative <lb/>histological appearance (data not shown); therefore, C18:1-acyl <lb/>plumbagin (2f) is of interest as a candidate material for anti-cancer <lb/>treatment. <lb/>Conclusions <lb/>We previously found that vitamin K 3 (2-methyl-1,4-naphtho-<lb/>quinone), juglone (5-hydroxy-1,4-naphthoquinone) conjugated <lb/>with fatty acids inhibited the activity of mammalian pols. In this <lb/>study, 5-O-acyl plumbagins (2), which are plumbagins (5-hydroxy-<lb/>2-methyl-1,4-naphthoquinone) conjugated with fatty acid, were <lb/>produced to establish an efficient chemical synthesis method. In <lb/>the synthesized ten 5-O-acyl plumbagins (2a-j), 2c-j are novel <lb/>compounds. These synthesized compounds were stronger inhib-<lb/>itors of the mammalian pols a, c, k, and l representing the pol <lb/>families B, A, Y, and X, respectively, than plumbagin (1). Of the <lb/>synthesized compounds, C18:1-acyl plumbagin (2f) showed the <lb/>strongest suppression of human cancer cell proliferation. The <lb/>human cancer cytotoxicity of this compound was realized through <lb/>the inhibition of pols, which are essential for DNA replication as <lb/>well as cell division. Because C18:1-acyl plumbagin (2f) potently <lb/>inhibited the activities of replicative pols, such as pols a and c and <lb/>suppressed human cancer cell proliferation, they might show in vivo <lb/>anti-tumor activity without any side effects. The in vivo anti-tumor <lb/>effect of C18:1-acyl plumbagin (2f) was stronger than that of <lb/>C18:1-acyl juglone (5f), because C18:1-acyl plumbagin (2f) is <lb/>more stable than C18:1-acyl juglone (5f) under basic conditions. <lb/>These results suggested that 5-O-acyl plumbagins (2), such as <lb/>C18:1-acyl plumbagin (2f), could be used as anti-cancer chemo-<lb/>therapy agents based on their mammalian pol inhibition. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgments <lb/>We are grateful for the following donations: calf pol a by Dr. M. Takemura <lb/>of Tokyo University of Science (Tokyo, Japan); rat pol b, and human pols d <lb/>and e by Dr. K. Sakaguchi of Tokyo University of Science (Chiba, Japan); <lb/>human pol c by Dr. M. Suzuki of Nagoya University School of Medicine <lb/>(Nagoya, Japan); mouse pol g and human pol i by Dr. F. Hanaoka of <lb/>Gakushuin University (Tokyo, Japan) and Dr. C. Masutani of Nagoya <lb/>University (Nagoya, Japan); human pol k by Dr. H. Ohmori of Kyoto <lb/>University (Kyoto, Japan); and human pols l and m by Dr. O. Koiwai of <lb/>Tokyo University of Science (Chiba, Japan). This study was carried out on <lb/>mass spectrometers at the Joint Usage/Research Center (JURC) at <lb/>Institute for Chemical Research, Kyoto University. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Author Contributions <lb/>Conceived and designed the experiments: KK YM. Performed the <lb/>experiments: MK IK SM KK. Analyzed the data: KT HY YM. <lb/>Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: MK SM KK KT. Wrote <lb/>the paper: KK YM. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>1. Berdis AJ (2008) DNA polymerases as therapeutic targets. Biochemistry <lb/>(Moscow) 47: 8253-8260. <lb/>2. Sakaguchi K, Sugawara F, Mizushina Y (2002) Inhibitors of eukaryotic DNA <lb/>polymerases. Seikagaku 74: 244-251. <lb/>3. Surh YJ (2003) Cancer chemoprevention with dietary phytochemicals. Nature <lb/>Rev Cancer 3: 768-780. <lb/>4. Liu RH (2004) Potential synergy of phytochemicals in cancer prevention: <lb/>mechanism of action. J Nutr 134: 3479S-3485S. <lb/>5. Kornberg K, Baker TA (1992) DNA replication. FreemanW.D. and Co. New <lb/>York, University Science Books. 197-225p. <lb/>6. Bebenek K, Kunkel TA (2004) Functions of DNA polymerases. Adv Protein <lb/>Chem 69: 137-165. <lb/>7. Hubscher U, Maga G, Spadari S (2002) Eukaryotic DNA polymerases. Ann Rev <lb/>Biochem 71: 133-163. <lb/>8. Loeb LA, Monnat Jr.RJ (2008) DNA polymerases and human disease. Nature <lb/>Rev Genet 9: 594-604. <lb/>9. Lange SS, Takata K, Wood RD (2011) DNA polymerases and cancer. Nature <lb/>Rev Cancer 11: 96-110. <lb/>10. Mizushina Y (2009) Specific inhibitors of mammalian DNA polymerase species. <lb/>Biosci Biotechnol Biochem 73: 1239-1251. <lb/>11. Mizushina Y (2011) Screening of novel bioactive compounds from food <lb/>components and nutrients. J Jpn Soc Nutr Food Sci 64: 377-384. <lb/>12. Mizushina Y, Yonezawa Y, Yoshida Y (2007) Selective inhibition of animal <lb/>DNA polymerases by fat-soluble vitamins A, D, E and K, and their related <lb/>compounds. Curr Enzyme Inhibition 3: 61-75. <lb/>13. Sasaki R, Suzuki Y, Yonezawa Y, Ota Y, Okamoto Y, et al. (2008) DNA <lb/>polymerase c inhibition by vitamin K 3 induces mitochondria-mediated <lb/>cytotoxicity in human cancer cells. Cancer Sci 99: 1040-1048. <lb/>14. Monks TJ, Hanzlik RP, Cohen GM, Ross D, Graham DG (1992) Quinone <lb/>chemistry and toxicity. Toxicol Appl Pharmacol 112: 2-16. <lb/>15. O&apos;Brien PJ (1991) Molecular mechanisms of quinone cytotoxicity. Chem Biol <lb/>Interact 80: 1-41. <lb/>16. Bolton JL, Trush MA, Penning TM, Dryhurst G, Monks TJ (2000) Role of <lb/>quinones in toxicology. Chem Res Toxicol 13: 135-160. <lb/>17. Cho AK, Stefano ED, You Y, Rodriguez CE, Debra A, et al. (2004) <lb/>Determination of Four Quinones in Diesel Exhaust Particles, SRM 1649a, <lb/>and Atmospheric PM2.5. Aerosol Sci Technol 38: 68-81 <lb/>18. Mossa JS, El-Feraly FS, Muhammad I (2004) Antimycobacterial constituents <lb/>from Juniperus procera, Ferula communis and Plumbago zeylanica and their in vitro <lb/>synergistic activity with isonicotinic acid hydrazide. Phytother Res 18: 934-937. <lb/>19. Srinivas P, Gopinath G, Banerji A, Dinakar A, Srinivas G (2003) Plumbagin <lb/>induces reactive oxygen species, which mediate apoptosis in human cervical <lb/>cancer cells. Mol Carcinog 40: 201-211. <lb/>20. Tilak JC, Adhikari S, Devasagayam TP (2004) Antioxidant properties of <lb/>Plumbagozeylanica, an Indian medicinal plant and its active ingredient, plumbagin. <lb/>Redox Rep 9: 219-227. <lb/>21. Ding Y, Chen ZJ, Liu S, Che D, Vetter M, et al. (2005) Inhibition of Nox-4 <lb/>activity by plumbagin, a plant-derived bioactive naphthoquinone. J Pharm <lb/>Pharmacol 57: 111-116. <lb/>22. Lee JH, Yeon JH, Kim H, Roh W, Chae J, et al. (2012) The natural anticancer <lb/>agent plumbagin induces potent cytotoxicity in MCF-7 human breast cancer <lb/>cells by inhibiting a PI-5 kinase for ROS generation. PLoS One 7: e45023. <lb/>23. Maruo S, Kuriyama I, Kuramochi K, Tsubaki K, Yoshida H, et al. (2011) <lb/>Inhibitory effect of novel 5-O-acyl juglones on mammalian DNA polymerase <lb/>activity, cancer cell growth and inflammatory response. Bioorg Med Chem 19: <lb/>5803-5812. <lb/>24. Tamai K, Kojima K, Hanaichi T, Masaki S, Suzuki M, et al. (1988) Structural <lb/>study of immunoaffinity-purified DNA polymerase a-DNA primase complex <lb/>from calf thymus. Biochim Biophys Acta 950: 263-273. <lb/>25. Date T, Yamaguchi M, Hirose F, Nishimoto Y, Tanihara K, et al. (1998) <lb/>Expression of active rat DNA polymerase b in Escherichia coli. Biochemistry 27: <lb/>2983-2990. <lb/>26. Umeda S, Muta T, Ohsato T, Takamatsu C, Hamasaki N, et al. (2000) The D-<lb/>loop structure of human mtDNA is destabilized directly by 1-methyl-4-<lb/>phenylpyridinium ion (MPP + ), a parkinsonism-causing toxin. Eur J Biochem <lb/>267: 200-206. <lb/>27. Oshige M, Takeuchi R, Ruike R, Kuroda K, Sakaguchi K (2004) Subunit <lb/>protein-affinity isolation of Drosophila DNA polymerase catalytic subunit. Protein <lb/>Expr Purif 35: 248-256. <lb/>28. Kusumoto R, Masutani C, Shimmyo S, Iwai S, Hanaoka F (2004) DNA binding <lb/>properties of human DNA polymerase g: implications for fidelity and <lb/>polymerase switching of translesion synthesis. Genes Cells 9: 1139-1150. <lb/>29. Biertu ¨mpfel C, Zhao Y, Kondo Y, Ramo ´n-Maiques S, Gregory M, et al. (2010) <lb/>Structure and mechanism of human DNA polymerase g. Nature 465: 1044-<lb/>1048. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Anti-Tumor Activity by C18:1-Acyl Plumbagin <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | www.plosone.org <lb/></note>

			<page>13 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">February 2014 | Volume 9 | Issue 2 | e88736 <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>30. Ohashi E, Murakumo Y, Kanjo N, Akagi J, Masutani C, et al. (2004) Interaction <lb/>of hREV1 with three human Y-family DNA polymerases. Genes Cells 9: 523-<lb/>531. <lb/>31. Shimazaki N, Yoshida K, Kobayashi T, Toji S, Tamai T, et al. (2002) Over-<lb/>expression of human DNA polymerase l in E. coli and characterization of the <lb/>recombinant enzyme. Genes Cells 7: 639-651. <lb/>32. Sakaguchi K, Hotta Y, Stern H (1980) Chromatin-associated DNA polymerase <lb/>activity in meiotic cells of lily and mouse. Cell Struct Funct 5: 323-334. <lb/>33. Uchiyama Y, Kimura S, Yamamoto T, Ishibashi T, Sakaguchi K (2004) Plant <lb/>DNA polymerase l, a DNA repair enzyme that functions in plant meristematic <lb/>and meiotic tissues. Eur J Biochem 271: 2799-2807. <lb/>34. Mizushina Y, Tanaka N, Yagi H, Kurosawa T, Onoue M, et al. (1996) Fatty <lb/>acids selectively inhibit eukaryotic DNA polymerase activities in vitro. Biochim <lb/>Biophys Acta 1308: 256-262. <lb/>35. Mizushina Y, Yoshida S, Matsukage A, Sakaguchi K (1997) The inhibitory <lb/>action of fatty acids on DNA polymerase b. Biochim Biophys Acta 1336: 509-<lb/>521. <lb/>36. Ogawa A, Murate T, Suzuki M, Nimura Y, Yoshida S (1998) Lithocholic acid, a <lb/>putative tumor promoter, inhibits mammalian DNA polymerase b. Jpn J Cancer <lb/>Res 89: 1154-1159. <lb/>37. Tamiya-Koizumi K, Murate T, Suzuki M, Simbulan CM, Nakagawa M, et al. <lb/>(1997) Inhibition of DNA primase by sphingosine and its analogues parallels <lb/>with their growth suppression of cultured human leukemic cells. Biochem Mol <lb/>Biol Int 41: 1179-1189. <lb/>38. Nakayama C, Saneyoshi M (1985) Inhibitory effects of 9-b-D-xylofuranosylade-<lb/>nine 59-triphosphate on DNA-dependent RNA polymerase I and II from cherry <lb/>salmon (Oncorhynchus masou). J Biochem (Tokyo) 97: 1385-1389. <lb/>39. Mizushina Y, Dairaku I, Yanaka N, Takeuchi T, Ishimaru C, et al. (2007) <lb/>Inhibitory action of polyunsaturated fatty acids on IMP dehydrogenase. <lb/>Biochimie 89: 581-590. <lb/>40. Soltis DA, Uhlenbeck OC (1982) Isolation and characterization of two mutant <lb/>forms of T4 polynucleotide kinase. J Biol Chem 257: 11332-11339. <lb/>41. Lu BC, Sakaguchi K (1991) An endo-exonuclease from meiotic tissues of the <lb/>basidiomycete Coprinus cinereus: Its purification and characterization. J Biol Chem <lb/>266: 21060-21066. <lb/>42. Mizushina Y, Murakami C, Ohta K, Takikawa H, Mori K, et al. (2002) <lb/>Selective inhibition of the activities of both eukaryotic DNA polymerases and <lb/>DNA topoisomerases by elenic acid. Biochem Pharmacol 63: 421-427. <lb/>43. Mosmann T (1983) Rapid colorimetric assay for cellular growth and survival: <lb/>application to proliferation and cytotoxicity assays. J Immunol Methods 65: 55-<lb/>63. <lb/>44. Mathew R, Kruthiventi AK, Prasad JV, Kumar SP, Srinu G, et al. (2010) <lb/>Inhibition of mycobacterial growth by plumbagin derivatives. Chem Biol Drug <lb/>Des 76: 34-42. <lb/>45. Mizushina Y, Kamisuki S, Mizuno T, Takemura M, Asahara H, et al. (2000) <lb/>Dehydroaltenusin, a mammalian DNA polymerase a inhibitor. J Biol Chem <lb/>275: 33957-33961. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Anti-Tumor Activity by C18:1-Acyl Plumbagin <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | www.plosone.org <lb/></note>

			<page>14 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">February 2014 | Volume 9 | Issue 2 | e88736 </note>


	</text>
</tei>