<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>Mar. Drugs 2014, 12, 477-490; doi:10.3390/md12010477 <lb/>marine drugs <lb/>ISSN 1660-3397 <lb/>www.mdpi.com/journal/marinedrugs <lb/>Communication <lb/>Alkaloids from the Mangrove-Derived Actinomycete <lb/>Jishengella endophytica 161111 <lb/>Pei Wang 1 , Fandong Kong 1 , Jingjing Wei 2 , Yi Wang 1 , Wei Wang 1 , Kui Hong 2, * and <lb/>Weiming Zhu 1, * <lb/>1 Key Laboratory of Marine Drugs, Ministry of Education of China, <lb/>School of Medicine and Pharmacy, Ocean University of China, Qingdao 266003, China; <lb/>E-Mails: wangpei850212@163.com (P.W.); kongfandong501@126.com (F.K.); <lb/>wangyi0213@ouc.edu.cn (Y.W.); wwwakin@ouc.edu.cn (W.W.) <lb/>2 Key Laboratory of Combinatorial Biosynthesis and Drug Discovery, Ministry of Education, <lb/>School of Pharmaceutical Sciences, Wuhan University, Wuhan 430071, China; <lb/>E-Mail: rxwzq@163.com <lb/>* Authors to whom correspondence should be addressed; E-Mails: kuihong31@whu.edu.cn (K.H.); <lb/>weimingzhu@ouc.edu.cn (W.Z.); Tel./Fax: +86-532-8203-1268 (W.Z.). <lb/>Received: 28 November 2013; in revised form: 24 December 2013 / Accepted: 7 January 2014 / <lb/>Published: 21 January 2014 <lb/>Abstract: A new alkaloid, 2-(furan-2-yl)-6-(2S,3S,4-trihydroxybutyl)pyrazine (1), <lb/>along with 12 known compounds, 2-(furan-2-yl)-5-(2S,3S,4-trihydroxybutyl)pyrazine (2), <lb/>(S)-4-isobutyl-3-oxo-3,4-dihydro-1H-pyrrolo[2,1-c][1,4]oxazine-6-carbaldehyde <lb/>(3), <lb/>(S)-4-isopropyl-3-oxo-3,4-dihydro-1H-pyrrolo[2,1-c][1,4]oxazine-6-carbaldehyde <lb/>(4), <lb/>(4S)-4-(2-methylbutyl)-3-oxo-3,4-dihydro-1H-pyrrolo[2,1-c][1,4]oxazine-6-carbaldehyde (5), <lb/>(S)-4-benzyl-3-oxo-3,4-dihydro-1H-pyrrolo[2,1-c][1,4]oxazine-6-carbaldehyde <lb/>(6), <lb/>flazin <lb/>(7), <lb/>perlolyrine <lb/>(8), <lb/>1-hydroxy-β-carboline <lb/>(9), <lb/>lumichrome <lb/>(10), <lb/>1H-indole-3-carboxaldehyde (11), 2-hydroxy-1-(1H-indol-3-yl)ethanone (12), and <lb/>5-(methoxymethyl)-1H-pyrrole-2-carbaldehyde (13), were isolated and identified from the <lb/>fermentation broth of an endophytic actinomycetes, Jishengella endophytica 161111. The <lb/>new structure 1 and the absolute configurations of 2-6 were determined by spectroscopic <lb/>methods, J-based configuration analysis (JBCA) method, lactone sector rule, and electronic <lb/>circular dichroism (ECD) calculations. Compounds 8-11 were active against the influenza <lb/>A virus subtype H1N1 with IC 50 and selectivity index (SI) values of 38.3(±1.2)/25.0(±3.6)/ <lb/>39.7(±5.6)/45.9(±2.1) μg/mL and 3.0/16.1/3.1/11.4, respectively. The IC 50 and SI values of <lb/>positive control, ribavirin, were 23.1(±1.7) μg/mL and 32.2, respectively. The results <lb/>OPEN ACCESS <lb/>Mar. Drugs 2014, 12 <lb/>478 <lb/>showed that compound 9 could be a promising new hit for anti-H1N1 drugs. The absolute <lb/>configurations of 2-5, 13 C nuclear magnetic resonance (NMR) data and the specific <lb/>rotations of 3-6 were also reported here for the first time. <lb/>Keywords: mangrove; actinomycete; Jishengella endophytica 161111; pyrazine derivative; <lb/>anti-H1N1 virus activity <lb/></front>

			<body>1. Introduction <lb/>Mangroves, unique forest ecosystems found mainly in the tropical and subtropical intertidal <lb/>regions, represent a rich biological diversity and a high population of actinomycetes [1,2]. From these <lb/>actinomycetes, many bioactive compounds such as cytotoxic streptocarbazoles A and B have been <lb/>obtained [3]. In addition, there is also evidence that the mangrove ecosystem is a largely unexplored <lb/>source for novel actinomycetes with the potential to produce biologically active secondary <lb/>metabolites [4]. In order to pursue bioactive products from mangrove actinomycetes, a novel <lb/>endophytic actinomycetes, identified as Jishengella endophytica 161111, had been isolated from the <lb/>root of the mangrove plant, Xylocarpus granatum (Meliaceae) [5]. J. endophytica 161111 was found to <lb/>produce alkaloids in a saline culture medium by thin layer chromatography (TLC) visualizing with <lb/>Dragendorff&apos;s reagent. Chemical investigations on the ethyl acetate (EtOAc) extract of fermentation <lb/>broth of strain 161111 resulted in the isolation and identification of three pyrazine derivatives, <lb/>2-(furan-2-yl)-6-(2S,3S,4-trihydroxybutyl)pyrazine (1) and 2-(furan-2-yl)-5-(2S,3S,4-trihydroxybutyl) <lb/>pyrazine (2) [6] and lumichrome (10) [7]; four pyrrololactones, (S)-4-isobutyl-3-oxo-3,4-dihydro-1 <lb/>H-pyrrolo[2,1-c][1,4]oxazine-6-carbaldehyde (3) [8], (S)-4-isopropyl-3-oxo-3,4-dihydro-1H-pyrrolo <lb/>[2,1-c][1,4]oxazine-6-carbaldehyde (4) [8], (4S)-4-(2-methylbutyl)-3-oxo-3,4-dihydro-1H-pyrrolo <lb/>[2,1-c][1,4]oxazine-6-carbaldehyde (5) [8,9] and (S)-4-benzyl-3-oxo-3,4-dihydro-1H-pyrrolo[2,1-c] <lb/>[1,4]oxazine-6-carbaldehyde (6) [10]; three β-carbolines, flazin (7) [11], perlolyrine (8) [12] <lb/>and 1-hydroxy-β-carboline (9) [13]; along with 1H-indole-3-carboxaldehyde (11) [14,15], <lb/>2-hydroxy-1-(1H-indol-3-yl) ethanone (12) [14,15], and 5-(methoxymethyl)-1H-pyrrole-2-carbaldehyde <lb/>(13) [16] (Figure 1). Compounds 8-11 showed anti-influenza A (H1N1) virus activity with the half <lb/>maximal inhibitory concentration (IC 50 ) and selectivity index (SI) values of 38.3(±1.2)/25.0(±3.6)/ <lb/>39.7(±5.6)/45.9(±2.1) μg/mL and 3.0/16.1/3.1/11.4, respectively. Pyrazine alkaloids from marine <lb/>organisms exhibited cytotoxic and antimicrobial activities [17-21], three of which were identified from <lb/>the mangrove plant [22] and fungi [23,24]. β-Carbolines, as a type of natural indol alkaloids, displayed <lb/>cytotoxic [25], antiviral [26,27], antimicrobial [28], antiparasitic [29], and antithrombotic activities [30]. <lb/>Apart from the terrestrial organisms, marine organisms, including mangrove fungi [24,31], are also a <lb/>major source of β-carbolines [32-40]. Pyrrololactones that had been reported as the volatile components <lb/>of the roasted roots of Cichorium intrybus [8] were not identified from the marine organisms. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Mar. Drugs 2014, 12 <lb/></note>

			<page>479 <lb/></page>

			<body>Figure 1. Chemical structures of compounds 1-13 from J. endophytica 161111. <lb/>2. Results and Discussion <lb/>2.1. Structure Elucidation <lb/>The EtOAc extract of the fermentation broth of J. endophytica 161111 was subjected to extensive <lb/>chromatographic separations over silica gel, RP-18, Sephadex LH-20 and high performance liquid <lb/>chromotography (HPLC) to yield the new compound 1 and the known compounds 2-13. <lb/>Compound 1 was obtained as brown oil. Its molecular formula was determined as C 12 H 14 N 2 O 4 on <lb/>the basis of high resolution electrospray ionization mass spectrum (HRESIMS) peak at m/z 273.0849 <lb/>[M + Na] + (calcd. for C 12 H 14 N 2 O 4 Na 273.0846). The similarity of 1D-and 2D-NMR data (Table S2 in <lb/>Supplementary Information) between 1 and the known crotonine (2) [6] indicated the similar planar <lb/>structure. The signals at δ H 7.23 (1H, d, J = 4.0 Hz), 6.63 (1H, dd, J = 2.1, 4.0 Hz) and 7.72 (1H, d, <lb/>J = 2.1 Hz) revealed the presence of a α-substituted furan moiety, which was further identified by the <lb/>1 H-1 H correlation spectroscopy (COSY) of H-3′/H-4′/H-5′ and the key heteronuclear multiple bond <lb/>correlations (HMBC) of H-3′ (δ 7.23) to C-2′ (δ 151.1), C-4′ (δ 112.0) and C-5′ (δ 144.6), of H-4′ <lb/>(δ H 6.63) to C-2′, C-3′ (δ 110.5) and C-5′, and of H-5′ (δ 7.72) to C-2′ and C-3′. The existence of <lb/>2,3,4-trihydroxybutyl moiety was deduced from the 1 H-1 H COSY correlations of H-1″/H-2″/H-3″/H-4″ <lb/>along with the key HMBC correlations of H-1″ (δ 3.24/2.93) to C-2″ (δ 71.5) and C-3″ (δ 74.8), H-2″ <lb/>(δ 4.03) to C-3″ and C-4″ (δ 63.2), H-3″ (δ 3.58) to C-1″ (δ 38.4), C-2″ and C-4″, and H-4″ <lb/>(δ 3.80/3.65) to C-2″ and C-3″. The remainder C 4 H 2 N 2 displayed two sp 2 methine signals at δ H/C <lb/>8.78/136.7 and 8.38/142.7, and two sp 2 quaternary carbon signals at δ C 144.2 and 155.3, which were <lb/>ascribable to a disubstituted pyrazine nucleus [41]. The obvious HMBC correlations from H-3 (δ 8.78) <lb/>to C-2 (δ 144.2) and C-2′, H-5 (δ 8.38) to C-3 (δ 136.7) and C-6 (δ 155.3), and from H-2″ to C-5 <lb/>(δ 142.7) and C-6 indicated that the α-substituted furan moiety and the 2,3,4-trihydroxybutyl moiety <lb/>were linked onto C-2 and C-6 of the pyrazine nucleus, respectively. The relative configuration of 1 <lb/>was determined by J-based configuration analysis (JBCA) method [42]. The low temperature NMR <lb/>(-4 °C ) of 1 revealed a large coupling constant between H-2″ and H-3″ (J = 7.2 Hz), indicating an <lb/>anti-relationship between the two protons. In addition, low temperature NMR (-4 °C ) of 1 also <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Mar. Drugs 2014, 12 <lb/></note>

			<page>480 <lb/></page>

			<body>displayed nuclear Overhauser effect spectroscopy (NOESY) of H-1″/H-3″, H-1″/H-4″, and H-4″/H-2″. <lb/>These data indicated threo-configuration between C-2″ and C-3″ (Figure 2). The absolute <lb/>configuration of 1 was determined by use of quantum chemical ECD calculation [43]. The preliminary <lb/>conformational distribution search was performed by HyperChem 7.5 software. The corresponding <lb/>minimum geometries were further fully optimized by using density functional theory (DFT) at the <lb/>B3LYP/6-31G(d) level as implemented in the Gaussian 03 program package. The stable conformers <lb/>obtained were submitted to ECD calculation by the time-dependent DFT (TDDFT) (B3LYP/6-31G(d)) <lb/>method. The overall predicted ECD spectrum of 1 was subsequently compared with the measured one [43]. <lb/>The measured circular dichroism (CD) curve of 1 showed Cotton effect at λ max (Δε) 310 (-0.14), 284 <lb/>(+0.12) and 237 (-1.3) nm, matching well with the calculated ECD curve of (2″S,3″S)-1 (Figure 3). <lb/>Thus, the new structure, 1, was established as 2-(furan-2-yl)-6-(2S,3S,4-trihydroxybutyl)pyrazine. <lb/>Figure 2. Selected 2D NMR correlations for 1 and Newman projections showing NOESY <lb/>correlations and 3 J H-2″,H-3″ values of 1 and 2. <lb/>Figure 3. CD and calculated ECD spectra for 1 and 2. <lb/>Although the planar structures of 2-5 had reported in the literatures [6,8,9], their absolute <lb/>configurations have not been resolved yet. The planar structures of 2 and 6 here were elucidated by <lb/>comparison of their NMR data with those reported [6,10]. Then, the same methods as 1 were used to <lb/>resolve the relative and absolute configurations of 2. The large 3 J H-2″,H-3″ value (7.1 Hz) and <lb/>the NOESY correlations of H-1″/H-3″ and H-1″/H-4″/H-2″ in the low temperature NMR (-4 °C ) <lb/>of 2 revealed the same threo-configuration of two hydroxy groups at C-2″ and C-3″ (Figure 2). <lb/>Compound 2 showed a CD Cotton effect at λ max (Δε) 316 (-0.54), 267 (+0.35) and 235 (-1.0) nm, <lb/>matching with the calculated ECD curve of (2″S,3″S)-2 (Figure 3). Thus, compound 2 was determined <lb/>as 2-(furan-2-yl)-5-(2S,3S,4-trihydroxybutyl)pyrazine. <lb/>Though absolute structure 6 had been presented in the literature [10], no reference data on absolute <lb/>configuration, such as CD and specific rotation of 6, could be used. Lactone sector rule [44] could be <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Mar. Drugs 2014, 12 <lb/></note>

			<page>481 <lb/></page>

			<body>used to determine the absolute configuration of 6. The molecule was viewed from the line on the plane <lb/>of the ester group along the bisectrix of the O-C=O angle, i.e., the line from C-2 to C-3 as shown in <lb/>Figure 4 for (3S). The functional group at C-3 lying in the back upper left sector was responsible for <lb/>the positive CD Cotton effect resulted from n-π* transition of lactone, which was well in accordance <lb/>with the positive Cotton effect at λ max 293 nm of 6 (Figure 4). The deduction was further confirmed by <lb/>ECD quantum chemical calculations using the TDDFT method at the B3LYP/6-31G(d) level in <lb/>Gaussian 03 [43]. The measured CD curve of 6 showed Cotton effect at λ max (Δε) 293 (+13.1), <lb/>249 (-4.7), 211 (+6.8) nm, matching with the calculated ECD curve of (3S)-6 and opposite to that of <lb/>(3R)-6 (Figure 5). Thus, the absolute configuration of 6 was unambiguous determined as S-, that is <lb/>(S)-4-benzyl-3-oxo-3,4-dihydro-1H-pyrrolo[2,1-c][1,4]oxazine-6-carbaldehyde. <lb/>Figure 4. Application of lactone sector rule to 3-6. <lb/>Figure 5. CD and calculated ECD spectra of 3-6. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Mar. Drugs 2014, 12 <lb/></note>

			<page>482 <lb/></page>

			<body>Compounds 3-5 were found to have the molecular formulas of C 12 H 15 NO 3 , C 11 H 13 NO 3 , and <lb/>C 12 H 15 NO 3 by HRESI-MS peaks at m/z 222.1131 [M + H] + , 208.0974 [M + H] + , and 222.1129 [M + H] + <lb/>(calcd. for C 12 H 16 NO 3 222.1125, C 11 H 14 NO 3 208.0968, C 12 H 16 NO 3 222.1125), respectively. The <lb/>similarity of ultraviolet (UV) and NMR spectra between 3-5 and 6 indicates compounds 3-5 contain <lb/>the same3-oxo-3,4-dihydro-1H-pyrrolo[2,1-c][1,4]oxazine-6-carbaldehyde nucleus. The remaining <lb/>moieties of C 4 H 9 , C 3 H 7 and C 4 H 9 for 3-5 could be deduced as isobutyl, isopropyl, and sec-butyl, <lb/>respectively, from their 1D NMR data (Table 1). Thus, the planar structures of 3-5 were <lb/>4-isobutyl-3-oxo-3,4-dihydro-1H-pyrrolo[2,1-c][1,4]oxazine-6-carbaldehyde [8], 4-isopropyl-3-oxo-3, <lb/>4-dihydro-1H-pyrrolo[2,1-c][1,4]oxazine-6-carbaldehyde <lb/>[8], <lb/>and <lb/>4-(2-methylbutyl)-3-oxo-3, <lb/>4-dihydro-1H-pyrrolo [2,1-c] [1,4]oxazine-6-carbaldehyde [8,9], respectively. The planar structure 3 <lb/>was further supported by 1 H-1 H COSY correlations of H-14/H-13/H-12/H-11/H-3 and H-6 (δ H 7.14) to <lb/>H-7 (δ H 6.31) combined with the key HMBC correlations from H-11 (δ H 2.00, 1.60) to C-2 (δ C 167.5), <lb/>C-3 (δ C 56.4), C-13 (δ C 21.6), and C-14 (δ C 23.3), from H-9 (δ H 5.70, 5.51) to C-2, C-7 (δ C 107.2), and <lb/>C-8 (δ C 132.5), from H-3 (δ H 5.65) to C-2, C-8, C-12 (δ C 24.7), of H-7 (δ H 6.31) to C-5 (δ C 130.7), C-6 <lb/>(δ C 125.2), of H-6 to C-7, C-8, and C-10 (δ C 180.1). The same lactone sector rule and ECD quantum <lb/>chemical calculation used in 6 were also applied to elucidate the absolute configurations of 3-5. Thus, <lb/>the same (3S)-configurations of 3-5 could be deduced from the same negative sign of the specific <lb/>rotations and the positive CD Cotton effects at the long wave length along with concordance of CD <lb/>with the calculated ECD of (3S)-isomer and opposition to ECD of (3R)-isomer (Figure 5). <lb/>Table 1. 1 H and 13 C NMR data for 3-6 (δ in ppm). <lb/>Position <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>6 <lb/>δ C , Type <lb/>δ H , Mult. <lb/>(J in Hz) <lb/>δ C , Type <lb/>δ H , Mult. <lb/>(J in Hz) <lb/>δ C , Type <lb/>δ H , Mult. <lb/>(J in Hz) <lb/>δ C , Type <lb/>δ H , Mult. <lb/>(J in Hz) <lb/>2 <lb/>167.5, qC <lb/>166.7, qC <lb/>166.5, qC <lb/>167.2, qC <lb/>3 <lb/>56.4, CH <lb/>5.65, dd, <lb/>(5.7, 10.2) <lb/>63.1, CH <lb/>5.36, d, (8.0) 62.0, CH <lb/>5.46, d, (6.9) <lb/>59.0, CH <lb/>5.84, t, (5.6) <lb/>5 <lb/>130.7, qC <lb/>131.4, qC <lb/>131.2, qC <lb/>130.7, qC <lb/>6 <lb/>125.2, CH <lb/>7.14, d, (4.0) <lb/>125.4, CH 7.17, d, (4.0) 125.6, CH <lb/>7.2, d, (3.8) <lb/>125.4, CH 7.19, d, (4.0) <lb/>7 <lb/>107.2, CH <lb/>6.31, d, (4.0) <lb/>107.2, CH 6.34, d, (4.0) 107.1, CH 6.34, d, (3.8) 106.4, CH 6.17, d, (4.0) <lb/>8 <lb/>132.5, qC <lb/>132.7, qC <lb/>132.8, qC <lb/>132.4, qC <lb/>9 <lb/>63.7, CH 2 <lb/>5.70, d, (15.2) <lb/>5.51, d, (15.2) <lb/>64.2, CH 2 <lb/>5.64, d, (15.5) <lb/>5.53, d, (15.5) <lb/>64.4, CH 2 <lb/>5.64, d, (15.6) <lb/>5.54, d, (15.6) <lb/>63.6, CH 2 <lb/>5.24, d, (15.1) <lb/>4.06, d, (15.1) <lb/>10 <lb/>180.1, CH <lb/>9.49, s <lb/>180.2, CH <lb/>9.51, s <lb/>180.0, CH <lb/>9.5, s <lb/>179.9, CH <lb/>9.51, s <lb/>11 <lb/>41.3, CH 2 <lb/>2.00, ddd, <lb/>(4.3, 10.2, 13.4) <lb/>1.60, ddd, <lb/>(5.7, 9.3, 13.4) <lb/>32.4, CH <lb/>2.33, m <lb/>39.3, CH <lb/>2.08, m <lb/>39.5, CH 2 <lb/>3.33, m <lb/>12 <lb/>24.7, CH <lb/>1.66, m <lb/>19.3, CH 3 0.97, d, (6.8) 25.8, CH 2 1.39, m; 1.25, m 135.1, qC <lb/>13 <lb/>21.6, CH 3 <lb/>1.00, d, (6.4) <lb/>18.8, CH 3 0.92, d, (6.8) 15.5, CH 3 0.90, d, (7.0) 129.8, CH 6.85, d, (7.3) <lb/>14 <lb/>23.3, CH 3 <lb/>0.89, d, (6.4) <lb/>11.8, CH 3 <lb/>0.91, t, (7.1) <lb/>129.1, CH 7.25, t, (7.3) <lb/>15 <lb/>128.2, CH 7.29, t, (7.3) <lb/>16 <lb/>129.1, CH 7.25, t, (7.3) <lb/></body>

			<page>17 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">129.8, CH 6.85, d, (7.3) <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">Mar. Drugs 2014, 12 <lb/></note>

			<page>483 <lb/></page>

			<body>2.2. The Bioactivities of Compounds 1-13 from J. endophytica 161111 <lb/>Compounds 1-13 were tested for antivirus effects on H1N1 by the cytopathic effect (CPE) <lb/>inhibition assay [45,46] and ribavirin was used as the positive control with an IC 50 value of <lb/>23.1 ± 1.7 μg/mL. The results (Table S1 in Supplementary Information) showed that compounds 8-11 <lb/>showed moderate anti-H1N1 activity with IC 50 values of 38.3 ± 1.2, 25.0 ± 3.6, 39.7 ± 5.6, and <lb/>45.9 ± 2.1 μg/mL, respectively. In addition, the cytotoxic effects of 8-11 on Madin-Daby canine <lb/>kidney (MDCK) normal cells were also evaluated by 3-(4,5-dimethyl-2-thiazolyl)-2,5-diphenyl-2 <lb/>H-tetrazolium bromide (MTT) [47]. The results showed that compounds 8-11 and ribavirin exhibited <lb/>very weak cytotoxicities against MDCK normal cell with the half maximal cytotoxic concentration <lb/>(CC 50 ) values of 116.3 ± 12.1, 403.2 ± 31.4, 124.1 ± 10.5, 522.5 ± 24.5, and 744.2 ± 18.5 μg/mL, <lb/>respectively. The SI values of compounds 8-11 and ribavirin were 3.0, 16.1, 3.1, 11.4, and <lb/>32.2, respectively. <lb/>Both naturally occurring and chemically synthesized β-carbolines exhibited good activities <lb/>against a set of virus, such as human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) [26,48], herpes simplex virus <lb/>(HSV) [27,49], vaccinia virus [50], vesicular stomatitis virus [50,51], poliovirus [49], and influenza A <lb/>and B virus [51]. It was reported that the derivatives with the oxathiazepine 7-membered ring showed <lb/>potential activities against influenza A and B [51]. This study showed that the simple β-carboline <lb/>alkaloids were active against H1N1 virus and the unsubstituted H-3 is essential for the anti-H1N1 <lb/>activity of this kind of compounds. In addition, the compound 9 could be a promising new hit for <lb/>anti-H1N1 drugs. In addition, further chemical modifications are necessary to improve the anti-H1N1 <lb/>virus activity. <lb/>3. Experimental Section <lb/>3.1. General Experimental Procedures <lb/>Specific rotations were obtained on a JASCO P-1020 digital polarimeter. UV spectra <lb/>were measured on a Beckman DU 640 spectrophotometer. IR spectra were recorded on a Nicolet <lb/>Nexus 470 spectrophotometer as KBr disks. CD spectra were collected using a JASCO J-715 <lb/>spectropolarimeter. NMR data of 7, 8, 11, and 13 were measured on a JEOL JNM-ECP 600 <lb/>spectrometer, while NMR of 1, 2, 3-6, 9, 10, and 12, and all NOESY spectra were recorded on a <lb/>Bruker Avance 600 spectrometer. Electrospray ionization mass spectra (ESIMS) and HRESIMS <lb/>measurements were taken on a Q-TOFULTIMA GLOBAL GAA076 LC mass spectrometer. <lb/>Semipreparative HPLC was performed using an octadecylsilyl (ODS) column (YMC-pak ODS-A, <lb/>Allentown, PA, USA, 10 × 250 mm, 5 μm, 4.0 mL/min) and C 3 column (Agilent Zorbax StableBond <lb/>C 3 , Palo Alto, CA, USA, 4.6 × 150 mm, 5 μm, 1.0 mL/min). TLC and column chromatography (CC, <lb/>2.5 × 103 cm) were performed on plates pre-coated with silica gel GF 254 (10-40 μm, Qingdao Marine <lb/>Chemical Factory, Qingdao, China), and over Sephadex LH-20 (Amersham Biosciences, Uppsala, <lb/>Sweden), respectively. Vacuum-liquid chromatography (VLC, 6 × 24 cm and 3.6 × 30 cm) utilized silica <lb/>gel (200-300 mesh, Qingdao Marine Chemical Factory, Qingdao, China) and RP-18 (40-63 μm, <lb/>Merck, Darmstadt, Germany). Glucose (Shanghai Huixing Biochemical Reagent Co., Ltd., Shanghai, <lb/>China); yeast extract and peptone (Beinjing Shuangxuan Microbe Culture Medium Products Factory, <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Mar. Drugs 2014, 12 <lb/></note>

			<page>484 <lb/></page>

			<body>Beijing, China); CaCO 3 (Tianjijn Bodi Chemical Co., Ltd., Tianjin, China); KNO 3 (Sinopharm <lb/>Chemical Reagent Co., Ltd., Shanghai, China); NaCl (Sinopharm Chemical Reagent Co., Ltd., <lb/>Shanghai, China). <lb/>3.2. Actinomycetes Material <lb/>Jishengella endophytica 161111 was isolated and identified from the healthy roots of the mangrove <lb/>plant, Xylocarpus granatum, collected from the mangrove reserve zone in Hainan Province, China [5]. <lb/>The producing strain was prepared on oatmeal agar (ISP3) medium and stored in Hong&apos;s Lab. at 4 °C. <lb/>3.3. Fermentation and Extraction <lb/>The spores of J. endophytica 161111 were directly cultured in 1000 mL Erlenmeyer flasks <lb/>containing 200 mL fermentation media consisted of glucose 2%, yeast extract 0.5%, peptone 0.5%, <lb/>KNO 3 1.5%, CaCO 3 0.4%, and NaCl 0.4% (pH 7.2). The cultures were incubated on a rotatory shaker <lb/>at 220 rpm at 28 °C for 30 days. The whole fermentation broth (100 L) was divided into three equal <lb/>parts and extracted three times with equal volumes of EtOAc separately. The whole EtOAc solutions <lb/>were combined and evaporated under reduced pressure to give a dark brown gum (10 g). <lb/>3.4. Purification and Identification <lb/>The EtOAc extract (10 g) was subjected to SiO 2 VLC, eluting with CH 2 Cl 2 -petroleum ether <lb/>(0%~100%) and then with MeOH-CH 2 Cl 2 (0%~50%), to give nine fractions (Fr.1-Fr.9). Fraction 3 <lb/>(1.31 g) was separated into three subfractions by CC over Sephadex LH-20, eluted with <lb/>MeOH/CH 2 Cl 2 (1:1). Fraction 3-3 (351 mg) was further subjected to HPLC separation eluteding with <lb/>50% MeCN/H 2 O to yield 3 (2 mg, t R 9.93 min) and 6 (1 mg, t R 10.74 min). Compound 7 (25 mg) was <lb/>purified from the precipitate of fraction 5 (512 mg) after washing with MeOH, and the filtrate <lb/>of fraction 5 was separated into five parts (Fr.5-1-Fr.5-4) by Sephadex LH-20 with CH 3 OH. <lb/>Compound 11 (3 mg, t R 6.46 min) was obtained from Fr.5-4 (71 mg) by HPLC purification eluting <lb/>with 60% MeOH. Fraction 4 (413 mg) was separated by CC over RP-18 to afford four subfractions <lb/>(Fr.4-1-Fr.4-5), and compounds 9 (3 mg, t R 7.3 min) and 10 (3 mg, t R 9.7 min) were obtained from <lb/>Fr.4-4 (93 mg) by HPLC purifications eluted with 60% MeOH and 50% MeOH, respectively. Fr.4-2 <lb/>(87 mg) and Fr.4-3 (77 mg) were both further separated into four parts (Fr.4-2-1-Fr.4-2-4 and <lb/>Fr.4-3-1-Fr.4-3-4) by Sephadex LH-20 with MeOH. Compounds 12 (4 mg, t R 8.97 min) and 13 (5 mg, <lb/>t R 7.6 min) were purified from Fr.4-2-2 (21 mg) and Fr.4-2-3 (17 mg) by HPLC eluting with 40% and <lb/>60% MeOH, respectively. And Fr.4-3-2 (16 mg) and Fr.4-3-3 (10 mg) were purified by HPLC eluting <lb/>with 70% MeOH to give 4 (2 mg, t R 5.3 min) and 5 (2 mg, t R 5.0 min), respectively. Fraction 7 <lb/>(414 mg) gave four parts (Fr.7-1-Fr.7-4) after subjection to CC over Sephadex LH-20 with MeOH. <lb/>Fr.7-2 (92 mg) was further purified by HPLC, with 30% MeOH, to yield the mixture (3 mg, <lb/>t R 12.33 min) of 1 and 2 by ODS column. The mixture was further purified by HPLC over C 3 column <lb/>with 25% MeOH to give pure 1 (2 mg, t R 10.08 min) and 2 (1 mg, t R 11.98 min). Compound 8 (7 mg, <lb/>t R 8.68 min) was obtained from Fr.7-3 (133 mg) by HPLC with 50% MeOH. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Mar. Drugs 2014, 12 <lb/></note>

			<page>485 <lb/></page>

			<body>2-(Furan-2-yl)-6-(2S,3S,4-trihydroxybutyl)pyrazine (1): A brown oil. [α] D <lb/>20 -11.5 (c 0.05, MeOH); <lb/>UV (MeOH) λ max (log ε) 240 (3.4), 273 (3.6), 328 (3.4) nm; CD (c 0.05, MeOH) λ ext (Δε) 310 (-0.14), <lb/>284 (+0.12), 237 (-1.3) nm; 1 H (600 MHz, MeOH-d 4 ) and 13 C NMR (150 MHz, MeOH-d 4 ), see <lb/>Table 2; HRESIMS m/z 273.0849 [M + Na] + (calcd for C 12 H 14 N 2 O 4 Na 273.0846). <lb/>Table 2. 1 H and 13 C NMR data for 1 and 2 (δ in ppm). <lb/>Position <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>δ C , Type <lb/>δ H , Mult. <lb/>(J in Hz) <lb/>δ H , Mult. <lb/>(J in Hz, -4 °C) <lb/>δ C , Type <lb/>δ H , Mult. <lb/>(J in Hz) <lb/>δ H , Mult. <lb/>(J in Hz, -4 °C) <lb/>2 <lb/>144.2, qC <lb/>142.5, qC <lb/></body>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<body>136.7, CH <lb/>8.78, s <lb/>8.79, s <lb/>138.7, CH <lb/>8.90, d, (0.7) <lb/>8.91, d, (1.0) <lb/>5 <lb/>142.7, CH <lb/>8.38, s <lb/>8.38, s <lb/>153.4, qC <lb/>6 <lb/>155.3, qC <lb/>144.3, CH <lb/>8.50, d, (0.7) <lb/>8.50, d, (1.0) <lb/>2′ <lb/>151.1, qC <lb/>151.0, qC <lb/>3′ <lb/>110.5, CH <lb/>7.23, d, (4.0) <lb/>7.25, d, 3.4 <lb/>109.9, CH <lb/>7.18, d, (3.4) <lb/>7.19,d, (3.4) <lb/>4′ <lb/>112.0, CH <lb/>6.63, dd, <lb/>(2.1, 4.0) <lb/>6.64, dd, <lb/>(1.7, 3.4) <lb/>111.9, CH <lb/>6.63, d, <lb/>(1.7, 3.4) <lb/>6.64, dd, <lb/>(1.7, 3.4) <lb/>5′ <lb/>144.6, CH <lb/>7.72, d, (2.1) <lb/>7.74, d, (1.7) <lb/>144.6, CH <lb/>7.71, d, (1.7) <lb/>7.73, d, (1.7) <lb/>1″ <lb/>38.4, CH 2 <lb/>3.24, dd, <lb/>(3.1, 14.0) <lb/>2.93, dd, <lb/>(9.4, 14.0) <lb/>3.24, dd, <lb/>(2.9, 14.0) <lb/>2.91, dd, <lb/>(9.7, 14.0) <lb/>38.3, CH 2 <lb/>3.22, dd, <lb/>(2.8, 14.0) <lb/>2.93, dd, <lb/>(9.4, 14.0) <lb/>3.22, dd, <lb/>(2.8, 14.0) <lb/>2.91, dd, <lb/>(9.5, 14.1) <lb/>2″ <lb/>71.5, CH <lb/>4.03, ddd, <lb/>(3.1, 7.0, 9.4) <lb/>4.01, ddd, <lb/>(2.9, 7.2, 9.7) <lb/>71.6, CH <lb/>3.97, ddd, <lb/>(2.8, 7.0, 9.4) <lb/>3.95, ddd, <lb/>(2.8, 7.1, 9.5) <lb/>3″ <lb/>74.8, CH <lb/>3.58, ddd, <lb/>(3.8, 7.0, 6.2) <lb/>3.57, ddd, <lb/>(3.8, 7.2, 6.5) <lb/>74.8, CH <lb/>3.57, <lb/>(3.7, 7.0, 6.5) <lb/>3.56, ddd, <lb/>(3.7, 7.1, 6.5) <lb/>4″ <lb/>63.2, CH 2 <lb/>3.80, dd, <lb/>(3.8, 11.4) <lb/>3.65, dd, <lb/>(6.2, 11.4) <lb/>3.80, dd, <lb/>(3.8, 11.2) <lb/>3.63, dd, <lb/>(6.5, 11.2) <lb/>63.2, CH 2 <lb/>3.79, dd, <lb/>(3.7, 11.3) <lb/>3.64, dd, <lb/>(6.2, 11.3) <lb/>3.78, dd, <lb/>(3.7, 11.3) <lb/>3.62, dd, <lb/>(6.5, 11.3) <lb/>2-(Furan-2-yl)-5-(2S,3S,4-trihydroxybutyl)pyrazine (2): Brown oil. [α] D <lb/>20 -11.3 (c 0.03, MeOH); <lb/>UV (MeOH) λ max (log ε) 240 (3.2), 273 (3.4), and 328 (3.1) nm; CD (c 0.05, MeOH) λ ext (Δε) 316 <lb/>(-0.54), 267 (+0.35), 235 (-1.0) nm; 1 H (600 MHz, MeOH-d 4 ) and 13 C NMR (150 MHz, MeOH-d 4 ), <lb/>see Table 2; HRESIMS m/z 273.0849 [M + Na] + (calcd for C 12 H 14 N 2 O 4 Na 273.0846). <lb/>(S)-4-Isobutyl-3-oxo-3,4-dihydro-1H-pyrrolo[2,1-c][1,4]oxazine-6-carbaldehyde (3): A brown <lb/>oil. [α] D <lb/>20 -32 (c 0.05, acetone); UV (MeOH) λ max (log ε) 254 (3.3), and 291 (3.9) nm; CD <lb/>(c 0.08, MeOH) λ max (Δε) 292 (+2.9), 248 (-1.0), 207 (+2.5) nm; 1 H (600 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) and 13 C <lb/>NMR (150 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ), see Table 1; HRESIMS m/z 222.1131 [M + H] + (calcd for <lb/>C 12 H 14 N 2 O 4 Na 222.1125). <lb/>(S)-4-Isopropyl-3-oxo-3,4-dihydro-1H-pyrrolo[2,1-c][1,4]oxazine-6-carbaldehyde (4): A brown <lb/>oil. [α] D <lb/>20 -88 (c 0.12, acetone); UV (MeOH) λ max (log ε) 254 (3.4) and 291 (4.03) nm; CD (c 0.02, <lb/>MeOH) λ max (Δε) 298 (+16.1), 290 (-1.9), 280 (+6.6), 253 (-8.9), 208 (+8.8) nm; 1 H (600 MHz, <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Mar. Drugs 2014, 12 <lb/></note>

			<page>486 <lb/></page>

			<body>DMSO-d 6 ) and 13 C NMR (150 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ), see Table 1; HRESIMS m/z 208.0974 [M + H] + <lb/>(calcd for C 12 H 14 N 2 O 4 Na 208.0968). <lb/>(4S)-4-(2-Methylbutyl)-3-oxo-3,4-dihydro-1H-pyrrolo[2,1-c][1,4]oxazine-6-carbaldehyde (5): <lb/>A brown oil; [α] D <lb/>20 -57 (c 0.06, acetone); UV (MeOH) λ max (log ε) 254 (3.6) and 291 (4.2) nm; CD <lb/>(c 0.08, MeOH) λ max (Δε) 293 (+5.8), 252 (-2.7), 208 (+3.1) nm; 1 H (600 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) and <lb/>13 C NMR (150 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ), see Table 1; HRESIMS m/z 222.1129 [M + H] + (calcd <lb/>for C 12 H 14 N 2 O 4 Na 222.1125). <lb/>(S)-4-Benzyl-3-oxo-3,4-dihydro-1H-pyrrolo[2,1-c][1,4]oxazine-6-carbaldehyde (6): A brown <lb/>oil. [α] D <lb/>20 -46 (c 0.1, acetone); UV (MeOH) λ max (log ε) 257 (3.4) and 295 (3.8) nm; CD <lb/>(c 0.02, MeOH) λ max (Δε) 293 (+13.1), 249 (-4.7), 211 (+6.8) nm; 1 H (600 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) and 13 C <lb/>NMR (150 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) see Table 1; HRESIMS m/z 256.0976 [M + H] + (calcd for <lb/>C 12 H 14 N 2 O 4 Na 256.0968). <lb/>3.5. Bioassays <lb/>The antiviral activity against H1N1 virus was evaluated by the CPE inhibition assay [45,46]. <lb/>Confluent MDCK cell monolayers were firstly incubated with influenza virus (A/Puerto Rico/8/34 <lb/>(H1N1), PR/8) at 37 °C for 1 h. After removing the virus dilution, cells were maintained in infecting <lb/>media (RPMI 1640, 4 μg/mL of trypsin) containing different concentrations of test compounds and <lb/>ribavirin (positive control) at 37 °C . After 48 h incubation at 37 °C , the cells were fixed with 100 μL of <lb/>4% formaldehyde for 20 min at room temperature. After removal of the formaldehyde, the cells were <lb/>stained with 0.1% crystal violet for 30 min. The plates were washed and dried, and the intensity of <lb/>crystal violet staining for each well was measured in a microplate reader (Bio-Rad, Hercules, CA, <lb/>USA) at 570 nm. The IC 50 was calculated as the compound concentration required inhibiting influenza <lb/>virus yield at 48 h post-infection by 50%. Ribavirin was used as the positive control with an IC 50 value <lb/>of 23.1 ± 1.7 μg/mL. <lb/>Cytotoxicity was assayed by the MTT [47]. In the MTT assay, MDCK normal cell line were <lb/>cultured in RPMI-1640, supplemented with 10% FBS, under a humidified atmosphere of 5% CO 2 and <lb/>95% air at 37 °C, cell suspensions with a density of 4.6 × 10 4 cells/mL (198 μL) was plated in 96-well <lb/>microtiter plates and incubated for 24 h. Then, the test solutions in MeOH (2 μL) were added to each <lb/>well and further incubated for 36 h. The MTT solution (20 µL, 5 mg/mL in RPMI-1640 medium) was <lb/>then added to each well and incubated for 4 h. Old medium containing MTT (150 μL) was then gently <lb/>replaced by dimethylsulfoxide (DMSO) and pipetted to dissolve any formazan crystals formed. <lb/>Absorbance was then determined on a Spectra Max Plus plate reader at 570 nm. Ribavirin was used as <lb/>positive control (CC 50 744.2 ± 18.5 μg/mL for MDCK normal cell line). <lb/>4. Conclusions <lb/>A new pyrazine derivative, 2-(furan-2-yl)-6-(2S,3S,4-trihydroxybutyl)pyrazine (1), was isolated <lb/>and identified from the fermentation products of Jishengella endophytica 161111 endophytic <lb/>with mangrove plant, Xylocarpus granatum (Meliaceae). The absolute configurations and the key <lb/>reference data of [α] D , CD and 13 C NMR of 2-(furan-2-yl)-5-(2S,3S,4-trihydroxybutyl)pyrazine (2), <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Mar. Drugs 2014, 12 <lb/></note>

			<page>487 <lb/></page>

			<body>(S)-4-isobutyl-3-oxo-3,4-dihydro-1H-pyrrolo[2,1-c][1,4]oxazine-6-carbaldehyde (3), (S)-4-isopropyl-<lb/>3-oxo-3,4-dihydro-1H-pyrrolo[2,1-c][1,4]oxazine-6-carbaldehyde (4), and (4S)-4-(2-methylbutyl)-3-oxo-3, <lb/>4-dihydro-1H-pyrrolo[2,1-c][1,4]oxazine-6-carbaldehyde (5) were reported here for the first time. In <lb/>addition, β-carboline alkaloid 9 exhibited moderate anti-H1N1 virus activity and weak cytotoxicity. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgments <lb/>This work was financially supported by the grants from 973 Program of China (No. 2010CB833804), <lb/>from NSFC (Nos. 41376148, 21172204, 81373298 &amp; 31170467), from 863 Program of China <lb/>(Nos. 2013AA092901, 2012AA092104 and 2011AA09070106), and from the Special Fund for Marine <lb/>Scientific Research in the Public Interest of China (No. 2010418022-3). The authors are grateful to <lb/>Haipeng Lin (Institute of Tropical Biosiences and Biotechnology) for his help on preparing the crude <lb/>extracts from the 100 L fermentation broth. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Conflicts of Interest <lb/>The authors declare no conflict of interest. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>1. Bandaranayake, W.M. Bioactivities, bioactive compounds and chemical constituents of mangrove <lb/>Plants. Wetl. Ecol. Manag. 2002, 10, 421-452. <lb/>2. Hong, K.; Gao, A.H.; Xie, Q.Y.; Gao, H.; Zhuang, L.; Lin, H.P.; Yu, H.P.; Li, J.; Yao, X.S.; <lb/>Goodfellow, M.; et al. Actinomycetes for marine drug discovery isolated from mangrove soils <lb/>and plants in China. Mar. Drugs 2009, 7, 24-44. <lb/>3. Fu, P.; Yang, C.L.; Wang, Y.; Liu, P.P.; Ma, Y.M.; Xu, L.; Su, M.B.; Hong, K.; Zhu, W.M. <lb/>Streptocarbazoles A and B, two novel indolocarbazoles from the marine-derived actinomycete <lb/>strain Streptomyces sp. F MA. Org. Lett. 2012, 14, 2422-2425. <lb/>4. Ara, I.; Kudo, T.; Matsumoto, A.; Takahashi, Y.; Omura, S. Nonomuraea maheshkhaliensis sp. <lb/>nov., a novel actinomycete isolated from mangrove rhizosphere mud. J. Gen. Appl. Microbiol. <lb/>2007, 53, 159-166. <lb/>5. Xie, Q.Y.; Wang, C.; Wang, R.; Qu, Z.; Lin, H.P.; Goodfellow, M.; Hong, K. Jishengella endophytica <lb/>gen. nov., sp. nov., a new member of the family Micromonosporaceae. Int. J. Syst. Evol. <lb/>Microbiol. 2011, 61, 1153-1159. <lb/>6. Wu, X.A.; Zhao, Y.M.; Yu, N.J. A novel analgesic pyrazine derivative from the leaves of <lb/>Croton tiglium L. J. Asian Nat. Prod. Res. 2007, 9, 451-455. <lb/>7. Ding, Z.G.; Zhao, J.Y.; Yang, P.W.; Li, M.G.; Huang, R.; Cui, X.L.; Wen, M.L. 1 H and 13 C NMR <lb/>assignments of eight nitrogen containing compounds from Nocardia alba sp.nov (YIM 30243 T ). <lb/>Magn. Reson. Chem. 2009, 47, 366-370. <lb/>8. Sannai, Y.; Fujimori, T.; Kato, K. Studies on flavor components of roasted chicory root. <lb/>Agric. Biol. Chem. 1982, 46, 429-433. <lb/>9. Tressl, R.; Nittka, C.; Kersten, E. Formation of isoleucine-specific maillard products from <lb/>[l-13 C]-D-glucose and [l-13 C]-D-fructose. J. Agric. Food Chem. 1995, 43, 1163-1169. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Mar. Drugs 2014, 12 <lb/></note>

			<page>488 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>10. Jeric, I.; Simicic, L.; Stipetic, M.; Horvat, S. Synthesis and reactivity of the monosaccharide esters <lb/>of amino acids as models of teichoic acid fragment. Glycoconj. J. 2000, 17, 273-282. <lb/>11. Su, B.N.; Chang, L.C.; Park, E.J.; Cuendet, M.; Santarsiero, B.D.; Mesecar, A.D.; Mehta, R.G.; <lb/>Fong, H.H.S.; Pezzuto, J.M.; Kinghorn, A.D. Bioactive constituents of the seeds of Brucea javanica. <lb/>Planta Med. 2002, 68, 730-733. <lb/>12. Dassonneville, B.; Witulski, B.; Detert, H. [2+2+2] Cycloadditions of alkynylynamides-A total <lb/>synthesis of perlolyrine and the first total synthesis of -isoperlolyrine‖. Eur. J. Org. Chem. 2011, <lb/>2011, 2836-2844. <lb/>13. Jiao, W.H.; Gao, H.; Li, C.Y.; Zhou, G.X.; Kitanaka, S.; Ohmura, A.; Yao, X.S. β-Carboline <lb/>alkaloids from the stems of Picrasma quassioides. Magn. Reson. Chem. 2010, 48, 490-495. <lb/>14. Ashour, M.A.; Elkhayat, E.S.; Ebel, R.; Edrada, R.; Proksch, P. Indole alkaloid from the red sea <lb/>sponge Hyrtios erectus. Arkivoc 2007, 2007, 225-231. <lb/>15. Yang, S.W.; Cordell, G.A. Metabolism studies of indole derivatives using a staurosporine <lb/>producer, Streptomyces staurosporeus. J. Nat. Prod. 1997, 60, 44-48. <lb/>16. Don, M.J.; Shen, C.C.; Lin, Y.L.; Syu, W.J.; Ding, Y.H.; Sun, C.M. Nitrogen-containing <lb/>compounds from Salvia miltiorrhiza. J. Nat. Prod. 2005, 68, 1066-1070. <lb/>17. Duran, R.; Zubia, E.; Ortega, M.J.; Naranjo, S.; Salva, J. Novel alkaloids from the red ascidian <lb/>Botryllus leachi. Tetrahedron 1999, 55, 13225-13232. <lb/>18. Takahashi, Y.; Iinuma, Y.; Kubota, T.; Tsuda, M.; Sekiguchi, M.; Mikami, Y.; Fromont, J.; <lb/>Kobayash, J. Hyrtioseragamines A and B, new alkaloids from the sponge Hyrtios species. <lb/>Org. Lett. 2011, 13, 628-631. <lb/>19. Pettit, G.R.; Inoue, M.; Kamano, Y.; Herald, D.L.; Arm, C.; Dufresne, C.; Christie, N.D.; <lb/>Schmidt, J.M.; Doubek, D.L.; Krupa, T.S. Isolation and structure of the powerful cell growth <lb/>inhibitor cephalostatin 1. J. Am. Chem. Soc. 1988, 110, 2006-2007. <lb/>20. Pettit, G.R.; Tan, R.; Xu, J.P.; Ichihara, Y.; Williams, M.D.; Boyd, M.R. Antineoplastic agents. 398. <lb/>Isolation and structure elucidation of cephalostatins 18 and 19. J. Nat. Prod. 1998, 61, 955-958. <lb/>21. Pettit, G.R.; Xu, J.P.; Williams, M.D.; Christie, N.D.; Doubek, D.L.; Schmidt, J.M. Isolation and <lb/>structure of cephalostatins 10 and 11. J. Nat. Prod. 1994, 57, 52-63. <lb/>22. Zhou, Y.; Wu, J.; Zou, K. Xylogranatinin, a new pyrido[1, 2-a] pyrazine alkaloid from the fruit of <lb/>a chinese mangrove Xylocarpus granatum. Chem. Nat. Compd. 2007, 43, 426-428. <lb/>23. Zhu, F.; Chen, G.Y.; Chen, X.; Huang, M.Z.; Wan, X.Q. Aspergicin, a new antibacterial <lb/>alkaloid produced by mixed fermentation of two marine-derived mangrove epiphytic fungi. <lb/>Chem. Nat. Compd. 2011, 47, 767-769. <lb/>24. Yang, J.X.; Huang, R.M.; Qiu, S.X.; She, Z.G.; Lin, Y.C. A new isobenzofuranone from the <lb/>mangrove endophytic fungus Penicillium sp. (ZH58). Nat. Prod. Res. 2013, 27, 1902-1905. <lb/>25. Ishida, J.; Wang, H.K.; Bastow, K.F.; Hu, C.Q.; Lee, K.H. Antitumor agents 201. 1 Cytotoxicity <lb/>of harmine and β-carboline analogs. Bioorg. Med. Chem. Lett. 1999, 9, 3319-3324. <lb/>26. Wang, Y.H.; Tang, J.G.; Wang, R.R.; Yang, L.M.; Dong, Z.J.; Du, L.; Shen, X.; Liu, J.K.; <lb/>Zheng, Y.T. Flazinamide, a novelb-carboline compound with anti-HIV actions. Biochem. Biophys. <lb/>Res. Commun. 2007, 355, 1091-1095. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Mar. Drugs 2014, 12 <lb/></note>

			<page>489 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>27. Rinehart, K.L., Jr.; Kobayashi, J.; Harbour, G.C.; Hughes, R.G., Jr.; Mizsak, S.A.; Scahil, T.A. <lb/>Eudistomins C, E, K, and L, potent antiviral compounds containing a novel oxathiazepine ring <lb/>from the caribbean tunicate Eudistoma olivaceum. J. Am. Chem. Soc. 1984, 106, 1524-1526. <lb/>28. Hee Jae, S.; Lee, H.S.; Lee, D.S. The synergistic antibacterial activity of 1-acetyl-β-carboline and <lb/>β-lactams against methicillin-resistant Staphylococcus aureus(MRSA). J. Microbiol. Biotechnol. <lb/>2010, 20, 501-505. <lb/>29. Rao, K.V.; Santarsiero, B.D.; Mesecar, A.D.; Schinazi, R.F.; Tekwani, B.L.; Hamann, M.T. <lb/>New manzamine alkaloids with activity against infectious and tropical parasitic diseases from an <lb/>indonesian sponge. J. Nat. Prod. 2003, 66, 823-828. <lb/>30. Li, L.; Cui, G.H.; Zhao, M.; Wang, Y.J.; Wang, H.; Li, W.; Peng, S.Q. Assembly of <lb/>β-cyclodextrin with 3S-tetrahydro-β-carboline-3-carboxylic acid and self-assembly of <lb/>6-(3′S-carboline-3′-carboxylamino ethylamino)-6-deoxy-β-cyclodextrin: Approaches to enhance <lb/>anti-oxidation stability and anti-thrombotic potency. J. Phys. Chem. B 2008, 112, 12139-12147. <lb/>31. Ding, L.; Dahse, H.M.; Hertweck, C. Cytotoxic alkaloids from Fusarium incarnatum associated <lb/>with the mangrove tree Aegiceras corniculatum. J. Nat. Prod. 2012, 75, 617-621. <lb/>32. Sandler, J.S.; Colin, P.L.; Hooper, J.N.A.; John Faulkner, D. Cytotoxic β-carbolines and cyclic <lb/>Peroxides from the palauan sponge Plakortis nigra. J. Nat. Prod. 2002, 65, 1258-1261. <lb/>33. Schupp, P.; Poehner, T.; Edrada, R.; Ebel, R.; Berg, A.; Wray, V.; Proksch, P. Eudistomins W and <lb/>X, two new β-carbolines from the micronesian tunicate Eudistoma sp. J. Nat. Prod. 2003, 66, <lb/>272-275. <lb/>34. Wang, W.H.; Nam, S.J.; Lee, B.C.; Kang, H. β-carboline alkaloids from a korean tunicate <lb/>Eudistoma sp. J. Nat. Prod. 2008, 71, 163-166. <lb/>35. Marisa, T.; Michele, R.P. 5-bromo-8-methoxy-1-methyl-β-carboline, an alkaloid from the New <lb/>Zealand marine bryozoan Pterocella Wesiculosa. J. Nat. Prod. 2009, 72, 796-798. <lb/>36. Harwood, D.T.; Urban, S.; Blunt, J.W.; Munro, M.H.G. β-carboline alkaloids from a new zealand <lb/>marine bryozoan, Cribricellina Cribraria. Nat. Prod. Res. 2003, 17, 15-19. <lb/>37. Cabrera, G.M.; Seldes, A.M. A β-carboline alkaloid from the soft coral Lignopsis spongiosum. <lb/>J. Nat. Prod. 1999, 62, 759-760. <lb/>38. Penez, N.; Culioli, G.; Perez, T.; Briand, J.F.; Thomas, O.P.; Blache, Y. Antifouling properties of <lb/>simple indole and purine alkaloids from the mediterranean gorgonian Paramuricea clavata. <lb/>J. Nat. Prod. 2011, 74, 2304-2308. <lb/>39. Huang, H.B.; Yao, Y.L.; He, Z.X.; Yang, T.T.; Ma, J.Y.; Tian, X.P.; Li, Y.Y.; Huang, C.G.; <lb/>Chen, X.P.; Li, W.J.; et al. Antimalarial β-carboline and indolactam alkaloids from <lb/>Marinactinospora thermotolerans, a deep sea isolate. J. Nat. Prod. 2011, 74, 2122-2127. <lb/>40. Zheng, L.; Chen, H.M.; Han, X.T.; Lin, W.; Yan, X.J. Antimicrobial screening and active <lb/>compound isolation from marine bacterium NJ6-3-1 associated with the sponge Hymeniacidon <lb/>perleve. World J. Microbol. Biotechnol. 2005, 21, 201-206. <lb/>41. Seeman, J.I.; Paine, J.B., III; Secor, H.V.; Im, H.S.; Bernstein, E.R. Supersonic jet studies of alkyl <lb/>substituted pyrazines and pyridines. Minimum-energy conformations and torsional motion. J. Am. <lb/>Chem. Soc. 1992, 114, 5269-5280. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Mar. Drugs 2014, 12 <lb/></note>

			<page>490 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>42. Matsumori, N.; Kaneno, D.; Murata, M.; Nakamura, H.; Tachibana, K. Stereochemical <lb/>determination of acyclic structures based on carbon-proton spin-coupling constants. A method of <lb/>configuration analysis for natural products. J. Org. Chem. 1999, 64, 866-876. <lb/>43. Stephens, P.J.; Pan, J.J. Determination of the absolute configurations of pharmacological natural <lb/>products via density functional theory calculations of vibrational circular dichroism: The new <lb/>cytotoxic iridoid prismatomerin. J. Org. Chem. 2007, 72, 7641-7649. <lb/>44. Jexkings, J.P.; Klyne, W.; Scope, P.M. Optical rotatory dispersion. Part XXIV. Lactones. <lb/>J. Chem. Soc. 1965, 7211-7229; doi:10.1039/JR9650007211. <lb/>45. Grassauer, A.; Weinmuellner, R.; Meier, C.; Pretsch, A.; Prieschl-Grassauer, E.; Unger, H. <lb/>Iota-carrageenan is a potent inhibitor of rhinovirus infection. Virol. J. 2008, 5, 107. <lb/>46. Hung, H.C.; Tseng, C.P.; Yang, J.M.; Ju, Y.W.; Tseng, S.N.; Chen, Y.F.; Chao, Y.S.; Hsieh, H.P.; <lb/>Shih, S.R.; Hsu, J.T. Aurintricarboxylic acid inhibits influenza virus neuraminidase. Antivir. Res. <lb/>2009, 81, 123-131. <lb/>47. Mosmann, T. Rapid colorimetric assay for cellular growth and survival: Application to <lb/>proliferation and cytotoxicity assays. J. Immunol. Methods 1983, 65, 55-63. <lb/>48. Tang, J.G.; Wang, Y.H.; Wang, R.R.; Dong, Z.J.; Yang, L.M.; Zheng, Y.T.; Liu, J.K. Synthesis of <lb/>analogues of flazin, in particular, flazinamide, as promising anti-HIV agents. Chem. Biodivers. <lb/>2008, 5, 447-460. <lb/>49. Nazari Formagio, A.S.; Santos, P.R.; Zanoli, K.; Ueda-Nakamura, T.; Dusman Tonin, L.T.; <lb/>Nakamura, C.V.; Sarragiotto, M.H. Synthesis and antiviral activity of β-carboline derivatives <lb/>bearing a substituted carbohydrazide at C-3 against poliovirus and herpes simplex virus (HSV-1). <lb/>Eur. J. Med. Chem. 2009, 44, 4695-4701. <lb/>50. Van Maarseveen, J.H.; Scheeren, H.W.; Clercq, E.D.; Balzarini, J.; Kruse, C.G. Antiviral and <lb/>Ttumor cell antiproliferative SAR studies on tetracyclic eudistomins II. Bioorg. Med. Chem. 1997, <lb/>5, 955-970. <lb/>51. Van Maameveen, J.H.; Hermkens, P.H.H.; Clercq, E.D.; Balzarini, J.; Scheeren, H.W.; Kruse, C.G. <lb/>Antiviral and antitumor structure-activity relationship studies on tetracyclic eudistomines. <lb/>J. Med. Chem. 1992, 35, 3223-3230. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="footnote">© 2014 by the authors; licensee MDPI, Basel, Switzerland. This article is an open access article <lb/>distributed under the terms and conditions of the Creative Commons Attribution license <lb/>(http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/). </note>


	</text>
</tei>