<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>1 <lb/>Scientific RepoRts | 6:39815 | DOI: 10.1038/srep39815 <lb/>www.nature.com/scientificreports <lb/>New Formyl Phloroglucinol <lb/>Meroterpenoids from the Leaves of <lb/>Eucalyptus robusta <lb/>Zhi-Chun Shang * , Ming-Hua Yang * , Rui-Huan Liu, Xiao-Bing Wang &amp; Ling-Yi Kong <lb/>Seven new formyl phloroglucinol meroterpenoids (FPMs), namely eucalrobusones J-P (1-7), as well <lb/>as three known ones (8-10) were isolated from the leaves of Eucalyptus robusta. Their structures were <lb/>elucidated by spectroscopic data analysis, and their absolute configurations were determined by <lb/>applications of the Snatzke&apos;s helicity rule and the electron circular dichroism (ECD) calculation. These <lb/>FPMs are diverse in coupling patterns between phloroglucinol and sesquiterpenoid units, forming novel <lb/>polycyclic ring systems. Compound 1 possesses a new carbon skeleton that a 1-oxaspiro[5.6]dodecane <lb/>core is formed through C-14 rather than C-4 of the aromadendrane moiety. Compound 2 features a <lb/>novel 6/7/5 ring-fused 6-oxabicyclo[3.2.2]nonane skeleton. Compounds 3-5 are rare aristolane-based <lb/>FPMs. By forming different oxo bridges, compound 3 is the first sample of FPM with benzo-dihydrofuran <lb/>structure, and compound 4 possesses a novel 6/6/6/6/3-fused pentacyclic skeleton. Compounds 1, 6, and <lb/>8 exhibited significant antifungal activities against Candida glabrata with MIC 50 values of 2.57, 1.95, and <lb/>2.49 μg/mL, respectively. <lb/></front>

			<body>In recent years, phloroglucinol derivatives have been a hot research topic of natural products, not only because <lb/>of their numerous bioactivities, such as anti-HIV 1 , antimicrobial 2 , and antitumor 3 effects, but also due to their <lb/>diversified skeletons with highly complex polycyclic systems and multiple chiral centers 4-6 . Formyl phloro-<lb/>glucinol meroterpenoids (FPMs) are important derivatives of phloroglucinol. Through hetero Diels-Alder <lb/>reaction 6-8 or nucleophilic addition 9-11 , phloroglucinol of FPMs could couple with different terpene moieties, <lb/>mainly forming dihydropyran-fused or open-chain structures. In addition, reaction at the active sites of phloro-<lb/>glucinol (C-7′ /C-12′ /OH-3′ ) could also generate other coupling patterns, such as macrocarpal A 1 , eucalrobu-<lb/>sone A 10 , and eucalyptal A 11 . In our continuous 1 H NMR-guided isolation 10 , ten FPMs (Fig. 1) with various <lb/>spiro-heterocycles and polycyclic systems were isolated from the leaves of Eucalyptus robusta. These FPMs feature <lb/>various oxa-heterocyclic systems with five-to eight-membered rings due to different coupling patterns between <lb/>phloroglucinol and sesquiterpenoid units. Within FPMs, 1 and 3 are novel oxaspiro compounds. The unprece-<lb/>dented 1-oxaspiro[5.6]dodecane subunit that constituted through C-10/C-14 of aromadendrane, makes 1 a new <lb/>carbon skeleton; the 1-oxaspiro[4.5]decane subunit in 3 also gives the first sample of forming dihydrofuran ring <lb/>between two moieties. Compound 2 is a guaiane based FPM, in which the two rare oxo bridges between C-3′ /C-6 <lb/>and C-10/C-11 lead to an unusual polycyclic ring system. Compounds 3-5 are rare aristolane-based FPMs that <lb/>only two examples were reported before 12 . In addition, these natural products showed different antifungal activi-<lb/>ties against Candida albicans and C. glabrata. Compounds 1, 6, and 8 showed the most potent antifungal activities <lb/>against C. glabrata with MIC 50 values of 2.57, 1.95, and 2.49 μg/mL, respectively. Herein, we report the isolation <lb/>and structure elucidation of these FPMs, as well as their antifungal activities. <lb/>Results and Discussion <lb/>Structure elucidation. Eucalrobusone J (1) gave an HRESIMS ion at m/z 453.2648 [M-H] -, consistent with <lb/>the molecular formula of C 28 H 38 O 5 . In its NMR data (Tables 1 and 2), the characteristic formyl phloroglucinol <lb/>moiety was found, especially due to the chelated phenolic hydroxyls (δ H 13.31 and 13.46, each 1H, s) and formyls <lb/>(δ H 10.03, 1H, s, δ C 192.5 and δ H 10.14, 1H, s, δ C 191.9). Two secondary methyls (δ H 0.94, 3H, d, J = 6.3 Hz and <lb/>δ H 0.99, 3 H, d, J = 6.3 Hz) and the key HMBC correlations from Me-10′ to C-11′ , from Me-11′ to C-8′ , and from <lb/>H-9′ to C-7′ constructed an isoamyl moiety. The remaining 15 carbons that contained three methyls (δ H 0.93, <lb/> </body>
			
			<front>State Key Laboratory of Natural Medicines, Department of Natural Medicinal Chemistry, China Pharmaceutical <lb/>University, 24 Tong Jia Xiang, Nanjing 210009, People&apos; s Republic of China. * These authors contributed equally to <lb/>this work. Correspondence and requests for materials should be addressed to L.-Y.K. (email: cpu_lykong@126.com) <lb/>Received: 06 October 2016 <lb/>accepted: 28 November 2016 <lb/>Published: 22 December 2016 <lb/>OPEN <lb/></front>

			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificreports/ <lb/></note>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Scientific RepoRts | 6:39815 | DOI: 10.1038/srep39815 <lb/></note>

			<body>1.02, and 1.04, each 3H) revealed a sesquiterpenoid moiety in 1. An aromadendrane-type sesquiterpenoid moi-<lb/>ety was established by 2D NMR analyses (Fig. 2): the 1 H-1 H COSY spectrum gave one spin system (C-1 to C-9) <lb/>and the key HMBC correlations from Me-12 to C-6/C-7, from H 2 -3/H-5 to C-15, and from H-5/H 2 -8 to C-10 <lb/>revealed the skeleton. Moreover, the obvious downfield shift of C-10 (δ C 86.5) and the HMBC correlations from <lb/>H 2 -14 to C-7′ /C-8′ /C-1/C-9 and from H-7′ to C-10 revealed the novel coupling pattern of two moieties, which <lb/>was named the oxa-spiro [5.6] ring. The relative configuration of 1 was established by the ROESY spectrum. The <lb/>key correlations (Fig. 2) of H-7′ /H-2β and H-14β/H-5 indicated that H-7′ and H-2β were closely proximate in <lb/>space and that the two planes of dihydropyran and tetrahydrooxepine rings were in a vertically approximate <lb/>manner. The ROESY correlations of H-5/H-8β, H-7/H-8α, Me-12/H-5, Me-15/H-6, and H-6/H-1 indicated the <lb/>α-orientations of H-1, H-6, and H-7 and the β-orientations of H-4 and H-5. The absolute configuration was <lb/>determined by application of the Snatzke&apos;s helicity rule 10,13-16 . The P/M-helicity of the dihydropyran ring in FPMs <lb/>controlled the signs of Cotton effects approximately between 270-310 nm (Fig. 6). Therefore, the negative Cotton <lb/>effect at 310 nm (Δ ε = -2.97, Fig. 6A) assigned the 10S and 7′ R configurations. <lb/>Eucalrobusone K (2), C 28 H 36 O 6 , was also a phloroglucinol-sesquiterpene adduct. The comprehensive analysis <lb/>of NMR data (Tables 1 and 2) verified its modified guaiane-type moiety. The 1 H-1 H COSY spectrum established <lb/>two spin systems (C-2 to C-3 and C-6 to C-9), and the HMBC correlations from Me-14 to C-1 and from Me-15 <lb/>to C-5 located a tetrasubstituted double bond at Δ 1(5) . The key HMBC correlations (Fig. 3) of H 2 -8 with C-6/C-<lb/>10/C-11, of Me-15 with C-3/C-4/C-5/C-7′ , of Me-13 with C-12/C-11/C-7, and of Me-14 with C-1/C-9/C-10 <lb/>subsequently confirmed the carbon skeleton of its sesquiterpene moiety, which coupled with the isoamyl through <lb/>the C-7′ -C-4 bond. Meanwhile, the remaining two degrees of unsaturation and the observed four oxygenated car-<lb/>bons at C-3′ , C-6, C-10, and C-11 (δ C 168.4, 85.8, 71.2, and 74.6, respectively) revealed that there were two oxygen <lb/>bridges in 2. The diagnostic downfield shift of C-6 (δ C 85.8) revealed its ether linkage to the deshielding benzene <lb/>ring 10,11,17 , and consequently the oxygen bridge between C-10 and C-11 was established to fulfil the unsaturated <lb/>degree 18 . The ROESY correlations (Fig. 3) of H-6/H-8′ a, H-6/Me-15, H-6/H-8β, H-8α/Me-12, and H-12′ /H-7 <lb/>revealed the α-oriented H-7′ and the β-oriented H-6, H-7, Me-14, and Me-15. In order to determine its absolute <lb/>configuration, quantum chemical electron circular dichroism (ECD) calculation was applied 10,17 , and indicated <lb/>the 4R, 6R, 7R, 10S, and 7′ R configurations (Figure S1). <lb/>Eucalrobusone L (3) was assigned the molecular formula of C 28 H 38 O 5 according to its pseudomolecular ion <lb/>peak at m/z 453.2650 [M-H] -. Analysis of NMR data (Tables 1 and 2) also established the formyl phlorogluci-<lb/>nol moiety. The existence of two spin systems (C-2 to C-15 and C-6 to C-10) and the key HMBC correlations <lb/>from Me-12 to C-6/C-7, from Me-14 to C-4/C-6/C-10, and from H-2/H-3/H-10 to C-1 (Fig. 4) established the <lb/>aristolane-type sesquiterpene moiety. The HMBC correlations from H 2 -8′ to C-1, from H-7′ to C-10, and from <lb/>H 2 -2 to C-7′ established that the two moieties were coupled through the C-7′ -C-1 bond. However, the two moie-<lb/>ties only occupied nine degrees of unsaturation. The remained one degree of unsaturation and the very downfield <lb/>shift of C-1 (δ C 98.9) revealed the oxa-spiro [4.5] ring between above two moieties 10,11 . The two moieties were <lb/>arranged in an approximately vertical manner by the key ROESY correlations (Fig. 4) of H-7′ /H-10 and H-8′ <lb/>a/H-2α. Subsequently, the ROESY correlations of H-6/Me-14, H-6/Me-13, H-6/H-10, and H-4/Me-12 assigned <lb/>the β-oriented H-4 and the α-oriented H-6, H-7, H-10, Me-14, and H-7′ . The absolute configuration of 3 was <lb/>determined as 1R, 4R, 5R, 6S, 7R, 10S, and 7′ S based on the ECD calculation (Figure S1). <lb/>Figure 1. Structures of compounds 1-10. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificreports/ <lb/></note>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Scientific RepoRts | 6:39815 | DOI: 10.1038/srep39815 <lb/></note>

			<body>Careful analysis of NMR data (Tables 1 and 2) revealed that eucalrobusone M (4) had the very similar <lb/>structure to 3. However, the oxidized C-10 (δ C 87.5) and 2D NMR correlations (Fig. 5) confirmed that the oxo <lb/>bridge was between C-10 and C-3′ in 4, led to an unusual 6/6/6/6/3 ring system. Another difference was the <lb/>β-orientation of H-7′ , which was assigned by the key ROESY correlations of H-7′ /H-9β and H-1/H-9β. The other <lb/>relative configurations of the chiral centers were determined the same as those of 3, due to the ROESY correla-<lb/>tions (Fig. 5). According to the Snatzke&apos;s helicity rule, the absolute configurations of C-1, C-10, and C-7′ in 4 were <lb/>assigned as 1R, 10S, and 7′ S by ECD spectrum, in which positive Cotton effect at 295 nm (Δ ε = + 6.67, Fig. 6B) <lb/>was observed 10 . <lb/>Eucalrobusone N (5) had the molecular formula C 28 H 38 O 5 that was determined by HRESIMS analysis <lb/>([M-H] -, m/z 453.2645). Its NMR data (Tables 1 and 2) showed similarity to those of eucarobustol A 12 . The only <lb/>difference between them was the location of double bond which was assigned between C-1 and C-10 in 5 by the <lb/>HMBC correlations from H-7′ to C-2/C-10, from H 2 -8′ to C-1, and from H-2/H-6/H 2 -8/Me-14 to C-10. The <lb/>ROESY correlations of H-6/Me-14, H-6/Me-13, H-6/H-7, and H-4/Me-12 established the same configuration <lb/>of aristolane moiety to those of 3 and 4. Obviously, 5 was the precursor of 3 and 4, which therefore assigned the <lb/>same absolute configurations of aristolane moiety. Meanwhile, the shielding effect of the benzene ring resulted <lb/>in the diagnostically upfield shifted Me-14 (δ H 1.02), which occurred under the condition of 7′ S configuration <lb/>(Figure S2) 4 . <lb/>The NMR data (Tables 1 and 2) analysis revealed that eucalrobusones O-P (6-7) were two FPMs of the same <lb/>carbon skeleton with euglobal-III 19 , possessing germacrane-type moieties. Yet the Me-15 existed as terminal <lb/>double bond in both 6 and 7 due to the HMBC correlations from H 2 -3 to C-15 and from H 2 -2/H-6 to C-4. <lb/>Furthermore, the hydroxylation of C-5 (δ C 72.6) in 6 was revealed by the HMBC correlations from H-5 to C-3/C-<lb/>7/C-15, while the carbonylation of C-5 (δ C 203.7) in 7 was established by the HMBC correlations from H 2 -3/H-7/ <lb/>H 2 -15 to C-5. Both of their relative configurations were consistent with euglobal-III, and the H-5 in 6 was elu-<lb/>cidated as β-orientation by the key ROESY correlations of H-5/Me-12, H-7/Me-13, and H-5/H-15a. The abso-<lb/>lute configurations of C-1, C-10, and C-7′ in 6 and 7 were assigned as 1R, 10S, and 7′ S by the application of the <lb/>Snatzke&apos;s helicity rule (Fig. 6C,D). <lb/>no. <lb/>1 a <lb/>2 a <lb/>3 a <lb/>4 a <lb/>5 b <lb/>6 a <lb/>7 a <lb/>1 <lb/>2.27, dd (17.2, 8.3) <lb/>2.27, m <lb/>2.05, m <lb/>1.92, m <lb/>2α <lb/>1.30, m <lb/>2.28 c , m <lb/>1.98, m <lb/>1.63, m <lb/>2.22, m <lb/>1.88, m <lb/>2.00, m <lb/>2β <lb/>1.67, m <lb/>2.61, m <lb/>1.67, m <lb/>1.19 c , m <lb/>2.13, m <lb/>1.64, m <lb/>1.34 c , m <lb/>3α <lb/>1.27, m <lb/>2.11, m <lb/>1.66, m <lb/>1.35 c , m (2 H) <lb/>1.32 c , m (2 H) <lb/>2.60, m <lb/>2.82, br t (12.4) <lb/>3β <lb/>1.62, m <lb/>1.68, m <lb/>1.50, m <lb/>2.22, ddd (12.3, 9.1, 1.9) <lb/>2.23, m <lb/>4 <lb/>2.02, m <lb/>1.58, m <lb/>1.77, m <lb/>1.70, m <lb/>5 <lb/>1.36 c , m <lb/>3.86, d (10.6) <lb/>6 <lb/>0.61, br t <lb/>4.46, br s <lb/>0.40, d (9.6) <lb/>0.62, d (9.8) <lb/>0.59, d (9.2) <lb/>0.90, m <lb/>2.27, d (10.1) <lb/>7 <lb/>0.70, m <lb/>2.29, m <lb/>0.73, td (9.6, 3.4) <lb/>0.95 c , m <lb/>0.79, m <lb/>0.68, m <lb/>1.34 c , m <lb/>8α <lb/>1.87, m <lb/>2.28 c , m <lb/>2.03, m <lb/>1.92, m <lb/>1.99, m <lb/>1.75, m <lb/>1.61, m <lb/>8β <lb/>0.99 c , m <lb/>1.31, m <lb/>1.34, m <lb/>1.13, m <lb/>1.40, m <lb/>1.63, m <lb/>1.03, m <lb/>9α <lb/>1.63 c , m <lb/>1.88, m <lb/>1.17, m <lb/>1.47, m <lb/>1.86, m <lb/>2.09, m <lb/>2.06, m <lb/>9β <lb/>2.21, m <lb/>1.65, m <lb/>1.31, m <lb/>1.73, m <lb/>2.62, br dd (13.8, 3.3) <lb/>1.84, m <lb/>1.58, m <lb/>10 <lb/>1.36, m <lb/>12 d <lb/>1.02, s <lb/>1.35, s <lb/>1.18, s <lb/>1.23, s <lb/>1.04, s <lb/>1.03, s <lb/>1.30, s <lb/>13 <lb/>1.04, s <lb/>1.47, s <lb/>1.00, s <lb/>1.04, s <lb/>0.98, s <lb/>1.08, s <lb/>1.06, s <lb/>14α <lb/>1.80, m <lb/>1.28, s <lb/>1.15, s <lb/>1.19 c , s <lb/>1.02, s <lb/>1.42, s <lb/>1.31, s <lb/>14β <lb/>2.05, m <lb/>15a <lb/>0.93, d (7.1) <lb/>0.97, s <lb/>1.02, d (6.7) <lb/>0.95 c , d (6.9) <lb/>0.96, d (6.9) <lb/>5.41, s <lb/>5.71, s <lb/>15b <lb/>5.08, s <lb/>5.50, s <lb/>7′ <lb/>3.02, m <lb/>3.21, dd (11.2, 2.5) 3.29, dd (8.1, 4.7) <lb/>2.85, m <lb/>4.26, dd (10.1, 6.5) <lb/>3.02, m <lb/>3.05, m <lb/>8′ a <lb/>1.63 c , m <lb/>1.84, m <lb/>1.69, m <lb/>2.37, m <lb/>2.05, m <lb/>1.48, m <lb/>1.49, m <lb/>8′ b <lb/>1.36 c , m <lb/>1.41, m <lb/>1.52, m <lb/>1.23, m <lb/>1.25, m <lb/>1.38, m <lb/>1.34 c , m <lb/>9′ <lb/>1.71, m <lb/>1.15, m <lb/>1.70, m <lb/>1.67, m <lb/>1.38, m <lb/>1.80, m <lb/>1.85, m <lb/>10′ <lb/>0.99 c , d (6.3) <lb/>0.88, d (6.5) <lb/>0.96, d (5.5) <lb/>0.97, d (6.5) <lb/>0.86, d (6.5) <lb/>0.99, d (6.4) <lb/>0.97, d (6.4) <lb/>11′ <lb/>0.94, d (6.3) <lb/>0.79, d (6.5) <lb/>0.95, d (5.5) <lb/>0.94, d (6.5) <lb/>0.84, d (6.5) <lb/>0.87, d (6.4) <lb/>0.88, d (6.4) <lb/>12′ <lb/>10.03, s <lb/>10.11, s <lb/>9.84, s <lb/>10.01, s <lb/>9.89 c , s <lb/>9.99, s <lb/>9.96, s <lb/>13′ <lb/>10.14, s <lb/>10.27, s <lb/>10.10, s <lb/>10.12, s <lb/>9.89 c , s <lb/>10.15, s <lb/>10.15, s <lb/>OH-1′ <lb/>13.31, s <lb/>13.27, s <lb/>13.04, s <lb/>13.65, s <lb/>13.32, s <lb/>13.30, s <lb/>OH-5′ <lb/>13.46, s <lb/>13.21, s <lb/>12.81, s <lb/>13.39, s <lb/>13.43, s <lb/>13.42, s <lb/>Table 1. 1 H NMR data for compounds 1-7 (500 MHz, J in Hz). a Measured in CDCl 3 . b Measured in CD 3 OD. <lb/>c <lb/>Overlapped. d β-oriented. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificreports/ <lb/></note>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Scientific RepoRts | 6:39815 | DOI: 10.1038/srep39815 <lb/></note>

			<body>Three known FPMs, macrocarpal C 20 , eucalyptal D 17 , and euglobal V 21 , were also isolated from this plant. <lb/>Their structures were confirmed by comparison of their spectroscopic data with values reported in literature. <lb/>Plausible biosynthetic pathways of 1-7 were proposed (Fig. 7). The formation of carbocation in phloroglu-<lb/>cinol precursor was thought to play a constructive role to trigger nucleophilic addition in the biosynthesis 4,11,17 . <lb/>Thereafter, the different ion migration in terpene units made the cyclization diversify in oxa-heterocyclic rings. <lb/>Although the dihydropyran rings of 1, 6, and 7 also could be deduced by the hetero Diels-Alder reaction 6-8,22 , but <lb/>nucleophilic addition should be more responsible for those different coupling patterns and the diversified terpene <lb/>moieties. <lb/>Antifungal assays. Considering the reported antifungal effect of the genus Eucalyptus 2,9,23,24 , we tested the <lb/>antifungal activities of all the isolates against C. albicans and C. glabrata. As results shown in Table 3, compounds <lb/>1, 6, and 8 exhibited significant antifungal activities against C. glabrata, and compounds 6 and 8 showed moder-<lb/>ate antifungal activities against C. albicans. Obviously, the FPMs were important components responsible for the <lb/>no. <lb/>1 a <lb/>2 a <lb/>3 a <lb/>4 a <lb/>5 b <lb/>6 a <lb/>7 a <lb/>1 <lb/>45.3 <lb/>148.3 <lb/>98.9 <lb/>31.5 <lb/>133.9 <lb/>39.3 <lb/>29.0 <lb/>2 <lb/>26.5 <lb/>32.2 <lb/>33.3 <lb/>20.7 <lb/>28.2 <lb/>31.8 <lb/>38.6 <lb/>3 <lb/>34.8 <lb/>34.5 <lb/>27.4 <lb/>25.3 <lb/>28.5 <lb/>34.7 <lb/>31.0 <lb/>4 <lb/>36.9 <lb/>51.8 <lb/>40.2 <lb/>34.3 <lb/>38.8 <lb/>154.6 <lb/>154.3 <lb/>5 <lb/>39.1 <lb/>137.4 <lb/>38.7 <lb/>42.2 <lb/>38.9 <lb/>72.6 <lb/>203.7 <lb/>6 <lb/>28.5 <lb/>85.8 <lb/>34.8 <lb/>36.0 <lb/>35.6 <lb/>32.7 <lb/>34.8 <lb/>7 <lb/>26.9 <lb/>43.0 <lb/>19.7 c <lb/>22.1 <lb/>21.4 <lb/>29.3 <lb/>38.5 <lb/>8 <lb/>19.5 <lb/>20.1 <lb/>21.2 <lb/>17.7 <lb/>22.0 <lb/>18.4 <lb/>17.3 <lb/>9 <lb/>38.8 <lb/>32.7 <lb/>18.8 <lb/>29.2 <lb/>24.5 <lb/>42.0 <lb/>42.1 <lb/>10 <lb/>86.5 <lb/>71.2 <lb/>50.7 <lb/>87.5 <lb/>137.1 <lb/>86.8 <lb/>85.6 <lb/>11 <lb/>20.2 <lb/>74.6 <lb/>19.7 c <lb/>20.5 <lb/>19.3 <lb/>19.1 <lb/>27.3 <lb/>12 <lb/>16.1 <lb/>32.0 <lb/>16.5 <lb/>17.5 <lb/>17.2 <lb/>15.5 <lb/>15.6 <lb/>13 <lb/>28.8 <lb/>31.0 <lb/>31.7 <lb/>31.9 <lb/>30.5 <lb/>29.4 <lb/>29.6 <lb/>14 <lb/>23.1 <lb/>28.4 <lb/>18.7 <lb/>21.5 <lb/>23.8 <lb/>25.6 <lb/>25.1 <lb/>15 <lb/>16.0 <lb/>25.6 <lb/>16.1 <lb/>16.4 <lb/>17.0 <lb/>114.2 <lb/>120.2 <lb/>1′ <lb/>169.3 <lb/>170.2 <lb/>166.4 <lb/>171.4 <lb/>173.6 <lb/>168.6 <lb/>168.9 <lb/>2′ <lb/>106.0 <lb/>117.8 <lb/>109.1 <lb/>104.3 <lb/>106.4 <lb/>108.9 <lb/>108.9 <lb/>3′ <lb/>164.1 <lb/>168.4 <lb/>169.1 <lb/>166.1 <lb/>166.5 <lb/>163.7 <lb/>163.4 <lb/>4′ <lb/>104.5 <lb/>108.3 <lb/>101.1 <lb/>104.7 108.8 c 104.3 <lb/>104.3 <lb/>5′ <lb/>168.5 <lb/>167.6 <lb/>169.5 <lb/>168.3 <lb/>167.7 <lb/>168.5 <lb/>168.5 <lb/>6′ <lb/>104.0 <lb/>106.1 <lb/>104.8 <lb/>105.3 108.8 c 103.9 <lb/>104.1 <lb/>7′ <lb/>25.2 <lb/>41.5 <lb/>44.1 <lb/>31.4 <lb/>36.5 <lb/>30.6 <lb/>28.2 <lb/>8′ <lb/>42.9 <lb/>39.3 <lb/>38.4 <lb/>35.9 <lb/>42.1 <lb/>42.1 <lb/>42.2 <lb/>9′ <lb/>26.4 <lb/>27.2 <lb/>26.9 <lb/>25.6 <lb/>27.8 <lb/>26.9 <lb/>27.2 <lb/>10′ <lb/>21.8 <lb/>22.1 <lb/>22.5 <lb/>21.6 <lb/>24.0 <lb/>21.7 <lb/>21.9 <lb/>11′ <lb/>23.8 <lb/>24.5 <lb/>23.4 <lb/>24.4 <lb/>22.7 <lb/>24.6 <lb/>24.4 <lb/>12′ 192.5 <lb/>193.5 <lb/>190.8 <lb/>192.6 192.4 c 192.2 <lb/>192.1 <lb/>13′ 191.9 <lb/>192.8 <lb/>191.8 <lb/>191.9 192.4 c 191.9 <lb/>191.8 <lb/>Table 2. 13 C NMR data for compounds 1-7 (125 MHz). a Measured in CDCl 3 . b Measured in CD 3 OD. <lb/>c <lb/>Overlapped. <lb/>Figure 2. Key 1 H-1 H COSY, HMBC, and ROESY correlations of 1. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificreports/ <lb/></note>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Scientific RepoRts | 6:39815 | DOI: 10.1038/srep39815 <lb/></note>

			<body>antifungal activities in the genus Eucalyptus, which were consistent with the literature 2,23 . In view of the moderate <lb/>active 4, as well as the inactive 3 and 5, the coupling pattern of phloroglucinol and terpene might be important <lb/>for their antifungal activities against C. glabrata. Observation of the structures and activities of compounds 6-7 <lb/>indicated that the hydroxyl of C-5 should be a beneficial group for antifungal activity of 6. <lb/>In conclusion, seven new FPMs (1-7) were obtained, of which 1-4 are noteworthy skeletons because of the <lb/>unusual coupling patterns that formed diverse oxa-heterocyclic systems. Nucleophilic addition played an impor-<lb/>tant role in their biosynthesis, which enabled the formation of different terpene carbocation that further lead to <lb/>the structural variety. These FPMs showed different antifungal activities, which along with other reported ones, <lb/>enlightened us to consider FPMs as antifungal precursors. But further researches, such as the structure-activity <lb/>relationship, the in vivo evaluation, and the mechanism research should be carried out. <lb/>Figure 3. Key 1 H-1 H COSY, HMBC, and ROESY correlations of 2. <lb/>Figure 4. Key 1 H-1 H COSY, HMBC, and ROESY correlations of 3. <lb/>Figure 5. Key 1 H-1 H COSY, HMBC, and ROESY correlations of 4. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificreports/ <lb/></note>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Scientific RepoRts | 6:39815 | DOI: 10.1038/srep39815 <lb/></note>

			<body>Methods <lb/>General experimental procedures. All optical rotation values were measured on a Jasco P-1020 polarim-<lb/>eter (Jasco, Tokyo, Japan). UV spectra were determined on a Shimadzu UV-2450 spectrophotometer (Shimadzu, <lb/>Figure 7. Plausible biosynthetic pathways of 1-7. <lb/>Figure 6. The P/M-helicity rules and ECD spectra of 1 (A), 4 (B), 6 (C), and 7 (D). <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificreports/ <lb/></note>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Scientific RepoRts | 6:39815 | DOI: 10.1038/srep39815 <lb/></note>

			<body>Tokyo, Japan). ECD spectra were measured on a Jasco J-810 spectropolarimeter (Jasco, Tokyo, Japan) using <lb/>spectroscopic grade solvent (MeOH). IR spectra (KBr pellets) were recorded on a Bruker Tensor 27 spectrom-<lb/>eter (Bruker, Bremen, Germany). NMR spectra were obtained with a Bruker AVIII-500 spectrometer (Bruker, <lb/>Bremen, Germany). CDCl 3 and CD 3 OD with TMS as internal standard were used as solvent, and the signals of the <lb/>residual solvent protons and the solvent carbon signals were used as internal references (δ H = 7.26 and δ C = 77.26 <lb/>for CDCl 3 and δ H = 3.31 and δ C = 49.00 for CD 3 OD, respectively). ESIMS and HRESIMS spectra were acquired <lb/>on an Agilent 1100 series LC-MSD-Trap-SL mass analyzer and an Agilent UPLC-Q-TOF (Agilent Technologies, <lb/>Palo Alto, CA, USA), respectively. TLC analyses were carried out using precoated silica gel GF 254 plates (Qingdao <lb/>Marine Chemical Plant, Qingdao, P. R. China). Column chromatographic methods were performed on Silica <lb/>gel (200-300 mesh, Qingdao Haiyang Chemical Co., Ltd.), Sephadex LH-20 (Pharmacia, Sweden), and RP-C 18 <lb/>silica (40-63 μm, FuJi, Japan). Preparative HPLC was performed on the LC-6A instrument that used a SPD-10A <lb/>detector and a shim-pack RP-C 18 column (10 μm, 20 × 200 mm, Shimadzu, Tokyo, Japan). Analytical HPLC was <lb/>performed on an Agilent 1200 Series instrument with a DAD detector by using a shim-pack VP-ODS column <lb/>(250 × 4.6 mm, Agilent Technologies, Palo Alto, CA, USA). <lb/>Plant material. The leaves of E. robusta were collected from Bozhou, Anhui Province, People&apos;s Republic <lb/>of China, in October 2013, which were authenticated by Prof. Mian Zhang of the Department of Medicinal <lb/>Plants, China Pharmaceutical University. A voucher specimen (accession number DYA201310) was stored at the <lb/>Department of Natural Medicinal Chemistry, China Pharmaceutical University. <lb/>Extraction and isolation. The air-dried and powdered leaves of E. robusta (15.0 kg) were percolated with <lb/>95% EtOH for four times at room temperature. The combined EtOH residue (1.55 kg) was suspended in water and <lb/>then extracted with petroleum ether (PE, 4.0 L × 4) and EtOAc (4.0 L × 4). The PE soluble partition (350 g) was <lb/>fractionated by column chromatography over silica gel with a gradient of PE/EtOAc (100:1 to 1:2, v/v) to afford <lb/>fractions A-E. Fr.B (70.8 g) was subsequently separated by silica gel column with PE/EtOAc (100:0 to 1:1, v/v) as <lb/>eluent to yield seven subfractions (Frs.B1-7). Then, Fr.B3 (20.3 g) was separated by silica gel column using PE/ <lb/>EtOAc (100:1 to 1:1, v/v) as eluent to yield five subfractions (Frs.B3a-e). Fr.B3c (6.3 g) was then chromatographed <lb/>on a RP-C 18 column (MeOH/H 2 O, 60:40/100:0, v/v) to obtain eight fractions (Frs.B3c1-8). Fr.B3c6 (100.8 mg) was <lb/>separated by preparative HPLC, with 90% methanol in water, to yield compounds 8 (5.1 mg, 25.5 min), 5 (10.2 mg, <lb/>31.0 min), and 6 (6.8 mg, 40.5 min). Fr.B3c7 (400.6 mg) was chromatographed over a Sephadex LH-20 column, <lb/>eluted with CH 2 Cl 2 /MeOH (1:1, v/v) to yield five further fractions (Frs.B3c7a-e). Fr.B3c7c (90.3 mg) was purified <lb/>by preparative HPLC using the mobile phase MeOH/H 2 O (95:5, v/v) to yield compounds 9 (3.5 mg, 30.5 min) <lb/>and 4 (3.8 mg, 42.3 min). Fr.B3b (4.5 g) was applied to a silica gel column (PE/EtOAc, 100:0 to 1:1, v/v), then sep-<lb/>arated over Sephadex LH-20 (CH 2 Cl 2 /MeOH, 1:1, v/v), and purified finally by preparative HPLC (MeCN/H 2 O, <lb/>90:10, v/v) to give, in turn, 10 (5.3 mg, 28.0 min), 3 (3.4 mg, 33.7 min), and 7 (5.8 mg, 45.1 min). Fr.B3a (3.6 g) was <lb/>applied to a silica gel column (PE/EtOAc, 100:0 to 1:1, v/v), purified finally by preparative HPLC (MeCN/H 2 O, <lb/>95:10, v/v) to yield compounds 1 (9.4 mg, 38.7 min) and 2 (2.8 mg, 50.1 min). <lb/>Eucalrobusone J (1): White powder; α <lb/>[ ] D <lb/>23 -45.1 (c 0.11, MeOH); UV (MeOH) λ max (log ε) 205 (0.62), 278 <lb/>(1.35) nm; ECD (MeOH, Δ ε) 200 (+ 1.58), 231 (-1.27), 268 (-1.42), 310 (-2.97) nm; IR (KBr) ν max 3452, 2955, <lb/>1620, 1403 cm -1 ; 1 H and 13 C NMR data, see Tables 1 and 2; ESIMS m/z 453.2 [M-H] -; HRESIMS m/z 453.2648 <lb/>([M-H] -, C 28 H 37 O 5 ; calcd 453.2646). <lb/>Eucalrobusone K (2): White powder; α <lb/>[ ] D <lb/>23 -2.0 (c 0.10, MeOH); UV (MeOH) λ max (log ε) 205 (0.88), 269 <lb/>(0.76) nm; ECD (MeOH, Δ ε) 207 (-6.08), 232 (+ 1.50), 282 (+ 2.86) nm; IR (KBr) ν max 3450, 1720, 1235, <lb/>1015 cm -1 ; 1 H and 13 C NMR data, see Tables 1 and 2; ESIMS m/z 467.3 [M-H] -; HRESIMS m/z 467.2437 <lb/>([M-H] -, C 28 H 35 O 6 ; calcd 467.2439). <lb/>Eucalrobusone L (3): White powder; α <lb/>[ ] D <lb/>23 -2.4 (c 0.03, MeOH); UV (MeOH) λ max (log ε) 192 (0.33), 205 <lb/>(0.63), 278 (0.59), 382 (0.12) nm; ECD (MeOH, Δ ε) 214 (-0.99), 241 (+ 0.19), 273 (-0.39) nm; IR (KBr) ν max <lb/>Compounds <lb/>C. albicans a <lb/>C. glabrata a <lb/>1 <lb/>&gt; 50 <lb/>2.57 ± 0.06 <lb/>2 <lb/>&gt; 50 <lb/>&gt; 50 <lb/>3 <lb/>49.29 ± 4.78 <lb/>&gt; 50 <lb/>4 <lb/>47.24 ± 5.60 <lb/>15.40 ± 3.17 <lb/>5 <lb/>&gt; 50 <lb/>&gt; 50 <lb/>6 <lb/>12.54 ± 2.14 <lb/>1.95 ± 0.68 <lb/>7 <lb/>&gt; 50 <lb/>30.56 ± 3.67 <lb/>8 <lb/>12.50 ± 2.25 <lb/>2.49 ± 0.83 <lb/>9 <lb/>&gt; 50 <lb/>&gt; 50 <lb/>10 <lb/>&gt; 50 <lb/>&gt; 50 <lb/>Fluconazole b <lb/>0.25 ± 0.12 <lb/>Amphotericin B b <lb/>0.26 ± 0.07 <lb/>Table 3. Antifungal activities of compounds 1-10 against C. albicans and C. glabrata. a MIC 50 value of <lb/>antifungal activities, μg/mL. b Positive control. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificreports/ <lb/></note>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Scientific RepoRts | 6:39815 | DOI: 10.1038/srep39815 <lb/></note>

			<body>3445, 1640, 1400, 1050 cm -1 ; 1 H and 13 C NMR data, see Tables 1 and 2; ESIMS m/z 453.2 [M-H] -; HRESIMS m/z <lb/>453.2650 ([M-H] -, C 28 H 37 O 5 ; calcd 453.2646). <lb/>Eucalrobusone M (4): White powder; α <lb/>[ ] D <lb/>23 + 18.2 (c 0.03, MeOH); UV (MeOH) λ max (log ε) 195 (0.12), 203 <lb/>(0.23), 280 (0.12) nm; ECD (MeOH, Δ ε) 224 (+ 2.05), 295 (+ 6.67) nm; IR (KBr) ν max 3440, 1635, 1405, <lb/>1055 cm -1 ; 1 H and 13 C NMR data, see Tables 1 and 2; ESIMS m/z 453.2 [M-H] -; HRESIMS m/z 453.2647 <lb/>([M-H] -, C 28 H 35 O 6 ; calcd 453.2646). <lb/>Eucalrobusone N (5): White powder; α <lb/>[ ] D <lb/>23 + 53.8 (c 0.13, MeOH); UV (MeOH) λ max (log ε) 248 (0.42), 276 <lb/>(1.29), 388 (0.39) nm; ECD (MeOH, Δ ε) 207 (+ 2.01), 224 (+ 7.99), 263 (-0.65), 300 (+ 0.33) nm; IR (KBr) ν max <lb/>3443, 2924, 1632, 1400, 1057 cm -1 ; 1 H and 13 C NMR data, see Tables 1 and 2; ESIMS m/z 453.3 [M-H] -; <lb/>HRESIMS m/z 453.2645 ([M-H] -, C 28 H 37 O 5 ; calcd 453.2646). <lb/>Eucalrobusone O (6): White powder; α <lb/>[ ] D <lb/>23 + 10.3 (c 0.07, MeOH); UV (MeOH) λ max (log ε) 205 (0.58), 277 <lb/>(0.96), 343 (0.11) nm; ECD (MeOH, Δ ε) 200 (-7.60), 285 (+ 3.96), 346 (+ 1.55) nm; IR (KBr) ν max 3424, 2929, <lb/>1401 cm -1 ; 1 H and 13 C NMR data, see Tables 1 and 2; ESIMS m/z 469.4 [M-H] -; HRESIMS m/z 469.2599 <lb/>([M-H] -, C 28 H 37 O 6 ; calcd 469.2596). <lb/>Eucalrobusone P (7): White powder; α <lb/>[ ] D <lb/>23 + 24.0 (c 0.10, MeOH); UV (MeOH) λ max (log ε) 205 (0.72), 278 <lb/>(1.02), 344 (0.14) nm; ECD (MeOH, Δ ε) 200 (-17.74), 284 (+ 8.64), 344 (+ 2.46) nm; IR (KBr) ν max 3430, 2935, <lb/>1430 cm -1 ; 1 H and 13 C NMR data, see Tables 1 and 2; ESIMS m/z 467.3 [M-H] -; HRESIMS m/z 467.2441 <lb/>([M-H] -, C 28 H 35 O 6 ; calcd 467.2439). <lb/>Quantum chemical ECD calculation. The geometries generated based on NMR were optimized using <lb/>MM2. The corresponding minimum geometries found were further re-optimized by DFT calculations at the <lb/>B3LYP/6-31 G + (d, p) level. ECD computations were performed by means of the TD-SCF method under <lb/>B3LYP/6-311 G + (d, 2p) level with 19 nm UV correction (σ = 0.39) for compound 2 and 22 nm UV correction <lb/>(σ = 0.30) for compound 3, respectively. <lb/>Antifungal assays. The antifungal assay was performed by using broth microdilution method as previously <lb/>reported 25,26 . Briefly, test compounds were serially diluted and co-incubated with standard microbial suspensions <lb/>in 96-well plates for 24 h at 37 °C. The optical densities at 530 nm (OD530) were measured by using a spectro-<lb/>photometer and growth inhibition of each concentration was calculated. The MIC 50 value was defined as the <lb/>minimum concentration of compound at which the growth of microorganism was half inhibited. All calculations <lb/>were performed using GraphPad Prism 6 (GraphPad Software, San Diego, CA). Fluconazole and amphotericin <lb/>B were used as the positive control in assays of all isolates antifungal activities against C. albicans and C. glabrata, <lb/>respectively. All experiments were performed in three independent experiments. <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>1. Nishizawa, M. et al. Macrocarpals: HIV-RTase inhibitors of Eucalyptus globulus. Tetrahedron Lett. 33, 2983-2986 (1992). <lb/>2. Shou, Q. Y. et al. Rhodomyrtals A-D, four unusual phloroglucinol-sesquiterpene adducts from Rhodomyrtus psidioides. RSC Adv. 4, <lb/>13514-13517 (2014). <lb/>3. Yang, S. P. et al. Potent HGF/c-Met axis inhibitors from Eucalyptus globulus: the coupling of phloroglucinol and sesquiterpenoid is <lb/>essential for the activity. J. Med. Chem. 55, 8183-8187 (2012). <lb/>4. Tanaka, T., Mikamiyama, H., Maeda, K. &amp; Iwata, C. Total synthesis of (-)-macrocarpal C. Stereoselective coupling reaction with a <lb/>novel hexasubstituted benzene Cr(CO) 3 complex as a biomimetic chiral benzyl cation equivalent. J. Org. Chem. 63, 9782-9793 <lb/>(1998). <lb/>5. Singh, I. P., Sidana, J., Bharatea, S. B. &amp; Foley, W. J. Phloroglucinol compounds of natural origin: synthetic aspects. Nat. Prod. Rep. <lb/>27, 393-416 (2010). <lb/>6. Bharate, S. B. &amp; Singh, I. P. A two-step biomimetic synthesis of antimalarial robustadials A and B. Tetrahedron Lett. 47, 7021-7024 <lb/>(2006). <lb/>7. Tran, D. N. &amp; Cramer, N. Biomimetic synthesis of (+ )-ledene, (+ )-viridiflorol, (-)-palustrol, (+ )-spathulenol, and psiguadial A, C, <lb/>and D via the platform terpene (+ )-bicyclogermacrene. Chem. Eur. J. 20, 10654-10660 (2014). <lb/>8. Bharate, S. B. et al. S-Euglobals: Biomimetic synthesis, antileishmanial, antimalarial, and antimicrobial activities. Bioorg. Med. Chem. <lb/>16, 1328-1336 (2008). <lb/>9. Tian, L. W. et al. Eucalmaidials A and B, phloroglucinol-coupled sesquiterpenoids from the juvenile leaves of Eucalyptus maiden. <lb/>RSC Adv. 4, 21373-21378 (2014). <lb/>10. Shang, Z. C., Yang, M. H., Jian, K. L., Wang, X. B. &amp; Kong, L. Y. 1 H NMR-guided isolation of formyl-phloroglucinol meroterpenoids <lb/>from the leaves of Eucalyptus robusta. Chem. Eur. J. 22, 11778-11784 (2016). <lb/>11. Yin, S. et al. Eucalyptals A-C with a new skeleton isolated from Eucalyptus globules. Org. Lett. 9, 5549-5552 (2007). <lb/>12. Yu, Y. et al. Eucarobustols A-I, conjugates of sesquiterpenoids and acylphloroglucinols from Eucalyptus robusta. J. Nat. Prod. 79, <lb/>1365-1372 (2016). <lb/>13. Slade, D., Ferreira, D. &amp; Marais, J. P. J. Circular dichroism, a powerful tool for the assessment of absolute configuration of flavonoids. <lb/>Phytochemistry 66, 2177-2215 (2005). <lb/>14. Snatzke, G. &amp; Ho, P. C. Circular dichroism-XLVI: rules for benzene cotton-effects. Tetrahedron 27, 3645-3653 (1971). <lb/>15. Imae, Y. et al. Jasisoquinolines A and B, architecturally new isoquinolines, from a marine sponge Jaspis sp. Org. Lett. 13, 4798-4801 <lb/>(2011). <lb/>16. Alali, F. et al. Cytotoxic homoisoflavones from the bulbs of Bellevalia eigii. J. Nat. Prod. 78, 1708-1715 (2015). <lb/>17. Wang, J. et al. Eucalyptals D and E, new cytotoxic phloroglucinols from the fruits of Eucalyptus globulus and assignment of absolute <lb/>configuration. Tetrahedron Lett. 53, 2654-2658 (2012). <lb/>18. Gijsen, H. J. M., Wijnberg, J. B. P. A., Stork, G. A. &amp; Groot, A. D. The synthesis of (-)-kessane, starting from natural (+ ) <lb/>-aromadendrene-II. Tetrahedron 47, 4409-4416 (1991). <lb/>19. Kozuka, M. et al. The granulation-inhibiting principles from Eucalyptus globulus Labill. III. The structures of euglobal-III, -IVb, and <lb/>-VII. Chem. Pharm. Bull. 30, 1964-1973 (1982). <lb/>20. Yamakoshi, Y., Murata, M., Shimizu, A. &amp; Homma, S. Isolation and characterization of macrocarpals B-G antibacterial compounds <lb/>from Eucalyptus macrocarpa. Biosci. Biotech. Biochem. 56, 1570-1576 (1992). <lb/>21. Amano, T. et al. Isolation and characterization of euglobals from Eucalyptus globulus Labill. by preparative reversed-phase liquid <lb/>chromatography. J. Chromatogr. A 208, 347-355 (1981). <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificreports/ <lb/></note>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Scientific RepoRts | 6:39815 | DOI: 10.1038/srep39815 <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>22. Yang, X. L., Hsieh, K. L. &amp; Liu, J. K. Guajadial: an unusual meroterpenoid from guava leaves Psidium guajava. Org. Lett. 9, 5135-5138 <lb/>(2008). <lb/>23. Ghisalberti, E. L. Bioactive acylphloroglucinol derivatives from Eucalyptus, species. Phytochemistry 41, 7-22 (1996). <lb/>24. Wu, S. B., Long, C. &amp; Kennelly, E. J. Structural diversity and bioactivities of natural benzophenones. Nat. Prod. Rep. 31, 1158-1174 <lb/>(2014). <lb/>25. Wang, Y., Yang, M. H., Wang, X. B., Li, T. X. &amp; Kong, L. Y. Bioactive metabolites from the endophytic fungus Alternaria alternata. <lb/>Fitoterapia 99, 153-158 (2014). <lb/>26. Li, T. X., Yang, M. H., Wang, X. B., Wang, Y. &amp; Kong, L. Y. Synergistic antifungal meroterpenes and dioxolanone derivatives from the <lb/>endophytic fungus Guignardia sp. J. Nat. Prod. 78, 2511-2520 (2015). <lb/></listBibl>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgements <lb/>This research work was supported by the National Natural Science Foundation of China (81503218), the Program <lb/>for Changjiang Scholars and Innovative Research Team in University (IRT_15R63), the Priority Academic <lb/>Program Development of Jiangsu Higher Education Institutions (PAPD), and the Fundamental Research Funds <lb/>for the Central Universities (2016ZZD010). <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Author Contributions <lb/>K.L.Y., Y.M.H., and S.Z.C. designed the phytochemical and biological tests. W.X.B. conducted the density <lb/>functional theory calculations. S.Z.C. administrated the isolation of compounds and analyzed NMR and MS data. <lb/>S.Z.C. and Y.M.H. wrote the paper. L.R.H. administrated the biological tests. Y.M.H. measured the NMR data. <lb/>Additional Information <lb/>Supplementary information accompanies this paper at http://www.nature.com/srep <lb/>Competing financial interests: The authors declare no competing financial interests. <lb/></div>

			<front>How to cite this article: Shang, Z.-C. et al. New Formyl Phloroglucinol Meroterpenoids from the Leaves of <lb/>Eucalyptus robusta. Sci. Rep. 6, 39815; doi: 10.1038/srep39815 (2016). <lb/>Publisher&apos;s note: Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and <lb/>institutional affiliations. <lb/>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License. The images <lb/>or other third party material in this article are included in the article&apos;s Creative Commons license, <lb/>unless indicated otherwise in the credit line; if the material is not included under the Creative Commons license, <lb/>users will need to obtain permission from the license holder to reproduce the material. To view a copy of this <lb/>license, visit http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/ <lb/>© The Author(s) 2016 </front>


	</text>
</tei>