<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>Design and synthesis of a potent, highly selective, orally bioavailable, <lb/>retinoic acid receptor alpha agonist <lb/>Earl Clarke a , Christopher I. Jarvis a , Maria B. Goncalves a , S. Barret Kalindjian a , David R. Adams c , <lb/>Jane T. Brown c , Jason J. Shiers c , David M.A. Taddei c , Elodie Ravier c , Stephanie Barlow c , Iain Miller c , <lb/>Vanessa Smith c , Alan D. Borthwick b,⇑ , Jonathan P.T. Corcoran a,⇑ <lb/>a Neuroscience Drug Discovery Unit, Wolfson Centre for Age-Related Diseases, Guy&apos;s Campus, King&apos;s College, London SE1 1UL, UK <lb/>b DrugMolDesign, 15 Temple Grove, London NW11 7UA, UK <lb/>c Sygnature Discovery Limited, Biocity, Pennyfoot Street, Nottingham NG1 1GF, UK <lb/>a r t i c l e i n f o <lb/>Article history: <lb/>Received 28 September 2017 <lb/>Revised 6 December 2017 <lb/>Accepted 8 December 2017 <lb/>Available online 9 December 2017 <lb/>a b s t r a c t <lb/>A ligand-based virtual screening exercise examining likely bioactive conformations of AM 580 (2) and <lb/>AGN 193836 (3) was used to identify the novel, less lipophilic RARa agonist 4-(3,5-dichloro-4-ethoxy-<lb/>benzamido)benzoic acid 5, which has good selectivity over the RARb, and RARc receptors. Analysis of <lb/>the medicinal chemistry parameters of the 3,5-substituents of derivatives of template 5 enabled us to <lb/>design a class of drug-like molecules with lower intrinsic clearance and higher oral bioavailability which <lb/>led to the novel RARa agonist 4-(3-chloro-4-ethoxy-5-isopropoxybenzamido)-2-methylbenzoic acid 56 <lb/>that has high RARa potency and excellent selectivity versus RARb (2 orders of magnitude) and RARc <lb/>(4 orders of magnitude) at both the human and mouse RAR receptors with improved drug-like properties. <lb/>This RARa specific agonist 56 has high oral bioavailability (&gt;80%) in both mice and dogs with a good PK <lb/>profile and was shown to be inactive in cytotoxicity and genotoxicity screens. <lb/>Ó 2017 The Authors. Published by Elsevier Ltd. This is an open access article under the CC BY license (http:// <lb/>creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/). <lb/></front>

			<body>1. Introduction <lb/>The retinoic acid receptors (RARa, RARb, and RARc) are mem-<lb/>bers of the nuclear receptor superfamily. Compounds which bind <lb/>to and activate the RARs are termed retinoids and comprise both <lb/>natural retinol (Vitamin A) metabolites and synthetic analogs. Reti-<lb/>noids regulate a wide variety of biological processes such as verte-<lb/>brate embryonic morphogenesis and organogenesis, cell growth <lb/>arrest, differentiation, and apoptosis, as well as their disorders. 1 <lb/>The RARa isoform is found in the majority of tissues and has <lb/>been implicated in a number of diseases, most notably acute <lb/>promyelocytic leukemia (APL). Selective RARa agonists have been <lb/>shown to inhibit proliferation and induce apoptosis of mammary <lb/>tumor oncogenesis in murine models (MMTV-neu and MMTV-<lb/>wnt1 transgenic mice) relevant to human cancer, 2 and to inhibit <lb/>LPS-induced B-lymphocyte proliferation. 3 Selective RARa agonists <lb/>have also been shown to prevent neuronal cell death caused by <lb/>amyloid-b and, when administered orally, can prevent amyloid-b <lb/>production and Alzheimer&apos;s disease progression in a mouse <lb/>model. 4 It has been shown 5 that selective RARa agonists sup-<lb/>pressed allospecific immune response and significantly prolonged <lb/>the survival of mouse cardiac allografts and can ameliorate nephri-<lb/>tis in lupus-prone mice, NZB/NZW F1. 6 This supports the rationale <lb/>for using RARa agonists as immunosuppressants in human organ <lb/>transplantation. Thus selective RARa agonists have the therapeutic <lb/>potential for the treatment of cancer, dermatological diseases, Alz-<lb/>heimer&apos;s disease and immunological disorders. <lb/>Synthetic RARa, RARb, and RARc agonists have been developed <lb/>from all-trans-retinoic acid (ATRA), and usually consist of a lipophi-<lb/>lic ring, a linker and a carboxylic acid (Fig. 1). There has been an <lb/>extensive studies on the SAR 7,8,9,10 of the RARa agonists based <lb/>essentially on the bicyclic 5,5,8,8-tetramethyl-5,6,7,8-tetrahydron-<lb/>aphthalene derivatives which evolved from ATRA. All three agonist, <lb/>AM 580 (2), AGN 193836 (3), AGN 195183 (4) and antagonist BMS <lb/>195614 (1) (Fig. 1) which contain an amide linker and a benzoic <lb/>acid, arose from these studies. <lb/>However, although AM 580 (2) and AGN 195183 (4) have mod-<lb/>erate and good selectivity respectively for RARa, over RARb and <lb/>RARc they are quite lipophilic (cLog P 6.3 and 7.2). In addition <lb/>AM 580 (2) has been shown to be toxic, 11,12 and the more recently <lb/>discovered compound AGN 195183 (4) 10 which was in Phase I clin-<lb/>ical trials for cancer has been discontinued. 13 Our aim was to find a <lb/>novel, potent, highly selective RARa agonist not based on the <lb/>bicyclic 5,5,8,8-tetramethyl-5,6,7,8-tetrahydronaphthalene class <lb/>that was ligand efficient, orally bioavailable and without the <lb/></body>

			<front>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.bmc.2017.12.015 <lb/>0968-0896/Ó 2017 The Authors. Published by Elsevier Ltd. <lb/>This is an open access article under the CC BY license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/). <lb/>⇑ Corresponding authors. <lb/>E-mail address: alan.d.borthwick@drugmoldesign.com (A.D. Borthwick). <lb/>Bioorganic &amp; Medicinal Chemistry 26 (2018) 798-814 <lb/>Contents lists available at ScienceDirect <lb/>Bioorganic &amp; Medicinal Chemistry <lb/>j o u r n a l h o m e p a g e : w w w . e l s e v i e r . c o m / l o c a t e / b m c <lb/></front>

			<body>lipophilic obesity seen with (2), (3) and (4). We outline here how <lb/>we discovered our initial hit compound 5 and how this was devel-<lb/>oped into the orally bioavailable, highly potent and selective RARa <lb/>agonist 56 (Fig. 1) which exhibits promising drug-like properties. <lb/>2. Chemistry <lb/>The phenyl carboxamido-benzoic acids (Schemes 1, 3, 4 and 5) <lb/>and phenyl carbamoyl-benzoic acid 26 (Scheme 2) were prepared <lb/>by coupling the appropriately substituted aniline with a substi-<lb/>tuted benzoic acid using a variety of standard methods for the for-<lb/>mation of an amide bond. The 3,5-dichloro-4-alkoxy compounds <lb/>12-15 and 17-21 (Scheme 1) were prepared by alkylation of the <lb/>phenolic group of methyl 3,5-dichloro-4-hydroxybenzoate 6 fol-<lb/>lowed by hydrolysis of the benzoate ester. Coupling the resultant <lb/>acid 7 via the acid chloride by reaction with oxalyl chloride or <lb/>directly with HATU, with the appropriate methyl 4-aminobenzoate <lb/>8 followed by hydrolysis with lithium hydroxide gave the required <lb/>acids 12-15 and 17-21. <lb/>For compound 16 the initial alkylation of 6 was carried out with <lb/>benzyl bromide, and the resulting benzyloxy compound was <lb/>hydrolyzed, coupled with the aniline 8 (R 2 = H) and the benzyl <lb/>group was removed using boron trichloride to result in compound <lb/>11 (R 2 = H). This material was then alkylated using 1,1-di-tert-<lb/>butoxy-N,N-dimethylmethanamine in toluene at 80 °C. A final <lb/>hydrolysis using lithium hydroxide in a mixture of tetrahydrofuran <lb/>and water gave the tertiary butoxy compound 16. <lb/>A similar sequence (Scheme 2) coupling the aniline 24 and acid <lb/>chloride 23 (obtained from acid 22) followed by hydrolysis gave <lb/>the phenolic acid 25 which upon alkylation with ethyl iodide fol-<lb/>lowed by hydrolysis gave the reverse amide analog 26. <lb/>The 3,4,5-trialkoxybenzamido-benzoic acids 31-34 were pre-<lb/>pared in four or five steps from methyl 3,4,5-trihydroxybenzoate <lb/>27 as illustrated in Scheme 3. <lb/>For the symmetrical tri-alkoxy compound 31, treatment of 27 <lb/>with sodium hydrogen carbonate and ethyl iodide gave mainly <lb/>compound 28 (R 1 = Et) where alkylation had only occurred in the <lb/>4-position of the substrate. After purification, this compound on <lb/>treatment with potassium carbonate and 2-bromopropane gave <lb/>an intermediate compound where both remaining hydroxyl groups <lb/>had reacted with the alkylating reagent. Hydrolysis resulted in the <lb/>fully alkylated benzoic acid 29 (R 1 = Et, R 2 = R 3 = iPr) which was <lb/>coupled via the acid chloride to give the methyl ester of compound <lb/>31. A final hydrolysis using lithium hydroxide yielded compound <lb/>31. The other tri-alkoxy derivatives 32-34 were similarly prepared <lb/>(Scheme 3). <lb/>The 3-chloro-4,5-dialkoxybenzamido benzoic acids 39-45 and <lb/>49-59 were prepared as described in Schemes 4 and 5. The com-<lb/>mercially available 3-chloro-4-hydroxy-5-methoxybenzoic acid <lb/>35 was treated sequentially with boron tribromide and <lb/>trimethylsilyl chloride in methanol to leave methyl 3,4-dihy-<lb/>droxy-5-chlorobenzoate 36. <lb/>For the derivatives 39, 40, 42, 43, and 44, (Scheme 4) where the <lb/>alkoxy groups are the same, both hydroxyl groups in 36 were alky-<lb/>lated by using potassium carbonate and the appropriate alkyl <lb/>halide in N, N-dimethylformamide heated to 70 °C. <lb/>Hydrolysis gave rise to the fully substituted benzoic acids 37 (R <lb/>= iPr), 37 (R = cyclobutyl) and 37 (R = cyclopentyl. These were then <lb/>coupled to the aniline 38 via the acid chloride generated by treat-<lb/>ment of the benzoic acid with oxalyl chloride. <lb/>The di-tert-butoxy derivatives 41 and 45 were synthesized from <lb/>the acid 37 (R = t Bu), which was prepared by reacting the two <lb/>hydroxyl groups in 36 with N, N-dimethylformamide di-tert-butyl <lb/>acetal followed by hydrolysis, and then coupling the product <lb/>directly with aniline 38 using HATU. A final treatment of the cou-<lb/>pled products with lithium hydroxide in aqueous 1,4-dioxane gave <lb/>the required acids. <lb/>The non-identical di-alkoxy compounds 49-57 and 59 were <lb/>also prepared via methyl 3,4-dihydroxy-5-chlorobenzoate 36, <lb/>while 58 was prepared from 3-chloro-4-hydroxy-5-methoxyben-<lb/>zoic acid 35 via benzoic acid 48 (R 2 = Me, R 3 = Et) (Scheme 5). <lb/>On treatment of 36 with potassium carbonate and benzyl bro-<lb/>mide, the 4-benzyloxy methyl ester 46 was produced. For 49 this <lb/>was then alkylated with isopropyl bromide and base to give the <lb/>N <lb/>H <lb/>OH <lb/>O <lb/>O <lb/>OH <lb/>N <lb/>H <lb/>F <lb/>OH <lb/>O <lb/>F <lb/>O <lb/>X <lb/>CO 2 H <lb/>N <lb/>H <lb/>OH <lb/>O <lb/>O <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>H <lb/>O <lb/>Cl <lb/>Cl <lb/>CO 2 H <lb/>EtO <lb/>N <lb/>H <lb/>O <lb/>Cl <lb/>O <lb/>O <lb/>CO 2 H <lb/>all-trans-retinoic acid <lb/>AGN 193836 <lb/>1 <lb/>3 X = Br <lb/>4 X = Cl <lb/>2 AM 580 <lb/>AGN 195183 <lb/>ATRA <lb/>1 <lb/>4 <lb/>6 <lb/>9 <lb/>15 <lb/>18 <lb/>BMS 195614 α Antagonist <lb/>5 <lb/>56 <lb/>Fig. 1. RARa agonists and antagonist. <lb/>E. Clarke et al. / Bioorganic &amp; Medicinal Chemistry 26 (2018) 798-814 <lb/></body>

			<page>799 <lb/></page>

			<body>3-isopropoxy-4-benzyloxy compound 47 (R 2 = iPr) which was <lb/>hydrogenated, alkylated with ethyl iodide and base and hydro-<lb/>lyzed to give rise to the benzoic acid 48 (R 2 = iPr, R 3 = Et). This ben-<lb/>zoic acid 48 was then coupled to the aniline 38 (R 1 = H) using T3P <lb/>in ethyl acetate and triethylamine as a base, followed by hydrolysis <lb/>with lithium hydroxide to provide the final compound 49. The <lb/>other non-identical di-alkoxy compounds 50-57 and 59 were sim-<lb/>ilarly prepared via their corresponding benzoic acids 48 <lb/>(Scheme 5). <lb/>3. Results and discussion <lb/>A ligand-based virtual screening approach, which ranks com-<lb/>pounds by their similarity towards known active ligands, was <lb/>adopted in a search for a novel chemical series of small molecule <lb/>RARa agonists. The extended electron density representation <lb/>offered by the Cresset XED force-field provides a way to character-<lb/>ize the calculated field around a molecule. 14 The subsequent <lb/>molecular comparison uses four different 3D fields, positive and <lb/>7 <lb/>8 <lb/>10 <lb/>6 <lb/>12 R 1 = Pr, R 2 = H <lb/>14 R 1 = iPr, R 2 = H <lb/>13 R 1 = Bu, R 2 = H <lb/>16 R 1 = tBu, R 2 = H <lb/>11 <lb/>(i) <lb/>(ii) <lb/>(iii) <lb/>15 R 1 = <lb/>, R 2 = H <lb/>17 R 1 = Et, R 2 = F <lb/>18 R 1 = Et, R 2 = Me <lb/>19 R 1 = Et, R 2 = OH <lb/>20 R 1 = Et, R 2 = Cl <lb/>21 R 1 = Et, R 2 = CF 3 <lb/>(iv) <lb/>(v) <lb/>(ii) <lb/>(ii) <lb/>9 <lb/>(vi) <lb/>(vii) <lb/>or (viii) <lb/>Scheme 1. 4-(3,5-Dichloro-4-alkoxy-benzamido)benzoic acids. (Reagents and conditions: (i) K 2 CO 3 , R 1 Br, DMF, 80 °C, 3 h; (ii) LiOH, THF, H 2 O, room temp, 12 h; (iii) (COCl) 2 , <lb/>CH 2 Cl 2 , DMF, 0 °C, 1 h then methyl 4-amino-2-R 2 -benzoate, NEt 3 , room temp, 12 h or HATU, DMF, DIPEA, 5 min, then methyl 4-amino-2-R 2 -benzoate, DMF, room temp, 18 h; <lb/>(iv) R 1 = Bn, R 2 = Me; BCl 3 , CH 2 Cl 2 , 0 °C then room temp, 12 h; (v) 1,1-di-tert-butoxy-N,N-dimethylmethanamine, toluene, 80 °C, 3 h, then room temp, 12 h; (vi) 1,1-di-tert-<lb/>butoxy-N,N-dimethylmethanamine, toluene, 80 °C, 3 h, then further 1,1-di-tert-butoxy-N,N-dimethylmethanamine, 2 mol, added, 80 °C, 16 h. (vii) H 2 , Pd/C, MeOH, room <lb/>temp; (viii) R 1 = Et, R 2 = MeO, R = t Bu; BCl 3 , CH 2 Cl 2 , 0 °C then room temp 2 h). <lb/>22 <lb/>26 <lb/>23 <lb/>25 <lb/>24 <lb/>(i) <lb/>(ii) <lb/>(iii) <lb/>(iv) <lb/>Scheme 2. 4-(3,5-Dichloro-4-ethoxyphenylcarbamoyl)benzoic acid. (Reagents and conditions: (i) (COCl) 2 ,CH 2 Cl 2 , DMF, 0 °C, then room temp 2 h; (ii) DIPEA, CH 2 Cl 2 , room <lb/>temp, 16 h, then LiOH, THF, H 2 O, room temp, 16 h; (iii) K 2 CO 3 , EtI, DMF, 65 °C, 18 h, then further EtI, 70 °C, 3 h; (iv) LiOH, THF, H 2 O, room temp, 5 h). <lb/></body>

			<page>800 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">E. Clarke et al. / Bioorganic &amp; Medicinal Chemistry 26 (2018) 798-814 <lb/></note>

			<body>negative charge, steric shape and hydrophobicity, and allows a <lb/>complete 3D conformational analysis of compounds to be per-<lb/>formed. 15,16 The crystal structure of the selective RARa antagonist <lb/>BMS 195614 (1) in the human RARa active site 17 was overlaid with <lb/>AM 580 (2), the antagonist removed and the resulting complete <lb/>assembly minimized to give the putative bioactive conformation <lb/>of AM 580 (2). This procedure was also performed for AGN <lb/>193836 (3) to get its bioactive conformation. Molecular fields were <lb/>added to each of these bioactive conformations (Fig. 2). <lb/>These unique molecular field patterns were used to search Cres-<lb/>set&apos;s database of 2.5 M commercially available molecules, and the <lb/>results ranked in similarity to the initial bioactive conformations <lb/>(see Supplementary data for further details). <lb/>This methodology identified 3000 commercially available com-<lb/>pounds as possible hit compounds. The 200 compounds that had <lb/>the highest field overlays, Lipinski likeness, and synthetic tractabil-<lb/>ity, were purchased. These were tested in transactivation assays at <lb/>the RARa, b and c receptors. Full dose-response curves were gener-<lb/>ated for each active agonist, and the potency of each compound <lb/>was expressed as a ratio of its EC 50 compared to that of reference <lb/>ATRA EC 50 value generated on each 96 well plate. This produced <lb/>several potent hits, including the lead compound 5 (Table 1). The <lb/>3,5-dichloro-4-ethoxy derivative 5 was considered to be one of <lb/>the better starting points for a lead optimization exercise, not only <lb/>because of its potency as an RARa agonist but also because of its <lb/>good selectivity over the RARb and RARc receptors, with moderate <lb/>lipophilicity (cLog P = 4.4) compared to AGN 195183 (4) (cLog P = <lb/>7.2). In addition, it had no systematic Cyp450 liability (inactive at <lb/>25 lM at Cyp1A, 2C19, 2C9, 2D6 and 3A4 isoforms), and was not <lb/>cytotoxic in COS-7 cells (i.e. showed &lt;20% cell death @ 50 Â EC 50 <lb/>at the RAR alpha receptors). <lb/>Our aim was to increase the RARa potency and selectivity over <lb/>RARb while retaining the excellent selectivity over RARc shown by <lb/>5 and achieve oral bioavailability in the rat. The target profile was <lb/>RARa potency (RARa EC 50 /ATRA EC 50 &lt; 10) with a selectivity of 2 <lb/>orders of magnitude over RARb and 3 orders of magnitude over <lb/>RARc with an oral bioavailability of &gt;35% in the rat. <lb/>Initial SAR showed that the three aromatic substituents in 5 <lb/>seemed important for potency as the disubstituted, 3,5-dichloro <lb/>derivative 60 was less potent at RARa and also less selective than <lb/>the 3,5-dichloro-4-ethoxy derivative 5 at RARb and RARc. This <lb/>helped focus our SAR on derivatives with a 3,4,5 substituted aro-<lb/>matic ring. <lb/>3.1. 4-Substituted derivatives <lb/>We initially concentrated on the 4-substituent (Table 1). <lb/>Increasing the length of the 4-alkoxy substituent to n-propoxy 12 <lb/>and n-butoxy 13 resulted in a loss of selectivity at RARb and RARc. <lb/>(iv) <lb/>35 <lb/>38 <lb/>36 <lb/>(iv) <lb/>(iii) <lb/>39 R = iPr, R 1 = H <lb/>, R 1 = H <lb/>40 R = <lb/>41 R = tBu, R 1 = H <lb/>, R 1 = H <lb/>42 R = <lb/>43 R = iPr, R 1 = F <lb/>44 R = iPr, R 1 = Me <lb/>45 R = tBu, R 1 = Me <lb/>(v) <lb/>37 <lb/>(i) <lb/>(ii) <lb/>Scheme 4. 4-(3-Chloro-4,5-dialkoxybenzamido)benzoic acids with identical alkoxy groups. (Reagents and conditions: (i) BBr 3 , CH 2 Cl 2 , 0 °C, 2 h; (ii) TMSCl, MeOH, 50 °C, 16 <lb/>h; (iii) K 2 CO 3 , RI, DMF, 70 °C, 46 h; (iv) LiOH, THF, H 2 O, room temp, 18 h; (v) (COCl) 2 , CH 2 Cl 2 , DMF, 0 °C, 1 h then methyl 4-amino-2-R 1 -benzoate, NEt 3 , room temp, 12 h). <lb/>27 <lb/>31 R 1 = Et, R 2 = R 3 = iPr <lb/>33 R 1 = R 2 = R 3 = iPr <lb/>(i) <lb/>(ii) <lb/>(iii) <lb/>32 R 1 = Et, , R 2 = R 3 = <lb/>28 <lb/>(ii: R 1 = R 2 ) <lb/>(iii) <lb/>(iii) <lb/>34 R 1 = R 2 = Et, R 3 = iPr <lb/>(iv) <lb/>29 <lb/>30 <lb/>Scheme 3. 4-(3,4,5-Trialkoxybenzamido)benzoic acids. (Reagents and conditions: (i) NaHCO 3 , R 1 I, DMF, 30 °C, 72 h; (ii) K 2 CO 3 , R 2 Br, DMF, 50 °C, 48 h; (iii) LiOH, THF, H 2 O, <lb/>room temp, 16 h; (iv) (COCl) 2 , CH 2 Cl 2 , DMF, 0 °C, 1 h then methyl 4-amino-benzoate, NEt 3 , room temp, 12 h). <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">E. Clarke et al. / Bioorganic &amp; Medicinal Chemistry 26 (2018) 798-814 <lb/></note>

			<page>801 <lb/></page>

			<body>Increasing the bulk of the 4-alkoxy substituent to isopropoxy 14 <lb/>and tert-butoxy 16 resulted in an increase in potency at RARa and <lb/>an increase in selectivity over RARb but a loss of selectivity at <lb/>RARc. In contrast, the cyclopentoxy compound, 15 was less selec-<lb/>tive than 5 at both RARb and RARc. <lb/>We also explored the reverse amide 26 of 5 which lost signifi-<lb/>cant selectivity against RARb when compared to 5 and hence fur-<lb/>ther work on the reverse amides was curtailed. <lb/>We next investigated the PK profile of these 3,5-dichloro-4-<lb/>alkoxy derivatives. We used intrinsic clearance figures in mouse <lb/>and human microsomes as a simple in vitro screen to minimize <lb/>the risk of Phase 1 metabolism, before progressing to in vivo stud-<lb/>ies. The PK profile of the 3,5-dichloro-4-alkoxy series of com-<lb/>pounds was poor. The ethoxy 5, tert-butoxy 16 and cyclopentoxy <lb/>15 derivatives all had a high mouse, and moderate human intrinsic <lb/>clearance and 15 was poorly orally absorbed with very low oral <lb/>bioavailability in the rat (Table 2). <lb/>3.2. 3,5-Disubstituted derivatives <lb/>To overcome these difficulties we turned our attention to the <lb/>3,5-sustituents in 5. The patent analysis in this class of compounds <lb/>showed that non-alkyl substituents in the 3,4,5-substituted aro-<lb/>matic ring of 5 appeared novel. With this in mind we analysed <lb/>the medicinal chemistry parameters of the 3,5-substituents of <lb/>our initial 4-OEt derivatives containing non-alkyl 3,5-substituents <lb/>5, 62, 63 and 3,5-dialkyl substituents 64 (Table 3). Ranking these <lb/>four derivatives in terms of RARa potency against the properties <lb/>of the 3,5 substituents in the second aromatic ring, such as size <lb/>(MR), lipophilicity (p) and electronic resonance (r) (Table 3), <lb/>shows that potency only increases with the lipophilicity p of the <lb/>3,5-sustituents (and not with the size or resonance effects of these <lb/>substituents). <lb/>A search of possible aromatic substituents showed that the iso-<lb/>propoxy group has a similar lipophilicity to a chlorine/bromine <lb/>atom found in 5/63 and a similar size to a tert-butyl found in the <lb/>35 <lb/>50 R 2 = <lb/>38 <lb/>, R 3 = Et, R 1 = H <lb/>(iv) <lb/>(vi) <lb/>36 <lb/>(v) <lb/>(vii) <lb/>(viii) (ix) <lb/>48 <lb/>49 R 2 = iPr, R 3 = Et, R 1 = H <lb/>46 <lb/>47 <lb/>51 R 2 = iPr, R 3 = Me, R 1 = H <lb/>52 R 2 = Et, R 3 = iPr, R 1 = H <lb/>53 R 2 = iPr, R 3 = Me, R 1 = F <lb/>54 R 2 = iPr, R 3 = Et, R 1 = F <lb/>55 R 2 = iPr, R 3 = Me, R 1 = Me <lb/>56 R 2 = iPr, R 3 = Et, R 1 = Me <lb/>57 R 2 = Et, R 3 = iPr, R 1 = Me <lb/>58 R 2 = Me, R 3 = Et, R 1 = Me <lb/>59 R 2 = <lb/>, R 3 = Et, R 1 = Me <lb/>(iii) <lb/>(i) (ii) <lb/>(ii) <lb/>(vi) <lb/>(vii) <lb/>Scheme 5. 4-(3-Chloro-4,5-dialkoxybenzamido)benzoic acids with non-identical alkoxy groups. (Reagents and conditions: (i) BBr 3 , CH 2 Cl 2 , 0 °C, 2 h; (ii) TMSCl, MeOH, 50 °C, <lb/>16 h; (iii) K 2 CO 3 , BnBr, DMF, 60 °C, 0.75 h; (iv) K 2 CO 3 , R 2 Br, DMF, 60 °C, 2 h; (v) H 2 , 10% Pd/C, MeOH; (vi) K 2 CO 3 , DMF, 60 °C, 10 min, then R 3 I, 40 °C, 3 h; (vii) LiOH, THF, H 2 O, <lb/>40 °C, 1 h, then room temp, 16 h; (viii) T3P, methyl 4-amino-2-R 1 -benzoate, NEt 3 , EtOAc, 60 °C, 4 h, then room temp, 16 h. (ix) LiOH, THF, H 2 O, 40 °C, 16 h). <lb/>Fig. 2. Cresset FieldScreen representation of bioactive conformation of AM580. <lb/>(Blue field points (spheres) highlight energy minima for a positively charged probe, <lb/>red for a negative probe. Yellow spheres represent an attractive van der Waals <lb/>minima for a neutral probe and orange spheres represent hydrophobic centroids. <lb/>Oxygen atoms are shown in red, nitrogen in blue. The size of the points is related to <lb/>the strength of the interaction). <lb/></body>

			<page>802 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">E. Clarke et al. / Bioorganic &amp; Medicinal Chemistry 26 (2018) 798-814 <lb/></note>

			<body>more potent derivative 64. This suggested that the 3,5-diiso-<lb/>propoxy derivative 31 should be at least as active as the chloro <lb/>and bromo derivatives 5 and 63, and why the 3,5-diethoxy analog <lb/>62 which is the least lipophilic, is the least active. <lb/>3.3. 3,4,5-Trialkoxy and 3,4,-dialkoxy derivatives <lb/>Encouragingly 31 proved to have good RARa potency (Table 3). <lb/>In addition, 31 has high selectivity over RARb and RARc (Table 4), <lb/>and low mouse and human intrinsic clearance with excellent oral <lb/>absorption and bioavailability (81%) in the rat (Table 2), although <lb/>it was shown to be only a partial RARa agonist. The close profile <lb/>of 5 and 31 in terms of RARa potency, as well as RARb and RARc <lb/>selectivity, shows that in this case, the iPrO group is a good bioisos-<lb/>tere of the Cl group. This led the project away from the 3,5-dichloro <lb/>template and enabled exploration of the alkoxy derivatives at these <lb/>positions which give a lipophilic surface without the high <lb/>lipophilicity of the similar sized tertiary butyl group seen in 64, <lb/>making the template more drug-like. Further analogs of this tri-<lb/>alkoxy template 31 were investigated in an attempt to increase <lb/>its alpha potency while maintaining the excellent beta and gamma <lb/>selectivity as well as its good PK profile. Increasing the size of the <lb/>3,5-substituents in 31 to give the di-cyclopentoxy derivative 32 or <lb/>increasing the size of the 4-substituents to give 33 maintained the <lb/>good RARa potency and RARb selectivity but lost selectivity against <lb/>RARc (Table 4). Decreasing the size of both the 3-and 5-isopropoxy <lb/>Table 1 <lb/>Potency and Selectivity of 3,5-dichloro-4-alkoxy RARa agonists. <lb/>N <lb/>H <lb/>O <lb/>Cl <lb/>Cl <lb/>RO <lb/>CO 2 H <lb/>26 <lb/>Cl <lb/>Cl <lb/>O <lb/>N <lb/>H <lb/>EtO <lb/>CO 2 H <lb/>Subtype-specific transactivation a <lb/>Relative EC 50 <lb/>b <lb/>Compd <lb/>RO <lb/>RARa <lb/>RARb <lb/>b /a ratio c <lb/>RARc <lb/>c /a ratio c <lb/>cLogP f <lb/>4 <lb/>AGN195183 <lb/>11 <lb/>1564 <lb/>141 <lb/>9836 <lb/>867 <lb/>7.2 <lb/>5 <lb/>EtO <lb/>24 <lb/>1917 <lb/>79 <lb/>&gt;3,00,000 <lb/>&gt;12,500 <lb/>4.4 <lb/>12 <lb/>PrO <lb/>15 <lb/>139 <lb/>9.5 <lb/>1196 <lb/>82 <lb/>4.9 <lb/>13 <lb/>BuO <lb/>84 <lb/>717 <lb/>8.5 <lb/>1477 <lb/>18 <lb/>4.6 <lb/>14 <lb/>i PrO <lb/>7 d <lb/>1417 <lb/>205 <lb/>823 <lb/>119 <lb/>4.7 <lb/>16 <lb/>t BuO <lb/>7 <lb/>2927 <lb/>426 <lb/>6250 <lb/>909 <lb/>5.1 <lb/>15 <lb/>10 <lb/>342 <lb/>33 <lb/>4703 <lb/>452 <lb/>5.3 <lb/>26 <lb/>-<lb/>30 <lb/>355 <lb/>12 <lb/>&gt;1,08,000 <lb/>&gt;3600 <lb/>4.4 <lb/>60 <lb/>H <lb/>92 d <lb/>642 <lb/>7 <lb/>5000 <lb/>55 <lb/>4.2 <lb/>61 <lb/>MeO <lb/>30 <lb/>9525 <lb/>318 <lb/>5850 <lb/>195 <lb/>3.9 <lb/>ATRA <lb/>1.0(1.51 nM) e <lb/>1.0(0.52 nM) e <lb/>1.0(0.22 nM) e <lb/>a Transactivation assays for the RAR alpha, beta and gamma receptors were performed using each of the mouse RAR ligand binding domains, Subtype-specific activity is <lb/>expressed in terms of relative EC 50 which is the concentration of retinoid required to produce 50% of the maximal observed response, normalised relative to that of ATRA. <lb/>b Mean EC 50 for each compound divided by the mean EC 50 of ATRA. Values were obtained from three separate experiments. Errors in these assays are approximately 20% of <lb/>the mean values. <lb/>c The relative EC 50 ratios of a to b and a to c. <lb/>d Compound behaves as a partial agonist relative to the amplitude of the normalizing ATRA output. <lb/>e Mean of ATRA EC 50 (nM). <lb/>f cLog P values were calculated in ChemDraw. <lb/>Table 2 <lb/>In vitro and in vivo PK. <lb/>Compd <lb/>a Log D pH 7.4 <lb/>LE b <lb/>intrinsic Cl int <lb/>c <lb/>rat pK d <lb/>mouse <lb/>(mL/min/mg protein) <lb/>human <lb/>(mL/min/mg protein) <lb/>AUC po <lb/>ngÁmin mL À1 <lb/>Cl <lb/>mL/kg/min <lb/>F% <lb/>5 <lb/>1.7 <lb/>0.45 <lb/>127 <lb/>18 <lb/>ND <lb/>ND <lb/>ND <lb/>15 <lb/>2.8 <lb/>0.41 <lb/>83 <lb/>26 <lb/>1674 <lb/>2 <lb/>0.3 <lb/>16 <lb/>2.6 <lb/>0.45 <lb/>91 <lb/>16 <lb/>ND <lb/>ND <lb/>ND <lb/>18 <lb/>1.7 <lb/>0.51 <lb/>38 <lb/>14 <lb/>74,396 <lb/>1.6 <lb/>12 <lb/>31 <lb/>1.6 <lb/>0.36 <lb/>8 <lb/>4 <lb/>7,83,782 <lb/>1 <lb/>81 <lb/>39 <lb/>2.6 <lb/>0.43 <lb/>31 <lb/>-<lb/>43,569 <lb/>10 <lb/>39 <lb/>49 <lb/>1.7 <lb/>0.47 <lb/>41 <lb/>11 <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>51 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>0.44 <lb/>9 <lb/>12 <lb/>50,940 <lb/>3 <lb/>13 <lb/>a Measured by octanol/buffer shake flask method at pH 7.4 (see Supplementary data file for details). 20 <lb/>b LE values were calculated by LE = (RT ln K d )/N, presuming EC 50 % K d . 18 <lb/>c Intrinsic clearance Cl int data for screening purposes only: Mouse and Human microsomes were incubated with the test compound at 37 °C in the presence of the co-factor, <lb/>NADPH. The data is the mean of 5 separate experiments. Compound disappearance monitored over 45 min period. SEM is less than 10% of the mean values. <lb/>d Rat PK (n = 4): AUC (ngÁmin mL À1 ) at 10 mg/kg, 8% Ethanol/92% PEG-400 formulation, Cl in mL min À1 kg À1 . ND = not determined. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">E. Clarke et al. / Bioorganic &amp; Medicinal Chemistry 26 (2018) 798-814 <lb/></note>

			<page>803 <lb/></page>

			<body>groups to give the 3,4,5-triethoxy derivative 62, resulted in a sub-<lb/>stantial loss of RARa potency (Table 3). In addition 31, 32 and 33 all <lb/>exhibited some partial agonist activity at RARa. However a close <lb/>analog the 3,4-diethoxy-5-isopropoxy derivative 34 showed that <lb/>it was possible to have full RARa agonist properties with trialkoxy <lb/>derivatives (Table 4). <lb/>This unsymmetrical derivative was further exploited by the <lb/>investigation of a series of 3,4-alkoxy derivatives (Table 4). Replac-<lb/>ing one of the isopropoxy groups in the lead with a chloro atom <lb/>gave the chloro-dialkoxy derivative 49 which had increased <lb/>potency at RARa and also maintained the excellent selectivity at <lb/>RARb and RARc. However, this compound was also only a partial <lb/>agonist at RARa. <lb/>Increasing the size of the 3-isopropoxy in 49to 3-cyclobutyl in <lb/>50 gave no change in profile. However, increasing the 4-ethoxy <lb/>group in 49 to the 4-isopropoxy in 39 gave a similar level of <lb/>Table 3 <lb/>3,5-Disubstituted-4-ethoxy derivatives. <lb/>R <lb/>1 <lb/>R <lb/>2 <lb/>EtO <lb/>CO 2 H <lb/>O <lb/>N <lb/>H <lb/>Compd <lb/>R 1 <lb/>R 2 <lb/>MR a R 1 + R 2 <lb/>p b R 1 + R 2 <lb/>r c R 1 + R 2 <lb/>RARa rel EC 50 <lb/>d <lb/>62 <lb/>EtO <lb/>EtO <lb/>25 <lb/>0.76 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>370 <lb/>5 <lb/>Cl <lb/>Cl <lb/>12.06 <lb/>1.42 <lb/>0.74 <lb/>24 <lb/>63 <lb/>Br <lb/>Br <lb/>17.76 <lb/>1.72 <lb/>0.78 <lb/>5 <lb/>64 <lb/>t Bu <lb/>t Bu <lb/>39.24 <lb/>3.96 <lb/>-0.20 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>31 <lb/>i PrO <lb/>i <lb/>PrO <lb/>34.12 <lb/>1.70 <lb/>0.20 <lb/>26 e <lb/>a Sum of size (MR) of meta substituents R 1 and R 2 . <lb/>b Sum of lipophilicity (p) of substituents R 1 and R 2 . <lb/>c Sum of electronic resonance effect (r) of meta substituents R 1 and R 2 . For parameters see ref 19. <lb/>d Relative EC 50 see a,b Table 1. <lb/>e Partial agonist see d Table 1. <lb/>Table 4 <lb/>Potency and selectivity of 3,4,5-trialkoxy and 3,4,-dialkoxy RARa agonists. <lb/>R <lb/>1 <lb/>R <lb/>2 <lb/>R <lb/>3 <lb/>N <lb/>H <lb/>OH <lb/>O <lb/>O <lb/>O <lb/>O <lb/>Subtype-specific transactivation a <lb/>Relative EC 50 <lb/>b <lb/>Compd <lb/>R 1 O <lb/>R 2 O <lb/>R 3 <lb/>RARa <lb/>RARb <lb/>b/a <lb/>ratio c <lb/>RARc <lb/>c/a <lb/>ratio c <lb/>62 <lb/>EtO <lb/>EtO <lb/>EtO <lb/>368 <lb/>64,148 <lb/>174 <lb/>16 <lb/>31 <lb/>i <lb/>PrO <lb/>EtO <lb/>i PrO <lb/>26 d <lb/>4560 <lb/>175 <lb/>56,900 <lb/>2190 <lb/>32 <lb/>EtO <lb/>29 d <lb/>4200 <lb/>145 <lb/>550 <lb/>19 <lb/>33 <lb/>i <lb/>PrO <lb/>i <lb/>PrO <lb/>i PrO <lb/>27 d <lb/>2600 <lb/>96 <lb/>225 <lb/>8 <lb/>34 <lb/>i <lb/>PrO <lb/>EtO <lb/>EtO <lb/>29 <lb/>2450 <lb/>84 <lb/>960 <lb/>34 <lb/>49 <lb/>i <lb/>PrO <lb/>EtO <lb/>Cl <lb/>0.7 d <lb/>103 <lb/>150 <lb/>11,721 <lb/>50 <lb/>EtO <lb/>Cl <lb/>1.0 d <lb/>115 <lb/>115 <lb/>1706 <lb/>39 <lb/>i <lb/>PrO <lb/>i <lb/>PrO <lb/>Cl <lb/>1.7 <lb/>89 <lb/>54 <lb/>838 <lb/>40 <lb/>Cl <lb/>2.4 d <lb/>53 <lb/>22 <lb/>447 <lb/>41 <lb/>t BuO <lb/>t <lb/>BuO <lb/>Cl <lb/>0.9 <lb/>38 <lb/>44 <lb/>162 <lb/>189 <lb/>42 <lb/>Cl <lb/>1.7 d <lb/>55 <lb/>32 <lb/>571 <lb/>336 <lb/>51 <lb/>i <lb/>PrO <lb/>MeO <lb/>Cl <lb/>5.3 <lb/>1500 <lb/>283 <lb/>10,833 <lb/>2043 <lb/>52 <lb/>EtO <lb/>i <lb/>PrO <lb/>Cl <lb/>2.1 <lb/>7.1 <lb/>3.1 <lb/>570 <lb/>ATRA <lb/>1.0(1.51 nM) e <lb/>1.0(0.52 nM) e <lb/>1.0(0.22 nM) e <lb/>a Transactivation assays were performed using the RAR alpha, beta and gamma receptors containing each of the mouse RAR ligand binding domains. Subtype-specific <lb/>activity is expressed in terms of relative EC 50 which is the concentration of retinoid required to produce 50% of the maximal observed response, normalised relative to that of <lb/>ATRA. <lb/>b The relative EC 50 is the mean EC 50 for each compound divided by the mean EC 50 of ATRA. Values were obtained from three separate experiments. Errors in these assays are <lb/>approximately 20% of the mean values. <lb/>c The relative EC 50 ratios of a to b and a to c. <lb/>d Compound behaves as a partial agonist relative to the amplitude of the normalizing ATRA output. <lb/>e Mean of ATRA EC 50 (nM). <lb/></body>

			<page>804 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">E. Clarke et al. / Bioorganic &amp; Medicinal Chemistry 26 (2018) 798-814 <lb/></note>

			<body>potency at RARa as a full agonist. The molecule was also an order of <lb/>magnitude more potent than 31 at RARa while maintaining excel-<lb/>lent selectivity at RARc with moderate selectivity at RARb. In addi-<lb/>tion, the di-isopropoxy derivative 39 was orally well absorbed in <lb/>the rat with a bioavailability of 39% (Table 2). Thus 39 satisfied <lb/>our target profile except for selectivity at RARb. Increasing the size <lb/>of the alkoxy groups to the di-cyclobutyl in 40, di-tert-butyl in 41 <lb/>and di-cyclopentyl in 42 maintained potency at RARa, but <lb/>decreased selectivity at RARb and RARc. Interestingly reducing <lb/>the size of the 4-ethoxy in 49 to 4-methoxy in 51 gave a full agonist <lb/>with good RARa potency and selectivity at RARb and RARc. How-<lb/>ever, it had a low oral bioavailability (13%) in the rat (Table 2). <lb/>3.4. Substitution of the benzoic acid ring <lb/>Ortho-fluoro substitution in the benzoic acid ring of the bicyclic <lb/>5,5,8,8-tetramethyl-5,6,7,8-tetrahydronaphthalene analogs which <lb/>lead to AGN 195183 (4) 10 has been shown to increase RARa binding <lb/>potency and increase selectivity over RARb and RARc in the trans-<lb/>activation assay. <lb/>Based on this precedent, a series of ortho-substituted benzoic <lb/>acid derivatives of our initial lead template 5 were prepared <lb/>(Table 5). While the ortho-fluoro substitution product 17 main-<lb/>tained potency and selectivity, the ortho-methyl substitution pro-<lb/>duct, 18 improved RARa potency 20-fold and maintained good <lb/>RARb and RARc selectivity. In addition, 18 had a lower mouse <lb/>and human intrinsic clearance, as well as a somewhat improved <lb/>bioavailability (12%) in the rat (Table 2), compared to the unsubsti-<lb/>tuted benzoic acid derivative 5. Compounds 19, 20 and 21 with lar-<lb/>ger substituent groups, either lost RARa potency or RARb/RARc <lb/>selectivity compared to 5. As a result of these findings, a series <lb/>ortho-methyl and ortho-fluoro substituted benzoic acid derivatives <lb/>of the 3,4-dialkoxy-5-chloro template were prepared (Table 6). The <lb/>initial trend from the 5 series (Table 5) was also seen in the 3,4-dia-<lb/>lkoxy-5-chloro series (Table 6). <lb/>The ortho-fluoro substituted derivatives 53, 54 and 43 (Table 6) <lb/>maintained RARa potency and selectivity compared to their corre-<lb/>sponding unsubstituted derivatives 51, 49 and 39 and, in addition, <lb/>had a lower mouse and human intrinsic clearance with the latter <lb/>being in single figures. However, although both 53 and 54 met <lb/>our target profile in terms of high RARa potency with a selectivity <lb/>of 2 orders of magnitude over RARb and 3 orders of magnitude over <lb/>RARc, they both had low oral bioavailability (15% and 12% respec-<lb/>tively) in the rat. The ortho-methyl substituted derivative 55 had a <lb/>similar mouse and lower human intrinsic clearance (Table 6) com-<lb/>pared to the unsubstituted derivative 51 (Table 2). However, it had <lb/>only partial RARa agonist activity. Both the ortho-methyl deriva-<lb/>tives 56 and 44 had good bioavailability (!40%) in the rat and <lb/>lower mouse intrinsic clearance (Table 6) compared to the unsub-<lb/>stituted derivatives 49 and 39 (Table 2), with 56 having the lowest <lb/>(single figure) human intrinsic clearance of these four derivatives. <lb/>While both derivatives 56 and 44 had high RARa potency and <lb/>good bioavailability 56 was superior in terms of selectivity at RARb <lb/>(2 orders of magnitude) and RARc (4 orders of magnitude) and pos-<lb/>sessed a better overall potency, selectivity and PK profile than the <lb/>other analogs 45, 57-59 shown in Table 6. <lb/>Table 5 <lb/>Ortho-substituted benzoic acid derivatives of 5. <lb/>N <lb/>H <lb/>O <lb/>Cl <lb/>Cl <lb/>CO 2 H <lb/>z <lb/>EtO <lb/>Compd <lb/>Z <lb/>RARa <lb/>rel EC 50 <lb/>a <lb/>b/a <lb/>ratio b <lb/>c/a <lb/>ratio b <lb/>5 <lb/>H <lb/>24 <lb/>80 <lb/>&gt;12,500 <lb/>17 <lb/>F <lb/>25 <lb/>80 <lb/>&gt;80 <lb/>18 <lb/>CH 3 <lb/>0.9 <lb/>82 <lb/>151 <lb/>19 <lb/>OH <lb/>33 c <lb/>37 <lb/>149 <lb/>20 <lb/>Cl <lb/>151 <lb/>64 <lb/>&gt;50 <lb/>21 <lb/>CF 3 <lb/>1.7 c <lb/>1.5 <lb/>11 <lb/>a,b and c see Table 1. <lb/>Table 6 <lb/>Ortho-fluoro and ortho-methyl (3-chloro-4,5-dialkoxybenzamido)benzoic acids. <lb/>Potency and Selectivity <lb/>PK <lb/>Compd <lb/>R 1 O <lb/>R 2 O <lb/>R 3 <lb/>RARa <lb/>rel EC 50 <lb/>a <lb/>b/a <lb/>ratio b <lb/>c/a <lb/>ratio b <lb/>LogD pH 7.4 <lb/>d <lb/>intrinsic Cl int <lb/>e <lb/>rat po f <lb/>mouse <lb/>human <lb/>AUC <lb/>Cl <lb/>F% <lb/>53 <lb/>i PrO <lb/>MeO <lb/>F <lb/>6.7 <lb/>609 <lb/>17,600 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>11 <lb/>0.3 <lb/>10,871 <lb/>15 <lb/>15 <lb/>54 <lb/>i PrO <lb/>EtO <lb/>F <lb/>1.1 <lb/>487 <lb/>6169 <lb/>1.4 <lb/>17.9 <lb/>3.3 <lb/>15,376 <lb/>12 <lb/>12 <lb/>43 <lb/>i PrO <lb/>i <lb/>PrO <lb/>F <lb/>2.7 <lb/>34 <lb/>300 <lb/>2.0 <lb/>18.8 <lb/>6.9 <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>55 <lb/>i PrO <lb/>MeO <lb/>Me <lb/>4.7 c <lb/>241 <lb/>509 <lb/>1.3 <lb/>10.6 <lb/>1.5 <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>44 <lb/>i PrO <lb/>i <lb/>PrO <lb/>Me <lb/>0.97 <lb/>45 <lb/>2947 <lb/>2.3 <lb/>26.2 <lb/>15 <lb/>77,670 <lb/>5.4 <lb/>66 <lb/>56 <lb/>i PrO <lb/>EtO <lb/>Me <lb/>1.6 <lb/>200 <lb/>11,000 <lb/>1.8 <lb/>37.6 <lb/>5.3 <lb/>70,765 <lb/>7 <lb/>40 <lb/>57 <lb/>EtO <lb/>i <lb/>PrO <lb/>Me <lb/>7 <lb/>286 <lb/>1675 <lb/>1.9 <lb/>25.7 <lb/>8.7 <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>58 <lb/>MeO <lb/>EtO <lb/>Me <lb/>33 <lb/>210 <lb/>&gt;250 <lb/>-<lb/>18.4 <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>59 <lb/>EtO <lb/>Me <lb/>2.6 <lb/>58 <lb/>38,461 <lb/>-<lb/>42.3 <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>45 <lb/>t BuO <lb/>t BuO <lb/>Me <lb/>0.64 <lb/>13,200 <lb/>128 <lb/>2.9 <lb/>36.2 <lb/>28.7 <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>a Relative EC 50 . <lb/>b Relative EC 50 ratios and c partial agonist see Table 1. <lb/>d Measured by octanol/buffer shake flask method at pH 7.4 see Table 2. <lb/>e Cl int (mL/min/mg protein) and f AUC (ngÁmin mL À1 ), Cl (mL min À1 kg À1 ) see Table 2. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">E. Clarke et al. / Bioorganic &amp; Medicinal Chemistry 26 (2018) 798-814 <lb/></note>

			<page>805 <lb/></page>

			<body>The 3-OEt, 4-OiPr geometrical isomer 57 was less potent and <lb/>less selective at RARc than 56 which is analogous to the trend seen <lb/>with compounds 51 and 49 in the unsubstituted benzoic acid ser-<lb/>ies. This emphasizes the need for a more lipophilic group than OEt <lb/>in the 3-and 5-position in this template which was initially seen in <lb/>Table 3. Thus the 3-OiPr, 4-OEt derivative 56 reached our target <lb/>profile in terms of potency, selectivity, and oral bioavailability. <lb/>The excellent RARa potency, good RARb and RARc selectivity <lb/>and PK profile of the full agonist 56 suggested further investiga-<lb/>tions to see if it had sufficient drug-like properties to be an orally <lb/>bioavailable, highly potent and selective RARa agonist with thera-<lb/>peutic potential. <lb/>3.5. Predevelopment studies of 4-(3-chloro-4-ethoxy-5-<lb/>isopropoxybenzamido)-2-methylbenzoic acid 56 <lb/>3.5.1. ADME profiling <lb/>Predevelopment ADME studies revealed that 56 has a good Cyp <lb/>450 profile with no significant inhibition IC 50 &gt; 25 lM against five <lb/>Cyp 450 isozymes (1A2, 2C9, 2C19, 2D6, 3A4), and has a human <lb/>and mouse plasma protein binding of 93% and 91% respectively. 20 <lb/>Compound 56 has also been examined by CEREP in a panel of <lb/>120 other receptors, channels and enzymes. The compound at 10 <lb/>lM demonstrated no significant interactions with any of the sites <lb/>examined leaving a window of some 4 orders of magnitude <lb/>between its actions at RAR and any non-RAR site. 21 The highest <lb/>inhibition of 25% was found for the 5HT2B site. To exclude poten-<lb/>tial cardiovascular side effects, compound 56 was tested in vitro on <lb/>the cardiac hERG channel and did not show any significant binding <lb/>to hERG up to the concentration of 10 lM. 20 <lb/>3.5.2. Hepatocyte stability <lb/>We initially used a microsomes assay as a screen to rank order <lb/>compounds of interest in terms of their metabolic stability. As <lb/>microsomes only contain phase I metabolising enzymes it was of <lb/>interest to screen our lead compound 56 in a secondary screen <lb/>using hepatocytes which contain the full complement of drug <lb/>metabolising enzymes present in the liver. <lb/>The metabolic stability of compound 56 was tested at two con-<lb/>centrations (1 lM and 30 lM) in mouse, rat, dog, Cynomolgus <lb/>monkey and human cryopreserved hepatocytes. The compound <lb/>was shown to be stable, with a long t½ and low clearance in all <lb/>species (Table 7), which correlates with the available PK data <lb/>(Table 8). <lb/>3.5.3. PK profile in mice and dogs <lb/>The PK profile of 56 was also studied in mice and dogs (Table 8). <lb/>Compound 56 showed low plasma clearance (Cl) and low volume <lb/>of distribution (Vss), resulting in sustained plasma half-lives in <lb/>each species (iv t 1/2 : mice, 1.9 h; dog, 9.2 h). In addition, oral <lb/>administration of 56 exhibited high bioavailabilities &gt;80% in both <lb/>mice and dogs. These results encouraged us to investigate 56 fur-<lb/>ther as a predevelopment candidate. <lb/>3.5.4. Human RAR alpha receptor <lb/>As we planned to perform PK and further in vivo evaluation in <lb/>rodents, we initially used the corresponding in vitro transcriptional <lb/>transactivation assays with gal4 fusion receptor constructs, created <lb/>using each of the mouse RAR ligand-binding domains. Although <lb/>the percentage identity of amino acid sequences between the <lb/>mouse and human RAR ligand-binding domains of all three RAR <lb/>types (a,b or c) is 99-100%, 23 we thought it prudent to confirm <lb/>the activity and selectivity of our lead compound 56 against the <lb/>human RAR ligand-binding domains in a transcriptional transacti-<lb/>vation assay before further predevelopment studies were investi-<lb/>gated. We also tested an earlier less active analog 15 from the <lb/>3,5-dichloro template, and AM 580 (2) for comparison (Table 9). <lb/>There is a good correspondence for RARa potency between <lb/>human vs mouse for 56 and 15 with the human being slightly more <lb/>potent, in contrast to the RARa potency for AM 580 (2) where the <lb/>human is less potent than the mouse (Table 9). Similarly, the a vs b <lb/>selectivity comparison for 56 and 15, shows that the human is <lb/>more selective than the mouse, while for AM 580 (2) the human <lb/>is less selective than the mouse. Also, a vs c selectivity for 56 is <lb/>4 orders of magnitude compared to AM 580 (2) where it is only <lb/>2 orders of magnitude for both human and mouse. <lb/>3.5.5. In vitro toxicology <lb/>In common with most of the other compounds in the series, the <lb/>lead compound 56 showed no cytotoxicity in COS-7 cells at a 50-<lb/>fold multiple of its EC 50 . 20 When examined in a high content cell <lb/>toxicity screen in HEPG2 cells (Cyprotex), 56 was found to have <lb/>no effect at concentrations up to 50 lM on cell or mitochondrial <lb/>viability markers. 20 This is in contrast to the more lipophilic mole-<lb/>cule AM 580 (2) which caused a significant increase in cell mem-<lb/>brane permeability and a significant decrease in mitochondrial <lb/>membrane potential at concentrations between 10 and 30 lM. <lb/>When 56 was examined for genetic toxicity, it was negative in <lb/>bacterial cytotoxicity tests up to 100 lM, negative in an Ames test <lb/>Table 8 <lb/>Pharmacokinetic Profiles of 56 in Mice and Dogs. a <lb/>iv <lb/>po <lb/>Species <lb/>Cl (mL/h/kg) <lb/>Vss (mL/kg) <lb/>t 1/2 (h) <lb/>C max (ng/mL) <lb/>T max (h) <lb/>F (%) <lb/>mice b <lb/>4.7 <lb/>0.3 <lb/>1.9 <lb/>2007 <lb/>0.25 <lb/>84 <lb/>dog c <lb/>2.3 <lb/>0.66 <lb/>9.2 <lb/>2050 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>83 <lb/>a Administered at a dose of 1 mg/kg by both iv and po routes in mice. Administered at a dose of 0.5 mg/kg, iv, 1 mg/kg, po, in dogs. Vehicle = 2% DMSO in 0.05 M phosphate <lb/>buffered saline, pH 7.4. Data are expressed as mean values (mice, n = 3. dogs n = 3). <lb/>b C57 mice. For assay details see Supplementary data file. <lb/>c Beagle dogs. For assay details see Supplementary data file. <lb/>Table 7 <lb/>Stability of 56 in hepatocytes. <lb/>Conc <lb/>(lM) <lb/>Species <lb/>Half-life <lb/>(minutes) a <lb/>Cl int (ll/min/million <lb/>cells) <lb/>1 <lb/>Mouse <lb/>224 <lb/>12 <lb/>Rat <lb/>357 <lb/>4 <lb/>Dog <lb/>&gt;450 <lb/>&lt;3 <lb/>Cynomolgus <lb/>monkey <lb/>&gt;450 <lb/>&lt;3 <lb/>Human <lb/>&gt;450 <lb/>&lt;3 <lb/>30 <lb/>Mouse <lb/>&gt;300 <lb/>&lt;9 <lb/>Rat <lb/>&gt;450 <lb/>&lt;3 <lb/>Dog <lb/>&gt;450 <lb/>&lt;3 <lb/>Cynomolgus <lb/>monkey <lb/>&gt;450 <lb/>&lt;3 <lb/>Human <lb/>&gt;450 <lb/>&lt;3 <lb/>a Data are expressed as mean values (n = 2). For assay details see Supplementary <lb/>data file. <lb/></body>

			<page>806 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">E. Clarke et al. / Bioorganic &amp; Medicinal Chemistry 26 (2018) 798-814 <lb/></note>

			<body>in three bacterial strains and in an in vitro micronucleus test in <lb/>CHO-K1 cells, in all cases in both the presence and absence of <lb/>S9. 21 In the absence of S9 it should be noted that AM 580 (2), the <lb/>reference RARa agonist has been shown by others to be a mutagen <lb/>in vitro. 11,12 <lb/>3.5.6. Ease of synthesis <lb/>The 4-(3-chloro-4-ethoxy-5-isopropoxybenzamido)-2-methyl-<lb/>benzoic acid 56 can be synthesized in 9 high yielding reaction steps <lb/>from 3-chloro-4-hydroxy-5-methoxybenzoic acid (35) (Scheme 5). <lb/>It is available as a stable highly crystalline, non-hygroscopic, white <lb/>powder with a melting point of 186 °C, and with a solubility of &gt;5 <lb/>mg/mL, as the sodium salt in water at 35 °C. <lb/>3.5.7. Profile of lead compound 56 <lb/>The 3-OiPr, 4-OEt, 5-Cl ortho methyl benzoic acid derivative 56 <lb/>met our target profile in terms of high RARa agonist potency with a <lb/>high degree of selectivity over RARb (of 2 orders of magnitude) and <lb/>excellent selectivity over RARc (4 orders of magnitude) at both the <lb/>mouse and human receptors. It has high levels of potency in the <lb/>RARa binding assay (IC 50 ) showing that the transactivation activity <lb/>observed was being mediated through the alpha receptor <lb/>(Table 10). As expected 56 was also selective vs RXR (IC 50 &gt; 10 <lb/>lM in human RXR a and b binding assays). 22 It also possesses good <lb/>drug-like properties, a low human intrinsic clearance (5.3 mL/min/ <lb/>mg protein) in microsomes and a measured Log D = 1.8, which <lb/>resulted in good oral exposure with low clearance and good <lb/>bioavailability (40%) in the rat (Table 10). In contrast, both 15 <lb/>and 2 have human intrinsic clearance in double figures and a <lb/>higher Log D = 2.8, which resulted in low oral exposure in the rat <lb/>with low bioavailability (0.3%) for 15. Compound 56 was also <lb/>shown to be metabolically stable to hepatocytes with a long t½ <lb/>and low clearance in human and 4 animal species (Table 7) <lb/>together with a high bioavailability (&gt;80%) in both mice and dogs <lb/>with low plasma clearance (CL) and a sustained plasma half-live <lb/>(iv t 1/2 : mice, 1.9 h; dog, 9.2 h) (Table 8). In addition 56 has a sol-<lb/>ubility of &gt;5 mg/mL as the sodium salt, no systematic Cyp 450 lia-<lb/>bility against five isoforms (1A2, 2C9, 2C19, 2D6, 3A4) and <lb/>demonstrated no inhibition (at 10 lM) in a binding assay for hERG <lb/>channels. It was not cytotoxic in COS-7 cells and was negative for <lb/>genetic toxicity in the Ames test and micronucleus test in CHO-K1 <lb/>cells. <lb/>4. Conclusions <lb/>We have used a ligand-based virtual screening exercise based <lb/>on the bioactive conformation of AM 580 (2) and AGN 193836 <lb/>(3) to identify the novel, less lipophilic RARa agonist 4-(3,5-<lb/>dichloro-4-ethoxybenzamido) benzoic acid 5, which has good <lb/>selectivity over the RARb, and RARc receptors. Analysis of the <lb/>Table 9 <lb/>Human and Mouse RARa Potency plus b and c selectivity. <lb/>Property <lb/>56 <lb/>15 <lb/>AM580(2) <lb/>ATRA <lb/>mouse a <lb/>human b <lb/>mouse a <lb/>human b <lb/>mouse a <lb/>human b <lb/>mouse <lb/>human <lb/>RARa rel EC 50 <lb/>1.6 <lb/>0.59 <lb/>10.4 <lb/>8.1 <lb/>0.02 <lb/>0.13 <lb/>1.0 (1.51 nM) c <lb/>1.0 (1.01 nM) d <lb/>Selectivity b/a ratio <lb/>200-fold <lb/>290-fold <lb/>33-fold <lb/>289-fold <lb/>1130-fold <lb/>162-fold <lb/>0.34-fold <lb/>0.33-fold <lb/>Selectivity c/a ratio <lb/>11,000-fold <lb/>&gt;13,000-fold <lb/>452-fold <lb/>2322-fold <lb/>826-fold <lb/>505-fold <lb/>0.15-fold <lb/>0.11-fold <lb/>a See Table 1. <lb/>b Transactivation RAR human assay. For details see Supplementary data file. <lb/>c Mean of ATRA EC 50 (nM) mouse assay RARa. <lb/>d Mean of ATRA EC 50 (nM) human assay RARa. <lb/>Table 10 <lb/>Comparison of the RARa Agonist Potency, selectivity versus the RARb and RARc Human and Mouse Receptors, Human Intrinsic Clearance and Pharmacokinetic Profile in Rat for 56 <lb/>and 15. <lb/>Binding Activity <lb/>Agonist Potency and Selectivity <lb/>PK <lb/>Compd <lb/>RARa <lb/>rel IC 50 <lb/>a <lb/>RARa <lb/>rel EC 50 <lb/>b m/ c hu <lb/>b/a <lb/>ratio <lb/>b <lb/>m/ c hu <lb/>c/a <lb/>ratio <lb/>b <lb/>m/ c hu <lb/>intrinsic Cl int <lb/>d <lb/>rat po e <lb/>f Log D <lb/>pH 7.4 <lb/>human <lb/>AUC <lb/>Cl <lb/>F% <lb/>56 <lb/>3.6 <lb/>1.6/0.6 <lb/>200/298 <lb/>11,000/&gt;13,000 <lb/>5.3 <lb/>70,765 <lb/>7 <lb/>40 <lb/>1.8 <lb/>15 <lb/>115 <lb/>10.4/8.1 <lb/>33/289 <lb/>452/2322 <lb/>26 <lb/>1674 <lb/>2 <lb/>0.3 <lb/>2.8 <lb/>AM 580(2) <lb/>9 <lb/>0.02/0.13 <lb/>1130/162 <lb/>826/505 <lb/>15.6 <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>2.8 <lb/>a RARa binding assay. The relative IC 50 is the mean IC 50 for each compound divided by the mean IC 50 of ATRA (IC 50 = 0.6 nM). Values were obtained from three separate <lb/>experiments. <lb/>b m = mouse receptor, see Table 1. <lb/>c hu = human receptor, see Table 9. <lb/>d Human microsomes Cl int (mL/min/mg protein). <lb/>e AUC po ngÁmin mL À1 ,Cl mL/kg/min. <lb/>f Log D see Table 2. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">E. Clarke et al. / Bioorganic &amp; Medicinal Chemistry 26 (2018) 798-814 <lb/></note>

			<page>807 <lb/></page>

			<body>medicinal chemistry parameters of the 3,5-substituents of deriva-<lb/>tives of template 5 showed that RARa potency is driven by the <lb/>lipophilicity of these substituents. It showed that the iPrO group <lb/>is a good bioisostere of the Cl group in this case and that the 4 0 -<lb/>(3,5-diisopropoxy-4-ethoxybenzamido)benzoic acid derivative 31 <lb/>has a close profile to 5 in terms of RARa potency as well as RARb <lb/>and RARc selectivity. The low mouse and human intrinsic clear-<lb/>ance with excellent oral absorption and bioavailability (81%) in <lb/>the rat shown by 31 led to the exploration of the more drug-like <lb/>branched dialkoxy derivatives, the best of which was the 4-(3-<lb/>chloro-4,5-diisopropoxybenzamido)benzoic acid derivative 39 <lb/>which was an order of magnitude more potent than 31 at RARa, <lb/>while maintaining excellent selectivity over RARc with moderate <lb/>selectivity at RARb and was orally well absorbed in the rat with a <lb/>bioavailability of 39%. Substitution at the ortho-position of benzoic <lb/>acid 5, with a range of groups, has shown that methyl groups are <lb/>the best at increasing potency while maintaining good RARb and <lb/>RARc selectivity. Methyl substitution at the ortho-position of the <lb/>4 0 -benzoic acid ring of a series of 4 0 -(3-chloro-4,5-dialkoxybenza-<lb/>mido)benzoic acid derivatives gave the novel RARa agonist 4-(3-<lb/>chloro-4-ethoxy-5-isopropoxybenzamido)-2-methylbenzoic acid <lb/>56 as the best in terms of RARa agonist potency and selectivity ver-<lb/>sus RARb (2 orders of magnitude) and RARc (4 orders of magni-<lb/>tude) at both the human and mouse RAR receptors. This potent <lb/>RARa-specific agonist with improved physicochemical properties <lb/>also has high bioavailability (&gt;80%) in both mice and dogs with a <lb/>good PK profile and drug-like properties and was shown to be neg-<lb/>ative in the cytotoxicity and genotoxicity screens warranting fur-<lb/>ther consideration as a potential therapeutic agent. <lb/>5. Experimental procedures <lb/>All starting materials and solvents, as well as compounds 5, 60, <lb/>61 and 62, were obtained from commercial sources. Hydrogena-<lb/>tions were performed either on a Thales H-cube flow reactor or <lb/>with a suspension of the catalyst under a balloon of hydrogen. <lb/>Microwave reactions were carried out on a Personal Chemistry <lb/>Smith Synthesizer Workstation with a 300 W single mode micro-<lb/>wave cavity. Ion exchange chromatography was performed using <lb/>strong cation exchange resin (SCX) cartridges purchased from <lb/>Sigma-Aldrich and washed with methanol prior to use. The reac-<lb/>tion mixture to be purified was first dissolved in methanol and <lb/>then loaded directly onto the SCX and washed with methanol. <lb/>The desired material was then eluted by washing with 1% NH 3 in <lb/>methanol. Silica gel column chromatography was performed using <lb/>Silicycle pre-packed silica (230-400 mesh, 40-63 lM) cartridges. <lb/>Preparative HPLC was carried out using a Gilson HPLC and an Agi-<lb/>lent 5 mm Prep-C18 21.2 Â 50 mm column. Detection was achieved <lb/>using a UV detector at 254 nm. Mobile phase A: 0.1% aqueous for-<lb/>mic acid, Mobile phase B: 0.1% formic acid in methanol. A flow rate <lb/>of 40 mL/min was used and a gradient employed as follows; 0.0-<lb/>0.8 min 5% B; 0.8-7.3 min 5-95% B; 7.3-8.3 min 95% B; 8.3-8.4 <lb/>min 95-5% B. Analytical LCMS was performed using an Agilent <lb/>1200 HPLC and mass spectrometer system with a Scalar 5 mm <lb/>C18 4.6 Â 50 mm column and peaks detected by positive or nega-<lb/>tive ion electrospray ionization and a UV detector at 254 nm. All <lb/>tested compounds were found to be of !95% purity using analyti-<lb/>cal LCMS. 1 H and 13 C NMR spectra were recorded using a Bruker <lb/>Avance III TM 400 spectrometer at 400 and 110 MHz respectively, <lb/>using either residual non-deuterated solvent or tetramethylsilane <lb/>as a reference in the various solvents specified. All animal studies <lb/>were ethically reviewed and carried out in accordance with the <lb/>United Kingdom Animals (Scientific Procedures) Act 1986 by CXR <lb/>Biosciences Ltd, James Lindsay Place, Dundee Technopole, Dundee <lb/>DD 5JJ. <lb/>5.1. Chemistry <lb/>5.1.1. 4-(3,5-Dichloro-4-(cyclopentyloxy)benzamido)benzoic acid (15) <lb/>Step (i): Methyl 3,5-dichloro-4-(cyclopentyloxy)benzoate <lb/>Methyl 3,5-dichloro-4-hydroxybenzoate 6 (1.00 g, 4.52 mmol) <lb/>was dissolved in N, N-dimethylformamide (8 mL) and treated with <lb/>bromocyclopentane (534 mL, 4.98 mmol), followed by potassium <lb/>carbonate (937 mg, 6.79 mmol). The mixture was stirred at 80 <lb/>°C <lb/>for 3 h and then partitioned between ethyl acetate (100 mL) and <lb/>water (100 mL). The aqueous phase was extracted with ethyl acet-<lb/>ate (50 mL) and the combined organic phases washed successively <lb/>with water (5 Â 50 mL) and brine (50 mL), then dried over magne-<lb/>sium sulfate and filtered. The solvent was removed in vacuo to <lb/>afford methyl 3,5-dichloro-4-(cyclopentyloxy) benzoate (1.10 g, <lb/>84% yield). 1 H NMR (400 MHz, CDCl 3 ) d 7.97 (2H, s), 5.04 (1H, m), <lb/>3.90 (3H, s), 2.04-1.91 (4H, m), 1.82-1.75 (2H, m), 1.69-1.60 <lb/>(2H, m). <lb/>Step (ii): 3,5-Dichloro-4-(cyclopentyloxy)benzoicacid (7: R 1 = <lb/>cyclopentyloxy). Methyl 3,5-dichloro-4-(cyclopentyloxy)benzoate <lb/>(1.05 g, 3.63 mmol) and lithium hydroxide (174 mg, 7.26 mmol) <lb/>were combined in tetrahydrofuran (10 mL), and water (1.5 mL) <lb/>was added dropwise until a solution formed. The resultant mixture <lb/>was stirred at room temperature for 12 h. The tetrahydrofuran was <lb/>removed in vacuo and the residue acidified using aqueous 1 M <lb/>hydrochloric acid. The resultant precipitate was filtered to afford <lb/>3,5-dichloro-4-(cyclopentyloxy)benzoic acid (7: R 1 = cyclopenty-<lb/>loxy), (820 mg, 82% yield). 1 H NMR (400 MHz, DMSO d 6 ) d 8.10 <lb/>(2H, s), 5.03 (1H, m), 2.04-1.91 (4H, m), 1.82-1.75 (2H, m), 1.69-<lb/>1.60 (2H, m). <lb/>Step (iii): Methyl 4-[3,5-dichloro-4-(cyclopentyloxy)benza-<lb/>mido]benzoate (10: R 1 = cyclopentyloxy, R 2 = H, R = Me). A solu-<lb/>tion of (7: R 1 = cyclopentyloxy) (100 mg, 363 mmol) in <lb/>dichloromethane (5 mL), cooled to 0 °C, was treated with oxalyl <lb/>chloride (63.6 mL, 727 mmol), followed by a drop of N, N-dimethyl-<lb/>formamide. The resultant mixture was stirred for 1 h at room tem-<lb/>perature. The solvent was evaporated in vacuo and the residue <lb/>dissolved in dichloromethane (5 mL) and then treated with a solu-<lb/>tion of methyl 4-aminobenzoate (8: R 2 = H, R = Me) (54.9 mg, 363 <lb/>mmol) and di-isopropylethylamine (190 mL, 1.09 mmol) in dichlor-<lb/>omethane (5 mL). The reaction mixture was stirred for12 h at room <lb/>temperature and then partitioned between dichloromethane (20 <lb/>mL) and aqueous 1 M hydrochloric acid (20 mL). The phases were <lb/>separated, and the organic phase was washed successively with <lb/>water (2 Â 20 mL), and brine (20 mL), dried over magnesium sul-<lb/>fate, filtered and then the solvent was removed in vacuo. The resi-<lb/>due was purified by silica gel chromatography (12 g, 0-100% ethyl <lb/>acetate/isohexane) to afford methyl 4-[3,5-dichloro-4-(cyclopenty-<lb/>loxy)benzamido]benzoate (10: R 1 = cyclopentyloxy, R 2 = H, R = <lb/>Me), (30 mg, 20% yield). 1H NMR (400 MHz, CDCl 3 ) d 8.06 (2H, d, <lb/>J = 8.8 Hz,), 7.85 (1H, br s), 7.82 (2H, s), 7.71 (2H, d, J = 8.8 Hz), <lb/>5.07-5.03 (1H, m), 3.92 (3H, s), 2.10-1.90 (4H, m), 1.85-1.70 (2H, <lb/>m), 1.70-1.60 (2H, m). <lb/>Step (iv): 4-[3,5-Dichloro-4-(cyclopentyloxy)benzamido]ben-<lb/>zoicacid (15). Compound (10: R 1 = cyclopentyloxy, R 2 = H, R = <lb/>Me), (30.0 mg, 73 mmol) and lithium hydroxide (3.5 mg, 0.147 <lb/>mmol) were combined in tetrahydrofuran (3 mL) and water was <lb/>added dropwise until a solution formed. The resultant mixture <lb/>was stirred at room temperature for 16 h. The tetrahydrofuran <lb/>was removed in vacuo and the residue acidified using aqueous 1 <lb/>M hydrochloric acid. The resultant precipitate was filtered to afford <lb/>4-[3,5-dichloro-4-(cyclopentyloxy)benzamido]benzoic acid 15 <lb/>(15.0 mg, 51% yield) as a white solid. 1 H NMR (400 MHz, DMSO d 6 ) <lb/>d 12.77 (1H, s), 10.58 (1H, s), 8.07 (2H, s), 7.93 (2H, d, J = 8.8 Hz,), <lb/>7.88 (2H, d, J = 8.8 Hz), 5.06-5.01 (1H, m), 1.90-1.60 (8H, m). m/z <lb/>392 (MÀH) À (ES À ). <lb/></body>

			<page>808 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">E. Clarke et al. / Bioorganic &amp; Medicinal Chemistry 26 (2018) 798-814 <lb/></note>

			<body>The compounds 12-14, 17, 20, 21, 63 and 64 were similarly <lb/>prepared as 15: see Supplementary data for experimental and <lb/>spectroscopic details. <lb/>5.1.2. 4-(4-(tert-Butoxy)-3,5-dichlorobenzamido)benzoic acid (16) <lb/>Step (i): Methyl 4-(benzyloxy)-3,5-dichlorobenzoate. Crude <lb/>methyl 4-(benzyloxy)-3,5-dichlorobenzoate (16.9 g) was prepared <lb/>from methyl 3,5-dichloro-4-hydroxybenzoate (6) (10 g, 45.2 <lb/>mmol) and benzyl bromide (15.5 g, 90 mmol) using a procedure <lb/>essentially the same as in step (i) for 15, except that the mixture <lb/>was stirred at room temperature for 18 h. The crude product was <lb/>partially purified by silica gel chromatography (330 g, 0-10% <lb/>EtOAc/isohexane) to afford a white solid. The material was used <lb/>in the next step without further purification. <lb/>Step (ii): 4-(Benzyloxy)-3,5-dichlorobenzoicacid (7: R 1 = CH 2 -<lb/>Ph). 4-(Benzyloxy)-3,5-dichlorobenzoic acid (7: R 1 = CH 2 Ph) <lb/>(12.8 g, 96% over 2 steps) was prepared from crude 4-(benzy-<lb/>loxy)-3,5-dichlorobenzoate (16.9 g) using a procedure essentially <lb/>the same as in step (iv) for 15: 1 H NMR (400 MHz, DMSO d 6 ) d <lb/>7.88 (2H, s), 7.56-7.48 (2H, m), 7.44-7.37 (3H, m), 5.05 (2H, s). <lb/>m/z 295 (MÀH) À (ES À ). <lb/>Step (iii): Methyl 4-(4-(benzyloxy)-3,5-dichlorobenzamido) <lb/>benzoate (10: R 1 = CH 2 Ph, R 2 = H, R = Me). Methyl 4-(4-(benzy-<lb/>loxy)-3,5-dichlorobenzamido)benzoate (10: R 1 = CH 2 Ph, R 2 = H, R <lb/>= Me) (9.81 g, 51%) was prepared from 4-(benzyloxy)-3,5-<lb/>dichlorobenzoic acid (7: R 1 = CH 2 Ph) (12.8 g, 43.2 mmol) using a <lb/>procedure essentially the same as in step (iii) for 15, except the <lb/>crude product was crystallized from isohexane/EtOAc to afford <lb/>the product as a white solid. 1 H NMR (400 MHz, CDCl 3 ) d 8.07 <lb/>(2H, d, J = 8.8 Hz), 7.84 (2H, s), 7.73 (2H, d, J = 8.8 Hz), 7.59-7.52 <lb/>(2H, m), 7.44-7.36 (3H, m), 5.13 (2H, s), 3.92 (3H, s). m/z 428 <lb/>(MÀH) À (ES À ). <lb/>Step (iv): Methyl 4-(3,5-dichloro-4-hydroxybenzamido)ben-<lb/>zoate(11: R 2 =H). A solution of methyl 4-(4-(benzyloxy)-3,5-<lb/>dichlorobenzamido)benzoate (10: R 1 = CH 2 Ph, R 2 = H, R = Me) <lb/>(8.8 g, 20.5 mmol) in DCM (500 mL) was cooled to 0 °C and treated <lb/>dropwise with boron trichloride (20.5 mL, 20.5 mmol, 1 M in <lb/>DCM). The mixture was then allowed to stir at room temperature <lb/>for 12 h. The mixture was cooled in an ice bath then quenched <lb/>by addition of water (150 mL). The resultant mixture was parti-<lb/>tioned between EtOAc (200 mL) and H 2 O (100 mL). The aqueous <lb/>phase was extracted with EtOAc (2 Â 75 mL) and the combined <lb/>organic phases washed successively with water (50 mL) and brine <lb/>(50 mL), then dried over MgSO 4 and filtered. The solvent was <lb/>removed in vacuo. The residue was crystallized from isohexane/ <lb/>EtOAc to afford methyl 4-(3,5-dichloro-4-hydroxybenzamido)ben-<lb/>zoate (11: R 2 = H) (5.81 g, 84%): 1 H NMR (400 MHz, DMSO d 6 ) d <lb/>11.06 (1H, s), 10.52 (1H, s), 8.06 (2H, s), 8.04-7.91 (4H, m), 3.88 <lb/>(3H, s). m/z 338 (MÀH) À (ES À ). <lb/>Step (v): Methyl 4-(4-(tert-butoxy)-3,5-dichlorobenzamido) <lb/>benzoate. A stirred suspension of methyl 4-(3,5-dichloro-4-<lb/>hydroxybenzamido)benzoate (11: R 2 = H) (100 mg, 294 mmol) in <lb/>toluene (2 mL) was heated at 80 °C until homogenous. The resul-<lb/>tant solution was treated with 1,1-di-tert-butoxy-N,N-dimethyl-<lb/>methanamine (141 mL, 588 mmol) and the mixture heated at 80 <lb/>°C <lb/>for 3 h, and then at room temperature for 18 h. Additional 1,1-di-<lb/>tert-butoxy-N,N-dimethylmethanamine (141 mL, 588 mmol) was <lb/>added and the mixture was heated at 80 °C for 5 h. The reaction <lb/>mixture was cooled to room temperature and the solvent was <lb/>removed in vacuo. The residue was diluted with water and <lb/>extracted with Et 2 O. The organic layer was dried over MgSO 4 , fil-<lb/>tered and concentrated in vacuo. The residue was partially purified <lb/>by silica gel chromatography (12 g, 0-50% EtOAc in isohexane) to <lb/>afford methyl 4-(4-(tert-butoxy)-3,5-dichlorobenzamido)benzoate <lb/>(82 mg, 71%). The material was used in the next step without fur-<lb/>ther purification. <lb/>Step (vi): 4-(4-(tert-Butoxy)-3,5-dichlorobenzamido)ben-<lb/>zoicacid (16). 4-(4-(tert-Butoxy)-3,5-dichlorobenzamido)benzoic <lb/>acid 16 (39 mg, 51%) was prepared as a white solid from methyl <lb/>4-(4-(tert-butoxy)-3,5-dichlorobenzamido)benzoate (82 mg, 294 <lb/>mmol) using a procedure essentially the same as in step (ii) for <lb/>15: 1 H NMR (400 MHz, DMSO d 6 ) d 12.79 (1H, s), 10.60 (1H, s), <lb/>8.06 (2H, s), 7.94 (2H, d, J = 8.1 Hz), 7.87 (2H d, J = 8.1 Hz), 1.49 <lb/>(9H, s). m/z 380 [MÀH] À (ES À ). <lb/>5.1.3. 4-(3,5-Dichloro-4-ethoxybenzamido)-2-methylbenzoic acid (18) <lb/>Step (iii): Methyl 4-(3,5-dichloro-4-ethoxybenzamido)-2-<lb/>methylbenzoate (10: R 1 = Et, R 2 = Me). A solution of 3,5-<lb/>dichloro-4-ethoxybenzoic acid (7: R 1 = Et) (285 mg, 1.21 mmol) <lb/>and DIPEA (1.05 mL, 6.05 mmol) in DMF (2.5 mL) was added to <lb/>HATU (690 mg, 1.82 mmol) and the orange mixture was stirred <lb/>for 5 min prior to the addition of methyl 4-amino-2-methylben-<lb/>zoate (8: R = R 2 = Me) (200 mg, 1.21 mmol) in DMF (1 mL). The <lb/>resulting dark orange solution was stirred for 18 h. 2 M HCl (10 <lb/>mL) was added and stirring continued for 10 min, and then the <lb/>mixture was extracted with diethyl ether. The organic layer was <lb/>washed with water (3 Â 15 mL), dried over MgSO 4 , filtered and <lb/>the solvent was evaporated in vacuo. The yellow residue was puri-<lb/>fied by silica gel chromatography (40 g, 0-100% EtOAc in isohex-<lb/>ane) to afford methyl 4-(3,5-dichloro-4-ethoxybenzamido)-2-<lb/>methylbenzoate (10: R 1 = Et, R = R 2 = Me) (267 mg, 56%): 1 H NMR <lb/>(400 MHz, CDCl 3 ) d 7.97 (d, J = 8.5 Hz, 1H), 7.81 (2H, s), 7.83-7.77 <lb/>(1H, m), 7.59-7.48 (2H, m), 4.18 (2H, q, J = 7.0 Hz), 3.89 (3H, s), <lb/>2.63 (3H, s), 1.49 (3H, t, J = 7.0 Hz). m/z 380 (MÀH) À (ES À ). <lb/>Step (ii): 4-(3,5-Dichloro-4-ethoxybenzamido)-2-methylben-<lb/>zoicacid (18). Lithium hydroxide (60 mg, 2.51 mmol) in water (1 <lb/>mL) was added dropwise to a stirring solution of methyl 4-(3,5-<lb/>dichloro-4-ethoxybenzamido)-2-methylbenzoate (10: R 1 = Et, R = <lb/>R 2 = Me) (267 mg, 56%) (240 mg, 0.628 mmol) in THF (5 mL) and <lb/>the resulting yellow solution was stirred for 5 days at room tem-<lb/>perature. The solvent was evaporated in vacuo and dissolved in <lb/>water (5 mL), then acidified with 2 M HCl. The resultant mixture <lb/>was extracted with EtOAc. The organic layer was washed with <lb/>water, dried over MgSO 4 and filtered and pre-adsorbed on silica. <lb/>Silica gel chromatography (40 g, 0-10% IPA in DCM) provided 4-<lb/>(3,5-dichloro-4-ethoxybenzamido)-2-methylbenzoic acid 18 (52 <lb/>mg, 22%) as a white solid: 1 H NMR (400 MHz, DMSO d 6 ) d 12.66 <lb/>(1H, s), 10.49 (1H, s), 8.08 (2H, s), 7.94-7.84 (1H, m), 7.75-7.65 <lb/>(2H, m), 4.14 (2H, q, J = 7.0 Hz), 2.54 (3H, s), 1.40 (3H, t, J = 7.0 <lb/>Hz). m/z 366 (MÀH) À (ES À ). <lb/>The compound 58 was similarly prepared as 18: see Supple-<lb/>mentary data for experimental and spectroscopic details. <lb/>5.1.4. 4-(3,5-Dichloro-4-ethoxybenzamido)-2-hydroxybenzoic acid <lb/>(19) <lb/>Steps (vi) and (vii): tert-Butyl 4-amino-2-methoxybenzoate <lb/>(8: <lb/>R= t Bu, <lb/>R 2 = OMe). <lb/>1,1-di-tert-Butoxy-N,N-dimethyl-<lb/>methanamine (608 mL, 2.54 mmol) was added dropwise to a solu-<lb/>tion of 2-methoxy-4-nitrobenzoic acid 9 (250 mg, 1.27 mmol) in <lb/>toluene (7.5 mL) at 80 °C. The reaction mixture was heated at <lb/>80 °C for 3 h, then a further quantity of 1,1-di-tert-butoxy-N,N-<lb/>dimethylmethanamine (608 mL, 2.54 mmol) was added. The reac-<lb/>tion mixture was heated at 80 °C for 16 h, then diluted with water <lb/>(10 mL) and extracted with Et 2 O (3 Â 10 mL). The combined <lb/>organic phases were washed with brine (30 mL), dried over MgSO 4 , <lb/>filtered and then concentrated in vacuo to afford tert-butyl <lb/>2-methoxy-4-nitrobenzoate (271 mg, 78%) as a pale yellow solid. <lb/>The material was used in the next step without further purifica-<lb/>tion. tert-Butyl 2-methoxy-4-nitrobenzoate (271 mg, 1.07 mmol) <lb/>was dissolved in MeOH (270 mL) and passed through a Thales <lb/>&apos;H-cube&apos; cartridge (10% Pd/C) at a flow rate of 1 mL/min at 25 <lb/>°C <lb/>under full H 2 mode. The solvent was removed in vacuo to afford <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">E. Clarke et al. / Bioorganic &amp; Medicinal Chemistry 26 (2018) 798-814 <lb/></note>

			<page>809 <lb/></page>

			<body>tert-butyl 4-amino-2-methoxybenzoate (8: R = t Bu, R 2 = OMe) <lb/>(234 mg, 92%) as a pale yellow solid: 1 H NMR (400 MHz, DMSO d 6 ) <lb/>d 7.41 (1H, d, J = 8.5 Hz), 6.16 (1H, d, J = 2.0 Hz), 6.09 (1H, dd, J = <lb/>8.5, 2.0 Hz), 5.82 (2H, br s), 3.68 (3H, s), 1.45 (9H, s). m/z 222 <lb/>[MÀH] À (ES À ). <lb/>Step (iii): tert-Butyl 4-(3,5-dichloro-4-ethoxybenzamido)-2-<lb/>methoxybenzoate (10: R 1 = Et, R 2 = OMe, R = t Bu). 3,5-Dichloro-<lb/>4-ethoxybenzoic acid (7: R 1 = Et) (75 mg, 0.32 mmol) in DCM (5 <lb/>mL) was treated with oxalyl chloride (56 lL, 0.64 mmol) dropwise, <lb/>followed by a drop of DMF. The reaction mixture was stirred at <lb/>room temperature for 1 h, and then the solvent was removed in <lb/>vacuo. The residue was dissolved in DCM (5 mL) and TEA (133 <lb/>lL, 957 lmol) was added. The mixture was added to tert-butyl 4-<lb/>amino-2-methoxybenzoate (8: R = t Bu, R 2 = OMe) (71 mg, 0.32 <lb/>mmol) and stirred at room temperature for 16 h. The mixture <lb/>was sequentially washed with sat. aq. NaHCO 3 (5 mL) and 1 M <lb/>HCl (5 mL), and the organic phase was concentrated in vacuo. <lb/>The residue was purified by silica gel chromatography (12 g, 0-<lb/>100% EtOAc in isohexane) to afford tert-butyl 4-(3,5-dichloro-4-<lb/>ethoxybenzamido)-2-methoxybenzoate (10: R 1 = Et, R 2 = OMe, R <lb/>= t Bu) (59 mg, 42%) as a white solid: 1 H NMR (400 MHz, DMSO d 6 ) <lb/>d 10.51 (1H, s), 8.09 (2H, s), 7.63 (1H, d, J = 8.5 Hz), 7.60 (1H, d, J = <lb/>1.9 Hz), 7.43 (1H, dd, J = 8.5, 1.9 Hz), 4.15 (2H, q, J = 7.0 Hz), 3.81 <lb/>(3H, s), 1.51 (9H, s), 1.41 (3H, t, J = 7.0 Hz). m/z 384 [MÀ t Bu+2H] + <lb/>(ES + ). <lb/>Step (viii): 4-(3,5-Dichloro-4-ethoxybenzamido)-2-hydroxy-<lb/>benzoicacid (19). A solution of tert-butyl 4-(3,5-dichloro-4-<lb/>ethoxybenzamido)-2-methoxybenzoate (10: R 1 = Et, R 2 = OMe, R <lb/>= t Bu) (55 mg, 0.13 mmol) in DCM (5 mL) was cooled to 0 °C and <lb/>treated dropwise with a solution of 1 M boron trichloride in DCM <lb/>(349 lL, 349 lmol). The reaction mixture was stirred at 0 °C for <lb/>1 h and then at room temperature for 2 h. The reaction mixture <lb/>was cooled to 0 °C and water (0.5 mL) and sat. aq. NaHCO 3 (2 <lb/>mL) were added. The resulting white precipitate was collected by <lb/>filtration and washed with water (2 mL). The solid was dried, then <lb/>purified by capture and release on SAX, eluting with 5% AcOH in <lb/>THF to afford 4-(3,5-dichloro-4-ethoxybenzamido)-2-hydroxyben-<lb/>zoic acid 19 (11 mg, 24%) as a white solid: 1 H NMR (400 MHz, <lb/>DMSO d 6 ) d 10.51 (1H, s), 8.06 (2H, s), 7.76 (1H, d, J = 8.7 Hz), <lb/>7.48 (1H, d, J = 2.0 Hz), 7.32-7.25 (1H, m), 4.14 (2H, q, J = 7.0 Hz), <lb/>1.91 (1H, s), 1.40 (3H, t, J = 7.0 Hz), 1.35 (1H, s). m/z 370 [M+H] + <lb/>(ES + ), 368 [MÀH] À (ES À ). <lb/>5.1.5. 4-(3,5-Dichloro-4-ethoxyphenylcarbamoyl)benzoic acid (26) <lb/>Steps (i) and (ii): 4-(3,5-Dichloro-4-hydroxyphenylcarbamoyl) <lb/>benzoicacid (25). A mixture of 4-(chlorocarbonyl)benzoic acid <lb/>methyl ester 23 (600 mg, ca. 3.02 mmol) contaminated with 4-<lb/>(methoxycarbonyl)benzoic acid 22 was suspended in DCM (5 mL) <lb/>and cooled to 0 °C. The mixture was treated with oxalyl chloride <lb/>(529 mL, 6.04 mmol) and DMF (1 drop). The resultant mixture <lb/>was warmed to room temperature, stirred for 2 h, and then con-<lb/>centrated in vacuo. The residue was dissolved in DCM (3 mL) and <lb/>a suspension of 4-amino-2,6-dichlorophenol 24 (511 mg, 2.9 <lb/>mmol) in DCM (18 mL) was added. The resultant suspension was <lb/>treated with DIPEA (1.58 mL, 9.06 mmol) and was stirred at room <lb/>temperature for 16 h. The solvent was removed in vacuo and the <lb/>residue partitioned between EtOAc/DCM and aqueous HCl (1 M). <lb/>The layers were separated and the organic layer was washed with <lb/>water and brine. The organic layer was dried over MgSO 4 , filtered <lb/>and then the solvent evaporated in vacuo to afford a pale brown <lb/>solid (930 mg), which was triturated in hot acetonitrile/methanol <lb/>(9:1) and filtered. The precipitate and filtrate were recombined, <lb/>the solvent was evaporated in vacuo and then the residue was dis-<lb/>solved in THF (40 mL). Water (10 mL) was added and the mixture <lb/>treated with lithium hydroxide (340 mg, 14.2 mmol). The mixture <lb/>was stirred for 16 h and then partitioned between EtOAc and aque-<lb/>ous HCl (1 M). The organic layer was washed successively with <lb/>water (2 Â 50 mL), brine, dried over MgSO 4 , filtered and then con-<lb/>centrated in vacuo to afford crude 4-(3,5-dichloro-4-hydrox-<lb/>yphenylcarbamoyl)benzoic acid 25 as a pale brown solid. This <lb/>material was used in the subsequent reaction step without <lb/>purification. <lb/>Step (iii): Ethyl 4-(3,5-dichloro-4-ethoxyphenylcarbamoyl) <lb/>benzoate. Crude 4-(3,5-dichloro-4-hydroxyphenylcarbamoyl)ben-<lb/>zoic acid 25 (450 mg) was dissolved in DMF (15 mL) and treated <lb/>with potassium carbonate (829 mg, 6.00 mmol) and iodoethane <lb/>(436 mL, 5.4 mmol). The mixture was stirred at 65 °C for 16 h. <lb/>Iodoethane (200 mL, 2.48 mmol) was added and the reaction mix-<lb/>ture stirred at 70 °C for 3 h. The mixture was partitioned between <lb/>EtOAc (150 mL) and aqueous HCl (100 mL, 1 M). The layers were <lb/>separated and the organic layer was washed successively with sat-<lb/>urated aqueous NaHCO 3 and water. The organic layer was dried <lb/>over MgSO 4 , filtered and the solvent evaporated in vacuo. The resi-<lb/>due was purified by silica gel chromatography (10-25% EtOAc/iso-<lb/>hexane) to afford ethyl 4-(3,5-dichloro-4-ethoxyphenylcarbamoyl) <lb/>benzoate (500 mg, 75% over 2 steps) as a pale pink solid: m/z 380 <lb/>(MÀH) + (ES À ). <lb/>Step (iv): 4-(3,5-Dichloro-4-ethoxyphenylcarbamoyl)ben-<lb/>zoicacid (26). Ethyl 4-(3,5-dichloro-4-ethoxyphenylcarbamoyl) <lb/>benzoate (109 mg, 285 mmol) in THF (5 mL) was treated with aque-<lb/>ous lithium hydroxide (1.43 mL, 1 M, 1.43 mmol) and the mixture <lb/>was stirred at room temperature for 5 h. The reaction mixture was <lb/>partitioned between EtOAc and aqueous HCl (1 M). The organic <lb/>layer was separated and washed successively with water and <lb/>brine. The organic layer was dried over MgSO 4 , filtered and then <lb/>concentrated in vacuo to afford 4-(3,5-dichloro-4-ethoxyphenyl-<lb/>carbamoyl)benzoic acid 26 (89 mg, 88%) as a pale lilac solid: 1 H <lb/>NMR (400 MHz, DMSO d 6 ) d 13.30 (1H, s), 10.58 (1H, s), 8.13-<lb/>7.99 (4H, m), 7.94 (2H, s), 4.04 (2H, q, J = 7.0 Hz), 1.37 (3H, t, J = <lb/>7.0 Hz). m/z 352 [MÀH] À (ES À ). <lb/>5.1.6. 4-(4-Ethoxy-3,5-diisopropoxybenzamido)benzoic acid (31) <lb/>Step (i): Methyl 3,5-dihydroxy-4-ethoxybenzoate(28: R 1 = Et). <lb/>A mixture of methyl 3,4,5-trihydroxybenzoate 27 (5g, 27.2 mmol), <lb/>iodoethane (2.194 mL, 27.2 mmol) and sodium hydrogen carbon-<lb/>ate (9.12 g, 109 mmol) was stirred in N,N-dimethylformamide <lb/>(50 mL) at 30 °C for 72 h. Water (50 mL) was added and the mix-<lb/>ture was extracted with ethyl acetate (2 Â 50 mL). The organic <lb/>layer was then washed with water (50 mL), brine (50 mL), dried <lb/>over magnesium sulfate, filtered and concentrated in vacuo. The <lb/>product was then purified by silica gel chromatography (80 g, 0-<lb/>20% hexane/ethyl acetate) to leave 28 (2.90 g, 50% yield). 1 H <lb/>NMR (400 MHz, CDCl 3 ) d 7.24 (2H, s), 5.68 (2H, s), 4.21 (2H, q, J <lb/>= 7.1 Hz), 3.89 (3H, s), 1.42 (3H, t, J = 7.0 Hz). <lb/>Step (ii): 3,5-Diisopropoxy-4-ethoxybenzoicacid (29: R 1 = Et, <lb/>R 2 = R 3 = iPr). Compound 28 (500 mg, 2.36 mmol) was combined <lb/>with 2-bromopropane (885 lL, 9.43 mmol) and potassium carbon-<lb/>ate (651 mg, 4.71 mmol) in N,N-dimethylformamide (5 mL). The <lb/>resulting suspension was stirred at 50 °C for 48 h. Water (5 mL) <lb/>was added and the mixture was extracted with ethyl acetate (2 <lb/>Â 5 mL). The organic layer was then washed with water (5 mL), <lb/>brine (5 mL), dried over magnesium sulfate, filtered and concen-<lb/>trated in vacuo. The crude product was then purified by silica gel <lb/>chromatography (40 g, 0-50% hexane/ethyl acetate) to leave <lb/>methyl 3,5-diisopropoxy-4-ethoxybenzoate (530 mg, 76% yield). <lb/>1 <lb/>H NMR (400 MHz, CDCl 3 ) d 7.27 (2H, s), 4.61-4.55 (2H, m), 4.10 <lb/>(2H, q, J = 7.1 Hz), 3.88 (3H, s), 1.38-1.33 (15H, m). <lb/>Step (iii): Methyl 3,5-diisopropoxy-4-ethoxybenzoatewas con-<lb/>verted to compound (29: R 1 = Et, R 2 = R 3 = iPr) in 57% yield using <lb/>lithium hydroxide in the procedure described for compound 15. <lb/>1 <lb/>H NMR (400 MHz, CDCl 3 ) d 7.34 (2H, s), 4.61-4.55 (2H, m), 4.10 <lb/>(2H, q, J = 7.1 Hz), 1.40-1.33 (15H, m). <lb/></body>

			<page>810 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">E. Clarke et al. / Bioorganic &amp; Medicinal Chemistry 26 (2018) 798-814 <lb/></note>

			<body>Step <lb/>(iv): <lb/>4-(4-Ethoxy-3,5-diisopropoxybenzamido)ben-<lb/>zoicacid (31). Compound (29: R 1 = Et, R 2 = R 3 = iPr) and 30 were <lb/>coupled and hydrolyzed to the title compound 31 (288 mg, 57% <lb/>for final step) as a white solid, using the procedures described for <lb/>the preparation of 15. 1 H NMR (400 MHz, CDCl 3 ) d 8.02 (2H, d, J <lb/>= 8.7 Hz), 7.85 (1H, br s), 7.75 (2H, d, J = 8.8 Hz), 7.09 (2H, s), <lb/>4.66-4.58 (2H, m), 4.10 (2H, q, J = 7.1 Hz), 1.39-1.33 (15H, m). m/ <lb/>z 400 (MÀH) À (ES À ), 402 (M+H) + (ES + ). <lb/>The compounds 32-34 were similarly prepared as 31: see Sup-<lb/>plementary data for experimental and spectroscopic details. <lb/>5.1.7. 4-[3-Chloro-4,5-bis(cyclopentyloxy)benzamido]benzoic acid <lb/>(42) <lb/>Step (i): Methyl 3-chloro-4,5-dihydroxybenzoate (36). Tribro-<lb/>moborane (7.86 mL, 82 mmol) was added dropwise to a stirring <lb/>mixture of 3-chloro-4-hydroxy-5-methoxybenzoic acid 35 (6.61 <lb/>g, 32.6 mmol) in dichloromethane (50 mL) under nitrogen at 0 °C. <lb/>The resulting orange mixture was stirred at the same temperature <lb/>for 2 h then poured portion wise onto ice/brine (250 mL). The <lb/>aqueous phase was extracted with ethyl acetate (2 Â 150 mL) <lb/>and the combined organic extracts were dried over magnesium <lb/>sulfate and filtered. The solvent was removed in vacuo to give 3-<lb/>chloro-4,5-dihydroxybenzoic acid (5.11 g, 79% yield). 1 H NMR <lb/>(400 MHz, DMSO d 6 ) d 12.69 (1H, br s), 10.14 (2H, br s), 7.35 (1H, <lb/>d, J = 2.0 Hz), 7.32 (1H, d, J = 2.0 Hz). m/z 187 [MÀH] À (ES). <lb/>Step (ii): A solution of 3-chloro-4,5-dihydroxybenzoic acid <lb/>(3.16 g, 16.76 mmol) and chlorotrimethylsilane (6.36 mL, 50.3 <lb/>mmol) in methanol (50 mL) was stirred at 50 °C, for 16 h, under <lb/>an atmosphere of nitrogen. The solvent was removed in vacuo <lb/>and the residue was partitioned between brine (75 mL) and ethyl <lb/>acetate (75 mL). The organic layer was washed with brine (75 <lb/>mL), dried over magnesium sulfate and filtered. The solvent was <lb/>removed in vacuo to give methyl 3-chloro-4,5-dihydroxybenzoate <lb/>36 (3.26 g, 82% yield). 1 H NMR (400 MHz, DMSO d 6 ) d 10.17 (2H, br <lb/>s), 7.38 (1H, d, J = 2.0 Hz), 7.35 (1H, d, J = 2.0 Hz), 3.78 (3H, s). m/z <lb/>201 [MÀH] À (ES À ). <lb/>Step (iii): 3-Chloro-4,5-bis(cyclopentyloxy)benzoicacid (37, R <lb/>= cyclopentyl). A mixture of methyl 3-chloro-4,5-dihydroxyben-<lb/>zoate 36 (300 mg, 1.48 mmol), iodocyclopentane (558 mL, 4.44 <lb/>mmol) and potassium carbonate (614 mg, 4.44 mmol) in DMF <lb/>(10 mL) was stirred at 70 °C for 46 h. The reaction mixture was <lb/>cooled to room temperature and then partitioned between 1 M <lb/>hydrochloric acid (75 mL) and ethyl acetate (100 mL). The phases <lb/>were separated and the organic phase was washed with brine (2 <lb/>Â 75 mL) then dried over magnesium sulfate and filtered. The sol-<lb/>vent was removed in vacuo and the residue was purified by silica <lb/>gel chromatography (40 g, 0-100% EtOAc and isohexane) to give <lb/>methyl 3-chloro-4,5-bis(cyclopentyloxy)benzoate (427 mg, 85% <lb/>yield). 1 H NMR (400 MHz, CDCl 3 ) d 7.66 (1H, d, J = 2.0 Hz), 7.45 <lb/>(1H, d, J = 2.0 Hz), 5.05-4.98 (1H, m), 4.87-4.83 (1H, m), 3.89 <lb/>(3H, s), 1.95-1.55 (16H, m). m/z 339 [M+H] + (ES + ). <lb/>Step (iv): Methyl 3-chloro-4,5-bis(cyclopentyloxy)benzoate <lb/>(400 mg, 1.18 mmol) was dissolved in a mixture of 1,4-dioxane <lb/>(10 mL) and water (5 mL) and lithium hydroxide (226 mg, 9.44 <lb/>mmol) was added. After stirring for 18 h at room temperature, <lb/>the mixture was partitioned between 1 M hydrochloric acid (20 <lb/>mL) and ethyl acetate (25 mL). The phases were separated and <lb/>the organic phase was washed with water (20 mL) then dried over <lb/>magnesium sulfate and filtered. The solvent was removed in vacuo <lb/>to give the title compound (37: R = cyclopentyl) (380 mg, 99% <lb/>yield). 1 H NMR (400 MHz, DMSO d 6 ) d 13.07 (1H, br s), 7.52 (1H, <lb/>d, J = 2.0 Hz), 7.45 (1H, d, J = 2.0 Hz), 4.97-4.91 (2H, m), 1.99-<lb/>1.90 (2H, m), 1.70-1.57 (14H, m). m/z 323 [MÀH] À (ES À ). <lb/>Step (v) and (iv): 4-[3-Chloro-4,5-bis(cyclopentyloxy)benza-<lb/>mido]benzoicacid (42). A mixture of 3-chloro-4,5-bis(cyclopenty-<lb/>loxy)benzoic acid (37: R = cyclopentyl) and methyl 4-<lb/>aminobenzoate (38: R 1 = H) was converted to the methyl 4-[3-<lb/>chloro-4,5-bis(cyclopentyloxy)benzamido]benzoate in 49% yield <lb/>using the procedure in step (iii) described for compound 15, 1 H <lb/>NMR (400 MHz, CDCl 3 ) d 8.06 (2H, d, J = 8.8H), 7.84 (1H, br s), <lb/>7.72 (2H, d, J = 8.8 Hz), 7.42-7.35 (2H, m), 5.08-4.98 (1H, m), <lb/>4.90-4.86 (1H, m), 3.92 (3H, s), 1.95-1.63 (16H, m). m/z 458 [M <lb/>+H] + (ES + ), 456 [MÀH] À (ES À ). Hydrolysis of methyl-4-[3-chloro-<lb/>4,5-bis(cyclopentyloxy)benzamido]benzoate using the procedure <lb/>in step (iv) described in the preparation of compound (37: R = <lb/>cyclopentyl) gave 4-[3-Chloro-4,5-bis(cyclopentyloxy)benzamido] <lb/>benzoic acid 42 in 72% yield as white solid. 1 H NMR (400 MHz, <lb/>DMSO d 6 ) d 12.74 (1H, br s), 10.45 (1H, s), 7.98-7.84 (4H, m), <lb/>7.69 (1H, d, J = 2.0 Hz), 7.52 (1H, d, J = 2.0 Hz), 5.01-4.95 (2H, m), <lb/>1.99-1.93 (2H, m), 1.73-1.48 (14H, m). m/z 442 [MÀH] À (ES À ). <lb/>The compounds 39, 40, 43, 44 were similarly prepared as 42: <lb/>see Supplementary data for experimental and spectroscopic <lb/>details. <lb/>5.1.8. 4-(3,4-Di-tert-butoxy-5-chlorobenzamido)benzoic acid (41) <lb/>Step (ix): 3,4-Di-tert-butoxy-5-chlorobenzoicacid (37: R = <lb/>t <lb/>Bu). N,N-Dimethylformamide di-tert-butyl acetal (5.92 mL, 24.7 <lb/>mmol) was added to a solution of methyl 3-chloro-4,5-dihydroxy-<lb/>benzoate 36 (500 mg, 2.47 mmol) in toluene (10 mL) and the reac-<lb/>tion mixture was stirred at RT under nitrogen for 21 h. The solvent <lb/>was removed in vacuo and the residue was purified by silica gel <lb/>chromatography (40 g, 0-20% EtOAc in iso-hexane) to give the <lb/>bis-alkylated intermediate, which was dissolved in 1,4-dioxane/ <lb/>water (20 mL, 1:1) and treated with lithium hydroxide (591 mg, <lb/>24.7 mmol). The mixture was stirred 18 h at room temperature. <lb/>The mixture was poured into 10% aqueous citric acid (100 mL) <lb/>and the precipitate was collected by filtration. The solid was <lb/>washed with water and dried to give 3,4-di-tert-butoxy-5-<lb/>chlorobenzoic acid (37: R = t Bu) (534 mg, 70%). 1 H NMR (400 <lb/>MHz, DMSO d 6 ) d 13.13 (1H, br s), 7.67 (1H, s), 7.53 (1H, s), 1.39 <lb/>(9H, s), 1.32 (9H, s). m/z 299 [MÀH] À (ES À ). <lb/>Step (x): 4-(3,4-Di-tert-butoxy-5-chlorobenzamido)benzoic acid <lb/>(41). <lb/>A mixture of 3,4-di-tert-butoxy-5-chlorobenzoic acid (37: R = <lb/>t <lb/>Bu) (250 mg, 0.831 mmol) and methyl 4-aminobenzoate (38: <lb/>R 1 = H) was converted to themethyl 4-(3,4-di-tert-butoxy-5-<lb/>chlorobenzamido)benzoate (185 mg, 50%) using the procedure <lb/>described for compound 18. 1 H NMR (400 MHz, DMSO d 6 ) <lb/>d:10.54 (1H, s), 7.96 (2H, d), 7.91 (2H, d), 7.86 (1H, d), 7.60 (1H, <lb/>d), 3.84 (3H, s), 1.41 (9H, s), 1.32 (9H, s). m/z 432 [MÀH] À (ES À ). <lb/>Hydrolysis of methyl 4-(3,4-di-tert-butoxy-5-chlorobenzamido) <lb/>benzoate (175 mg, 0.403 mmol) using the procedure described in <lb/>the preparation of compound (37: R = cyclopentyl) step (vii). gave <lb/>4-(3,4-di-tert-butoxy-5-chlorobenzamido)benzoic acid 41 (110 <lb/>mg, 64%) as a white solid: 1 H NMR (400 MHz, DMSO d 6 ) d 12.78 <lb/>(1H, br s). 10.49 (1H, s), 7.97-7.86 (3H, m), 7.85 (2H, d, J = 2.3 <lb/>Hz), 7.59 (1H, d, J = 2.2 Hz), 1.40 (9H, s), 1.34 (9H, s). m/z 418 <lb/>[MÀH] À (ES À ). <lb/>The compound 45 was similarly prepared as 41: see Supple-<lb/>mentary data for experimental and spectroscopic details. <lb/>5.1.9. 4-(3-Chloro-4-ethoxy-5-isopropoxybenzamido)-2-<lb/>methylbenzoic acid (56) <lb/>Step (iii): Methyl 4-benzyloxy-3-chloro-5-hydroxybenzoate <lb/>(46). Methyl 3-chloro-4,5-dihydroxybenzoate 36 (14.19 g, 70 <lb/>mmol) was dissolved in N,N-dimethylformamide (210 mL) and <lb/>treated with potassium carbonate (8.71 g, 63 mmol). After stirring <lb/>for 5 min, benzyl bromide (8.32 mL, 70 mmol) was added and the <lb/>mixture was heated to 60 °C for 0.75 h. The reaction mixture was <lb/>diluted with diethyl ether (500 mL) and washed successively with <lb/>1 M hydrochloric acid (500 mL) and with brine (2 Â 500 mL). The <lb/>aqueous phase was re-extracted with diethyl ether (500 mL) and <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">E. Clarke et al. / Bioorganic &amp; Medicinal Chemistry 26 (2018) 798-814 <lb/></note>

			<page>811 <lb/></page>

			<body>the combined organic layers were washed with brine (2 Â 500 mL) <lb/>and dried with magnesium sulfate. Filtration and evaporation left <lb/>the crude product which was purified by silica gel chromatography <lb/>(330 g, 0-100% ethyl acetate/isohexane) to leave methyl 4-(benzy-<lb/>loxy)-3-chloro-5-hydroxybenzoate 46 as an off-white solid (9.84 g, <lb/>48% yield). 1 H NMR (400 MHz, DMSO d 6 ) d 10.50 (1H, s), 7.57-7.53 <lb/>(2H, m), 7.52 (1H, d, J = 2.1 Hz), 7.47 (1H, d, J = 2.1 Hz), 7.46-7.37 <lb/>(3H, m), 5.14 (2H, s), 3.82 (3H, s). (m/z 293.3 [M+H] + (ES + ), 291.2 <lb/>[MÀH] À (ES À ). <lb/>Step (iv): Methyl 3-chloro-4-benzyloxy-5-isopropoxyben-<lb/>zoate (47: R 2 = iPr). Methyl 4-(benzyloxy)-3-chloro-5-hydroxy-<lb/>benzoate 46 (7.5 g, 25.6 mmol) was combined with potassium <lb/>carbonate (7.08 g, 51.2 mmol) in N,N-dimethylformamide (25 <lb/>mL). The mixture was stirred at RT for 5 min. 2-Bromopropane <lb/>(4.81 mL, 51.2 mmol) was added and the mixture stirred at 60 <lb/>°C <lb/>for 2 h. Water (25 mL) was added and the mixture was extracted <lb/>with ethyl acetate (3 Â 50 mL). The combined organic phase was <lb/>washed with brine (2 Â 50 mL) and then dried over magnesium <lb/>sulfate, filtered and concentrated in vacuo to leave a crude mixture <lb/>which was purified by silica gel chromatography (120 g, 0-100% <lb/>ethyl acetate/isohexane) to afford methyl 3-chloro-4-benzyloxy-<lb/>5-isopropoxybenzoate (47: R 2 = iPr), as a clear oil (4.91 g, 57% <lb/>yield). 1 H NMR (400 MHz, DMSO d 6 ) d 7.68 (1H, d, J = 2.0 Hz), <lb/>7.56-7.47 (3H, m), 7.43-7.28 (3H, m), 5.12 (2H, s), 4.77-4.72 <lb/>(1H, m), 3.90 (3H, s), 1.38 (6H, d, J = 6.1 Hz). m/z 335 [M+H] + (ES + ). <lb/>3-Chloro-4-ethoxy5-isopropoxybenzoicacid (48: R 2 = iPr, R 3 = <lb/>Et). Steps (v), (vi) and (vii). <lb/>Step (v): Methyl 3-chloro-4-hydroxy-5-isopropoxybenzoate. <lb/>Methyl 3-chloro-4-(benzyloxy)-5-isopropoxybenzoate (47: R 2 = <lb/>iPr) (4.91 g, 14.7 mmol) was dissolved in a mixture of methanol <lb/>(160 mL), dichloromethane (16 mL) and acetic acid (0.16 mL) and <lb/>the solution was passed through a Thales &apos;H-cube&apos; cartridge (10% <lb/>Pd/C) at a flow rate of 1 mL/min at 25 °C under an atmosphere of <lb/>hydrogen (full H 2 mode). The solvents were removed in vacuo to <lb/>afford methyl 3-chloro-4-hydroxy-5-isopropoxybenzoate (3.42 g, <lb/>85%). 1 H NMR (400 MHz, DMSO d 6 ) d 10.07 (1H, s), 7.53 (1H, d, J <lb/>= 2.0 Hz), 7.43 (1H, d, J = 2.0 Hz), 4.70-4.63 (1H, m), 3.82 (3H, s), <lb/>1.30 (6H, d, J = 6.0 Hz). m/z 245 [M+H] + (ES + ), 243 [MÀH] À (ES À ). <lb/>Step (vi): Methyl 3-chloro-4-ethoxy-5-isopropoxybenzoate. <lb/>Methyl 3-chloro-4-hydroxy-5-isopropoxybenzoate (3.42 g, 14 <lb/>mmol) was combined with potassium carbonate (3.86 g, 28 mmol) <lb/>in N,N-dimethylformamide (5 mL) and the mixture heated at 60 <lb/>°C <lb/>for 10 min. Iodoethane (2.26 mL, 28 mmol) was added dropwise <lb/>whereupon the mixture was stirred at 40 °C for 3 h. A further ali-<lb/>quot of iodoethane was added and heating and stirring was contin-<lb/>ued for 16 h. Water (50 mL) was added and the mixture was <lb/>extracted with ethyl acetate (3 Â 100 mL). The combined organic <lb/>phase was washed with brine (3 Â 50 mL) and then dried over <lb/>magnesium sulfate, filtered and concentrated in vacuo to leave a <lb/>crude mixture which was purified by silica gel chromatography <lb/>(120 g, 0-100% ethyl acetate/isohexane) to afford methyl 3-<lb/>chloro-4-ethoxy-5-isopropoxybenzoate as a white solid (3.17 g, <lb/>82% yield). 1 H NMR (400 MHz, DMSO d 6 ) d 7.67 (1H, d, J = 2.0 <lb/>Hz), 7.48 (1H, d, J = 2.5 Hz), 4.66-4.59 (1H, m), 4.16 (2H, q, J = <lb/>7.1 Hz), 3.90 (3H, s), 1.40 (3H, t, J = 7.0 Hz), 1.37 (6H, d, J = 6.0 <lb/>Hz). m/z 245 [M+H] + (ES + ), 243 [MÀH] À (ES À ). <lb/>Step (vii): 3-Chloro-4-ethoxy5-isopropoxybenzoicacid (48: R 2 <lb/>= iPr, R 3 = Et). Methyl 3-chloro-4-ethoxy-5-isopropoxybenzoate <lb/>(3.17 g, 11.6 mmol) was dissolved in tetrahydrofuran (226 mL) <lb/>and treated with 1 M aqueous lithium hydroxide solution (23.25 <lb/>mL, 23.25 mmol). Methanol (5 mL) was added so that a solution <lb/>formed and this was heated at 40 °C for 1 h. After stirring for a fur-<lb/>ther 16 h at room temperature, the reaction mixture was acidified <lb/>with 1 M hydrochloric acid and extracted with diethyl ether (3 Â <lb/>100 mL). The organic layer was dried over magnesium sulfate, <lb/>filtered and concentrated in vacuo to leave 3-chloro-4-ethoxy 5-<lb/>isopropoxybenzoic acid(48: R 2 = iPr, R 3 = Et) as a white solid <lb/>(2.83 g, 94% yield). 1 H NMR (400 MHz, DMSO d 6 ) d 13.21 (1H, s), <lb/>7.54 (1H, d, J = 1.9 Hz), 7.48 (1H, d J = 1.9 Hz,), 4.74-4.78 (1H, m), <lb/>4.11 (2H, q, J = 7.0 Hz), 1.37-1.21 (9H, m). m/z 257 [MÀH] À (ES À ). <lb/>5.1.10. 4-(3-Chloro-4-ethoxy-5-isopropoxybenzamido)-2-<lb/>methylbenzoic acid (56) <lb/>Step (viii): Methyl 4-(3-chloro-4-ethoxy-5-isopropoxybenza-<lb/>mido)-2-methylbenzoate. A suspension of 3-chloro-4-ethoxy 5-<lb/>isopropoxybenzoic acid (48: R 2 = iPr, R 3 = Et) (2.82 g, 10.9 mmol) <lb/>and methyl 4-amino-2-methylbenzoate (38: R 1 = Me) (2.16 g, <lb/>13.1 mmol) in ethyl acetate (33 mL) was treated with triethy-<lb/>lamine (4.56 mL, 32.7 mmol) followed by T3P (50 wt% in ethyl <lb/>acetate) (17.34 mL, 27.3 mmol) and the mixture was heated at <lb/>60 °C for 4 h and allowed to cool to room temperature for 16 h. <lb/>The reaction mixture was stirred vigorously with an aqueous solu-<lb/>tion of sodium hydrogencarbonate (50 mL) for 10 min and sepa-<lb/>rated. The aqueous layer was extracted with dichloromethane (3 <lb/>Â 100 mL) and the combined organic phases were dried (magne-<lb/>sium sulfate), filtered concentrated in vacuo and the residue puri-<lb/>fied by silica gel chromatography (40 g, 0:50:50 to 20:40:40 ethyl <lb/>acetate:dichloromethane:isohexane) to produce methyl 4-(3-<lb/>chloro-4-ethoxy-5-isopropoxybenzamido)-2-methylbenzoate as a <lb/>beige solid (3.24 g, 70% yield). 1 H NMR (400 MHz, CDCl 3 ) d 8.0 <lb/>(1H, d, J = 8.4 Hz), 7.8 (1H, s), 7.59-7.50 (2H, m), 7.43-7.36 (2H, <lb/>m), 4.69-4.73 (1H, m), 4.18 (2H, q, J = 7.1 Hz), 3.92 (3H, s), 2.6 <lb/>(3H, s), 1.46-1.37 (9H, m). m/z 406 [M+H] + (ES + ), 404 [MÀH] À <lb/>(ES À ). <lb/>Step (ix):1 M Lithium hydroxide solution (15.97 mL, 15.97 <lb/>mmol) was added to a solution of methyl 4-(3-chloro-4-ethoxy-<lb/>5-isopropoxybenzamido)-2-methylbenzoate (3.24 g, 7.98 mmol) <lb/>in tetrahydrofuran (32 mL). Methanol (5 mL) was added and the <lb/>mixture stirred at 40 °C for 16 h. A further aliquot of lithium <lb/>hydroxide solution (7.98 mL, 7.98 mmol) in methanol (5 mL) was <lb/>added and stirring at 40 °C was continued for 3 h. The reaction <lb/>mixture was partitioned between water (50 mL) and diethyl ether <lb/>(100 mL). The layers were separated and the aqueous layer was <lb/>acidified with 1 M hydrochloric acid solution. A precipitate evolved <lb/>which was filtered and washed with water (3 Â 10 mL) and diethyl <lb/>ether (3 Â 10 mL). After drying, this left 4-(3-chloro-4-ethoxy-5-<lb/>isopropoxybenzamido)-2-methylbenzoic acid 56 as a white solid <lb/>(2.55 g, 81%). Recrystallisation from dioxane/water (82:18) gave <lb/>white crystals mp 186 °C. 1 H NMR (400 MHz, DMSO d 6 ) d 12.64 <lb/>(1H, br s), 10.34 (1H, s), 7.86 (1H, d, J = 8.5 Hz,), 7.74-7.63 (3H, <lb/>m), 7.55 (1H, d, J = 2.0 Hz), 4.79-4.73 (1H, m), 4.10 (2H, q, J = 7.1 <lb/>Hz), 2.52 (3H, s), 1.37-1.26 (9H, m). 13 C NMR (101 MHz, DMSO d 6 ) <lb/>d 168.5, 164.4, 151.9, 148.0, 142.4, 140.9, 132.0, 130.9, 127.9, <lb/>125.5, 123.0, 121.4, 117.7, 114.2, 71.6, 69.3, 22.3, 22.2, 15.9. m/z <lb/>392 [M+H] + (ES + ), 390 [MÀH] À (ES À ). HRMS: C 20 H 23 ClNO 5 requires <lb/>(M+H) + 392.1265, found 392.1249 (error À4.0 ppm). <lb/>The compounds 49-55, 57 and 59 were similarly prepared as <lb/>56: see Supplementary data for experimental and spectroscopic <lb/>details. <lb/>5.2. Biological and ADME assays <lb/>5.2.1. Transactivation assays for mouse RAR alpha, beta and gamma <lb/>receptors <lb/>Transcriptional transactivation assays have been performed <lb/>with gal4 fusion receptor constructs, created using each of the <lb/>mouse RAR ligand-binding domains, co-transfected with the pFR-<lb/>luc (Stratagene) reporter construct in COS-7 cells. Thus, transfected <lb/>cells will constitutively express the gal4-RAR fusion protein which <lb/>in turn may be transactivated by ATRA to induce the expression of <lb/></body>

			<page>812 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">E. Clarke et al. / Bioorganic &amp; Medicinal Chemistry 26 (2018) 798-814 <lb/></note>

			<body>the luciferase that is driven by a gal4UAS. Briefly, on day one, 96 <lb/>well plates were seeded with 8000 cells per well then left to <lb/>recover overnight. On day two, the cells were co-transfected with <lb/>100 ng of reporter plasmid and 10 ng of the appropriate receptor <lb/>plasmid per well using lipofectamine (Invitrogen). On day three, <lb/>the lipofectamine containing media was replaced by a DMEM <lb/>without phenol red, followed by the addition of novel compounds <lb/>dissolved in 1 mL of DMSO to each well&apos;s 100 mL total volume. <lb/>Finally, on day four, the cells were lysed and their luciferase sub-<lb/>strate was provided by the BrightGlo reagent (Promega), the plates <lb/>were then read on the MicroBeta TriLux (Perkin Elmer). In each <lb/>experiment, an 8 point dose response curve of ATRA was run in <lb/>duplicate, and the various compounds tested were compared to <lb/>these values. <lb/>5.2.2. FlashPlate Ò Scintillation Proximity Binding Assay (SPA) <lb/>In the FlashPlate Ò Scintillation Proximity Assay (SPA) wells of a <lb/>96-well plate are coated with scintillant and capture antibody (or <lb/>similar) for tagged proteins. This requires just 100 ng of RAR pro-<lb/>teins and 2 nM [ 3 H]-retinoic acid per well. This enables competi-<lb/>tion of specifically bound [ 3 H]-retinoic acid by unlabelled <lb/>retinoid compounds. As only radioligand specifically bound to <lb/>the captured protein is sufficiently close to the scintillant to pro-<lb/>duce a signal, separation of bound and free radioactivity is not <lb/>required. Binding of the tritiated retinoid to biotinylated RARa is <lb/>specific, saturable, time dependent and reversible. We have suc-<lb/>cessfully applied our assay to a screen of known retinoid standards <lb/>and novel compounds and it is both rapid and reproducible (see <lb/>Supplementary data file for details). <lb/>5.2.3. Intrinsic clearance Cl int <lb/>In this in vitro model of hepatic clearance mouse or human liver <lb/>microsomes were incubated with the test compound at 37 °C in <lb/>the presence of the co-factor, NADPH, which initiates the reaction. <lb/>The reaction is terminated by the addition of methanol. Following <lb/>centrifugation, the supernatant is analyzed on the LC-MS/MS. The <lb/>disappearance of the test compound is monitored over a 45 min <lb/>time period. The data is the mean on 5 separate experiments. <lb/>SEM is less than 10% of the mean values. <lb/>The ln peak area ratio (compound peak area/internal standard <lb/>peak area) is plotted against time and the gradient of the line <lb/>determined. <lb/>The elimination rate constant (k) = (Àgradient), the Half life <lb/>(t 1/2 )(min) = 0.693/k and V(mL/mg) = volume of incubation (mL)/ <lb/>protein in the incubation (mg). <lb/>Intrinsic Clearance = (CL int )(mL/min/mg/protein) = V Â 0.693/k. <lb/>(see Supplementary data file for details). <lb/>5.2.4. PK studies in rats <lb/>Test compounds were administered orally and intravenously to <lb/>groups of 4 male Sprague-Dawley rats. Oral dosing solutions of <lb/>each Test Item were prepared at a concentration of 1 mg/mL in <lb/>8% ethanol and 92% PEG-400. The Test Items were orally adminis-<lb/>tered at a dose of 10 mg/kg and a dosing volume of 10 mL/kg. Intra-<lb/>venous dosing solutions of each Test Item were prepared at a <lb/>concentration of 0.25 mg/mL in 8% ethanol, 92% PEG-400. The Test <lb/>Items were intravenously administered at a dose of 0.5 mg/kg and <lb/>a dosing volume of 2 mL/kg. Approximately eight blood samples <lb/>were collected from each animal at appropriate intervals up to 6 <lb/>h post dosing for the iv groups and up to 24 h for the oral groups. <lb/>Whole blood concentrations of the Test Items were measured <lb/>using LC-MS/MS and selected pharmacokinetic parameters calcu-<lb/>lated using Pharsight WinNonLin software. For furthers details <lb/>see Supplementary data file. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgements <lb/>We thank the Wellcome Trust for their financial support (Grant <lb/>084286). <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">A. Supplementary data <lb/>Supplementary data including experimental and spectroscopic <lb/>details for similarly prepared compounds 12-14, 17, 20, 21, 32-<lb/>34, 39, 40, 43-45, 49-55, 57-59, 63 and 64. ADME, biological <lb/>assays, and virtual screening details associated with this article <lb/>can be found, in the online version, at https://doi.org/10.1016/j. <lb/>bmc.2017.12.015. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>1. Dollé P, Neiderreither K, eds. The Retinoids: Biology, Biochemistry, and <lb/>Disease. Hoboken, NJ: John Wiley Sons Inc; 2015. <lb/>2. Lu Y, Bertran S, Samuels TA, Mira-y-Lopez R, Farias EF. Mechanism of inhibition <lb/>of MMTV-neu and MMTV-wnt1 induced mammary oncogenesis by RAR[alpha] <lb/>agonist AM 580. Oncogene. 2010;29:3665-3676. <lb/>3. Yoshimura H, Kikuchi K, Hibi S, et al. Discovery of novel and potent retinoic acid <lb/>receptor a agonists: synthesis and evaluation of benzofuranyl-pyrrole and <lb/>benzothiophenyl-pyrrole derivatives. J Med Chem. 2000;43:2929-2937. <lb/>4. Jarvis CI, Goncalves MB, Clarke E, et al. Retinoic acid receptor-a signalling <lb/>antagonizes both intracellular and extracellular amyloid-b production and <lb/>prevents neuronal cell death caused by amyloid-b. Eur J Neurosci. <lb/>2010;32:1246-1255. <lb/>5. Seino KI, Yamauchi T, Shikata K, et al. Prevention of acute and chronic allograft <lb/>rejection by a novel retinoic acid receptor-a-selective agonist. Int Immunol. <lb/>2004;16:665-673. <lb/>6. Yamauchi T, Ishibashi A, Shikata K, et al. Effect of E6060 [4-{5-[7-fluoro-4-<lb/>(trifluoromethyl)benzo[b]furan-2-yl]-1H-2-pyrrolyl}benzoic acid], a novel <lb/>subtype-selective retinoid, on lupus-like nephritis in female (NZBxNZW)F1 <lb/>mice. J Pharmacol Exp Ther. 2005;312:938-944. <lb/>7. Shudo K, Kagechika H. Structural evolution of retinoids. Adv Drug Res. <lb/>1993;24:81-119. <lb/>8. Teng M, Duong TT, Klein ES, Pino ME, Chandraratna RA. Identification of a <lb/>retinoic acid receptor a subtype specific agonist. J Med Chem. <lb/>1996;39:3035-3038. <lb/>9. Kagechika H, Kawachi E, Hashimoto Y, Himi T, Shudo K. Retinobenzoic acids. 1. <lb/>Structure-activity relationships of aromatic amides with retinoidal activity. J <lb/>Med Chem. 1988;31:2182-2192. <lb/>10. Beard RL, Duong TT, Teng M, Klein ES, Standevan AM, Chandraratna RA. <lb/>Synthesis and biological activity of retinoic acid receptor-alpha specific amides. <lb/>Bioorg Med Chem Lett. 2002;12:3145-3148. <lb/>11. Arafa HM, Elmazar MM, Hamada FM, Reichert U, Shroot B, Nau H. Selective <lb/>agonists of retinoic acid receptors: comparative toxicokinetics and embryonic <lb/>exposure. Arch Toxicol. 2000;73:547-556. <lb/>12. Elmazar MM, Reichert U, Shroot B, Nau H. Pattern of retinoid-induced <lb/>teratogenic effects: possible relationship with relative selectivity for nuclear <lb/>retinoid receptors RAR alpha, RAR beta, and RAR gamma. Teratology. <lb/>1996;53:158-167. <lb/>13. Altucci L, Leibowitz MD, Ogilvie KM, de Lera AR, Gronemeyer H. RAR and RXR <lb/>modulation in cancer and metabolic disease. Nat Rev Drug Discov. <lb/>2007;6:793-810. <lb/>14. Vinter JG. Extended electron distributions applied to the molecular mechanics <lb/>of some intermolecular interactions. J Comput Aided Mol Des. 1994;8:653-668. <lb/>15. (a) Cheeseright T, Mackey M, Rose S, Vinter A. Molecular field extrema as <lb/>descriptors of biological activity: definition and validation. J Chem Inf Model. <lb/>2006;46:665-676; <lb/>(b) Cheeseright TJ, Mackey MD, Melville JL, Vinter JG. FieldScreen: virtual <lb/>screening using molecular fields. Application to the DUD data set. J Chem Inf <lb/>Model. 2008;48:2108-2117. <lb/>16. Vinter JG, Trollope KI. Multiconformational composite molecular-potential <lb/>fields in the analysis of drug-action. 1. Methodology and first evaluation using <lb/>5-HT and histamine action as examples. J Comput Aided Mol Des. <lb/>1995;9:297-307. <lb/>17. Bourguet W, Vivat V, Wurtz JM, Chambon P, Gronemeyer H, Moras D. Crystal <lb/>structure of a heterodimeric complex of RAR and RXR ligand-binding domains. <lb/>Mol Cell. 2000;5:289-298. <lb/>18. Hopkins AL, Groom CR, Alex A. Ligand efficiency: a useful metric for lead <lb/>selection. Drug Discov Today. 2004;9:430-431. <lb/>19. Mannhold R, Krogsgaard-Larsen P, Timmerman H. QSAR: Hansch analysis and <lb/>related approaches, Vol. 1. John Wiley &amp; Sons; 2008. <lb/>20. ADME assays: LogD octanol/water pH7.4, Cyp450 activity, and human plasma <lb/>protein binding and the Toxicity assays: High-Content Cell Toxicity Screen in <lb/>HEPG2 cells, Cytotoxicity Assay in COS-7 cells were carried out by the CRO <lb/>Cyprotex (see Supplementary data file for details). <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">E. Clarke et al. / Bioorganic &amp; Medicinal Chemistry 26 (2018) 798-814 <lb/></note>

			<page>813 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>21. Genetic Toxicity assays: Bacterial Cytotoxicity, Ames Tests, in vitro <lb/>Micronucleus test and the in vitro Pharmacology: Binding and Enzyme <lb/>Assays: including the CEREP panel of 120 other receptors, channels and <lb/>enzymes, and the hERG Binding Assay were carried out by the CRO Cerep (see <lb/>Supplementary data file for details). <lb/>22. The Retinoid X Receptor RXRa and RXRb radioligand binding assays using [ 3 H] <lb/>9-cis-retinoic acid and the respective human recombinant receptors, were <lb/>carried out by the CRO Panlabs Eurofins Pharma Discovery Services UK Limited, <lb/>Gemini Crescent, Dundee Technology Park, Dundee, DD2 1SW. <lb/>23. Leid M, Kastner P, Chambon P. Multiplicity generates diversity in the retinoic <lb/>acid signalling pathways. Trends Biochem Sci. 1992;17:427-433. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>814 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">E. Clarke et al. / Bioorganic &amp; Medicinal Chemistry 26 (2018) 798-814 </note>


	</text>
</tei>
