<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>The Biosynthesis of Enzymatically <lb/>Oxidized Lipids <lb/>Ali A. Hajeyah 1 * , William J. Griffiths 2 , Yuqin Wang 2 , Andrew J. Finch 3 <lb/>and Valerie B. O&apos;Donnell 1 <lb/>1 Systems Immunity Research Institute and Division of Infection and Immunity, Cardiff University, Cardiff, United Kingdom, <lb/>2 Institute of Life Science, Swansea University Medical School, Swansea, United Kingdom, 3 Centre for Tumour Biology, <lb/>Barts Cancer Institute, Queen Mary University of London, London, United Kingdom <lb/>Enzymatically oxidized lipids are a specific group of biomolecules that function as key <lb/>signaling mediators and hormones, regulating various cellular and physiological processes <lb/>from metabolism and cell death to inflammation and the immune response. They are <lb/>broadly categorized as either polyunsaturated fatty acid (PUFA) containing (free acid <lb/>oxygenated PUFA &quot;oxylipins&quot;, endocannabinoids, oxidized phospholipids) or cholesterol <lb/>derivatives (oxysterols, steroid hormones, and bile acids). Their biosynthesis is <lb/>accomplished by families of enzymes that include lipoxygenases (LOX), <lb/>cyclooxygenases (COX), cytochrome P450s (CYP), and aldo-keto reductases (AKR). In <lb/>contrast, non-enzymatically oxidized lipids are produced by uncontrolled oxidation and <lb/>are broadly considered to be harmful. Here, we provide an overview of the biochemistry <lb/>and enzymology of LOXs, COXs, CYPs, and AKRs in humans. Next, we present <lb/>biosynthetic pathways for oxylipins, oxidized phospholipids, oxysterols, bile acids and <lb/>steroid hormones. Last, we address gaps in knowledge and suggest directions for <lb/>future work. <lb/>Keywords: biosynthesis of oxidized lipids, lipoxygenase (LOX), cyclooxygenase (COX), cytochrome P450, aldo-keto <lb/>reductase (AKR), oxylipins, oxidized phospholipids, sterols and steroid hormones <lb/></front>

			<body>INTRODUCTION <lb/>Lipids are a key component of life. They play essential roles in membrane structure, cell signaling <lb/>and energy production. Like other biomolecules, they undergo chemical modifications that expand <lb/>their functional repertoire. One modification that has been steadily gaining attention is lipid <lb/>oxygenation, with interest being attributed to two factors: advances in analytical methods that allow <lb/>detection of oxygenated species, and the ever-growing body of literature implicating them in <lb/>biological processes and disease. &quot;Enzymatically oxidized lipids&quot; constitute a large portion of known <lb/>oxygenated lipid mediators, being bioactive lipids that are produced locally through specific <lb/></body>

			<front>Abbreviations: 4-HNE, 4-hydroxy-2-nonenal; AA, arachidonic acid; AKR, aldo-keto reductase; ALA, a-linolenic acid; COX, <lb/>cyclooxygenase; CE, cholesteryl ester; CYP, cytochrome P450; DGLA, dihomo-g-linolenic acid; DHA, docosahexaenoic acid; <lb/>DPEP2, dipeptidase 2; EET, epoxy-eicosatrienoic acid; EPA, eicosapentaenoic acid; GGT, g-glutamyl transpeptidase; GLA, <lb/>g-linolenic acid; GPCR, G protein-coupled receptor; HETE, hydroxy-eicosatetraenoic acid; HpETE, hydroperoxy-<lb/>eicosatetraenoic acid; HSD, hydroxysteroid dehydrogenase; LA, linoleic acid; LOX, lipoxygenase; LTA 4 , leukotriene A 4 ; <lb/>lysoPL, lysophospholipid; oxPL, oxidized phospholipids; PG, prostaglandin; PL, phospholipid; PUFA, polyunsaturated fatty <lb/>acid; SDR, short-chain dehydrogenase/reductase; SPM, specialized pro-resolving mediator. <lb/>Frontiers in Endocrinology | www.frontiersin.org <lb/>November 2020 | Volume 11 | Article 591819 <lb/>1 <lb/>Edited by: <lb/>Maria Fedorova, <lb/>Leipzig University, Germany <lb/>Reviewed by: <lb/>Consolato Sergi, <lb/>University of Alberta Hospital, Canada <lb/>Katja Hummitzsch, <lb/>University of Adelaide, Australia <lb/>*Correspondence: <lb/>Ali A. Hajeyah <lb/>hajeyahaa@cardiff.ac.uk <lb/>Specialty section: <lb/>This article was submitted to <lb/>Systems Endocrinology, <lb/>a section of the journal <lb/>Frontiers in Endocrinology <lb/>Received: 05 August 2020 <lb/>Accepted: 26 October 2020 <lb/>Published: 19 November 2020 <lb/>Citation: <lb/>Hajeyah AA, Griffiths WJ, Wang Y, <lb/>Finch AJ and O&apos;Donnell VB (2020) <lb/>The Biosynthesis of Enzymatically <lb/>Oxidized Lipids. <lb/>Front. Endocrinol. 11:591819. <lb/>doi: 10.3389/fendo.2020.591819 <lb/>REVIEW <lb/>published: 19 November 2020 <lb/>doi: 10.3389/fendo.2020.591819 <lb/></front>

			<body>biosynthetic pathways in response to extracellular stimuli. Those <lb/>derived from oxygenation of polyunsaturated fatty acids (PUFA) <lb/>such as arachidonic acid (AA) include prostaglandins (PG), <lb/>thromboxanes and leukotrienes, which function in modulating <lb/>inflammation, the immune response, and hemostasis, and are <lb/>broadly termed &quot;oxylipins&quot; (1, 2). Oxylipins also include <lb/>multiply oxygenated derivatives of eicosapentaenoic acid (EPA) <lb/>and docosahexaenoic acid (DHA), of which specific enantiomers <lb/>have been termed &quot;specialized pro-resolving mediators&quot; (SPM) <lb/>for their proposed roles in the resolution of inflammation (3). <lb/>SPMs derived from DHA include D-resolvins, maresins and <lb/>protectin. On the other hand, E-resolvins are proposed to be <lb/>generated from EPA but the enzymatic pathways are unclear and <lb/>require further investigation. Oxylipins also constitute a core <lb/>functional group on larger lipids including oxidized <lb/>phospholipids (oxPL), endocannabinoids and cholesteryl esters <lb/>(CE). Oxidized CEs are conversely associated with <lb/>atherosclerosis progression (4), whereas enzymatically oxidized <lb/>phospholipids (eoxPL) are pro-coagulant and promote a variety <lb/>of innate immune actions in leukocytes and platelets (5). <lb/>Enzymatically oxidized lipids are not limited to those <lb/>containing oxygenated PUFA functional groups. Oxidized <lb/>derivatives of cholesterol include steroid hormones, bile acids <lb/>and their oxysterol precursors. Steroid hormones regulate <lb/>multiple physiological processes including metabolism (e.g., <lb/>glucose homeostasis by glucocorticoids), water retention, <lb/>immune function, and development of sex characteristics (6-<lb/>8). Bile acids, while traditionally known for aiding in fat digestion <lb/>and bilirubin excretion, are also being increasingly revealed as <lb/>signaling molecules and metabolic regulators (9, 10). Similarly, <lb/>accumulating evidence is revealing oxysterols as more than just <lb/>bile acid intermediates with functions in signaling (11). <lb/>Enzymatic lipid oxidation is facilitated by a network of proteins <lb/>that use PUFAs or sterols as substrates, specifically, lipoxygenase <lb/>(LOX), cyclooxygenase (COX), and cytochrome P450 (CYP), all of <lb/>which exist as several isoforms exhibiting broad substrate specificity <lb/>(12-16). In general, PUFA oxygenation is initiated by COXs, LOXs, <lb/>and to a lesser extent CYPs. For example, the biosynthesis of PGs is <lb/>initiated by COXs, whereas the formation of leukotrienes begins <lb/>with a LOX. Additionally, crossover between COX, LOX, and CYP <lb/>is proposed to produce various SPMs. On the other hand, <lb/>cholesterol oxidation is dominated by CYPs. For example, <lb/>sidechain shortening during steroid hormone synthesis is <lb/>catalyzed by CYP11A1 (P450scc). Bile acids are synthesized from <lb/>cholesterol predominantly by two pathways: the neutral pathway <lb/>starting with an endoplasmic reticulum resident enzyme CYP7A1, <lb/>and the acidic pathway starting with CYP27A1 in mitochondria <lb/>(17). CYPs account for many enzymes in both pathways, catalyzing <lb/>the formation of oxysterols as well as oxygenated PUFAs. Last, aldo-<lb/>keto reductases (AKR) and hydroxysteroid dehydrogenases (HSD) <lb/>catalyze key redox reactions in bile acid and steroid <lb/>hormone biosynthesis. <lb/>By contrast, non-enzymatically oxidized lipids are produced <lb/>through uncontrolled oxidation via free radical mechanisms. <lb/>This involves the oxidation of lipids by free radicals, followed by <lb/>chain propagation and ultimately termination. Notably, during <lb/>oxygenation of PUFA, active site intermediates can escape to <lb/>react in an uncontrolled manner, leading to some oxidized lipids <lb/>forming due to non-enzymatic rearrangements of enzymatic <lb/>pathway intermediates. <lb/>Here, we provide an overview of major enzymes involved in <lb/>lipid metabolism, including LOXs, COXs, CYPs and AKRs. Then <lb/>we outline the biosynthetic pathways of oxylipins, oxPLs, <lb/>oxysterols, bile acids and steroid hormones. Finally, we address <lb/>outstanding questions and suggest directions for future work. <lb/>ENZYME FAMILIES INVOLVED IN THE <lb/>BIOSYNTHESIS OF OXIDIZED LIPIDS <lb/>Lipoxygenase (LOX) <lb/>Human LOX: Isoforms and Tissue Distribution <lb/>Lipoxygenases (LOX) are a family of non-heme iron-containing <lb/>dioxygenases. They catalyze the stereospecific addition of <lb/>dioxygen to lipids containing a (1Z,4Z)-pentadiene group <lb/>producing lipid hydroperoxides. The human genome contains <lb/>six functional LOX genes, expressed in various tissues (Table 1). <lb/>LOXs were traditionally named according to their positional <lb/>specificity for arachidonic acid (AA). However, the latest <lb/>characterized member eLOX3 has limited lipoxygenase activity <lb/>(38), while some LOXs show preference for other PUFA. <lb/>Sequence analysis of human LOXs (using UniProt entries (39)) <lb/>shows that 12R-LOX (ALOX12B) is evolutionarily closer to 15-<lb/>LOX-2 (ALOX15B; 48.2% identity) than 12S-LOX (ALOX12; <lb/>35.7% identity). Additionally, human 15-LOX-1 (ALOX15) <lb/>exhibits dual positional specificity which is not reflected in the <lb/>name (18). The lack of a robust naming system is a common <lb/>cause of confusion. Thus, the use of gene names alongside <lb/>enzyme names is recommended (14). <lb/>LOXs are typically constitutively expressed, except for 15-<lb/>LOX-1 (ALOX15) which is inducible by IL-4 and IL-13 in <lb/>monocyte-derived macrophages (28). Although 15-LOX-2 <lb/>(ALOX15B) is constitutively expressed in the same cell type, its <lb/>expression can be increased by cytokines, hypoxia, and <lb/>lipopolysaccharide. It is possible that other constitutively <lb/>expressed LOXs share this property. <lb/>Structure and Membrane Association <lb/>of Mammalian LOXs <lb/>There are a limited number of published crystal structures for <lb/>mammalian LOXs. Available structures of 5-and 15-LOXs show <lb/>a single polypeptide chain that consists of two domains: a small <lb/>b-barrel N-terminal domain and a larger a-helix-rich C-terminal <lb/>domain containing the catalytic non-heme iron (40-42). The <lb/>coordination positions of the catalytic iron are occupied by three <lb/>conserved His residues, the carboxyl group of the C-terminus Ile <lb/>residue, a water molecule and one last variable ligand (water, His, <lb/>Asn, or Ser). Studies on mammalian LOXs found that the N-<lb/>terminal domain is not required for catalytic activity, but instead <lb/>functions in membrane binding and regulation (43, 44). The N-<lb/>terminal domain of mammalian 5-LOXs (ALOX5) was found to <lb/>be important for the calcium-dependent translocation from the <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Hajeyah et al. <lb/>Biosynthesis of Oxidized Lipids <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Endocrinology | www.frontiersin.org <lb/>November 2020 | Volume 11 | Article 591819 <lb/></note>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<body>cytosol or nucleus (depending on cell type) to the nuclear <lb/>envelope and enzyme activity (45, 46). Similar findings were <lb/>reported for mammalian 15-LOXs, with the translocation from <lb/>the cytosol to the cell membrane instead (47, 48). Unlike other <lb/>LOXs, the activity of 5-LOX requires interaction with partner <lb/>proteins 5-lipoxygenase activating protein (FLAP), coactosin-<lb/>like protein (CLP) and cytosolic phospholipase A2 (cPLA 2 ) (49, <lb/>50). Additionally, 5-LOX undergoes phosphorylation at multiple <lb/>sites, regulating its translocation and activity, and is allosterically <lb/>activated by ATP (51-53). <lb/>On the other hand, 15-LOXs do not require accessory proteins <lb/>for free FA oxygenation. Instead, 15-LOXs form a complex with a <lb/>small scaffolding protein, phosphatidylethanolamine-binding <lb/>protein 1 (PEPB1) (54). This complex facilitates 15-LOX activity <lb/>on PL-esterified PUFA and is proposed to play regulatory roles in <lb/>ferroptosis along with GPX. PEPB1 has been suggested to direct 15-<lb/>LOX activity toward PL substrates when free AA is depleted (55). <lb/>The crystal structure of human 15-LOX-2 (ALOX15B) revealed a <lb/>hydrophobic loop in the N-terminal domain that is flanked by <lb/>calcium binding sites, a feature that is absent in 5-LOX (42). <lb/>Hydrogen-deuterium exchange mass spectrometry showed a <lb/>decrease in H/D exchange for the hydrophobic loop, supporting a <lb/>role in membrane hopping (48, 56). Both 5-LOX and 15-LOXs <lb/>associate with membranes in a calcium-dependent process but they <lb/>exhibit differences in activity, translocation and binding partners. <lb/>Calcium-dependent membrane association has also been <lb/>shown for platelet 12S-LOX (ALOX12), and more recently, <lb/>12R-LOX (ALOX12B), and eLOX3 (19, 57). The activity of <lb/>12S-LOX (ALOX12) is thought to be regulated by the <lb/>availability of its substrates, which are supplied through the <lb/>action of phospholipases. It is currently unknown whether <lb/>12S-LOX is regulated by other mechanisms. Research on the <lb/>regulation of 12R-LOX and eLOX3 is also limited, although <lb/>calcium has been shown to increase the activity of mouse 12R-<lb/>LOX but not eLOX3 (58). <lb/>Aside from the catalytic domain of 12S-LOX (ALOX12), no <lb/>crystal structures are available for 12-LOXs or eLOX3. However, <lb/>human platelet 12S-LOX (ALOX12) was characterized using <lb/>small-angle x-ray scattering, showing its occurrence as a dimer <lb/>in solution (59). This challenged the idea that all human LOXs <lb/>exist and function as monomers. Human 5-LOX displays full <lb/>activity as a monomer but forms functional dimers as well, <lb/>thought to exist in equilibrium (60). Similarly, rabbit 15-LOX-<lb/>1 (ALOX15) undergoes ligand-induced dimerization in aqueous <lb/>solutions, and molecular dynamics predicts stable dimers in the <lb/>presence of substrate fatty acids (61). This supports the idea of <lb/>monomer-dimer equilibria in LOXs. Human 15-LOX-1 (81.1% <lb/>sequence identity to rabbit) likely exhibits the same property. <lb/>In summary, all six human LOXs associate with membranes <lb/>in a calcium-dependent manner. 5-LOX requires the help of <lb/>protein partners for membrane translocation and activity, <lb/>whereas 15-LOXs only require a partner protein to efficiently <lb/>catalyze the oxygenation of PL-esterified PUFA. Less is known <lb/>about the regulation of 12-LOXs and eLOX3. Dimerization and <lb/>monomer-dimer equilibria have been observed in several LOX <lb/>isoforms and represent a potential regulatory mechanism. <lb/>Finally, complete crystal structures have yet to be reported for <lb/>12S-LOX, 12R-LOX, and eLOX3. In the case of 12S-LOX, a <lb/>crystal structure would be beneficial in the rational design of <lb/>inhibitors, as the enzyme functions in platelet activation. <lb/>Reaction Mechanism of LOX <lb/>The dioxygenase activity of LOX represents a highly controlled <lb/>form of lipid peroxidation (Figure 1A). First, stereospecific <lb/>hydrogen atom removal is carried out by the non-heme ferric <lb/>iron [Fe(III)]. Fe(III) is not a strong enough oxidizer to abstract <lb/>hydrogen directly. Thus, a mechanism involving proton-coupled <lb/>electron transfer (PCET) has been proposed (62) (Figure 1A). In <lb/>this, the electron is directly transferred to Fe(III) and the proton <lb/>is picked up by the hydroxide ligand in a concerted mechanism <lb/>(simultaneously), producing a lipid alkyl radical and ferrous iron <lb/>[Fe(II)]. This is followed by a rearrangement of the lipid radical <lb/>into the more stable conjugated diene. After that, dioxygen is <lb/>introduced onto the opposite side of the removed hydrogen <lb/>(antarafacially), generating a lipid peroxyl radical. Finally, the <lb/>lipid peroxyl radical is reduced by Fe(II) and protonated to form <lb/>a lipid hydroperoxide, through PCET. This reforms Fe(III) for <lb/>another round of catalysis. <lb/>TABLE 1 | Human LOXs: Genes, substrates, and major expression sites. <lb/>Gene <lb/>Protein <lb/>Preferred substrate(s) <lb/>Expression sites <lb/>Refs. <lb/>ALOX12 <lb/>12S-LOX <lb/>DHA &amp; EPA &gt; AA <lb/>Platelets, umbilical vein endothelial cells, vascular smooth muscle cells, <lb/>skin epidermis <lb/>(18-22), <lb/>ALOX12B 12R-LOX <lb/>O-Linoleoyl-w-hydroxyceramide <lb/>AA &amp; 8,11,14-eicosatrienoic acid &gt; <lb/>GLA <lb/>Hair roots, keratinocytes, B-cells, tonsil epithelial cells, bronchial epithelial <lb/>cells <lb/>(23-27) <lb/>ALOX15 <lb/>15-LOX-1 <lb/>(12/15 LOX murine <lb/>ortholog) <lb/>DHA &gt; EPA &gt; AA <lb/>Monocytes, macrophages, dendritic cells, eosinophils, reticulocytes, <lb/>tracheal epithelium <lb/>(18, 28-32) <lb/>ALOX15B 15-LOX-2 <lb/>(8-LOX <lb/>murine ortholog) <lb/>DHA &gt; EPA &gt; AA <lb/>Macrophages, hair roots, prostate, lung, cornea, skin <lb/>(18, 28, 33), <lb/>ALOX5 <lb/>5-LOX <lb/>AA &amp; 5S-HpETE <lb/>Leukocytes, dendritic cells, mast cells, lung, placenta <lb/>(34-36) <lb/>ALOXE3 <lb/>eLOX3 <lb/>9R-Hydroperoxy-linoleoyl-w-<lb/>hydroxyceramide <lb/>12R-HpETE <lb/>Skin epidermis <lb/>(25, 37) <lb/>AA arachidonic acid DHA, docosahexaenoic acid; EPA, eicosapentaenoic acid; GLA, g-linolenic acid; HpETE, hydroperoxy-eicosatetraenoic acid. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Hajeyah et al. <lb/>Biosynthesis of Oxidized Lipids <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Endocrinology | www.frontiersin.org <lb/>November 2020 | Volume 11 | Article 591819 <lb/></note>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<body>A <lb/>B <lb/>D <lb/>C <lb/>FIGURE 1 | Reaction mechanism of lipoxygenases (LOXs). (A) Dioxygenase activity. Hydrogen atom removal is thought to proceed through a proton-coupled electron transfer mechanism (PCET), in which the transfer of <lb/>electron and proton occur simultaneously (concerted mechanism), depicted separately for simplicity. (B) Lipohydroperoxidase activity. (C) Leukotriene synthase activity. (D) Activation of LOX by a hydroperoxide. <lb/></body>
			
			<note place="headnote">Hajeyah et al. <lb/>Biosynthesis of Oxidized Lipids <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Endocrinology | www.frontiersin.org <lb/>November 2020 | Volume 11 | Article 591819 <lb/></note>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<body>The stereo and regio-specificity of lipoxygenation are <lb/>determined by structural features which: (i) accommodate and <lb/>position the substrate in a specific orientation, and (ii) direct <lb/>radical rearrangement and oxygen insertion. These features <lb/>include a U-shaped cavity that accommodates the substrate <lb/>(63), a migration channel for oxygen (64), a glycine/alanine <lb/>&quot;switch&quot; that determines stereospecificity by directing oxygen <lb/>(65), and several amino acid residues that control positional <lb/>specificity (66, 67). These properties are explored in-depth by <lb/>Newcomer and Brash (68). <lb/>In addition to classical dioxygenase activity, LOXs catalyze <lb/>other reactions that involve free-radical processes like hydrogen <lb/>abstraction, homolytic bond cleavage, and radical rearrangement <lb/>(69). eLOX3 exhibits a hydroperoxide isomerase activity <lb/>(lipohydroperoxidase activity) which converts hydroperoxides <lb/>to epoxy-alcohols and ketones (70) (Figure 1B). eLOX3 has <lb/>restricted dioxygenase activity (38), and its hydroperoxide <lb/>isomerase activity is considered its primary catalytic reaction. <lb/>Also, mammalian 5-LOXs and human 15-LOX-1 (ALOX15) <lb/>possess leukotriene A 4 synthase activity which produces <lb/>epoxides from hydroperoxides (71-74). The mechanism <lb/>involves the homolytic cleavage of a hydroperoxide into an <lb/>alkoxy radical and hydrogen atom removal (via PCET) from a <lb/>bis-allylic methylene carbon generating an alkyl radical. The <lb/>resulting biradical is stabilized by epoxide formation <lb/>(Figure 1C). <lb/>LOXs are inactive in their basal form with Fe(II) and require <lb/>activation via oxidation into Fe(III) (Figure 1D). LOX activation <lb/>is facilitated by hydroperoxides such as their dioxygenase <lb/>reaction products. Although the proposed LOX catalytic cycle <lb/>regenerates the ferric iron for another round of catalysis, small <lb/>amounts of radical intermediates can escape the active site <lb/>resulting in an incomplete catalytic cycle and requiring <lb/>repeated activation of the enzyme (formation of Fe(III) by <lb/>hydroperoxide) for sustained catalysis (69, 75, 76). <lb/>Some LOXs exhibit suicide inactivation, a property in which <lb/>the reaction product rapidly inactivates the enzyme. Human 5-<lb/>LOX is irreversibly inactivated by both of its products 5-HpETE <lb/>and leukotriene A 4 (77). Similarly, rabbit reticulocyte 15-LOX <lb/>(human 15-LOX-1 ortholog) is inactivated by its product 15-<lb/>HpETE, and the mechanism is suggested to be through <lb/>formation of reactive intermediates that covalently bind the <lb/>enzyme (78). The dioxygenase reaction and the other two <lb/>activities (lipohydroperoxidase and leukotriene synthase) have <lb/>been proposed to inactive LOXs through different mechanisms, <lb/>but the mechanistic details remain unclear (78). <lb/>LOXs Act on a Broad Range of Substrates <lb/>LOX isoforms have different substrate preferences. Substrates of <lb/>mammalian 5-LOXs include AA, its hydroperoxide product 5S-<lb/>HpETE, as well as epoxy-alcohols derived from EPA and DHA <lb/>(71, 79). The former two are important in the biosynthesis of <lb/>leukotrienes, while the latter two are proposed to be precursors of <lb/>E-and D-series resolvins, respectively (75, 80). 15-LOXs <lb/>(ALOX15 and ALOX15B) accept AA, EPA, DHA, linoleic acid <lb/>(LA), and g-linolenic acid (GLA) as substrates. The preference of <lb/>human 15-LOX orthologs is: DHA &gt; EPA &gt; AA &gt; GLA &gt; LA <lb/>(18). One key difference is that 15-LOX-1 (ALOX15) possesses <lb/>dual positional specificity for some of its substrates (e.g., 12 and <lb/>15-lipoxygenase activities for AA), whereas 15-LOX-2 <lb/>(ALOX15B) exhibits singular specificity (15-lipoxygenase <lb/>activity) (55). The hydroperoxide isomerase and epoxidase <lb/>activities of 15-LOX-1 (ALOX15) are proposed to function in <lb/>the synthesis of eoxins, E-series resolvins, and protectin from <lb/>their respective precursors. Additionally, human 15-LOX-1 <lb/>oxygenates PUFA-containing fatty amides and 2-arachidonoyl-<lb/>glycerol ester (81, 82). Finally, mammalian 15-LOXs can catalyze <lb/>the oxygenation of PUFA in lysophospholipids (lysoPL), PLs, <lb/>CEs, and lipoproteins (83-88). <lb/>PUFA substrates of platelet 12S-LOX (ALOX12) include AA, <lb/>EPA, DHA, and dihomo-g-linolenic acid (DGLA) (18, 89). While <lb/>no single study has compared all substrates at the same time, one <lb/>determined the order of preference for the first three substrates <lb/>to be: DHA &gt; EPA &gt; AA (18). Another found comparable kinetic <lb/>parameters for EPA, AA, and DGLA as substrates (89). Both <lb/>observed a singular positional specificity for 12S-LOX. LA, GLA, <lb/>and a-linolenic acid (ALA) were all found to be poor substrates <lb/>for 12S-LOX (18, 89, 90). Furthermore, human 12S-LOX <lb/>possesses lipoxin synthase activity, which converts leukotriene <lb/>A 4 into lipoxins A and B (91). The enzymatic activities of 12S-<lb/>LOX are also proposed to function in the biosynthesis of <lb/>hepoxilins and maresins (92, 93). Recently, 12S-LOX was <lb/>shown to oxygenate 2-AA-lysoPL, proposing alternate <lb/>pathways for oxylipin and oxPL biosynthesis (94). <lb/>Mammalian 12R-LOX (ALOX12B) and eLOX3 (ALOXE3) are <lb/>co-expressed in skin and their functions are related. 12R-LOX <lb/>efficiently catalyzes the peroxidation of AA, DGLA and GLA, and <lb/>less efficiently LA, EPA and DHA (23, 24). Later, 12R-LOX was <lb/>shown to oxygenate LA esterified to w-hydroxyacyl-sphingosine <lb/>more efficiently than free LA (25). The hydroperoxide product of <lb/>this reaction is further converted into an epoxy-alcohol by the <lb/>isomerase activity of eLOX3. These two reactions are essential for <lb/>the proper formation of the water-impermeable barrier in <lb/>corneocytes (25). Human eLOX3 isomerase activity has also been <lb/>observed on the 12R-and 12S-hydroperoxides of AA, with the <lb/>reaction occurring 2-3 times faster for the R-stereoisomer (95). <lb/>These reactions produce hepoxilins, which play a role in skin <lb/>inflammation. Curiously, mouse 12R-LOX and eLOX3 metabolize <lb/>the methyl esters of AA and LA more efficiently than the <lb/>unmodified FAs (58). However, human and mouse orthologs are <lb/>known to exhibit differences in substrate preference and regio-<lb/>specificity (95). Thus, further work is needed to assess the ability of <lb/>human 12R-LOX to metabolize fatty methyl esters and whether that <lb/>reaction is biologically relevant. <lb/>Several aspects of LOX enzymology remain unresolved. First, <lb/>the functional implications of suicide inactivation are unknown, <lb/>that is, the reason why some LOXs have not evolved to resist <lb/>suicide inactivation. This suggests a biological function for this <lb/>property, perhaps in regulation. Additionally, the mechanistic <lb/>details of suicide inactivation are not fully understood. Second, <lb/>due to the ever-increasing list of LOX substrates, it has been <lb/>difficult to pinpoint biologically relevant substrates and assign <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Hajeyah et al. <lb/>Biosynthesis of Oxidized Lipids <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Endocrinology | www.frontiersin.org <lb/>November 2020 | Volume 11 | Article 591819 <lb/></note>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<body>clear functions to all LOX isoforms. For example, the function of <lb/>15-LOX-2 (ALOX15B) in macrophages remains unclear, <lb/>although it has been recently shown to regulate cholesterol <lb/>levels (96). Unique substrates of each isoform (e.g., CEs for 15-<lb/>LOXs, lysoPLs for 12S-LOX) might be worth investigating. <lb/>Cyclooxygenase (COX) <lb/>Human COX: Isoforms and Tissue Distribution <lb/>Cyclooxygenases (COXs), also called prostaglandin-<lb/>endoperoxide synthases and prostaglandin G/H synthases, are <lb/>heme-containing enzymes that possess both oxygenase and <lb/>peroxidase activities. There are two COX genes in humans: <lb/>PTGS1 and PTGS2, which encode for COX-1 and COX-2, <lb/>respectively. Traditionally, it was thought that COX-1 is <lb/>constitutively expressed, whereas COX-2 is inducible in <lb/>response to inflammatory signals. However, several studies <lb/>suggest constitutive COX-2 expression in the brain, lungs, gut, <lb/>thymus, kidneys, and blood vessels (97-99). In the vasculature, <lb/>COX-2 has been demonstrated to be a key source of vascular <lb/>prostacyclin (100, 101). COX-1 is ubiquitously expressed in the <lb/>body, and its expression sites include blood vessels, prostate, <lb/>immune cells (monocytes, T-cells), platelets, stomach, resident <lb/>inflammatory cells, smooth muscles, and mesothelium of many <lb/>organs (102-105). On the other hand, COX-2 is inducible in <lb/>many tissues including prostate, immune cells (T-cells, B-cells, <lb/>monocytes), and stomach (102-104, 106), but also constitutively <lb/>expressed in some tissues as previously mentioned. <lb/>Structure of COX <lb/>The role of COXs as mediators of inflammation and their <lb/>potential as drug targets were drivers for the elucidation of <lb/>their structures. The crystal structure of sheep COX-1 has been <lb/>solved in the presence and absence of various synthetic ligands <lb/>(107-109). Similarly, there are available structures for mouse <lb/>COX-2 in the presence and absence of natural and synthetic <lb/>ligands (13, 110-113), as well as human COX-2 with several <lb/>inhibitors (114, 115). <lb/>Both COX isoforms are homodimers, and this quaternary <lb/>structure is necessary for enzymatic activity (116). Each <lb/>monomer consists of three domains: An N-terminal epidermal <lb/>growth factor (EGF)-like domain, a membrane binding domain, <lb/>and a large C-terminal catalytic domain. The EGF-like domain is <lb/>located at the dimer interface and potentially facilitates <lb/>dimerization. It is also thought to facilitate membrane binding <lb/>(117). The membrane binding domain consists of four <lb/>amphipathic a-helices that insert into one face of a membrane <lb/>bilayer. Both COXs are found on the luminal face of the <lb/>endoplasmic reticulum (ER) and the inner and outer nuclear <lb/>membranes (118). However, COX-2 is also found in the Golgi <lb/>apparatus (119). The catalytic domain (in both isoforms) <lb/>contains separate oxygenase and peroxidase active sites on <lb/>opposite sides of the heme cofactor. The oxygenase active site <lb/>is located towards the membrane binding face at the end of a <lb/>hydrophobic tunnel that allows substrate entry, whereas the <lb/>peroxidase active site is in a groove on the opposite face of the <lb/>enzyme (120). <lb/>COXs undergo N-glycosylation at multiple asparagine <lb/>residues. This facilitates their proper folding, and regulates the <lb/>turnover of COX-2 by controlling its trafficking between the ER <lb/>and the Golgi apparatus (119, 121, 122). COX-2 can also be S-<lb/>nitrosylated by inducible nitric oxide synthase, which has been <lb/>proposed to enhance its activity (123). In vitro experiments on <lb/>recombinant human COX-1 and COX-2 demonstrated that both <lb/>isoforms can be S-nitrosylated by a nitric oxide donor, but only <lb/>COX-2 showed increased cyclooxygenase activity (124). Circular <lb/>dichroism data suggest an altered, less dynamic conformation for <lb/>both isoforms after S-nitrosylation with less a-helices, turns, and <lb/>random coils, but more b-sheets. The structural change was <lb/>more pronounced in COX-2 compared to COX-1. These <lb/>findings provide new insight into the structural dynamics of <lb/>COXs. The occurrence and biological relevance of this altered <lb/>COX conformation is unexplored in vivo and would benefit from <lb/>further investigation. <lb/>Although COXs are sequence homodimers, they are <lb/>considered conformational heterodimers because one <lb/>monomer functions as the catalytic subunit (E cat ) and the <lb/>other as an allosteric regulator (E allo ) (125-127). For both COX <lb/>isoforms, the binding of one heme molecule to E cat is required for <lb/>full activity. Several substrate and non-substrate FAs can bind <lb/>E allo to regulate the activity of E cat , and the two COX isoforms <lb/>exhibit differences in this regard. COX-1 is inhibited by palmitic <lb/>acid, stearic acid, margaric acid and oleic acid (127), none of <lb/>which are COX substrates. On the other hand, COX-2 is <lb/>stimulated by palmitic acid and stearic acid (126). Substrate <lb/>FAs (like AA and EPA) also bind to E allo to regulate COX <lb/>activity, with notable differences in the responses of the two <lb/>isoforms (reviewed in (128)). <lb/>Catalytic Mechanism of COX <lb/>COXs possess two enzymatic activities: a dioxygenase activity <lb/>and a peroxidase activity. The dioxygenase activity is a controlled <lb/>peroxidation process (129), and the role of the enzyme is to <lb/>direct hydrogen abstraction and the stereochemistry of <lb/>formation of intermediates (120). Unlike LOXs where <lb/>hydrogen abstraction is carried out by a non-heme associated <lb/>Fe(III), hydrogen abstraction in COX is carried out by a catalytic <lb/>tyrosyl radical (Figure 2A). The heme group oxidizes a tyrosine <lb/>residue in the active site into a radical, which then abstracts a <lb/>hydrogen (stereo-and regio-specifically) from the (1Z,4Z)-<lb/>pentadiene group of the lipid. Using AA as an example <lb/>substrate, the 13-pro-S hydrogen is abstracted. The resulting <lb/>alkyl radical rearranges into a conjugated diene before the <lb/>addition of dioxygen at C11, generating a peroxyl radical (11R-<lb/>stereochemistry). Rotation of the peroxyl radical positions the <lb/>outer oxygen atom in the correct orientation to attack the C9 <lb/>carbon resulting in an endoperoxide (130). A second cyclization <lb/>involving C8 and C12 generates a bicyclic ring and a radical at <lb/>C15. Note that the cyclopentane ring is formed in the trans <lb/>configuration (131). This differs from the non-enzymatically <lb/>generated isoprostanes which occur predominantly in the cis <lb/>configuration (132). Following the second cyclization, dioxygen <lb/>is added onto the si face of the C15, forming a peroxyl radical <lb/>(15S-stereochemistry). Hydrogen atom transfer from the active <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Hajeyah et al. <lb/>Biosynthesis of Oxidized Lipids <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Endocrinology | www.frontiersin.org <lb/>November 2020 | Volume 11 | Article 591819 <lb/></note>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<body>site tyrosine residue forms prostaglandin G 2 (PGG 2 ) and <lb/>regenerates the tyrosyl radical for another round of catalysis. <lb/>The peroxidase activity of COX reduces PGG 2 into PGH 2 <lb/>(Figure 2A). The mechanism involves a two-electron reduction <lb/>of the hydroperoxide into an alcohol, with a corresponding <lb/>oxidation of the heme group into the oxoferryl form (133) <lb/>(Figure 2B). Regeneration of the heme group can be achieved <lb/>by two sequential one-electron reductions. The peroxidase <lb/>activity is required for the dioxygenase activity as the oxidation <lb/>of the tyrosine into a radical is done by the oxoferryl-porphyrin <lb/>cation radical generated during the peroxidase reaction cycle <lb/>(133) (Figure 2B). Suicide inactivation has been described for <lb/>both the dioxygenase and peroxidase activities of COX <lb/>(133, 134). <lb/>The dioxygenase activity of COX can also result in a <lb/>lipoxygenase-type reaction, in which one dioxygen molecule is <lb/>introduced and no endoperoxide formation occurs (135, 136) <lb/>(Figure 2A). In this case, the peroxyl radical formed after the <lb/>addition of the oxygen is reduced into a hydroperoxide instead of <lb/>participating in the cyclization reaction. This reaction represents <lb/>an incomplete catalytic cycle and occurs as a side product. Using <lb/>AA as a substrate, this lipoxygenase-type reaction (after <lb/>A <lb/>B <lb/>FIGURE 2 | Reaction mechanism of cyclooxygenases (COXs). (A) Production of eicosanoids from arachidonic acid through the dioxygenase and peroxidase <lb/>activities of COX. The cyclooxygenase reaction is colored black. Peroxidase reactions are coloured blue. Reactions that produce HpETEs are colored red. Side <lb/>reactions that produce 15-HETEs are depicted by dashed arrows. (B) The peroxidase cycle generates the Tyr radical required for hydrogen abstraction (porphyrin <lb/>ring of heme not shown). <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Hajeyah et al. <lb/>Biosynthesis of Oxidized Lipids <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Endocrinology | www.frontiersin.org <lb/>November 2020 | Volume 11 | Article 591819 <lb/></note>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<body>reduction by peroxidase) leads to the formation of 11R-HETE <lb/>(HETE: hydroxy-eicosatetraenoic acid), 15R-HETE and 15S-<lb/>HETE (minor product compared to 15R-HETE in both <lb/>isoforms) (137). C11 and C15 are the same oxygen insertion <lb/>sites in the dioxygenase (cyclooxygenase reaction), and these by-<lb/>products are thought to arise from alternate conformations of <lb/>substrate in the active site (138). <lb/>Aspirin (acetylsalicylic acid) is an inhibitor of COXs, and its <lb/>mechanism of action involves the acetylation of a serine residue <lb/>(Ser530 in COX-2) in the active site. Acetylation of COX-1 leads <lb/>to complete inhibition (139), whereas the acetylation of COX-2 <lb/>promotes the lipoxygenase-type reaction and the formation of <lb/>15R-HETE (140). It was previously thought that acetylation <lb/>completely inhibits PG production by COX-2 (cyclooxygenase <lb/>reaction). However, recent evidence shows that the acetylated <lb/>enzyme retains that activity (15S-PG formation) but also more <lb/>favorably forms 15R-PGs (141), although PGs are still minor <lb/>products compared to 15R-HETE for acetylated-COX-2. These <lb/>findings are consistent with an earlier study that reported the <lb/>formation of 15R-PGE 2 in COX-2 Ser530 mutants (137). Thus, <lb/>both acetylation and mutagenesis of Ser530 in COX-2 promote <lb/>15R-PG formation. <lb/>COX Isoforms Differ in Their Substrate Specificity <lb/>COXs catalyze the transformation of AA into PGH 2 , which is a <lb/>precursor of other PGs (PGD 2, PGE 2 , PGF 2a , PGI 2 ) and <lb/>thromboxane. These oxygenated AA derivatives are generated <lb/>through the action of tissue-specific enzymes downstream of <lb/>COX (discussed in section 3.1) and play roles in inflammation, <lb/>blood flow regulation and blood clotting through interactions <lb/>with specific GPCRs (142). <lb/>COXs also accept other PUFAs as substrates including <lb/>DGLA, LA, ALA, EPA, and GLA (143), at least in vitro. An <lb/>early study determined the efficiency of substrate utilization for <lb/>human COXs (K cat /K m ) to be AA &gt; DGLA &gt; LA &gt; ALA, with <lb/>ALA being a poor substrate for COX-1. EPA and GLA are poor <lb/>substrates for both isoforms but they are better substrates for <lb/>COX-2 than for COX-1 (143). Later studies have tested other <lb/>PUFAs like eicosadienoic acid, adrenic acid, docosapentaenoic <lb/>acid and DHA as COX substrates (127, 144). In general, COX-2 <lb/>was found to be more efficient than COX-1 for a broader range of <lb/>PUFAs. That said, AA is the preferred substrate for both <lb/>isoforms, but COX-2 can oxygenate it at lower concentrations <lb/>compared to COX-1 due to differences in their allosteric <lb/>regulation by FAs (145). <lb/>COX-2 can also catalyze the 11R-, 15R-, 15S-dioxygenation and <lb/>bis-oxygenation of 5S-HETE, forming diHETEs in the former three <lb/>reactions and a di-endoperoxide product in the later reaction. <lb/>However, acetylation of COX-2 shifts the specificity into favoring <lb/>15R-dioxygenation producing 5S,15R-diHETE (146). Additionally, <lb/>COX-2 can oxygenate AA in complex lipids for example; <lb/>arachidonoylethanolamide, 2-arachidonoylglycerol (2-AG), and <lb/>N-arachidonoyl-glycine (147-149). Recently, 2-AA-lysoPL, and <lb/>ethanolamide derivatives of EPA and DHA were also shown to <lb/>be COX-2 substrates (88, 150). Oxygenation of AA-lysoPL by COX-<lb/>2 generates eicosanoid-lysoPL, which can be hydrolyzed to release <lb/>eicosanoids through intracellular lipases (88). The ability of COX-2 <lb/>to bind and oxygenate a broader range of substrates compared to <lb/>COX-1 has been attributed to a larger active site, the orientation of <lb/>an Arg residue in the substrate binding pocket and amino acid <lb/>residues lining the tunnel leading to the cyclooxygenase active <lb/>site (13). <lb/>COX isoforms exhibit differences in expression, tissue <lb/>distribution, allosteric regulation, and substrate specificity. <lb/>However, some aspects of COX biochemistry are unclear. For <lb/>example, the physiological functions of COX-2-derived <lb/>oxygenated endocannabinoids are unclear. Additionally, COX-<lb/>2 oxygenates AA-lysoPLs into eicosanoid-lysoPLs, which are <lb/>proposed to function in signaling and as precursors to other <lb/>mediators (88). However, the metabolism of eicosanoid-lysoPLs <lb/>requires further investigation. <lb/>Cytochrome P450 (CYP) <lb/>Human CYPs: Nomenclature and Tissue Distribution <lb/>Cytochrome P450s (CYP) are a superfamily of heme-containing <lb/>monooxygenases that are ubiquitous across all domains of life. <lb/>There are 57 functional CYP genes in humans, and their products <lb/>are further divided into 18 families and 41 sub-families based on <lb/>amino acid sequence (151, 152). A robust, unified nomenclature <lb/>system has been devised for CYPs, encompassing all known CYPs <lb/>across living organisms (153, 154). The name includes the root <lb/>&quot;CYP&quot;, followed by a number for family, a letter for subfamily, and <lb/>a gene-identifying number for isoforms. Additionally, an asterisk <lb/>and a number are added at the end to denote alleles (155). Families <lb/>and subfamilies are based on 40% and 55% amino acid sequence <lb/>identity, respectively. <lb/>CYPs are widely distributed in mammalian tissues (156-158), <lb/>with a particularly high expression in the liver, brain, kidney and <lb/>lung. Intracellularly, mammalian CYPs are generally bound to <lb/>mitochondrial membranes and the endoplasmic reticulum (ER; <lb/>microsomes when in vitro) (159, 160). There is also evidence of <lb/>mammalian CYPs in other compartments including the plasma <lb/>membrane and the nucleus, based on in vitro studies on cultured <lb/>cells (161-164). Some microsomal CYPs are also targeted into <lb/>the mitochondria (159). In the human genome, 50 out of the 57 <lb/>functional CYP genes code for microsomal CYPs, and the <lb/>remaining seven for mitochondrial isoforms. Some CYPs are <lb/>inducible by environmental stimuli, whereas others are <lb/>constitutively expressed (152). Induction of CYP expression by <lb/>environmental compounds can be through interactions with <lb/>nuclear receptors, transcriptional regulatory elements, or non-<lb/>coding RNAs (165). <lb/>Two major functions of CYPs are in drug metabolism and <lb/>lipid metabolism. Here, we focus on lipid metabolism which <lb/>involves members of most human CYP families. For an extensive <lb/>review, the reader is referred to Nelson and Nebert (166). <lb/>Structure of Mammalian CYPs <lb/>Structural characterization was first carried out on bacterial <lb/>CYPs, which are typically water soluble. On the other hand, <lb/>mammalian CYPs are membrane-bound, and initial attempts to <lb/>crystallize them were unsuccessful until a small N-terminal <lb/>hydrophobic helical segment was replaced with a hydrophilic <lb/>sequence from a related protein. The first structure to be <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Hajeyah et al. <lb/>Biosynthesis of Oxidized Lipids <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Endocrinology | www.frontiersin.org <lb/>November 2020 | Volume 11 | Article 591819 <lb/></note>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<body>published was of rabbit CYP2C5, a microsomal CYP isoform <lb/>that hydroxylates progesterone (167). Comparison of CYP2C5 <lb/>structure with closely related microbial CYPs showed a similar <lb/>folding geometry, but unique features of the mammalian enzyme <lb/>were observed such as a hydrophobic surface that was proposed <lb/>to play a role in membrane binding (167). <lb/>CYPs consist of two domains: a b-sheet-rich N-terminal <lb/>domain and a larger helix-rich C-terminal catalytic domain. <lb/>The N-terminal domain in microsomal CYPs contains a <lb/>transmembrane helix that plays a role in membrane anchoring, <lb/>but that role is not exclusive as CYPs contain other regions (in <lb/>the catalytic domain) that bind the membrane. This <lb/>transmembrane helix is not present in mitochondrial CYPs, <lb/>and their membrane binding is facilitated by hydrophobic and <lb/>amphipathic regions on the surface (160, 168). The N-terminus <lb/>also contains a signal peptide sequence for trafficking into the <lb/>appropriate compartment, that in the case of mitochondrial <lb/>CYPs, is cleaved during transport. The catalytic domain <lb/>contains a deep cavity that houses the heme prosthetic group. <lb/>A thiolate ion in a conserved cysteine residue occupies the fifth <lb/>coordination position of heme, and a water molecule occupies <lb/>the sixth position in the resting state. There is variable flexibility <lb/>in the active site among CYPs, and a high degree of flexibility has <lb/>been correlated to substrate promiscuity (169, 170). Residues in <lb/>helices surrounding the active site heme position the substrate <lb/>for catalysis. Additionally, in the CYP4 family, a covalent linkage <lb/>has been identified between the heme group and a conserved <lb/>glutamic acid residue (171), and this interaction plays a role in <lb/>substrate positioning for w-hydroxylation (hydroxylation at the <lb/>methyl end of FAs) (172). <lb/>Other structural features of CYPs include access channels that <lb/>allow entry of substrates from both the aqueous and membrane <lb/>compartments and an exit channel for the product (160). <lb/>Furthermore, oligomerization is well-documented in both <lb/>microsomal and mitochondrial CYPs, which can be between <lb/>subunits of the same CYP (homomeric; e.g., CYP2C2) or <lb/>different CYPs (heteromeric; e.g., CYP2E1/CYP3A4 and <lb/>CYP1A2/CYP2B4) (173-180). These interactions provide an <lb/>additional layer of regulation and play a role in substrate specificity. <lb/>Enzymology of Mammalian CYPs <lb/>CYPs catalyze a wide range of reactions (181, 182), but the most <lb/>common include C-hydroxylation, heteroatom oxidation, <lb/>heteroatom dealkylation, epoxidation, and group migration <lb/>(182). Many reactions of CYPs are dependent on their ability <lb/>(owing to the thiolate-heme group) to catalyze the scission of <lb/>dioxygen and incorporate one of the oxygen atoms into the <lb/>substrate, with the other being reduced to water. These reactions <lb/>require electron transfer from a donor, NADPH, to the heme iron. <lb/>However, transfer of electrons from NADPH to CYPs requires <lb/>protein partners: NADPH cytochrome P450 reductase in the case <lb/>of microsomal CYPs, and the combined functions of adrenodoxin <lb/>reductase and adrenodoxin in mitochondrial CYPs. Thus, CYPs <lb/>form complexes with their redox partners, at least during catalysis. <lb/>That said, not all CYP reactions require external oxygen or <lb/>electron donors. Examples are isomerization reactions catalyzed <lb/>by CYP5A1 (thromboxane synthase) and CYP8A1 (prostacyclin <lb/>synthase) (183), two enzymes involved in PGH 2 metabolism. <lb/>A generalized reaction mechanism for CYPs (Figure 3A) <lb/>contains the following steps: starting with the resting state, <lb/>substrate recruitment displaces H 2 O from the 6 th (axial) <lb/>position of the heme Fe(III). This is followed by a 1-electron <lb/>reduction from a donor forming Fe(II), O 2 binding, and another <lb/>1-electron reduction resulting in a negatively charged peroxo <lb/>group. Protonation of this complex twice by nearby H 2 O or <lb/>amino acid residues results in the scission of the dioxygen (O-O <lb/>bond) into an oxoferryl intermediate (compound I) and a water <lb/>molecule (184). Compound I is thought to be the direct oxidant <lb/>in many CYP oxidation reactions (185). In hydroxylation <lb/>reactions, compound I abstracts a hydrogen from an alkyl <lb/>group in the substrate generating a carbon radical and an iron <lb/>oxygen complex, which rapidly react together forming a <lb/>hydroxyl group on the substrate and regenerating the heme <lb/>iron into the Fe(III) state (Figure 3B). Although this is a <lb/>generalized reaction scheme for CYPs, the intermediates <lb/>following O 2 binding until compound I have been difficult to <lb/>characterize due to their instability and the exact electronic <lb/>structures are not fully assigned (185). <lb/>Mammalian CYPs Play Crucial Roles in Oxidative <lb/>Lipid Metabolism <lb/>CYPs are involved in the metabolism of a wide range of lipids <lb/>including PUFAs and sterols (Table 2). Hydroxylation and <lb/>epoxidation are two common CYP-mediated reactions for PUFA <lb/>substrates. CYPs can hydroxylate FAs terminally (w-<lb/>hydroxylation) or midchain. Similarly, CYP-mediated <lb/>epoxidation can occur on various double bonds in PUFA. CYPs <lb/>exhibit variable preference with respect to the reaction type and <lb/>positional specificity. CYP1-3 families catalyze epoxidation and <lb/>hydroxylation reactions for FAs, whereas the CYP4 family favors <lb/>hydroxylation over epoxidation, specifically w-hydroxylation (204). <lb/>Terminal hydroxylation of AA by CYPs produces 20-<lb/>hydroxyeicosatetraenoic acid (20-HETE), which functions in <lb/>blood pressure regulation and water balance (205). <lb/>Additionally, terminal hydroxylation functions in w-oxidation <lb/>(a catabolic pathway for FAs), the degradation of some <lb/>eicosanoids (206, 207), and the proper formation of the skin <lb/>permeability barrier (208). Midchain hydroxylation of PUFA <lb/>produces mono-hydroxylated derivatives (HETEs in the case of <lb/>AA) with various bioactivities (reviewed in (152)). Unlike LOXs <lb/>and COXs which oxygenate carbons two bonds away from bis-<lb/>allylic methylene carbons, CYPs can also oxygenate bis-allylic <lb/>carbons (producing 7-, 10-and 13-HETE from AA), and various <lb/>other positions (209-211). However, bis-allylic hydroxylation <lb/>products are unstable in mildly acidic conditions and rearrange <lb/>into conjugated dienes (211). <lb/>Epoxidation of AA by CYPs produce epoxy-eicosatrienoic <lb/>acids (EET). However, other PUFA like LA, EPA and DHA also <lb/>undergo CYP-mediated epoxidation. Epoxy derivatives of <lb/>PUFAs are implicated in blood pressure regulation and <lb/>inflammation (15). Their metabolism is undertaken by several <lb/>epoxide hydrolases including soluble epoxide hydrolase (sEH) <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Hajeyah et al. <lb/>Biosynthesis of Oxidized Lipids <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Endocrinology | www.frontiersin.org <lb/>November 2020 | Volume 11 | Article 591819 <lb/></note>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<body>A <lb/>B <lb/>FIGURE 3 | Reaction mechanism of cytochrome P450s (CYPs). (A) Generalized catalytic cycle of CYPs. (B) Hydroxylation of a generic substrate (R-H) by compound I via an oxygen rebound mechanism. <lb/></body>
			
			<note place="headnote">Hajeyah et al. <lb/>Biosynthesis of Oxidized Lipids <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Endocrinology | www.frontiersin.org <lb/>November 2020 | Volume 11 | Article 591819 <lb/></note>

			<page>10 <lb/></page>

			<body>and microsomal epoxide hydrolase (mEH) (212). The action of <lb/>epoxide hydrolases produces dihydroxy derivatives which <lb/>possess different bioactivities from their epoxide precursors (15). <lb/>Arachidonoylethanolamide also undergoes CYP hydroxylation <lb/>and epoxidation (213, 214). Similarly, CYPs catalyze epoxidation of <lb/>EPA and DHA ethanolamides, producing compounds with anti-<lb/>inflammatory and anti-angiogenic effects (215). These lipids can be <lb/>degraded by both sEH and fatty acid amide hydrolase (FAAH) <lb/>(215), suggesting a link between the CYP epoxygenase and <lb/>endocannabinoid pathways. The metabolism and biological roles <lb/>of these mediators is an active area of research (216). <lb/>CYPs catalyze several types of reactions in the metabolism of <lb/>sterols, some of which involve multiple oxygenation/ <lb/>hydroxylation steps. Demethylation of lanosterol by CYP51A1 <lb/>is a key reaction in cholesterol biosynthesis and involves three <lb/>successive oxidations of a methyl group, resulting in its release as <lb/>formic acid and the introduction of a double bond at the D ring <lb/>(217). Similarly, the formation of estradiol from testosterone via <lb/>the action of CYP19A1 (P450arom) involves the elimination of a <lb/>methyl group by three successive oxidation steps and the <lb/>introduction of a double bond at the A ring. Additionally, <lb/>cholesterol side-chain cleavage by CYP11A1 (P450scc) involves <lb/>two hydroxylation steps on different carbons followed by a C-C <lb/>bond cleavage (218). This reaction produces pregnenolone which <lb/>is a key intermediate in the formation of androgens, estrogens, <lb/>glucocorticoids and mineralocorticoids. <lb/>CYP-mediated hydroxylation reactions are ubiquitous in <lb/>cholesterol metabolism, leading to the formation of oxysterols, <lb/>steroid hormones and bile acids. Key enzymes in the bile acid <lb/>biosynthesis pathways are CYP7A1 (cholesterol 7a-hydroxylase), <lb/>CYP8B1 (sterol 12a-hydroxylase), CYP27A1 (commonly named <lb/>sterol 27-hydroxylase, but more correctly sterol (25R)26-<lb/>hydroxylase) and CYP7B1 (oxysterol 7a-hydroxylase) (219, 220). <lb/>Of these enzymes, CYP27A1 can both hydroxylate and carboxylate <lb/>the terminal carbon of the sterol side-chain (221). Other enzymes <lb/>involved in quantitatively minor bile acid biosynthesis pathways <lb/>are CYP46A1 (cholesterol 24S-hydroxylase) which 24S-<lb/>hydroxylates cholesterol (222, 223) and CYP3A4 which has 4b-<lb/>and 25-hydroxylase activity (189, 224). CYP enzymes involved in <lb/>steroid hormone biosynthesis include CYP11A (P450scc) (225), <lb/>CYP17A1 (steroid 17a-hydroxylase) (226), CYP21A2 (steroid 21-<lb/>hydroxylase), CYP11B1 (steroid 11b-hydroxylase), and 11B2 <lb/>(aldosterone synthase) and CYP19A1 (aromatase) (198). <lb/>Thus, CYPs play indispensable roles in the metabolism of <lb/>both PUFA and cholesterol. However, some human CYPs like <lb/>CYP2A7 and CYP20A1 have no assigned functions and remain <lb/>orphan enzymes. <lb/>Human Aldo-Keto Reductases (AKRs) and <lb/>Hydroxysteroid Dehydrogenases (HSDs) <lb/>AKRs: Nomenclature, Genes, and Tissue Distribution <lb/>Aldo-keto reductases (AKRs) are a superfamily of NADPH-<lb/>dependent oxidoreductases. They catalyze the reduction of <lb/>carbonyl groups to alcohols. A nomenclature system has been <lb/>proposed for AKRs (227). Like CYPs, AKRs are grouped into <lb/>families and subfamilies based on amino acid sequence. Families <lb/>have 40% sequence identity, whereas subfamilies are defined by <lb/>60% sequence similarity. The nomenclature consists of the root <lb/>TABLE 2 | Examples of human cytochrome P450s (CYPs) and their involvement in lipid metabolism. <lb/>Enzyme <lb/>Lipid substrate(s) <lb/>Reaction(s) <lb/>Refs. <lb/>CYP1A1 <lb/>AA, EPA, DHA <lb/>Epoxidation &amp; hydroxylation <lb/>(186) <lb/>CYP2C8 <lb/>AA, EPA, DPA, DHA <lb/>Epoxidation &amp; hydroxylation <lb/>(186-188) <lb/>CYP3A4 <lb/>Sterols <lb/>Hydroxylation <lb/>(189-191) <lb/>CYP4A11 <lb/>Lauric acid, PA <lb/>AA, EPA, DPA, DHA <lb/>w-Hydroxylation <lb/>w/w-1-Hydroxylation <lb/>(188, 192), <lb/>CYP4F2 <lb/>AA, EPA, DPA, DHA <lb/>w/w-1-Hydroxylation <lb/>(188) <lb/>CYP5A1 <lb/>(thromboxane synthase) <lb/>PGH 2 <lb/>Isomerization <lb/>(183) <lb/>CYP7A1 <lb/>Cholesterol, 7-DHC <lb/>7a-Hydroxylation, epoxidation, carbonylation <lb/>(161, 193, 194) <lb/>CYP7B1 <lb/>Oxysterols, steroids <lb/>7a-Hydroxylation <lb/>(195) <lb/>CYP8A1 <lb/>(prostacyclin synthase) <lb/>PGH 2 <lb/>Isomerization <lb/>(183) <lb/>CYP8B1 <lb/>Sterols <lb/>12a-Hydroxylation <lb/>(196) <lb/>CYP11A1 <lb/>(P450scc) <lb/>Cholesterol <lb/>Side-chain cleavage <lb/>(197) <lb/>CYP11B1 <lb/>11-Deoxycortisol, 11-deoxycorticosterone <lb/>11b-Hydroxylation <lb/>(198) <lb/>CYP11B2 <lb/>11-Deoxycorticosterone <lb/>11b-Hydroxylation, 18-hydroxylation &amp; oxidation <lb/>(198) <lb/>CYP17A1 <lb/>Pregnenolone, progesterone <lb/>17-Hydroxylation <lb/>(199) <lb/>CYP19A1 <lb/>(P450arom/aromatase) <lb/>Testosterone <lb/>Aromatization <lb/>(199) <lb/>CYP21A2 <lb/>Progesterone <lb/>Hydroxylation <lb/>(199) <lb/>CYP24A1 <lb/>Calcitriol <lb/>24-Hydroxylation <lb/>(200) <lb/>CYP26A1 <lb/>all-trans-Retinoic acid <lb/>Hydroxylation <lb/>(201) <lb/>CYP27A1 <lb/>Sterols <lb/>(25R)26-Hydroxylation and carboxylation <lb/>(197) <lb/>CYP39A1 <lb/>24-hydroxycholesterol <lb/>7a-Hydroxylation <lb/>(17) <lb/>CYP46A1 <lb/>Cholesterol, desmosterol <lb/>24S-Hydroxylation, 24S-epoxidation <lb/>(197, 202) <lb/>CYP51A1 <lb/>Lanosterol <lb/>14a-Demethylation <lb/>(203) <lb/>7-DHC, 7-dehydrocholesterol; AA, arachidonic acid; EPA, eicosapentaenoic acid; DPA, docosapentaenoic acid; DHA, docosahexaenoic acid; PA, palmitic acid; PGH 2 , prostaglandin H 2 . <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Hajeyah et al. <lb/>Biosynthesis of Oxidized Lipids <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Endocrinology | www.frontiersin.org <lb/>November 2020 | Volume 11 | Article 591819 <lb/></note>

			<page>11 <lb/></page>

			<body>&quot;AKR&quot; followed by a number for family, a letter for subfamily <lb/>and finally a number as a unique gene identifier. The <lb/>nomenclature has also been expanded to accommodate <lb/>multimers (228). The older (trivial) names of AKRs are still <lb/>heavily in use, which could lead to confusion. Thus, it is advised <lb/>to follow the nomenclature system proposed by Jez et al. (227). <lb/>There are 15 AKRs in the human genome spanning three families <lb/>and seven subfamilies. Human AKRs have variable expression and <lb/>accept a wide range of substrates (Table 3). They are involved in the <lb/>metabolism of sugars, prostaglandins and sterols, as well as the <lb/>detoxification of carbonyl compounds like lipid peroxidation <lb/>products. Additionally, members of family 6 (AKR6A3, AKR6A5, <lb/>and AKR6A9) are constituents of voltage-gated potassium channels <lb/>(250). All human AKRs have either established or proposed roles in <lb/>lipid metabolism except for AKR1E2. <lb/>Human AKRs are generally cytosolic with some exceptions. <lb/>AKR1B15 is found in mitochondria (236). Members of the <lb/>AKR1C subfamily in the lung (1C1, 1C2 and 1C3) are also <lb/>secreted in pulmonary surfactant (256). AKR1B10 is present in <lb/>lysosomes and is secreted into the intestinal lumen by epithelial <lb/>cells (257). AKR6 members form a complex with a plasma <lb/>membrane voltage channel on the cytosolic side. Finally, rat <lb/>AKR7A2 associates with the Golgi apparatus (258). Human <lb/>AKR7A2 contains a similar N-terminal amphipathic sequence <lb/>and likely associates with the Golgi apparatus. <lb/>Mammalian AKRs: Structure and Enzymology <lb/>Crystal structures have been solved for many mammalian AKRs. <lb/>They comprise of a triosephosphate isomerase barrel motif (a/b) <lb/>8 which has alternating a-helices and b-strands repeating eight <lb/>times. The a-helices surround an internal b-barrel formed by the <lb/>b-strands. The active site is located at the base of the barrel, in <lb/>which the substrate and the nicotinamide head group of NADPH <lb/>(cofactor) are proximally positioned for the reaction, while three <lb/>flexible loops form the back of the barrel and control substrate <lb/>specificity (259, 260). The structure also contains two additional <lb/>helices that are not part of the barrel motif. Family 1 AKRs are <lb/>monomeric, whereas families 6 and 7 form tetramers and dimers, <lb/>respectively (258, 261). <lb/>AKRs catalyze the stereospecific reduction of carbonyls into <lb/>alcohols. They can also catalyze the reverse oxidation reaction. <lb/>However, the reducing direction is generally favored due to the <lb/>abundance of reduced cofactor in the cellular environment. AKRs <lb/>can use both NADPH and NADH, but NADPH is the preferred <lb/>cofactor for most known AKRs as they interact with the <lb/>phosphoryl group present in NADPH but not NADH (262, 263). <lb/>The stereospecific nature of the reaction is due to the orientation of <lb/>the NADPH and the substrate in the active site. The NADPH is <lb/>bound in the anti-conformation (with respect to the ribose ring) <lb/>which promotes the transfer of the 4-pro-R hydride (264), and the <lb/>substrate is positioned perpendicular to the cofactor. <lb/>The reaction of AKRs follows an ordered bi-bi mechanism in <lb/>which the NADPH cofactor binds first and leaves last. The active <lb/>site of AKRs contains a highly conserved catalytic tetrad of Tyr, <lb/>Lys, Asp and His. The hydride transfer is facilitated by acid-base <lb/>catalysis involving the protonation state of Tyr and the other <lb/>catalytic residues. In the reduction direction, the protonated <lb/>form of Tyr acts as an acid by participating in proton relay <lb/>TABLE 3 | Human AKRs: Genes, expression sites, and example substrates. <lb/>Gene <lb/>Alternative protein name <lb/>Expression sites <lb/>Example substrates <lb/>Refs. <lb/>AKR1A1 Aldehyde reductase <lb/>Brain, kidney, liver, small <lb/>intestine <lb/>4-HNE, acrolein, succinic semi-aldehyde, D-glucuronic <lb/>acid, phospholipid aldehydes <lb/>(229, 230), <lb/>AKR1B1 Aldose reductase/Prostaglandin F <lb/>synthase <lb/>Ubiquitous <lb/>Glucose, 4-HNE &amp; its glutathione conjugate, acrolein, <lb/>PGH 2 , phospholipid aldehydes <lb/>(229, 230), <lb/>AKR1B10 Small intestine aldose reductase <lb/>Small intestine, colon, liver, <lb/>cornea <lb/>Farnesal, retinoids, acrolein, phospholipid aldehydes <lb/>(229, 231-235), <lb/>AKR1B15 Aldo-keto reductase/3-Keto-acyl CoA <lb/>reductase <lb/>Placenta, testis, adipose tissue <lb/>Androgens, estrogens, <lb/>3-keto-acyl CoA conjugates <lb/>(236) <lb/>AKR1C1 20a-HSD <lb/>Kidney, lung, liver, testis, brain <lb/>Progesterone, estrone, 5a-dihydrotestosterone, 4-HNE <lb/>(230, 237-239), <lb/>AKR1C2 Type 3 3a-HSD <lb/>Liver, brain, lung, prostate <lb/>Progesterone, estrone, 5a-dihydrotestosterone <lb/>(237, 238), <lb/>AKR1C3 Type 5 17b-HSD/Prostaglandin F <lb/>synthase <lb/>Liver, lung, prostate, brain, <lb/>breast, lymphocytes <lb/>Progesterone, estrone, 5a-dihydrotestosterone, PGH 2 , <lb/>PGD 2 , 4-HNE <lb/>(238, 240-242), <lb/>AKR1C4 Type 1 3a-HSD <lb/>Liver <lb/>3-Keto-5b-sterols, <lb/>5a-dihydrotestosterone <lb/>(230, 238), <lb/>AKR1D1 Steroid 5b-reductase <lb/>Liver, placenta, brain <lb/>D 4 -Ketosteroids, particularly bile acid intermediates <lb/>(237, 243-245), <lb/>AKR1E2 <lb/>1,5-Anhydro-D-fructose reductase <lb/>Liver, testis <lb/>1,5-Anhydro-D-fructose <lb/>(246, 247) <lb/>KCNAB1 Potassium voltage-gated channel b-<lb/>subunit-1 (Kvb1)/AKR6A3 <lb/>Brain, heart <lb/>Lipid peroxidation-derived aldehydes (presumed)* <lb/>(248, 249) <lb/>KCNAB2 Potassium voltage-gated channel b-<lb/>subunit-2 (Kvb2)/AKR6A5 <lb/>Brain, spinal cord <lb/>Methylglyoxal, acrolein, 4-ONE, oxPL, PGJ 2 * <lb/>( 250-252) <lb/>KCNAB3 Potassium voltage-gated channel b-<lb/>subunit-3 (Kvb3)/AKR6A9 <lb/>Brain <lb/>No data. <lb/>(253) <lb/>AKR7A2 Aflatoxin aldehyde reductase (AFAR1) <lb/>Ubiquitous <lb/>Aflatoxin B1, succinic semi-aldehyde, 4-HNE <lb/>(230, 254) <lb/>AKR7A3 Aflatoxin aldehyde reductase (AFAR2) <lb/>Liver, stomach, pancreas, <lb/>kidney <lb/>Aflatoxin B1 <lb/>(255), <lb/>*Evidence from work on the rat ortholog. 4-HNE, 4-hydroxy-2-nonenal; 4-ONE, 4-oxo-2-nonenal; HSD, hydroxysteroid dehydrogenase; oxPL, oxidized phospholipid; PG, prostaglandin <lb/>(e.g., PGH 2 , PGD 2 , PGJ 2 ). <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Hajeyah et al. <lb/>Biosynthesis of Oxidized Lipids <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Endocrinology | www.frontiersin.org <lb/>November 2020 | Volume 11 | Article 591819 <lb/></note>

			<page>12 <lb/></page>

			<body>with His (259) (Figure 4A). This polarizes the carbonyl group of <lb/>the substrate, allowing it to accept a hydride ion from the <lb/>cofactor. In the oxidation direction, the phenolate form of Tyr <lb/>(generated through proton relay with Lys and Asp) acts as a base <lb/>and abstracts a proton from the alcohol group of the substrate, <lb/>facilitating hydride transfer to the cofactor (259) (Figure 4B). <lb/>AKR1D subfamily members catalyze the irreversible 5b-<lb/>reduction of sterol double bonds into single bonds, instead of <lb/>the reversible reduction of carbonyls typical of AKRs (Figure <lb/>4C). They possess an altered catalytic tetrad with Glu replacing <lb/>His (265). This substitution allows the substrate to penetrate <lb/>deeper into the active site pocket, positioning C5 close to the 4-<lb/>pro-H of NADPH (259). The catalytic Glu residue is thought to <lb/>act as a superacid, facilitating the enolization of the steroid <lb/>double bond and allowing hydride transfer to C5 (259, 265). <lb/>Human AKR1B1 catalyzes the isomerization of PGH 2 to <lb/>PGD 2 in the absence of cofactor, as well as the reduction of <lb/>PGH 2 to PGF 2a in the presence of cofactor (266). Curiously, both <lb/>of these reactions are reported to be facilitated by a catalytic triad <lb/>of Lys, His and Asp, without the involvement of Tyr in catalysis, <lb/>although Tyr is still required for the p-nitrobenzaldehyde <lb/>reductase activity of the enzyme (266). Thus, both Tyr and His <lb/>can participate in acid-base catalysis, at least in AKR1B1. <lb/>Involvement of Human AKRs in Lipid Metabolism <lb/>Human AKRs play roles in the detoxification of reactive <lb/>carbonyls. Several AKRs metabolize lipid peroxidation-derived <lb/>aldehydes like acrolein and 4-HNE (Table 3). Additionally, some <lb/>AKRs (1A1, 1B1, 1B10, 6A5) can reduce oxidized phospholipids, <lb/>particularly phospholipid aldehydes (229, 251). These activities <lb/>mitigate the cytotoxicity of reactive carbonyls (240, 267-269), <lb/>and in the case of family 6 AKRs are also thought to function in <lb/>redox sensing (251). <lb/>Both AKR1B1 and AKR1C3 exhibit prostaglandin F synthase <lb/>activity (270, 271). AKR1B1 catalyzes the reduction of PGH 2 to <lb/>PGF 2a . AKR1C3 catalyzes the same reaction as well as the <lb/>A <lb/>B <lb/>C <lb/>FIGURE 4 | Catalytic mechanism of aldo-keto reductases (AKRs) in the: (A) Reduction direction and (B) Oxidation direction. (C) 5b-Reduction of steroid double <lb/>bond by AKR1D1. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Hajeyah et al. <lb/>Biosynthesis of Oxidized Lipids <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Endocrinology | www.frontiersin.org <lb/>November 2020 | Volume 11 | Article 591819 <lb/></note>

			<page>13 <lb/></page>

			<body>reversible reduction of PGD 2 to 9a,11b-PGF 2 (241). <lb/>Furthermore, AKR1B1 catalyzes the isomerization of PGH 2 to <lb/>PGD 2 exclusively in the absence of NADPH as noted previously. <lb/>However, the biological relevance of this activity is not clear as <lb/>this isomerization reaction is also catalyzed by two prostaglandin <lb/>D synthases (272), and the cellular redox status favors the <lb/>reduction reaction. Both PGF 2a and its isomer 9a,11b-PGF 2 <lb/>promote uterine contractions during labor (237). <lb/>Six of the 15 human AKRs are involved in sterol/steroid <lb/>metabolism: AKR1B15, the four members of the AKR1C <lb/>subfamily (also grouped as hydroxysteroid dehydrogenases; <lb/>HSDs), and AKR1D1. AKR1B15 catalyzes the 17b-reduction of <lb/>androgens and estrogens (236). AKR1C1 (20a-HSD) catalyzes the <lb/>20a-reduction of progesterone inactivating it (273), whereas <lb/>AKR1C2 (Type 3 3a-HSD) possesses a 3a-dehydrogenase activity <lb/>and deactivates 5a-dihydrotesterone (259). AKR1C3 (Type 5 17b-<lb/>HSD) exhibits 17-ketoreductase activity and produces testosterone <lb/>and estradiol from their respective precursors. <lb/>AKR1D1 and AKR1C4 (Type 1 3a-HSD) catalyze key steps <lb/>in bile acid biosynthesis. AKR1D1 catalyzes irreversible 5b-<lb/>reduction of a double bond in 3-ketosterols. This modification <lb/>changes the geometry of the steroid nucleus from flat to twisted, <lb/>with a bend in the A/B ring junction. Next, AKR1C4 catalyzes <lb/>the 3a-reduction of the ketosteroid, resulting in a 3a,5b-<lb/>configuration, a characteristic feature of bile acids. <lb/>Other HSDs Belong to the Short-Chain <lb/>Dehydrogenase/Reductase (SDR) Family <lb/>Some HSDs belong to a different family of enzymes: the short-<lb/>chain dehydrogenases/reductases (SDR). SDRs exhibit key <lb/>differences from AKRs in structure, kinetics, catalytic <lb/>mechanism, and reaction stereochemistry (reviewed in (274)). <lb/>Of note, HSDs of the SDR family work as either ketosteroid <lb/>reductases or hydroxysteroid oxidases, depending on their <lb/>preference for the corresponding forms of NADP(H) or NAD <lb/>(H). This contrasts with HSDs of the AKR1C family which <lb/>operate in the reduction direction using (primarily) NADPH <lb/>(274). Like CYPs and AKRs, a systematic nomenclature has been <lb/>proposed for SDRs (275). However, the old names (especially for <lb/>HSDs) remain heavily in use. HSDs of the SDR family have <lb/>important functions in sterol/steroid metabolism (Table 4). <lb/>BIOSYNTHETIC PATHWAYS OF OXIDIZED <lb/>LIPIDS <lb/>Oxygenated PUFA and Oxidized <lb/>Phospholipids <lb/>Classification of Oxygenated PUFA as Eicosanoids <lb/>and Docosanoids <lb/>The term &quot;oxylipin&quot; refers to oxygenated PUFA derivatives. It <lb/>encompasses a wide range of oxidized lipids like hydroxy-, <lb/>epoxy-, oxo-FAs, and endoperoxides. Oxylipins can be <lb/>classified according to their precursor into eicosanoids (C20) <lb/>or docosanoids (C22), etc., and this system will be used from here <lb/>on. Following the classification system of the LIPID MAPS <lb/>consortium, eicosanoids include prostaglandins, leukotrienes, <lb/>thromboxanes, lipoxins, hepoxilins, E-resolvins, as well as <lb/>hydroxy-, hydroperoxy-, epoxy-, and oxo-eicosanoids (286). <lb/>Likewise, docosanoids include D-resolvins, protectins, maresins, <lb/>hydroxy-, hydroperoxy-, epoxy-, and oxo-docosanoids. Structures <lb/>of these lipids are available on the LIPID MAPS database (287). <lb/>Here, we focus on the biosynthesis of eicosanoids derived <lb/>from AA and EPA, and docosanoids derived from DHA, as they <lb/>are the most studied. Due to the broad substrate specificity of <lb/>enzymes involved in lipid oxidation, PUFAs with shorter chains <lb/>or different number of double bonds also undergo similar <lb/>reactions. Similarly, oxygenation of endocannabinoids occurs <lb/>on the PUFA moiety and follows the enzymatic mechanisms <lb/>described here. Further aspects of oxygenated endocannabinoids <lb/>are discussed in other reviews (216, 288). <lb/>Release of PUFA from Membranes for Oxylipin <lb/>Biosynthesis <lb/>Intracellular concentration of free PUFA is tightly regulated <lb/>through conjugation with coenzyme A (CoA) and subsequent <lb/>esterification into lysoPL forming PL or shuttling into other <lb/>pathways (like b-oxidation). PUFAs are abundant in membrane <lb/>PLs, typically esterified at the sn-2 position. The classical pathway of <lb/>oxylipin biosynthesis involves the release of PUFA from membrane <lb/>PL via the action of lipases like phospholipase A 2 (PLA 2 ), <lb/>phospholipase C and diacylglycerol lipase (289, 290). PLA 2 <lb/>enzymes are classified into six types: secreted (sPLA 2 ), cytosolic <lb/>(cPLA 2 ), calcium-independent (iPLA 2 ), platelet-activating factor <lb/>TABLE 4 | Human SDR-HSDs and their substrates/reactions. <lb/>Gene <lb/>Alternative protein names <lb/>Substrates <lb/>Reaction <lb/>Refs. <lb/>HSD3B1 Type 1 3b-HSD/D 5-4 isomerase/SDR11E1 <lb/>3b-Hydroxy-D 5 -sterols <lb/>Oxidation &amp; isomerization <lb/>(276, 277), <lb/>HSD3B2 Type 2 3b-HSD/D 5-4 isomerase/SDR11E2 <lb/>3b-Hydroxy-D 5 -sterols <lb/>Oxidation &amp; isomerization <lb/>(277, 278), <lb/>HSD3B7 Type 7 3b-HSD/SDR11E3 <lb/>3b-Hydroxy-D 5 -sterols <lb/>Oxidation &amp; isomerization <lb/>(279) <lb/>HSD11B1 Type 1 11b-HSD/Corticosteroid 11b-dehydrogenase <lb/>isozyme 1/SDR26C1 <lb/>11b-Hydroxysterols (e.g. cortisol), <lb/>Oxidation <lb/>(280) <lb/>HSD11B2 Type 2 11b-HSD/Corticosteroid 11b-dehydrogenase <lb/>isozyme 2/SDR9C3 <lb/>11b-Hydroxysterols (e.g. cortisol), <lb/>Oxidation <lb/>(280) <lb/>HSD17B1 Type 1 17b-HSD/Estradiol 17b-dehydrogenase 1/ <lb/>SDR28C1 <lb/>Estrogens and androgens <lb/>Reduction <lb/>(281, 282) <lb/>HSD17B4 Type 4 17b-HSD/Peroxisomal multifunctional enzyme type <lb/>2/SDR8C1 <lb/>(24R,25R)-3a,7a,12a,24-Tetrahydroxy-5b-<lb/>cholestan-26-oyl-CoA <lb/>Reduction <lb/>(283) <lb/>HSD17B7 Type 7 17b-HSD/3-Ketosteroid reductase/SDR37C1 <lb/>3b-Hydroxysterols, 17b-estradiol <lb/>Reduction <lb/>(284, 285) <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Hajeyah et al. <lb/>Biosynthesis of Oxidized Lipids <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Endocrinology | www.frontiersin.org <lb/>November 2020 | Volume 11 | Article 591819 <lb/></note>

			<page>14 <lb/></page>

			<body>acetylhydrolases (PAH-AH), lysosomal (LPLA 2 ), and adipose <lb/>(AdPLA), and these are further divided into groups and <lb/>subgroups (291, 292). cPLA 2 a is localized in the cytosol but <lb/>translocates to intracellular membranes upon calcium activation, <lb/>and exhibits selectivity for phospholipids containing AA at the sn-2 <lb/>position (293, 294). On the other hand, the release of DHA from the <lb/>membrane can be facilitated by iPLA 2 b (295, 296). Last, sPLA 2 <lb/>enzymes are involved in the release of AA, EPA and DHA (297, <lb/>298). PLA 2 enzymes are extensively reviewed by Murakami (299). <lb/>Biosynthesis of Eicosanoids <lb/>Arachidonic acid is a substrate of eicosanoids produced through <lb/>the actions of COXs, LOXs, CYPs, and other downstream <lb/>enzymes (Figure 5A). The most established of these are mono-<lb/>oxygenation products of AA, DHA, and EPA and classic <lb/>prostaglandins, leukotrienes, and thromboxane from COXs, <lb/>LOXs, and CYPs. Most of these were described from the <lb/>1950s-90&apos;s in seminal studies, with many conducted at the <lb/>Karolinska Institute in Stockholm by Sune Bergstrom, Bengt <lb/>Samuelsson and colleagues. Indeed, the Nobel Prize for <lb/>Physiology and Medicine was awarded for discovery of <lb/>prostaglandins and related biologically active substances in <lb/>1985 to Bergstrom, Samuelsson and John Vane. More recently, <lb/>research has focused on characterization of multiply oxygenated <lb/>PUFAs from AA, EPA, and DHA including several which are <lb/>proposed to form from transcellular sequential oxygenation by <lb/>A <lb/>B <lb/>FIGURE 5 | Biosynthesis of eicosanoids derived from: (A) Arachidonic acid and (B) Eicosapentaenoic acid. HETE, hydroxy-eicosatetraenoic acid; Hp, hydroperoxy; <lb/>Ep, epoxy; LTA4H, leukotriene A 4 hydrolase; LTC4S, leukotriene C 4 synthase; GGT, g-glutamyl transpeptidase; DPEP2, dipeptidase 2; sEH, soluble epoxide <lb/>hydrolase; 12-HEDH, 12-hydroxyeicosanoid dehydrogenase; PGES, prostaglandin E synthase (m: microsomal, c = cytosolic); PGDS (prostaglandin D synthase (L: <lb/>lipocalin type, H: hematopoietic); 15-PGDH, 15-hydroxyprostaglandin dehydrogenase; PG-9KR, prostaglandin 9-ketoreductase; EET, epoxyeicosatrienoic acid; <lb/>DiHETrE, dihydroxy-eicosatrienoic acid; HEPE, hydroxy-eicosapenataenoic acid. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Hajeyah et al. <lb/>Biosynthesis of Oxidized Lipids <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Endocrinology | www.frontiersin.org <lb/>November 2020 | Volume 11 | Article 591819 <lb/></note>

			<page>15 <lb/></page>

			<body>various enzymes. However, for many of these, their specific <lb/>biosynthetic pathways, enantiomeric composition and <lb/>biological actions in tissues are not well understood and the <lb/>levels formed are extremely low in comparison to classic PGs and <lb/>monohydroxy-oxylipins. Furthermore, their bioactions often <lb/>require amounts of lipids that are considerably higher than <lb/>levels detected in cell and tissue samples, and thus could be <lb/>considered pharmacological. <lb/>COXs convert AA into PGG 2 which is reduced into PGH 2 <lb/>(Figure 5A). From there, PGH 2 functions as substrate for classic <lb/>PGs and thromboxane, generated by tissue-specific enzymes. <lb/>CYP5A1 (thromboxane synthase) is expressed in several cell <lb/>types and tissues (platelets, macrophages, lung, kidney, liver) and <lb/>catalyzes the isomerization of PGH 2 into thromboxane A 2 , a <lb/>potent vasoconstrictor and activator of platelet aggregation (300, <lb/>301). CYP5A1 also catalyzes the cleavage PGH 2 into <lb/>malondialdehyde and 12-hydroxyheptadecatrienoic acid. <lb/>CYP8A1 (prostacyclin synthase) is widely expressed (abundant <lb/>in ovary, heart, lung, skeletal muscle, and prostate) and catalyzes <lb/>the isomerization of PGH 2 into prostacyclin (PGI 2 ), a vasodilator <lb/>and inhibitor of platelet aggregation (302). <lb/>PGH 2 can also be converted into PGD 2 through the action of <lb/>AKR1B1 or PGD synthases, of which there are two isoforms: <lb/>lipocalin-type PGD synthase (in the central nervous system, male <lb/>genitalia, heart, cerebrospinal fluid and plasma) and <lb/>hematopoietic PGD synthase (in antigen-presenting cells, mast <lb/>cells and megakaryocytes) (266, 303). PGD 2 plays roles in the <lb/>regulation of body temperature, sleep cycle, pain perception and <lb/>the immune response (304). In the uterus, AKR1C3 catalyzes the <lb/>reduction of PGD 2 into 9a,11b-PGF 2 , which promotes uterine <lb/>contractions (237). Similarly, AKR1C3 and AKR1B1 catalyze the <lb/>reduction of PGH 2 into PGF 2 a, which also promotes uterine <lb/>contractions (305). Finally, PGH 2 can be converted into PGE 2 <lb/>via the action of PGE synthases, of which there are three <lb/>isoforms: an inducible microsomal isoform (mPGES-1), a <lb/>constitutive microsomal isoform (mPGES-2) and a constitutive <lb/>cytosolic isoform (cPGES) (306). PGE 2 is abundant in the body <lb/>and plays a complex role in immunity and inflammation (307). <lb/>Additionally, PGE 2 is reduced into PGF2a by prostaglandin 9-<lb/>ketoreductase (PG-9KR) (308). <lb/>COXs also produce 11R-, 15R-, and 15S-HpETEs as side <lb/>products, all three of which can be reduced into their <lb/>corresponding alcohols by peroxidase activity, which are in <lb/>turn reduced into oxo-ETEs by 15-hydroxyprostaglandin <lb/>dehydrogenase (15-PGDH). Bioactivities of HETEs and oxo-<lb/>ETEs are extensively reviewed by Powell and Rokach (309). <lb/>5-LOX converts AA into 5S-HpETE (Figure 5A), which is <lb/>reduced into 5S-HETE through the action of a peroxidase (e.g., <lb/>GPX) or converted into leukotriene A 4 (LTA 4 ) through the <lb/>leukotriene synthase activity of 5-LOX. Various immune cells <lb/>(neutrophils, monocytes, platelets) express 5-hydroxyeicosanoid <lb/>dehydrogenase (5-HEDH) which converts 5S-HETE into 5-oxo-<lb/>HETE, a potent chemoattractant for eosinophils (310). On the <lb/>other hand, LTA 4 serves as a precursor for LT peptide conjugates <lb/>(LTC 4 , D 4 and E 4 ) and lipoxins (A and B). LTC 4 , D 4 , and E 4 are <lb/>synthesized from LTA 4 through LTC 4 synthase (a gluthathione-<lb/>S-transferase), g-glutamyl transpeptidase (GGT) and dipeptidase <lb/>2 (DPEP2). Leukotrienes exhibit pro-inflammatory properties <lb/>and are implicated in asthma and allergic reactions (311). On the <lb/>other hand, lipoxins are thought to be synthesized by 12S-LOX <lb/>through a transcellular pathway which involves interactions <lb/>between two cell types (312). Lipoxins exhibit anti-<lb/>inflammatory properties and are proposed to play a role in <lb/>wound healing and tissue homeostasis (313). Alternatively, <lb/>LTA 4 can be hydrolyzed by leukotriene A 4 hydrolase (LTA4H) <lb/>into LTB 4 , which attracts neutrophils (314). <lb/>15-LOXs converts AA into 15S-HpETE (Figure 5A), which <lb/>can be reduced into 15S-HETE then oxidized into 15-oxo-ETE. <lb/>15S-HpETE and 15S-HETE are also substrates for 5-LOX, which <lb/>produces a 5S,6S epoxy intermediate that can be hydrolyzed into <lb/>lipoxins by unidentified hydrolases. Additionally, 15S-HpETE is <lb/>proposed to be a precursor for eoxin A 4 (a 14,15 leukotriene), <lb/>which is converted into peptide conjugates (eoxin C 4 , D 4 , and E 4 ) <lb/>similar to leukotrienes (315). Conversion of eoxin A 4 into C 4 is <lb/>thought to involve LTC4S. Enzymes that catalyze the following <lb/>two steps leading to eoxin D 4 and E 4 are unidentified, <lb/>presumably a GGT isoform and DPEP2. Eoxins are produced <lb/>in eosinophils, mast cells and airway epithelial cells, and have <lb/>been shown to possess pro-inflammatory properties (316). <lb/>12S-HpETE and 12R-HpETE are produced by 12S-LOX and <lb/>12R-LOX, respectively (Figure 5A). These hydroperoxides can <lb/>be reduced to their corresponding alcohols via a peroxidase, <lb/>and both alcohols further oxidized into 12-oxo-ETE by 12-<lb/>hydroxyeicosanoid dehydrogenase (12-HEDH) (309). Both <lb/>hydroperoxides are also precursors for hepoxilins, which are <lb/>epoxy-alcohols. eLOX3 in skin converts 12R-HpETE into either <lb/>hepoxilin A 3 or 12-oxo-ETE. On the other hand, 12S-HpETE <lb/>can be converted into hepoxilin A 3 or B 3 by either 12S-LOX or <lb/>eLOX3, but eLOX3 also generates 12-oxo-ETE (70, 317). <lb/>Hepoxilins A 3 and B 3 are hydrolyzed by sEH into trioxilins <lb/>A 3 and B 3 , respectively (318). Hepoxilin A 3 can also be <lb/>conjugated with glutathione via LTC4S producing hepoxilin <lb/>A 3 -C, which can be converted into a hepoxilin A 3 -D by GGT <lb/>(319). The occurrence of hepoxilin A 3 -E (cysteinyl conjugate) <lb/>has also been proposed but not confirmed. Hepoxilin A 3 is <lb/>proposed to regulate mucosal inflammation by recruiting <lb/>neutrophils across the epithelial junction into the gut <lb/>lumen (320). <lb/>CYPs generate various midchain R-and S-HETEs as well as 20-<lb/>HETE through hydroxylation of AA (Figure 5A). Alternatively, <lb/>epoxyeicosatrienoic acids (EET) are produced from AA through <lb/>epoxidation of its double bonds. Major mammalian CYP <lb/>epoxygenases include CYP2C8, CYP2C9, and CYP2J2 (15). EETs <lb/>are further metabolized by sEH (and potentially other epoxide <lb/>hydrolases) into dihydroxyeicosatrienoic acids (DiHETrE). Note <lb/>that EPA and other PUFA are also targets of CYP-mediated <lb/>reactions, which generate the corresponding hydroxy-, epoxy-, <lb/>and dihydroxy-derivatives. <lb/>&quot;E-resolvins&quot;, another class of eicosanoids, are proposed to be <lb/>generated from EPA (Figure 5B). COX-2 and CYPs have both been <lb/>proposed to act on EPA to produce 18R-hydroxyeicosapentaenoic <lb/>acid (18R-HEPE), which is in turn a proposed precursor for lipids <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Hajeyah et al. <lb/>Biosynthesis of Oxidized Lipids <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Endocrinology | www.frontiersin.org <lb/>November 2020 | Volume 11 | Article 591819 <lb/></note>

			<page>16 <lb/></page>

			<body>termed resolvins E1, E2 and E3 (E-resolvins). It is known that the <lb/>acetylation of COX-2 shifts its activity into favoring the <lb/>lipoxygenase-type reaction over the cyclooxygenase activity, and <lb/>that acetylated COX-2 generates 18R-HEPE from EPA (321). <lb/>However, acetylated COX-2 is not a physiologically relevant form, <lb/>and 18R-HEPE could be potentially generated through other means. <lb/>COX-2 is theoretically capable of generating 18R-HEPE from EPA <lb/>in a lipoxygenase-type reaction followed by peroxidase activity. <lb/>However, whether the generation of 18R-HEPE from EPA occurs in <lb/>vivo and in sufficient amounts without COX-2 acetylation is <lb/>unknown. Microbial CYPs have also be proposed as sources of <lb/>18R-HEPE during infection. E-resolvins are proposed to be <lb/>produced through a transcellular mechanism involving microbial <lb/>and mammalian cells (322). Alternatively, mammalian CYPs are <lb/>also potential sources of 18R-HEPE, although the exact isoforms <lb/>involved are unknown. <lb/>18R-HEPE can be metabolized by 5-LOX into a 5S-<lb/>hydroperoxy intermediate and further into a 5S,6S-epoxy <lb/>intermediate (323). The former is proposed to be converted <lb/>into resolvin E2 by a peroxidase, whereas the latter is proposed to <lb/>be hydrolyzed into resolvin E1 by LTA4H (324). 18S-analogues <lb/>of resolvin E1 and E2 have also been described and are proposed <lb/>to be generated from 18S-HEPE through a similar pathway <lb/>(Figure 5B), although the enzymatic sources of 18S-HEPE <lb/>(aside from acetylated COX-2) are also unknown. 18R-HEPE <lb/>is also proposed to be a precursor to two stereoisomers <lb/>collectively called resolvin E3 generated by 15-LOX-1 (325). <lb/>E-resolvins are proposed to exhibit anti-inflammatory effects and <lb/>promote the resolution of inflammation (325, 326). <lb/>Both lipoxins and E-resolvins have been classified as specialized <lb/>pro-resolving mediators (SPMs), a term which currently describes <lb/>families of oxygenated PUFA metabolites with proposed roles in the <lb/>resolution of inflammation and tissue regeneration generated at <lb/>extremely low levels in biological samples. <lb/>Biosynthesis of Docosanoids <lb/>Oxygenation of DHA by LOXs and CYPs forms oxygenated <lb/>docosanoids (hydroxy-, epoxy-, and dihydroxy derivatives). DHA <lb/>is also the precursor to several classes of multiply oxygenated <lb/>docosanoids, including additional SPMs which have been named <lb/>maresins, D-resolvins, and protectins (Figure 6). Maresin <lb/>biosynthesis has been proposed to start with action of 12S-LOX, <lb/>generating 14S-hydroperoxy-DHA (14S-HpDoHE) then a 13S,14S-<lb/>epoxy intermediate. Hydrolysis of this epoxy intermediate by sEH <lb/>or an unidentified hydrolase is proposed to generate maresin 2 and <lb/>maresin 1, respectively (93, 327). The biosynthesis of protectin and <lb/>D-resolvins both begin with 15-LOX-1 which generates a 17S-<lb/>hydroperoxide (17S-HpDoHE). Further conversion of this <lb/>hydroperoxide into a 16S,17S-epoxy intermediate by 15-LOX-1 <lb/>followed by hydrolysis (unidentified hydrolase) is proposed to <lb/>generate protectin D1 (328). Alternatively, 17S-HpDoHE could be <lb/>reduced into an alcohol by a peroxidase, which then serves as a <lb/>precursor for D-resolvins. In this route, 5-LOX is proposed to <lb/>generate two distinct products hydroperoxides (4S or 7S), which <lb/>FIGURE 6 | Biosynthesis of specialized pro-resolving mediators (SPMs) derived from docosahexaenoic acid. HDoHE, hydroxy-docosahexaenoic acid; Hp, <lb/>hydroperoxy; Ep, epoxy; CTR, conjugate in tissue regeneration (M: maresin, P: protectin, R: resolvin); sEH, soluble epoxide hydrolase; LTC4S, leukotriene C 4 <lb/>synthase; GGT, g-glutamyl transpeptidase; DPEP2, dipeptidase 2. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Hajeyah et al. <lb/>Biosynthesis of Oxidized Lipids <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Endocrinology | www.frontiersin.org <lb/>November 2020 | Volume 11 | Article 591819 <lb/></note>

			<page>17 <lb/></page>

			<body>undergo further transformations leading to several D-resolvins <lb/>(Figure 6). Additionally, epoxide intermediates in the previously <lb/>described pathways are proposed to undergo glutathione <lb/>conjugation by LTC4S, generating peptide conjugates of maresin, <lb/>protectin and D-resolvin named MCTR1, PCTR1, and RCTR1, <lb/>respectively (CTR = conjugate in tissue regeneration). These <lb/>conjugates are proposed to be metabolized by GGT and DPEP2, <lb/>similar to leukotrienes (329). <lb/>Oxygenation of Esterified PUFA and Biosynthesis of <lb/>Oxidized Phospholipids <lb/>The classical pathway for the biosynthesis of oxidized <lb/>phospholipids starts with the release of PUFA from membranes <lb/>through the action of PLA 2 . PUFA are then oxygenated by the <lb/>enzymes discussed earlier. This is followed by acylation of <lb/>oxygenated PUFA with CoA and esterification into a lysoPL via <lb/>the action of an sn-2 acyltransferase. <lb/>The generation of PL-esterified eicosanoids is well-<lb/>documented in mammalian cells such as epithelial, endothelial <lb/>and immune cells (330). HETE-PLs are acutely generated by <lb/>activated neutrophils, platelets and monocytes (331-333). <lb/>Similarly, PGD 2 and PGE 2 generated from COX-1-derived <lb/>PGH 2 in activated platelets are rapidly incorporated into PE-<lb/>lysoPLs (334). Also, EET-PLs have been detected in rat liver <lb/>(335). For most of these, the mechanism of formation requires <lb/>endogenous generation of an oxylipin, which is then rapidly <lb/>esterified into membrane PL pools (e.g., on a timescale of <lb/>minutes) via Lands cycle enzymes (336). <lb/>15-LOXs also contribute to the formation of oxPL by two <lb/>other pathways. The first involves direct oxygenation of <lb/>membrane PLs (331, 337). In the second pathway, 15-LOXs <lb/>oxygenate the PUFA moiety of CEs, then hydrolysis of <lb/>oxygenated PUFA from CE liberates oxygenated PUFA which <lb/>can be esterified to lysoPL (87). <lb/>Recent studies found that COX-2, 15-LOX-2, and platelet <lb/>12S-LOX can catalyze the oxygenation of 2-AA-lysoPL released <lb/>by iPLA 2 g in response to calcium ionophore stimulation (88, 94). <lb/>These reactions generate 2-eicosanoid-lysoPLs which are <lb/>proposed to be a source of free eicosanoids as well as acting as <lb/>signaling mediators themselves. 2-eicosanoid-lysoPLs can also be <lb/>converted into oxPLs through the action of sn-1 acyltransferase <lb/>(338). Cytochrome c has been recently been identified as a <lb/>plasmalogenase, and is proposed to be a source of 2-<lb/>eicosanoid-lysoPLs under conditions of oxidative stress (339). <lb/>These findings describe novel pathways for the biosynthesis of <lb/>oxPLs (Figure 7). Further research is required to assess the <lb/>contribution of these pathways to the formation of oxPLs and <lb/>other mediators in vivo. <lb/>Biosynthesis of Oxysterols, Bile Acids, and <lb/>Steroid Hormones <lb/>Oxysterols <lb/>Oxysterols are formed in the first steps of cholesterol <lb/>metabolism: they are oxidized forms of cholesterol and also of <lb/>its precursors (340). 7a-Hydroxycholesterol (7a-HC) is formed <lb/>from cholesterol by CYP7A1 and represents the first metabolite <lb/>in the neutral pathway of bile acid biosynthesis (Figure 8) (219, <lb/>220). (25R)26-Hydroxycholesterol (26-HC), more commonly <lb/>called 27-hydroxycholesterol, and 3b-hydroxycholest-5-en-<lb/>(25R)26-oic acid (3b-HCA) are both formed from cholesterol <lb/>by CYP27A1 and are the first members of the acidic or <lb/>alternative pathway of bile acid biosynthesis (219-221). While <lb/>CYP7A1 is an endoplasmic reticulum and liver specific protein, <lb/>CYP27A1 is mitochondrial and expressed in many tissues. <lb/>CYP46A1 is almost exclusively expressed in neurons, its <lb/>function is to maintain cholesterol balance in the brain, <lb/>converting cholesterol from a molecule unable to pass the <lb/>blood brain barrier to 24S-hydroxycholesterol (24S-HC), a <lb/>more polar molecule which can cross the barrier (222, 223, <lb/>341). CYP11A1, like CYP27A1, is a mitochondrial inner <lb/>membrane protein. It is highly expressed in steroidogenic <lb/>tissue and will oxidize cholesterol to pregnenolone in a three <lb/>step process involving 22R-hydroxycholesterol (22R-HC) and <lb/>20R,22R-dihydroxycholesterol as intermediates (20R,22R-diHC) <lb/>(342, 343) (Figure 9). The pathways of bile acid biosynthesis are <lb/>discussed in more detail below. <lb/>While most &quot;primary&quot; oxysterols are formed from cholesterol <lb/>in CYP catalyzed reactions, cholesterol 25-hydroxylase <lb/>(CH25H), the dominating enzyme that generates 25-<lb/>hydroxycholesterol (25-HC) is an exception, in that is not a <lb/>CYP, but a member of a family of enzymes that utilize di-iron <lb/>cofactors to catalyze the hydroxylation (344). CH25H is <lb/>expressed in activated immune cells and 25-HC has both anti-<lb/>bacterial and anti-viral activities (345-348). 25-HC is <lb/>metabolized by CYP7B1 to 7a,25-diHC, a ligand to the GPCR <lb/>Epstein Barr virus induced gene 2 (EBI2 or GPR183). 7a,25-<lb/>diHC acts as a chemoattractant to GPR183 expressing immune <lb/>cells (349, 350). An alternative route to 7a,25-diHC production <lb/>is through CYP3A4 oxidation of 7a-HC (190), while the same <lb/>enzyme has also been reported to act as a second cholesterol 25-<lb/>hydroxylase and also a 4b-hydroxylase of cholesterol (189, 351). <lb/>Oxysterols can also be formed from cholesterol precursors in <lb/>reactions catalyzed by CYP enzymes (202, 352). These reactions <lb/>may be important in patients suffering from inborn errors of <lb/>cholesterol biosynthesis such as Smith-Lemli-Opitz syndrome <lb/>(SLOS, 7-dehydrocholesterol reductase deficiency) and <lb/>desmosterolosis (3b-hydroxysterol-D 24 -reductase deficiency) or <lb/>where there is very high expression of sterol hydroxylases, e.g., <lb/>CYP7A1 in cerebrotendinous xanthomatosis, where CYP27A1 <lb/>is deficient. <lb/>Bile Acid Biosynthesis <lb/>There are two quantitatively major and at least five minor <lb/>pathways of bile acid biosynthesis and all pathways involve <lb/>multiple oxidation reactions (219, 220, 353-358). Besides CYP <lb/>enzymes, key oxidation reactions are carried out by <lb/>hydroxysteroid dehydrogenase (HSD) members of the short <lb/>chain dehydrogenase/reductase (SDR) family and reductions <lb/>by aldo-keto reductases (AKR) enzymes. One of the minor <lb/>pathways that results in the formation of 3b,5a,6b-<lb/>trihydroxycholan-24-oic acid involves of cholestane-3b,5a,6b-<lb/>triol which is likely formed via the cholesterol peroxidation <lb/>product 5,6-epoxycholesterol (219, 354). <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Hajeyah et al. <lb/>Biosynthesis of Oxidized Lipids <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Endocrinology | www.frontiersin.org <lb/>November 2020 | Volume 11 | Article 591819 <lb/></note>

			<page>18 <lb/></page>

			<body>While the acidic pathway may be most important in infants <lb/>(359), at later stages of life the neutral pathway is dominant. This is <lb/>initiated by CYP7A1 oxidation of cholesterol to generate 7a-HC in <lb/>the liver. Further oxidation may occur at C-12 by CYP8B1 to <lb/>generate 7a,12a-dihydroxycholesterol (7a,12a-diHC), which may <lb/>be preceded or succeeded by oxidation and isomerization of the 3b-<lb/>hydroxy-5-ene structure to a 3-oxo-4-ene by HSD3B7, giving 7a-<lb/>hydroxycholest-4-en-3-one (7a-HCO) and 7a,12a-<lb/>dihydroxycholest-4-en-3-one (7a,12a-diHCO), respectively <lb/>(Figure 8). A general feature of bile acid biosynthesis is that many <lb/>of the enzymes involved in the pathways accept multiple substrates <lb/>resulting in variations in the order of reactions depending on the <lb/>tissue in which they proceed (360). The next steps involve A-ring <lb/>reductions which may be succeeded or preceded by (25R)26-<lb/>hydroxylation and (25R)26-carboxylation to ultimately give <lb/>3a,7a,12a-trihydroxy-5b-cholanestan-(25R)26-oic acid. The A-<lb/>ring reductions are carried out by AKR1D1 and AKR1C4, while <lb/>CYP27A1 carries out the (25R)26-oxidations. Side-chain <lb/>shortening of the cholestanoic acid proceeds in the peroxisome <lb/>through the CoA-thioester formed by bile acid Co-A synthetase <lb/>(BACS, SLC27A5) or very long chain acyl-CoA synthetase (VLCS, <lb/>SLC27A2). Following C-25 racemization by a-methylacyl-CoA <lb/>racemase (AMACR) the next oxidation involves the introduction <lb/>of D 24 double bond by the enzyme acyl-CoA oxidase 2 (ACOX2). <lb/>The D 24 double bond is then hydrated by D-bifunctional protein <lb/>(DBP), which then oxidizes the C-24 hydroxy to a C-24 ketone via <lb/>HSD17B4 activity. The resulting product 3a,7a,12a-trihydroxy-<lb/>24-oxo-5b-cholestan-(25R)26-oyl-CoA is then oxidized by the <lb/>enzyme peroxisomal thiolase 2 (SPCx) to the thioester of cholic <lb/>acid ready for conjugation with glycine, taurine, or hydrolysis to the <lb/>free acid by peroxisomal acyl-CoA thioesterase (ACOT) (219, 220). <lb/>The acidic pathway starts with (25R)26-hydroxylation and <lb/>(25R)26-carboxylation of cholesterol by CYP27A1 and this and <lb/>many other steps may proceed extrahepatically (Figure 8). Most <lb/>of the enzymes involved in the neutral pathway are also involved <lb/>in the acidic pathway although not in the same order (361). An <lb/>exception is CYP7A1, which is replaced by CYP7B1 as the 7a-<lb/>hydroxylase in the acidic pathway. CYP7B1 is expressed in many <lb/>tissues, not just liver (362, 363), and unlike CYP7A1 uses side-<lb/>chain oxysterols as its substrate. The acidic pathway mostly <lb/>generates chenodeoxycholic acid rather than cholic acid, so <lb/>CYP8B1 has minor involvement. The order of A-ring <lb/>reduction and side-chain cleavage can be reversed in the acidic <lb/>pathway with the formation of bile acid intermediates possessing <lb/>3-oxo-4-ene or 3b-hydroxy-5-ene functions. <lb/>Steroid Hormone Biosynthesis <lb/>The classical steroid hormones aldosterone (mineralocorticoid), <lb/>cortisol (glucocorticoid), testosterone (male sex hormone) and <lb/>17b-estradiol (female sex hormone) are all formed from <lb/>FIGURE 7 | Biosynthetic pathways of oxidized phospholipids. (1) The classical pathway involves the action of PLA 2 on membrane phospholipids, releasing sn-2 PUFA which <lb/>are oxygenated by cyclooxygenases (COXs), lipoxygenases (LOXs), and cytochrome P450s (CYPs) then re-esterified. *Oxygenated PUFA can be also be esterified with <lb/>plasmalogen lysophospholipids (2) Direct oxygenation of membrane phospholipids by 15-LOXs. (3) 15-LOX-mediated oxygenation of PUFA in cholesteryl esters followed by <lb/>hydrolysis of oxygenated PUFA provides substrates for the classical pathway. (4) An alternative pathway involves the action of PLA 1 , forming 2-PUFA-lysophospholipids which <lb/>are oxygenated by COX-2, 12S-LOX, and 15-LOXs then re-esterified with FA. (5) Cytochrome c releases 2-PUFA-lysophospholipids by cleaving the vinyl ether bond in <lb/>plasmalogen phospholipids, providing substrates for the alternative pathway. PLA, Phospholipase A; oxPUFA, oxygenated PUFA; ACS, acyl-CoA synthase; CE, cholesteryl <lb/>ester; CEH, neutral cholesterol ester hydrolase; FA, fatty acid/acyl; lysoPL, lysophospholipid. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Hajeyah et al. <lb/>Biosynthesis of Oxidized Lipids <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Endocrinology | www.frontiersin.org <lb/>November 2020 | Volume 11 | Article 591819 <lb/></note>

			<page>19 <lb/></page>

			<body>FIGURE 8 | A simplified view of the major bile acid biosynthesis pathways. The &quot;neutral&quot; pathway (highlighted in blue) starts with 7a-hydroxylation of cholesterol by <lb/>CYP7A1, the &quot;acidic&quot; pathway with (25R)26-hydroxylation then (25R)26-carboxylation of cholesterol by CYP27A1. In the &quot;acidic&quot; pathway (highlighted in red) <lb/>CYP7B1 is the 7a-hydroxylase. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Hajeyah et al. <lb/>Biosynthesis of Oxidized Lipids <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Endocrinology | www.frontiersin.org <lb/>November 2020 | Volume 11 | Article 591819 <lb/></note>

			<page>20 <lb/></page>

			<body>cholesterol through multiple oxidation reactions (Figure 9) (364, <lb/>365). Pregnenolone formed via CYP11A1 oxidation of <lb/>cholesterol represents an intermediate between oxysterol and <lb/>steroid hormone biosynthesis. It is oxidized by HSD3B2 to <lb/>progesterone on the pathway to aldosterone or by CYP17A1 to <lb/>17a-hydroxypregnenolone on the route to cortisol. Both these <lb/>pathways use CYP21A2 as a C-21 hydroxylase and CYP11B <lb/>enzymes as the 11b-hydroxylase. Note, HSD3B1 is the enzyme <lb/>which generates progesterone from pregnenolone in the <lb/>placenta, when progesterone acts as the hormone of <lb/>pregnancy. Further oxidation of 17a-hydroxypregnenolone by <lb/>CYP17A1 leads to dehydroepiandrosterone on the road to <lb/>testosterone and17b-estradiol. In this pathway additional <lb/>oxidations and reductions are carried out by HSD3B2 and <lb/>FIGURE 9 | Simplified view of steroid hormone biosynthesis. Highlighted in red are the classical steroid hormones, progesterone, aldosterone, cortisol, testosterone, <lb/>and 17b-estradiol. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Hajeyah et al. <lb/>Biosynthesis of Oxidized Lipids <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Endocrinology | www.frontiersin.org <lb/>November 2020 | Volume 11 | Article 591819 <lb/></note>

			<page>21 <lb/></page>

			<body>HSD17B3, respectively, while CYP19A1 is required to generate <lb/>estrogens. Besides being synthesized in the adrenal gland and sex <lb/>organs it is noteworthy that steroids can be synthesized in the <lb/>brain and are then named neurosteroids (366, 367). A more <lb/>general term for brain steroids which may be synthesized in the <lb/>brain or imported from the periphery and exert rapid non-<lb/>genomic effects is neuroactive steroids. It is beyond the scope of <lb/>this review to discuss steroid hormone biosynthesis and <lb/>metabolism in greater detail and the reader is directed to the <lb/>excellent reviews of Shackleton and colleagues (364, 368-370). <lb/>CONCLUDING REMARKS <lb/>Enzymatically oxidized lipids are derivatives of PUFA or cholesterol <lb/>with critical functions in cellular and physiological processes as <lb/>signaling mediators and hormones. Their biosynthesis is highly <lb/>regulated and carried out by enzymes that include LOXs, COXs, <lb/>CYPs, and AKRs. Advances in our understanding of these enzymes <lb/>have led to the discovery of novel lipid mediators and their <lb/>biosynthetic routes. Many functional aspects of these enzymes <lb/>and their products remain unclear, requiring further investigation. <lb/>These include elucidating the function of 15-LOX-2 (ALOX15B) in <lb/>macrophages, the regulatory mechanisms of 12-LOXs and eLOX3, <lb/>the mechanistic details of transcellular biosynthesis, the origin of 18-<lb/>HEPE required for E-resolvin biosynthesis, the biological functions <lb/>of orphan CYPs, and the bioactivities/functions of oxygenated <lb/>endocannabinoids. The relative physiological importance of some <lb/>multiply oxygenated PUFA mediators, which are generated in <lb/>extremely low amounts, also needs to be further clarified. This is <lb/>also true for multiply oxygenated derivatives of cholesterol. <lb/>Research on oxygenated PUFA and oxysterols has been <lb/>carried out largely in parallel, and both areas have benefited <lb/>greatly from advances in analytical methods. However, there are <lb/>still major questions to be answered in terms of their proposed <lb/>roles in human disease including atherosclerosis and <lb/>neurodegeneration. Here, we presented biosynthetic pathways <lb/>of oxygenated PUFA and oxysterols, highlighting their (known) <lb/>functions to show the diversity of products but also to draw <lb/>connections between the two groups. An integrated approach <lb/>encompassing the analysis of both lipid groups could be useful in <lb/>examining the etiology of disease. Despite their involvement in <lb/>the progression of disease such as atherosclerosis and <lb/>neurodegenerative disease, the two lipid groups are rarely <lb/>analyzed together. We propose that oxygenated PUFA and <lb/>oxysterols are more connected than previously thought, <lb/>especially as 15-LOX is being increasingly recognized as a <lb/>regulator of cholesterol metabolism. The immune and nervous <lb/>systems are both of particular interest as major sites of <lb/>cholesterol metabolism and 15-LOX expression. Further work <lb/>on the enzymology of 15-LOX with cholesteryl substrates could <lb/>lead to the discovery of novel oxidized lipids. For example, 15-<lb/>LOX oxygenation of PUFA esters of oxysterols could generate <lb/>novel lipids that link both classes directly in cell types that <lb/>possess the enzymatic machinery for oxysterol and oxylipin <lb/>biosyntheses (e.g., macrophages). An alternative biosynthetic <lb/>route could be through the esterification of oxylipins with free <lb/>oxysterols. That said, the detection of these proposed molecules <lb/>could be challenging due to low abundance and sensitivity to <lb/>alkaline conditions commonly used in analysis. Finally, the <lb/>substrate promiscuity of many of the enzymes involved in <lb/>production of oxidized lipids provides a technical challenge for <lb/>dissection of (patho)physiological function of specific oxidized <lb/>lipids. Clearly, there is plenty of scope for ongoing exploration of <lb/>the molecular, cellular, and physiological functions of <lb/>oxidized lipids. <lb/>AUTHOR CONTRIBUTIONS <lb/>AH planned the manuscript. AH, WG, and YW wrote the <lb/>manuscript with input from AF and VO. All authors <lb/>contributed to the article and approved the submitted version. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement">ACKNOWLEDGMENTS <lb/>AAH acknowledges funding from Kuwait University and support <lb/>from the Kuwait Cultural Office (KCO) in London. Work in <lb/>Swansea was supported by the UK Biotechnology and Biological <lb/>Sciences Research Council (BBSRC, grant numbers BB/N015932/ <lb/>1 to WJG and BB/L001942/1 to YW). AJF is supported by funding <lb/>from Barts Charity. VBO is a Royal Society Wolfson Merit Award <lb/>Holder and acknowledges funding from the Wellcome Trust for <lb/>LIPID MAPS (203014/Z/16/Z). <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>REFERENCES <lb/>1. Tilley SL, Coffman TM, Koller BH. Mixed messages: modulation of <lb/>inflammation and immune responses by prostaglandins and <lb/>thromboxanes. J Clin Invest (2001) 108(1):15-23. doi: 10.1172/JCI13416 <lb/>2. Slatter DA, Percy CL, Allen-Redpath K, Gajsiewicz JM, Brooks NJ, Clayton <lb/>A, et al. Enzymatically oxidized phospholipids restore thrombin generation <lb/>in coagulation factor deficiencies. JCI Insight (2018) 3(6):e98459. <lb/>doi: 10.1172/jci.insight.98459 <lb/>3. Buckley CD, Gilroy DW, Serhan CN. Proresolving lipid mediators and <lb/>mechanisms in the resolution of acute inflammation. Immunity (2014) 40 <lb/>(3):315-27. doi: 10.1016/j.immuni.2014.02.009 <lb/>4. Choi SH, Sviridov D, Miller YI. Oxidized cholesteryl esters and <lb/>inflammation. Biochim Biophys Acta Mol Cell Biol Lipids (2017) 1862 <lb/>(4):393-7. doi: 10.1016/j.bbalip.2016.06.020 <lb/>5. Lauder SN, Allen-Redpath K, Slatter DA, Aldrovandi M, O&apos;Connor A, <lb/>Farewell D, et al. Networks of enzymatically oxidized membrane lipids <lb/>support calcium-dependent coagulation factor binding to maintain <lb/>hemostasis. Sci Signal (2017) 10(507):eaan2787. doi: 10.1126/ <lb/>scisignal.aan2787 <lb/>6. Stachenfeld NS. Sex hormone effects on body fluid regulation. Exerc Sport <lb/>Sci Rev (2008) 36(3):152-9. doi: 10.1097/JES.0b013e31817be928 <lb/>7. Kuo T, McQueen A, Chen TC, Wang JC. Regulation of Glucose <lb/>Homeostasis by Glucocorticoids. Adv Exp Med Biol (2015) 872:99-126. <lb/>doi: 10.1007/978-1-4939-2895-8_5 <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Hajeyah et al. <lb/>Biosynthesis of Oxidized Lipids <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Endocrinology | www.frontiersin.org <lb/>November 2020 | Volume 11 | Article 591819 <lb/></note>

			<page>22 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>8. Bereshchenko O, Bruscoli S, Riccardi C. Glucocorticoids, Sex Hormones, <lb/>and Immunity. Front Immunol (2018) 9:1332(1332):1332. doi: 10.3389/ <lb/>fimmu.2018.01332 <lb/>9. Lefebvre P, Cariou B, Lien F, Kuipers F, Staels B. Role of bile acids and bile <lb/>acid receptors in metabolic regulation. Physiol Rev (2009) 89(1):147-91. <lb/>doi: 10.1152/physrev.00010.2008 <lb/>10. Studer E, Zhou X, Zhao R, Wang Y, Takabe K, Nagahashi M, et al. <lb/>Conjugated bile acids activate the sphingosine-1-phosphate receptor 2 in <lb/>primary rodent hepatocytes. Hepatology (2012) 55(1):267-76. doi: 10.1002/ <lb/>hep.24681 <lb/>11. Griffiths WJ, Wang Y. Oxysterol research: a brief review. Biochem Soc Trans <lb/>(2019) 47(2):517-26. doi: 10.1042/BST20180135 <lb/>12. Garavito RM, DeWitt DL. The cyclooxygenase isoforms: structural insights <lb/>into the conversion of arachidonic acid to prostaglandins. Biochim Biophys <lb/>Acta (BBA) -Mol Cell Biol Lipids (1999) 1441(2-3):278-87. doi: 10.1016/ <lb/>s1388-1981(99)00147-x <lb/>13. Vecchio AJ, Orlando BJ, Nandagiri R, Malkowski MG. Investigating <lb/>substrate promiscuity in cyclooxygenase-2: the role of Arg-120 and <lb/>residues lining the hydrophobic groove. J Biol Chem (2012) 287 <lb/>(29):24619-30. doi: 10.1074/jbc.M112.372243 <lb/>14. Kuhn H, Banthiya S, van Leyen K. Mammalian lipoxygenases and their <lb/>biological relevance. Biochim Biophys Acta (2015) 1851(4):308-30. <lb/>doi: 10.1016/j.bbalip.2014.10.002 <lb/>15. Spector AA, Kim HY. Cytochrome P450 epoxygenase pathway of <lb/>polyunsaturated fatty acid metabolism. Biochim Biophys Acta (2015) 1851 <lb/>(4):356-65. doi: 10.1016/j.bbalip.2014.07.020 <lb/>16. Mikulska-Ruminska K, Shrivastava I, Krieger J, Zhang S, Li H, Bayir H, et al. <lb/>Characterization of Differential Dynamics, Specificity, and Allostery of <lb/>Lipoxygenase Family Members. J Chem Inf Model (2019) 59(5):2496-508. <lb/>doi: 10.1021/acs.jcim.9b00006 <lb/>17. Pandak WM, Kakiyama G. The acidic pathway of bile acid synthesis: Not <lb/>just an alternative pathway(). Liver Res (2019) 3(2):88-98. doi: 10.1016/ <lb/>j.livres.2019.05.001 <lb/>18. Kutzner L, Goloshchapova K, Heydeck D, Stehling S, Kuhn H, Schebb NH. <lb/>Mammalian ALOX15 orthologs exhsibit pronounced dual positional <lb/>specificity with docosahexaenoic acid. Biochim Biophys Acta Mol Cell Biol <lb/>Lipids (2017) 1862(7):666-75. doi: 10.1016/j.bbalip.2017.04.001 <lb/>19. Simard-Bisson C, Parent LA, Moulin VJ, Fruteau de Laclos B. <lb/>Characterization of Epidermal Lipoxygenase Expression in Normal <lb/>Human Skin and Tissue-Engineered Skin Substitutes. J Histochem <lb/>Cytochem (2018) 66(11):813-24. doi: 10.1369/0022155418788117 <lb/>20. Funk CD, Funk LB, FitzGerald GA, Samuelsson B. Characterization of <lb/>human 12-lipoxygenase genes. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A (1992) 89(9):3962-<lb/>6. doi: 10.1073/pnas.89.9.3962 <lb/>21. Chen XS, Brash AR, Funk CD. Purification and characterization of <lb/>recombinant histidine-tagged human platelet 12-lipoxygenase expressed in <lb/>a baculovirus/insect cell system. Eur J Biochem (1993) 214(3):845-52. <lb/>doi: 10.1111/j.1432-1033.1993.tb17988.x <lb/>22. Weisinger G, Grafi-Cohen M, Hirsh M, Knoll E, Sharon O, Many A, et al. <lb/>12S-Lipoxygenase is necessary for human vascular smooth muscle cell <lb/>survival. Exp Cell Res (2013) 319(10):1586-93. doi: 10.1016/ <lb/>j.yexcr.2013.04.001 <lb/>23. Boeglin WE, Kim RB, Brash AR. A 12R-lipoxygenase in human skin: <lb/>mechanistic evidence, molecular cloning, and expression. Proc Natl Acad <lb/>Sci U.S.A. (1998) 95(12):6744-9. doi: 10.1073/pnas.95.12.6744 <lb/>24. Sun D, McDonnell M, Chen XS, Lakkis MM, Li H, Isaacs SN, et al. Human <lb/>12(R)-lipoxygenase and the mouse ortholog. Molecular cloning, expression, <lb/>and gene chromosomal assignment. J Biol Chem (1998) 273(50):33540-7. <lb/>doi: 10.1074/jbc.273.50.33540 <lb/>25. Zheng Y, Yin H, Boeglin WE, Elias PM, Crumrine D, Beier DR, et al. <lb/>Lipoxygenases mediate the effect of essential fatty acid in skin barrier <lb/>formation: a proposed role in releasing omega-hydroxyceramide for <lb/>construction of the corneocyte lipid envelope. J Biol Chem (2011) 286 <lb/>(27):24046-56. doi: 10.1074/jbc.M111.251496 <lb/>26. Schneider C, Keeney DS, Boeglin WE, Brash AR. Detection and cellular <lb/>localization of 12R-lipoxygenase in human tonsils. Arch Biochem Biophys <lb/>(2001) 386(2):268-74. doi: 10.1006/abbi.2000.2217 <lb/>27. Garcia-Verdugo I, BenMohamed F, Tattermusch S, Leduc D, Charpigny G, <lb/>Chignard M, et al. A role for 12R-lipoxygenase in MUC5AC expression by <lb/>respiratory epithelial cells. Eur Respir J (2012) 40(3):714-23. doi: 10.1183/ <lb/>09031936.00023111 <lb/>28. Wuest SJ, Crucet M, Gemperle C, Loretz C, Hersberger M. Expression and <lb/>regulation of 12/15-lipoxygenases in human primary macrophages. <lb/>Atherosclerosis (2012) 225(1):121-7. doi: 10.1016/j.atherosclerosis.2012.07.022 <lb/>29. Turk J, Maas RL, Brash AR, Roberts LJ,2, Oates JA. Arachidonic acid 15-<lb/>lipoxygenase products from human eosinophils. J Biol Chem (1982) 257 <lb/>(12):7068-76. <lb/>30. Sigal E, Grunberger D, Highland E, Gross C, Dixon RA, Craik CS. <lb/>Expression of cloned human reticulocyte 15-lipoxygenase and <lb/>immunological evidence that 15-lipoxygenases of different cell types are <lb/>related. J Biol Chem (1990) 265(9):5113-20. <lb/>31. Conrad DJ, Kuhn H, Mulkins M, Highland E, Sigal E. Specific inflammatory <lb/>cytokines regulate the expression of human monocyte 15-lipoxygenase. Proc <lb/>Natl Acad Sci U S A (1992) 89(1):217-21. doi: 10.1073/pnas.89.1.217 <lb/>32. Spanbroek R, Hildner M, Kohler A, Muller A, Zintl F, Kuhn H, et al. IL-4 <lb/>determines eicosanoid formation in dendritic cells by down-regulation of 5-<lb/>lipoxygenase and up-regulation of 15-lipoxygenase 1 expression. Proc Natl <lb/>Acad Sci U.S.A. (2001) 98(9):5152-7. doi: 10.1073/pnas.091076998 <lb/>33. Brash AR, Boeglin WE, Chang MS. Discovery of a second 15S-lipoxygenase <lb/>in humans. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A (1997) 94(12):6148-52. doi: 10.1073/ <lb/>pnas.94.12.6148 <lb/>34. Matsumoto T, Funk CD, Radmark O, Hoog JO, Jornvall H, Samuelsson B. <lb/>Molecular cloning and amino acid sequence of human 5-lipoxygenase. Proc <lb/>Natl Acad Sci U S A (1988) 85(1):26-30. doi: 10.1073/pnas.85.1.26 <lb/>35. Colamorea T, Di Paola R, Macchia F, Guerrese MC, Tursi A, Butterfield JH, <lb/>et al. 5-Lipoxygenase upregulation by dexamethasone in human mast cells. <lb/>Biochem Biophys Res Commun (1999) 265(3):617-24. doi: 10.1006/ <lb/>bbrc.1999.1732 <lb/>36. Spanbroek R, Hildner M, Steinhilber D, Fusenig N, Yoneda K, Radmark O, <lb/>et al. 5-lipoxygenase expression in dendritic cells generated from CD34(+) <lb/>hematopoietic progenitors and in lymphoid organs. Blood (2000) 96 <lb/>(12):3857-65. doi: 10.1182/blood.V96.12.3857 <lb/>37. Krieg P, Marks F, Furstenberger G. A gene cluster encoding human <lb/>epidermis-type lipoxygenases at chromosome 17p13.1: cloning, physical <lb/>mapping, and expression. Genomics (2001) 73(3):323-30. doi: 10.1006/ <lb/>geno.2001.6519 <lb/>38. Zheng Y, Brash AR. Dioxygenase activity of epidermal lipoxygenase-3 <lb/>unveiled: typical and atypical features of its catalytic activity with natural <lb/>and synthetic polyunsaturated fatty acids. J Biol Chem (2010) 285 <lb/>(51):39866-75. doi: 10.1074/jbc.M110.155374 <lb/>39. UniProt C. UniProt: a worldwide hub of protein knowledge. Nucleic Acids <lb/>Res (2019) 47(D1):D506-D15. doi: 10.1093/nar/gky1049 <lb/>40. Choi J, Chon JK, Kim S, Shin W. Conformational flexibility in mammalian <lb/>15S-lipoxygenase: Reinterpretation of the crystallographic data. Proteins <lb/>(2008) 70(3):1023-32. doi: 10.1002/prot.21590 <lb/>41. Gilbert NC, Bartlett SG, Waight MT, Neau DB, Boeglin WE, Brash AR, et al. <lb/>The structure of human 5-lipoxygenase. Science (2011) 331(6014):217-9. <lb/>doi: 10.1126/science.1197203 <lb/>42. Kobe MJ, Neau DB, Mitchell CE, Bartlett SG, Newcomer ME. The structure <lb/>of human 15-lipoxygenase-2 with a substrate mimic. J Biol Chem (2014) 289 <lb/>(12):8562-9. doi: 10.1074/jbc.M113.543777 <lb/>43. Walther M, Anton M, Wiedmann M, Fletterick R, Kuhn H. The N-terminal <lb/>domain of the reticulocyte-type 15-lipoxygenase is not essential for <lb/>enzymatic activity but contains determinants for membrane binding. <lb/>J Biol Chem (2002) 277(30):27360-6. doi: 10.1074/jbc.M203234200 <lb/>44. Walther M, Hofheinz K, Vogel R, Roffeis J, Kuhn H. The N-terminal beta-<lb/>barrel domain of mammalian lipoxygenases including mouse 5-lipoxygenase <lb/>is not essential for catalytic activity and membrane binding but exhibits <lb/>regulatory functions. Arch Biochem Biophys (2011) 516(1):1-9. doi: 10.1016/ <lb/>j.abb.2011.09.004 <lb/>45. Hammarberg T, Provost P, Persson B, Radmark O. The N-terminal domain <lb/>of 5-lipoxygenase binds calcium and mediates calcium stimulation of <lb/>enzyme activity. J Biol Chem (2000) 275(49):38787-93. doi: 10.1074/ <lb/>jbc.M006136200 <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Hajeyah et al. <lb/>Biosynthesis of Oxidized Lipids <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Endocrinology | www.frontiersin.org <lb/>November 2020 | Volume 11 | Article 591819 <lb/></note>

			<page>23 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>46. Chen XS, Funk CD. The N-terminal &quot;beta-barrel&quot; domain of 5-lipoxygenase <lb/>is essential for nuclear membrane translocation. J Biol Chem (2001) 276 <lb/>(1):811-8. doi: 10.1074/jbc.M008203200 <lb/>47. Brinckmann R, Schnurr K, Heydeck D, Rosenbach T, Kolde G, K hn H. <lb/>Membrane Translocation of 15-Lipoxygenase in Hematopoietic Cells Is <lb/>Calcium-Dependent and Activates the Oxygenase Activity of the Enzyme. <lb/>Blood (1998) 91(1):64-74. doi: 10.1182/blood.V91.1.64 <lb/>48. Bender G, Schexnaydre EE, Murphy RC, Uhlson C, Newcomer ME. <lb/>Membrane-dependent Activities of Human 15-LOX-2 and Its Murine <lb/>Counterpart: IMPLICATIONS FOR MURINE MODELS OF <lb/>ATHEROSCLEROSIS. J Biol Chem (2016) 291(37):19413-24. <lb/>doi: 10.1074/jbc.M116.741454 <lb/>49. Basavarajappa D, Wan M, Lukic A, Steinhilber D, Samuelsson B, Radmark <lb/>O. Roles of coactosin-like protein (CLP) and 5-lipoxygenase-activating <lb/>protein (FLAP) in cellular leukotriene biosynthesis. Proc Natl Acad Sci U <lb/>S A (2014) 111(31):11371-6. doi: 10.1073/pnas.1410983111 <lb/>50. Hafner AK, Gerstmeier J, Hornig M, George S, Ball AK, Schroder M, et al. <lb/>Characterization of the interaction of human 5-lipoxygenase with its <lb/>activating protein FLAP. Biochim Biophys Acta (2015) 1851(11):1465-72. <lb/>doi: 10.1016/j.bbalip.2015.08.010 <lb/>51. Luo M, Jones SM, Peters-Golden M, Brock TG. Nuclear localization of 5-<lb/>lipoxygenase as a determinant of leukotriene B4 synthetic capacity. Proc Natl <lb/>Acad Sci U S A (2003) 100(21):12165-70. doi: 10.1073/pnas.2133253100 <lb/>52. Sun QY, Zhou HH, Mao XY. Emerging Roles of 5-Lipoxygenase <lb/>Phosphorylation in Inflammation and Cell Death. Oxid Med Cell Longev <lb/>(2019) 2019:2749173. doi: 10.1155/2019/2749173 <lb/>53. Smyrniotis CJ, Barbour SR, Xia Z, Hixon MS, Holman TR. ATP allosterically <lb/>activates the human 5-lipoxygenase molecular mechanism of arachidonic <lb/>acid and 5(S)-hydroperoxy-6(E),8(Z),11(Z),14(Z)-eicosatetraenoic acid. <lb/>Biochemistry (2014) 53(27):4407-19. doi: 10.1021/bi401621d <lb/>54. Wenzel SE, Tyurina YY, Zhao J, St Croix CM, Dar HH, Mao G, et al. PEBP1 <lb/>Wardens Ferroptosis by Enabling Lipoxygenase Generation of Lipid Death <lb/>Signals. Cell (2017) 171(3):628-41 e26. doi: 10.1016/j.cell.2017.09.044 <lb/>55. Snodgrass RG, Brune B. Regulation and Functions of 15-Lipoxygenases in <lb/>Human Macrophages. Front Pharmacol (2019) 10:719:719. doi: 10.3389/ <lb/>fphar.2019.00719 <lb/>56. Droege KD, Keithly ME, Sanders CR, Armstrong RN, Thompson MK. Structural <lb/>Dynamics of 15-Lipoxygenase-2 via Hydrogen-Deuterium Exchange. <lb/>Biochemistry (2017) 56(38):5065-74. doi: 10.1021/acs.biochem.7b00559 <lb/>57. Hagmann W, Kagawa D, Renaud C, Honn KV. Activity and protein <lb/>distribution of 12-lipoxygenase in HEL cells: Induction of membrane-<lb/>association by phorbol ester TPA, modulation of activity by glutathione <lb/>and 13-HPODE, and Ca2+-dependent translocation to membranes. <lb/>Prostaglandins (1993) 46(6):471-7. doi: 10.1016/0090-6980(93)90066-g <lb/>58. Siebert M, Krieg P, Lehmann WD, Marks F, Furstenberger G. Enzymic <lb/>characterization of epidermis-derived 12-lipoxygenase isoenzymes. Biochem <lb/>J (2001) 355(Pt 1):97-104. doi: 10.1042/0264-6021:3550097 <lb/>59. Aleem AM, Jankun J, Dignam JD, Walther M, Kuhn H, Svergun DI, et al. <lb/>Human platelet 12-lipoxygenase, new findings about its activity, membrane <lb/>binding and low-resolution structure. J Mol Biol (2008) 376(1):193-209. <lb/>doi: 10.1016/j.jmb.2007.11.086 <lb/>60. Hafner AK, Cernescu M, Hofmann B, Ermisch M, Hornig M, Metzner J, <lb/>et al. Dimerization of human 5-lipoxygenase. Biol Chem (2011) 392 <lb/>(12):1097-111. doi: 10.1515/BC.2011.200 <lb/>61. Ivanov I, Shang W, Toledo L, Masgrau L, Svergun DI, Stehling S, et al. <lb/>Ligand-induced formation of transient dimers of mammalian 12/15-<lb/>lipoxygenase: a key to allosteric behavior of this class of enzymes? Proteins <lb/>(2012) 80(3):703-12. doi: 10.1002/prot.23227 <lb/>62. Lehnert N, Solomon EI. Density-functional investigation on the mechanism <lb/>of H-atom abstraction by lipoxygenase. J Biol Inorg Chem (2003) 8(3):294-<lb/>305. doi: 10.1007/s00775-002-0415-6 <lb/>63. Neau DB, Gilbert NC, Bartlett SG, Boeglin W, Brash AR, Newcomer ME. <lb/>The 1.85 A structure of an 8R-lipoxygenase suggests a general model for <lb/>lipoxygenase product specificity. Biochemistry (2009) 48(33):7906-15. <lb/>doi: 10.1021/bi900084m <lb/>64. Collazo L, Klinman JP. Control of the Position of Oxygen Delivery in <lb/>Soybean Lipoxygenase-1 by Amino Acid Side Chains within a Gas Migration <lb/>Channel. J Biol Chem (2016) 291(17):9052-9. doi: 10.1074/jbc.M115.709154 <lb/>65. Coffa G, Brash AR, Samuelsson B. A single active site residue directs <lb/>oxygenation stereospecificity in lipoxygenases: Stereocontrol is linked to <lb/>the position of oxygenation. Proc Natl Acad Sci U States America (2004) 101 <lb/>(44):15579-84. doi: 10.1073/pnas.0406727101 <lb/>66. Schwarz K, Walther M, Anton M, Gerth C, Feussner I, Kuhn H. Structural <lb/>basis for lipoxygenase specificity. Conversion of the human leukocyte 5-<lb/>lipoxygenase to a 15-lipoxygenating enzyme species by site-directed <lb/>mutagenesis. J Biol Chem (2001) 276(1):773-9. doi: 10.1074/ <lb/>jbc.M005114200 <lb/>67. Walther M, Ivanov I, Myagkova G, Kuhn H. Alterations of lipoxygenase <lb/>specificity by targeted substrate modification and site-directed mutagenesis. <lb/>Chem Biol (2001) 8(8):779-90. doi: 10.1016/s1074-5521(01)00050-3 <lb/>68. Newcomer ME, Brash AR. The structural basis for specificity in lipoxygenase <lb/>catalysis. Protein Sci (2015) 24(3):298-309. doi: 10.1002/pro.2626 <lb/>69. Ivanov I, Kuhn H, Heydeck D. Structural and functional biology of <lb/>arachidonic acid 15-lipoxygenase-1 (ALOX15). Gene (2015) 573(1):1-32. <lb/>doi: 10.1016/j.gene.2015.07.073 <lb/>70. Yu Z, Schneider C, Boeglin WE, Marnett LJ, Brash AR. The lipoxygenase <lb/>gene ALOXE3 implicated in skin differentiation encodes a hydroperoxide <lb/>isomerase. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A (2003) 100(16):9162-7. doi: 10.1073/ <lb/>pnas.1633612100 <lb/>71. Rouzer CA, Matsumoto T, Samuelsson B. Single protein from human <lb/>leukocytes possesses 5-lipoxygenase and leukotriene A4 synthase activities. <lb/>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A (1986) 83(4):857-61. doi: 10.1073/pnas.83.4.857 <lb/>72. Shimizu T, Izumi T, Seyama Y, Tadokoro K, Radmark O, Samuelsson B. <lb/>Characterization of leukotriene A4 synthase from murine mast cells: <lb/>evidence for its identity to arachidonate 5-lipoxygenase. Proc Natl Acad <lb/>Sci U S A (1986) 83(12):4175-9. doi: 10.1073/pnas.83.12.4175 <lb/>73. Ueda N, Yamamoto S, Oates JA, Brash AR. Stereoselective hydrogen <lb/>abstraction in leukotriene A4 synthesis by purified 5-lipoxygenase of <lb/>porcine leukocytes. Prostaglandins (1986) 32(1):43-8. doi: 10.1016/0090-<lb/>6980(86)90141-3 <lb/>74. MacMillan DK, Hill E, Sala A, Sigal E, Shuman T, Henson PM, et al. <lb/>Eosinophil 15-lipoxygenase is a leukotriene A4 synthase. J Biol Chem (1994) <lb/>269(43):26663-8. <lb/>75. Hong S, Gronert K, Devchand PR, Moussignac RL, Serhan CN. Novel <lb/>docosatrienes and 17S-resolvins generated from docosahexaenoic acid in <lb/>murine brain, human blood, and glial cells. Autacoids in anti-inflammation. <lb/>J Biol Chem (2003) 278(17):14677-87. doi: 10.1074/jbc.M300218200 <lb/>76. Kuhn H, Wiesner R, Stender H, Schewe T, Lankin VZ, Nekrasov A, et al. <lb/>Requirement of monohydroperoxy fatty acids for the oxygenation of 15LS-<lb/>HETE by reticulocyte lipoxygenase. FEBS Lett (1986) 203(2):247-52. <lb/>doi: 10.1016/0014-5793(86)80752-9 <lb/>77. Lepley RA, Fitzpatrick FA. Irreversible inactivation of 5-lipoxygenase by <lb/>leukotriene A4. Characterization of product inactivation with purified <lb/>enzyme and intact leukocytes. J Biol Chem (1994) 269(4):2627-31. <lb/>78. Wiesner R, Suzuki H, Walther M, Yamamoto S, Kuhn H. Suicidal <lb/>inactivation of the rabbit 15-lipoxygenase by 15S-HpETE is paralleled by <lb/>covalent modification of active site peptides. Free Radical Biol Med (2003) 34 <lb/>(3):304-15. doi: 10.1016/s0891-5849(02)01244-3 <lb/>79. Kohli P, Levy BD. Resolvins and protectins: mediating solutions to <lb/>inflammation. Br J Pharmacol (2009) 158(4):960-71. doi: 10.1111/j.1476-<lb/>5381.2009.00290.x <lb/>80. Arita M, Yoshida M, Hong S, Tjonahen E, Glickman JN, Petasis NA, et al. <lb/>Resolvin E1, an endogenous lipid mediator derived from omega-3 <lb/>eicosapentaenoic acid, protects against 2,4,6-trinitrobenzene sulfonic acid-<lb/>induced colitis. Proc Natl Acad Sci U.S.A. (2005) 102(21):7671-6. <lb/>doi: 10.1073/pnas.0409271102 <lb/>81. Forsell PK, Brunnstrom A, Johannesson M, Claesson HE. Metabolism of <lb/>anandamide into eoxamides by 15-lipoxygenase-1 and glutathione <lb/>transferases. Lipids (2012) 47(8):781-91. doi: 10.1007/s11745-012-3684-z <lb/>82. Kim HY, Spector AA. Synaptamide, endocannabinoid-like derivative of <lb/>docosahexaenoic acid with cannabinoid-independent function. <lb/>Prostaglandins Leukot Essent Fatty Acids (2013) 88(1):121-5. doi: 10.1016/ <lb/>j.plefa.2012.08.002 <lb/>83. Schewe T, Halangk W, Hiebsch C, Rapoport SM. A lipoxygenase in rabbit <lb/>reticulocytes which attacks phospholipids and intact mitochondria. FEBS <lb/>Lett (1975) 60(1):149-52. doi: 10.1016/0014-5793(75)80439-x <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Hajeyah et al. <lb/>Biosynthesis of Oxidized Lipids <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Endocrinology | www.frontiersin.org <lb/>November 2020 | Volume 11 | Article 591819 <lb/></note>

			<page>24 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>84. Belkner J, Wiesner R, Rathman J, Barnett J, Sigal E, Kuhn H. Oxygenation of <lb/>lipoproteins by mammalian lipoxygenases. Eur J Biochem (1993) 213 <lb/>(1):251-61. doi: 10.1111/j.1432-1033.1993.tb17755.x <lb/>85. Kuhn H, Barnett J, Grunberger D, Baecker P, Chow J, Nguyen B, et al. <lb/>Overexpression, purification and characterization of human recombinant <lb/>15-lipoxygenase. Biochim Biophys Acta (1993) 1169(1):80-9. doi: 10.1016/ <lb/>0005-2760(93)90085-n <lb/>86. Huang LS, Kang JS, Kim MR, Sok DE. Oxygenation of arachidonoyl <lb/>lysophospholipids by lipoxygenases from soybean, porcine leukocyte, or <lb/>rabbit reticulocyte. J Agric Food Chem (2008) 56(4):1224-32. doi: 10.1021/ <lb/>jf073016i <lb/>87. Hutchins PM, Murphy RC. Cholesteryl ester acyl oxidation and remodeling <lb/>in murine macrophages: formation of oxidized phosphatidylcholine. J Lipid <lb/>Res (2012) 53(8):1588-97. doi: 10.1194/jlr.M026799 <lb/>88. Liu X, Moon SH, Jenkins CM, Sims HF, Gross RW. Cyclooxygenase-2 <lb/>Mediated Oxidation of 2-Arachidonoyl-Lysophospholipids Identifies <lb/>Unknown Lipid Signaling Pathways. Cell Chem Biol (2016) 23(10):1217-<lb/>27. doi: 10.1016/j.chembiol.2016.08.009 <lb/>89. Ikei KN, Yeung J, Apopa PL, Ceja J, Vesci J, Holman TR, et al. Investigations <lb/>of human platelet-type 12-lipoxygenase: role of lipoxygenase products in <lb/>platelet activation. J Lipid Res (2012) 53(12):2546-59. doi: 10.1194/ <lb/>jlr.M026385 <lb/>90. Hada T, Ueda N, Takahashi Y, Yamamoto S. Catalytic properties of human <lb/>platelet 12-lipoxygenase as compared with the enzymes of other origins. <lb/>Biochim Biophys Acta (BBA) -Lipids Lipid Metab (1991) 1083(1):89-93. <lb/>doi: 10.1016/0005-2760(91)90128-5 <lb/>91. Romano M, Chen XS, Takahashi Y, Yamamoto S, Funk CD, Serhan CN. <lb/>Lipoxin synthase activity of human platelet 12-lipoxygenase. Biochem J <lb/>(1993) 296( Pt 1):127-33. doi: 10.1042/bj2960127 <lb/>92. Anton R, Vila L. Stereoselective biosynthesis of hepoxilin B3 in human <lb/>epidermis. J Invest Dermatol (2000) 114(3):554-9. doi: 10.1046/j.1523-<lb/>1747.2000.00903.x <lb/>93. Deng B, Wang CW, Arnardottir HH, Li Y, Cheng CY, Dalli J, et al. Maresin <lb/>biosynthesis and identification of maresin 2, a new anti-inflammatory and <lb/>pro-resolving mediator from human macrophages. PloS One (2014) 9(7): <lb/>e102362. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0102362 <lb/>94. Liu X, Sims HF, Jenkins CM, Guan S, Dilthey BG, Gross RW. 12-LOX <lb/>catalyzes the oxidation of 2-arachidonoyl-lysolipids in platelets generating <lb/>eicosanoid-lysolipids that are attenuated by iPLA2gamma knockout. J Biol <lb/>Chem (2020) 295(16):5307-20. doi: 10.1074/jbc.RA119.012296 <lb/>95. Yu Z, Schneider C, Boeglin WE, Brash AR. Human and mouse eLOX3 have <lb/>distinct substrate specificities: implications for their linkage with <lb/>lipoxygenases in skin. Arch Biochem Biophys (2006) 455(2):188-96. <lb/>doi: 10.1016/j.abb.2006.09.002 <lb/>96. Snodgrass RG, Zezina E, Namgaladze D, Gupta S, Angioni C, Geisslinger G, <lb/>et al. A Novel Function for 15-Lipoxygenases in Cholesterol Homeostasis <lb/>and CCL17 Production in Human Macrophages. Front Immunol (2018) <lb/>9:1906:1906. doi: 10.3389/fimmu.2018.01906 <lb/>97. Therland KL, Stubbe J, Thiesson HC, Ottosen PD, Walter S, Sorensen GL, <lb/>et al. Cycloxygenase-2 is expressed in vasculature of normal and ischemic <lb/>adult human kidney and is colocalized with vascular prostaglandin E2 EP4 <lb/>receptors. J Am Soc Nephrol (2004) 15(5):1189-98. doi: 10.1097/ <lb/>01.asn.0000124673.79934.24 <lb/>98. Kirkby NS, Zaiss AK, Urquhart P, Jiao J, Austin PJ, Al-Yamani M, et al. LC-<lb/>MS/MS confirms that COX-1 drives vascular prostacyclin whilst gene <lb/>expression pattern reveals non-vascular sites of COX-2 expression. PloS <lb/>One (2013) 8(7):e69524. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0069524 <lb/>99. Kirkby NS, Chan MV, Zaiss AK, Garcia-Vaz E, Jiao J, Berglund LM, et al. <lb/>Systematic study of constitutive cyclooxygenase-2 expression: Role of NF-<lb/>kappaB and NFAT transcriptional pathways. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A <lb/>(2016) 113(2):434-9. doi: 10.1073/pnas.1517642113 <lb/>100. Grosser T, Fries S, FitzGerald GA. Biological basis for the cardiovascular <lb/>consequences of COX-2 inhibition: therapeutic challenges and opportunities. <lb/>J Clin Investigation (2006) 116(1):4-15. doi: 10.1172/JCI27291 <lb/>101. Tang SY, Monslow J, Todd L, Lawson J, PureE, FitzGerald GA. <lb/>Cyclooxygenase-2 in endothelial and vascular smooth muscle cells <lb/>restrains atherogenesis in hyperlipidemic mice. Circulation (2014) 129 <lb/>(17):1761-9. doi: 10.1161/circulationaha.113.007913 <lb/>102. Hla T, Neilson K. Human cyclooxygenase-2 cDNA. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A <lb/>(1992) 89(16):7384-8. doi: 10.1073/pnas.89.16.7384 <lb/>103. O&apos;Neill GP, Ford-Hutchinson AW. Expression of mRNA for <lb/>cyclooxygenase-1 and cyclooxygenase-2 in human tissues. FEBS Lett <lb/>(1993) 330(2):156-60. doi: 10.1016/0014-5793(93)80263-t <lb/>104. Pablos JL, Santiago B, Carreira PE, Galindo M, Gomez-Reino JJ. <lb/>Cyclooxygenase-1 and -2 are expressed by human T cells. Clin Exp <lb/>Immunol (1999) 115(1):86-90. doi: 10.1046/j.1365-2249.1999.00780.x <lb/>105. Zidar N, Odar K, Glavac D, Jerse M, Zupanc T, Stajer D. Cyclooxygenase in <lb/>normal human tissues-is COX-1 really a constitutive isoform, and COX-2 an <lb/>inducible isoform? J Cell Mol Med (2009) 13(9B):3753-63. doi: 10.1111/ <lb/>j.1582-4934.2008.00430.x <lb/>106. Ryan EP, Pollack SJ, Murant TI, Bernstein SH, Felgar RE, Phipps RP. <lb/>Activated Human B Lymphocytes Express Cyclooxygenase-2 and <lb/>Cyclooxygenase Inhibitors Attenuate Ab Production. J Immunol (2005) <lb/>174(8):5134.2-. doi: 10.4049/jimmunol.174.8.5134-a <lb/>107. Picot D, Loll PJ, Garavito RM. The X-ray crystal structure of the membrane <lb/>protein prostaglandin H2 synthase-1. Nature (1994) 367(6460):243-9. <lb/>doi: 10.1038/367243a0 <lb/>108. Rimon G, Sidhu RS, Lauver DA, Lee JY, Sharma NP, Yuan C, et al. Coxibs <lb/>interfere with the action of aspirin by binding tightly to one monomer of <lb/>cyclooxygenase-1. Proc Natl Acad Sci U.S.A. (2010) 107(1):28-33. <lb/>doi: 10.1073/pnas.0909765106 <lb/>109. Sidhu RS, Lee JY, Yuan C, Smith WL. Comparison of cyclooxygenase-1 <lb/>crystal structures: cross-talk between monomers comprising cyclooxygenase-<lb/>1 homodimers. Biochemistry (2010) 49(33):7069-79. doi: 10.1021/bi1003298 <lb/>110. Kurumbail RG, Stevens AM, Gierse JK, McDonald JJ, Stegeman RA, Pak JY, et al. <lb/>Structural basis for selective inhibition of cyclooxygenase-2 by anti-<lb/>inflammatory agents. Nature (1996) 384(6610):644-8. doi: 10.1038/384644a0 <lb/>111. Rowlinson SW, Kiefer JR, Prusakiewicz JJ, Pawlitz JL, Kozak KR, Kalgutkar <lb/>AS, et al. A novel mechanism of cyclooxygenase-2 inhibition involving <lb/>interactions with Ser-530 and Tyr-385. J Biol Chem (2003) 278(46):45763-9. <lb/>doi: 10.1074/jbc.M305481200 <lb/>112. Vecchio AJ, Malkowski MG. The structural basis of endocannabinoid <lb/>oxygenation by cyclooxygenase-2. J Biol Chem (2011) 286(23):20736-45. <lb/>doi: 10.1074/jbc.M111.230367 <lb/>113. Xu S, Hermanson DJ, Banerjee S, Ghebreselasie K, Clayton GM, Garavito <lb/>RM, et al. Oxicams bind in a novel mode to the cyclooxygenase active site via <lb/>a two-water-mediated H-bonding Network. J Biol Chem (2014) 289 <lb/>(10):6799-808. doi: 10.1074/jbc.M113.517987 <lb/>114. Lucido MJ, Orlando BJ, Vecchio AJ, Malkowski MG. Crystal Structure of <lb/>Aspirin-Acetylated Human Cyclooxygenase-2: Insight into the Formation of <lb/>Products with Reversed Stereochemistry. Biochemistry (2016) 55(8):1226-38. <lb/>doi: 10.1021/acs.biochem.5b01378 <lb/>115. Orlando BJ, Malkowski MG. Substrate-selective Inhibition of <lb/>Cyclooxygeanse-2 by Fenamic Acid Derivatives Is Dependent on Peroxide <lb/>Tone. J Biol Chem (2016) 291(29):15069-81. doi: 10.1074/jbc.M116.725713 <lb/>116. Xiao G, Chen W, Kulmacz RJ. Comparison of structural stabilities of <lb/>prostaglandin H synthase-1 and -2. J Biol Chem (1998) 273(12):6801-11. <lb/>doi: 10.1074/jbc.273.12.6801 <lb/>117. Michael Garavito R, Malkowski MG, DeWitt DL. The structures of <lb/>prostaglandin endoperoxide H synthases-1 and -2. Prostaglandins Other <lb/>Lipid Mediators (2002) 68-69:129-52. doi: 10.1016/s0090-6980(02)00026-6 <lb/>118. Spencer AG, Woods JW, Arakawa T, Singer II, Smith WL. Subcellular <lb/>localization of prostaglandin endoperoxide H synthases-1 and -2 by <lb/>immunoelectron microscopy. J Biol Chem (1998) 273(16):9886-93. <lb/>doi: 10.1074/jbc.273.16.9886 <lb/>119. Yuan C, Smith WL. A cyclooxygenase-2-dependent prostaglandin E2 <lb/>biosynthetic system in the Golgi apparatus. J Biol Chem (2015) 290 <lb/>(9):5606-20. doi: 10.1074/jbc.M114.632463 <lb/>120. Rouzer CA, Marnett LJ. Cyclooxygenases: structural and functional insights. <lb/>J Lipid Res (2009) 50 Suppl(Suppl):S29-34. doi: 10.1194/jlr.R800042-JLR200 <lb/>121. Otto JC, DeWitt DL, Smith WL. N-glycosylation of prostaglandin <lb/>endoperoxide synthases-1 and -2 and their orientations in the <lb/>endoplasmic reticulum. J Biol Chem (1993) 268(24):18234-42. <lb/>122. Sevigny MB, Li CF, Alas M, Hughes-Fulford M. Glycosylation regulates <lb/>turnover of cyclooxygenase-2. FEBS Lett (2006) 580(28-29):6533-6. <lb/>doi: 10.1016/j.febslet.2006.10.073 <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Hajeyah et al. <lb/>Biosynthesis of Oxidized Lipids <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Endocrinology | www.frontiersin.org <lb/>November 2020 | Volume 11 | Article 591819 <lb/></note>

			<page>25 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>123. Kim SF, Huri DA, Snyder SH. Inducible nitric oxide synthase binds, S-<lb/>nitrosylates, and activates cyclooxygenase-2. Science (2005) 310(5756):1966-<lb/>70. doi: 10.1126/science.1119407 <lb/>124. Qiao J, Ma L, Roth J, Li Y, Liu Y. Kinetic basis for the activation of human <lb/>cyclooxygenase-2 rather than cyclooxygenase-1 by nitric oxide. Org Biomol <lb/>Chem (2018) 16(5):765-70. doi: 10.1039/c7ob02992f <lb/>125. Yuan C, Rieke CJ, Rimon G, Wingerd BA, Smith WL. Partnering between <lb/>monomers of cyclooxygenase-2 homodimers. Proc Natl Acad Sci U.S.A. <lb/>(2006) 103(16):6142-7. doi: 10.1073/pnas.0601805103 <lb/>126. Dong L, Vecchio AJ, Sharma NP, Jurban BJ, Malkowski MG, Smith WL. <lb/>Human cyclooxygenase-2 is a sequence homodimer that functions as a <lb/>conformational heterodimer. J Biol Chem (2011) 286(21):19035-46. <lb/>doi: 10.1074/jbc.M111.231969 <lb/>127. Zou H, Yuan C, Dong L, Sidhu RS, Hong YH, Kuklev DV, et al. Human <lb/>cyclooxygenase-1 activity and its responses to COX inhibitors are <lb/>allosterically regulated by nonsubstrate fatty acids. J Lipid Res (2012) 53 <lb/>(7):1336-47. doi: 10.1194/jlr.M026856 <lb/>128. Smith WL, Malkowski MG. Interactions of fatty acids, nonsteroidal anti-<lb/>inflammatory drugs, and coxibs with the catalytic and allosteric subunits of <lb/>cyclooxygenases-1 and -2. J Biol Chem (2019) 294(5):1697-705. doi: 10.1074/ <lb/>jbc.TM118.006295 <lb/>129. Marnett LJ. Cyclooxygenase mechanisms. Curr Opin Chem Biol (2000) 4 <lb/>(5):545-52. doi: 10.1016/s1367-5931(00)00130-7 <lb/>130. Silva PJ, Fernandes PA, Ramos MJ. A theoretical study of radical-only and <lb/>combined radical/carbocationic mechanisms of arachidonic acid <lb/>cyclooxygenation by prostaglandin H synthase. Theor Chem Acc: Theory <lb/>Computation Model (Theoretica Chim Acta) (2003) 110(5):345-51. <lb/>doi: 10.1007/s00214-003-0476-9 <lb/>131. Cebria-Prats A, Gonzaez-Lafont , Lluch JM. Unraveling the Molecular <lb/>Details of the Complete Mechanism That Governs the Synthesis of <lb/>Prostaglandin G2 Catalyzed by Cyclooxygenase-2. ACS Omega (2019) 4 <lb/>(1):2063-74. doi: 10.1021/acsomega.8b03575 <lb/>132. O&apos;Connor DE, Mihelich ED, Coleman MC. Stereochemical course of the <lb/>autooxidative cyclization of lipid hydroperoxides to prostaglandin-like <lb/>bicyclic endoperoxides. J Am Chem Soc (1984) 106(12):3577-84. <lb/>doi: 10.1021/ja00324a028 <lb/>133. Rouzer CA, Marnett LJ. Mechanism of free radical oxygenation of <lb/>polyunsaturated fatty acids by cyclooxygenases. Chem Rev (2003) 103 <lb/>(6):2239-304. doi: 10.1021/cr000068x <lb/>134. Smith WL, Song I. The enzymology of prostaglandin endoperoxide H <lb/>synthases-1 and -2. Prostaglandins Other Lipid Med (2002) 68-69:115-28. <lb/>doi: 10.1016/s0090-6980(02)00025-4 <lb/>135. Bailey JM, Bryant RW, Whiting J, Salata K. Characterization of 11-HETE <lb/>and 15-HETE, together with prostacyclin, as major products of the <lb/>cyclooxygenase pathway in cultured rat aorta smooth muscle cells. J Lipid <lb/>Res (1983) 24(11):1419-28. <lb/>136. Setty BN, Stuart MJ, Walenga RW. Formation of 11-hydroxyeicosatetraenoic <lb/>acid and 15-hydroxyeicosatetraenoic acid in human umbilical arteries is <lb/>catalyzed by cyclooxygenase. Biochim Biophys Acta (1985) 833(3):484-94. <lb/>doi: 10.1016/0005-2760(85)90106-7 <lb/>137. Schneider C, Boeglin WE, Prusakiewicz JJ, Rowlinson SW, Marnett LJ, Samel <lb/>N, et al. Control of prostaglandin stereochemistry at the 15-carbon by <lb/>cyclooxygenases-1 and -2. A critical role for serine 530 and valine 349. <lb/>J Biol Chem (2002) 277(1):478-85. doi: 10.1074/jbc.M107471200 <lb/>138. Thuresson ED, Lakkides KM, Smith WL. Different catalytically competent <lb/>arrangements of arachidonic acid within the cyclooxygenase active site of <lb/>prostaglandin endoperoxide H synthase-1 lead to the formation of different <lb/>oxygenated products. J Biol Chem (2000) 275(12):8501-7. doi: 10.1074/ <lb/>jbc.275.12.8501 <lb/>139. Loll PJ, Picot D, Garavito RM. The structural basis of aspirin activity inferred <lb/>from the crystal structure of inactivated prostaglandin H2 synthase. Nat <lb/>Struct Biol (1995) 2(8):637-43. doi: 10.1038/nsb0895-637 <lb/>140. Lecomte M, Laneuville O, Ji C, DeWitt DL, Smith WL. Acetylation of human <lb/>prostaglandin endoperoxide synthase-2 (cyclooxygenase-2) by aspirin. J Biol <lb/>Chem (1994) 269(18):13207-15. <lb/>141. Gimenez-Bastida JA, Boeglin WE, Boutaud O, Malkowski MG, Schneider C. <lb/>Residual cyclooxygenase activity of aspirin-acetylated COX-2 forms 15 R-<lb/>prostaglandins that inhibit platelet aggregation. FASEB J (2019) 33(1):1033-<lb/>41. doi: 10.1096/fj.201801018R <lb/>142. Ricciotti E, FitzGerald GA. Prostaglandins and inflammation. Arterioscler <lb/>T h r o m b V a s c B i o l ( 2 0 1 1 ) 3 1 ( 5 ) : 9 8 6 -1 0 0 0 . d o i : 1 0 . 1 1 6 1 / <lb/>ATVBAHA.110.207449 <lb/>143. Laneuville O, Breuer DK, Xu N, Huang ZH, Gage DA, Watson JT, et al. Fatty <lb/>acid substrate specificities of human prostaglandin-endoperoxide H <lb/>synthase-1 and -2. Formation of 12-hydroxy-(9Z, 13E/Z, 15Z)-<lb/>octadecatrienoic acids from alpha-linolenic acid. J Biol Chem (1995) 270 <lb/>(33):19330-6. doi: 10.1074/jbc.270.33.19330 <lb/>144. Yuan C, Sidhu RS, Kuklev DV, Kado Y, Wada M, Song I, et al. <lb/>Cyclooxygenase Allosterism, Fatty Acid-mediated Cross-talk between <lb/>Monomers of Cyclooxygenase Homodimers. J Biol Chem (2009) 284 <lb/>(15):10046-55. doi: 10.1074/jbc.M808634200 <lb/>145. Dong L, Zou H, Yuan C, Hong YH, Kuklev DV, Smith WL. Different Fatty <lb/>Acids Compete with Arachidonic Acid for Binding to the Allosteric or <lb/>Catalytic Subunits of Cyclooxygenases to Regulate Prostanoid Synthesis. J <lb/>Biol Chem (2016) 291(8):4069-78. doi: 10.1074/jbc.M115.698001 <lb/>146. Mulugeta S, Suzuki T, Hernandez NT, Griesser M, Boeglin WE, Schneider C. <lb/>Identification and absolute configuration of dihydroxy-arachidonic acids <lb/>formed by oxygenation of 5S-HETE by native and aspirin-acetylated COX-2. <lb/>J Lipid Res (2010) 51(3):575-85. doi: 10.1194/jlr.M001719 <lb/>147. Yu M, Ives D, Ramesha CS. Synthesis of prostaglandin E2 ethanolamide <lb/>from anandamide by cyclooxygenase-2. J Biol Chem (1997) 272(34):21181-6. <lb/>doi: 10.1074/jbc.272.34.21181 <lb/>148. Kozak KR, Rowlinson SW, Marnett LJ. Oxygenation of the <lb/>endocannabinoid, 2-arachidonylglycerol, to glyceryl prostaglandins by <lb/>cyclooxygenase-2. J Biol Chem (2000) 275(43):33744-9. doi: 10.1074/ <lb/>jbc.M007088200 <lb/>149. Prusakiewicz JJ, Kingsley PJ, Kozak KR, Marnett LJ. Selective oxygenation of <lb/>N-arachidonylglycine by cyclooxygenase-2. Biochem Biophys Res Commun <lb/>(2002) 296(3):612-7. doi: 10.1016/s0006-291x(02)00915-4 <lb/>150. de Bus I, Zuilhof H, Witkamp R, Balvers M, Albada B. Novel COX-2 <lb/>products of n-3 polyunsaturated fatty acid-ethanolamine-conjugates <lb/>identified in RAW264.7 macrophages. J Lipid Res (2019) 60(11):1829-40. <lb/>doi: 10.1194/jlr.M094235 <lb/>151. Nelson DR, Zeldin DC, Hoffman SM, Maltais LJ, Wain HM, Nebert DW. <lb/>Comparison of cytochrome P450 (CYP) genes from the mouse and human <lb/>genomes, including nomenclature recommendations for genes, pseudogenes <lb/>and alternative-splice variants. Pharmacogenetics (2004) 14(1):1-18. <lb/>doi: 10.1097/00008571-200401000-00001 <lb/>152. Nebert DW, Wikvall K, Miller WL. Human cytochromes P450 in health and <lb/>disease. Philos Trans R Soc Lond B Biol Sci (2013) 368(1612):20120431. <lb/>doi: 10.1098/rstb.2012.0431 <lb/>153. Nebert DW, Adesnik M, Coon MJ, Estabrook RW, Gonzalez FJ, Guengerich <lb/>FP, et al. The P450 gene superfamily: recommended nomenclature. DNA <lb/>(1987) 6(1):1-11. doi: 10.1089/dna.1987.6.1 <lb/>154. Nelson DR. The cytochrome p450 homepage. Hum Genomics (2009) 4 <lb/>(1):59-65. doi: 10.1186/1479-7364-4-1-59 <lb/>155. Sim SC, Ingelman-Sundberg M. The Human Cytochrome P450 (CYP) Allele <lb/>Nomenclature website: a peer-reviewed database of CYP variants and their <lb/>associated effects. Hum Genomics (2010) 4(4):278-81. doi: 10.1186/1479-<lb/>7364-4-4-278 <lb/>156. Anzenbacher P, Anzenbacherova E. Cytochromes P450 and metabolism of <lb/>xenobiotics. Cell Mol Life Sci (2001) 58(5-6):737-47. doi: 10.1007/ <lb/>pl00000897 <lb/>157. Nishimura M, Yaguti H, Yoshitsugu H, Naito S, Satoh T. Tissue distribution <lb/>of mRNA expression of human cytochrome P450 isoforms assessed by high-<lb/>sensitivity real-time reverse transcription PCR. Yakugaku Zasshi (2003) 123 <lb/>(5):369-75. doi: 10.1248/yakushi.123.369 <lb/>158. Renaud HJ, Cui JY, Khan M, Klaassen CD. Tissue distribution and gender-<lb/>divergent expression of 78 cytochrome P450 mRNAs in mice. Toxicol Sci <lb/>(2011) 124(2):261-77. doi: 10.1093/toxsci/kfr240 <lb/>159. Sangar MC, Bansal S, Avadhani NG. Bimodal targeting of microsomal <lb/>cytochrome P450s to mitochondria: implications in drug metabolism and <lb/>toxicity. Expert Opin Drug Metab Toxicol (2010) 6(10):1231-51. <lb/>doi: 10.1517/17425255.2010.503955 <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Hajeyah et al. <lb/>Biosynthesis of Oxidized Lipids <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Endocrinology | www.frontiersin.org <lb/>November 2020 | Volume 11 | Article 591819 <lb/></note>

			<page>26 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>160. Srejber M, Navratilova V, Paloncyova M, Bazgier V, Berka K, Anzenbacher <lb/>P, et al. Membrane-attached mammalian cytochromes P450: An overview of <lb/>the membrane&apos;s effects on structure, drug binding, and interactions with <lb/>redox partners. J Inorg Biochem (2018) 183:117-36. doi: 10.1016/ <lb/>j.jinorgbio.2018.03.002 <lb/>161. Erickson SK, Bosterling B. Cholesterol 7 alpha-hydroxylase from human <lb/>liver: partial purification and reconstruction into defined phospholipid-<lb/>cholesterol vesicles. J Lipid Res (1981) 22(5):872-6. <lb/>162. Loeper J, Descatoire V, Maurice M, Beaune P, Belghiti J, Houssin D, et al. <lb/>Cytochromes P-450 in human hepatocyte plasma membrane: Recognition by <lb/>several autoantibodies. Gastroenterology (1993) 104(1):203-16. doi: 10.1016/ <lb/>0016-5085(93)90853-5 <lb/>163. Neve EP, Ingelman-Sundberg M. Molecular basis for the transport of <lb/>cytochrome P450 2E1 to the plasma membrane. J Biol Chem (2000) 275 <lb/>(22):17130-5. doi: 10.1074/jbc.M000957200 <lb/>164. Leung YK, Lau KM, Mobley J, Jiang Z, Ho SM. Overexpression of <lb/>cytochrome P450 1A1 and its novel spliced variant in ovarian cancer cells: <lb/>alternative subcellular enzyme compartmentation may contribute to <lb/>carcinogenesis. Cancer Res (2005) 65(9):3726-34. doi: 10.1158/0008-<lb/>5472.CAN-04-3771 <lb/>165. Li D, Tolleson WH, Yu D, Chen S, Guo L, Xiao W, et al. Regulation of <lb/>cytochrome P450 expression by microRNAs and long noncoding RNAs: <lb/>Epigenetic mechanisms in environmental toxicology and carcinogenesis. <lb/>J Environ Sci Health C Environ Carcinog Ecotoxicol Rev 37(3):180-<lb/>214. doi: 10.1080/10590501.2019.1639481 <lb/>166. Nelson DR, Nebert DW. Cytochrome P450 (CYP) Gene Superfamily. eLS. <lb/>Chichester: John Wiley &amp; Sons, Ltd (Ed (2018) p. 1-19. doi: 10.1002/ <lb/>9780470015902.a0005667.pub3 <lb/>167. Williams PA, Cosme J, Sridhar V, Johnson EF, McRee DE. Mammalian <lb/>microsomal cytochrome P450 monooxygenase: structural adaptations for <lb/>membrane binding and functional diversity. Mol Cell (2000) 5(1):121-31. <lb/>doi: 10.1016/s1097-2765(00)80408-6 <lb/>168. Annalora AJ, Goodin DB, Hong WX, Zhang Q, Johnson EF, Stout CD. <lb/>Crystal structure of CYP24A1, a mitochondrial cytochrome P450 involved in <lb/>vitamin D metabolism. J Mol Biol (2010) 396(2):441-51. doi: 10.1016/ <lb/>j.jmb.2009.11.057 <lb/>169. Pochapsky TC, Kazanis S, Dang M. Conformational plasticity and structure/ <lb/>function relationships in cytochromes P450. Antioxid Redox Signal (2010) 13 <lb/>(8):1273-96. doi: 10.1089/ars.2010.3109 <lb/>170. Ohkura K, Kawaguchi Y, Watanabe Y, Masubuchi Y, Shinohara Y, Hori H. <lb/>Flexible structure of cytochrome P450: promiscuity of ligand binding in the <lb/>CYP3A4 heme pocket. Anticancer Res (2009) 29(3):935-42. <lb/>171. Hoch U, Ortiz De Montellano PR. Covalently linked heme in cytochrome <lb/>p4504a fatty acid hydroxylases. J Biol Chem (2001) 276(14):11339-46. <lb/>doi: 10.1074/jbc.M009969200 <lb/>172. Hsu MH, Baer BR, Rettie AE, Johnson EF. The Crystal Structure of <lb/>Cytochrome P450 4B1 (CYP4B1) Monooxygenase Complexed with <lb/>Octane Discloses Several Structural Adaptations for omega-Hydroxylation. <lb/>J Biol Chem (2017) 292(13):5610-21. doi: 10.1074/jbc.M117.775494 <lb/>173. Schwarz D, Chernogolov A, Kisselev P. Complex formation in vesicle-<lb/>reconstituted mitochondrial cytochrome P450 systems (CYP11A1 and <lb/>CYP11B1) as evidenced by rotational diffusion experiments using EPR and <lb/>ST-EPR. Biochemistry (1999) 38(29):9456-64. doi: 10.1021/bi990584l <lb/>174. Szczesna-Skorupa E, Mallah B, Kemper B. Fluorescence resonance energy <lb/>transfer analysis of cytochromes P450 2C2 and 2E1 molecular interactions in <lb/>living cells. J Biol Chem (2003) 278(33):31269-76. doi: 10.1074/ <lb/>jbc.M301489200 <lb/>175. Hu G, Johnson EF, Kemper B. CYP2C8 exists as a dimer in natural <lb/>membranes. Drug Metab Dispos (2010) 38(11):1976-83. doi: 10.1124/ <lb/>dmd.110.034942 <lb/>176. Li B, Yau P, Kemper B. Identification of cytochrome P450 2C2 protein <lb/>complexes in mouse liver. Proteomics (2011) 11(16):3359-68. doi: 10.1002/ <lb/>pmic.201100001 <lb/>177. Kandel SE, Lampe JN. Role of protein-protein interactions in cytochrome <lb/>P450-mediated drug metabolism and toxicity. Chem Res Toxicol (2014) 27 <lb/>(9):1474-86. doi: 10.1021/tx500203s <lb/>178. Davydov DR, Davydova NY, Sineva EV, Halpert JR. Interactions among <lb/>cytochromes P450 in microsomal membranes: oligomerization of <lb/>cytochromes P450 3A4, 3A5, and 2E1 and its functional consequences. <lb/>J Biol Chem (2015) 290(6):3850-64. doi: 10.1074/jbc.M114.615443 <lb/>179. Connick JP, Reed JR, Backes WL. Characterization of Interactions Among <lb/>CYP1A2, CYP2B4, and NADPH-cytochrome P450 Reductase: Identification <lb/>of Specific Protein Complexes. Drug Metab Dispos (2018) 46(3):197-203. <lb/>doi: 10.1124/dmd.117.078642 <lb/>180. Zhang H, Yokom AL, Cheng S, Su M, Hollenberg PF, Southworth DR, et al. <lb/>The full-length cytochrome P450 enzyme CYP102A1 dimerizes at its <lb/>reductase domains and has flexible heme domains for efficient catalysis. <lb/>J Biol Chem (2018) 293(20):7727-36. doi: 10.1074/jbc.RA117.000600 <lb/>181. Isin EM, Guengerich FP. Complex reactions catalyzed by cytochrome P450 <lb/>enzymes. Biochim Biophys Acta (2007) 1770(3):314-29. doi: 10.1016/ <lb/>j.bbagen.2006.07.003 <lb/>182. Lamb DC, Waterman MR. Unusual properties of the cytochrome P450 <lb/>superfamily. Philos Trans R Soc Lond B Biol Sci (2013) 368(1612):20120434. <lb/>doi: 10.1098/rstb.2012.0434 <lb/>183. Hecker M, Ullrich V. On the mechanism of prostacyclin and thromboxane <lb/>A2 biosynthesis. J Biol Chem (1989) 264(1):141-50. <lb/>184. Cook DJ, Finnigan JD, Cook K, Black GW, Charnock SJ. Chapter Five -<lb/>Cytochromes P450: History, Classes, Catalytic Mechanism, and Industrial <lb/>Application. In: CZ Christov, editor. Advances in Protein Chemistry and <lb/>Structural Biology. Academic Press (2016). p. 105-26. doi: 10.1016/ <lb/>bs.apcsb.2016.07.003 <lb/>185. Guengerich FP. Mechanisms of Cytochrome P450-Catalyzed Oxidations. <lb/>ACS Catal (2018) 8(12):10964-76. doi: 10.1021/acscatal.8b03401 <lb/>186. Fer M, Dreano Y, Lucas D, Corcos L, Salaun JP, Berthou F, et al. Metabolism <lb/>of eicosapentaenoic and docosahexaenoic acids by recombinant human <lb/>cytochromes P450. Arch Biochem Biophys (2008) 471(2):116-25. <lb/>doi: 10.1016/j.abb.2008.01.002 <lb/>187. Barbosa-Sicard E, Markovic M, Honeck H, Christ B, Muller DN, Schunck <lb/>WH. Eicosapentaenoic acid metabolism by cytochrome P450 enzymes of the <lb/>CYP2C subfamily. Biochem Biophys Res Commun (2005) 329(4):1275-81. <lb/>doi: 10.1016/j.bbrc.2005.02.103 <lb/>188. Arnold C, Markovic M, Blossey K, Wallukat G, Fischer R, Dechend R, et al. <lb/>Arachidonic acid-metabolizing cytochrome P450 enzymes are targets of <lb/>{omega}-3 fatty acids. J Biol Chem (2010) 285(43):32720-33. doi: 10.1074/ <lb/>jbc.M110.118406 <lb/>189. Honda A, Miyazaki T, Ikegami T, Iwamoto J, Maeda T, Hirayama T, et al. <lb/>Cholesterol 25-hydroxylation activity of CYP3A. J Lipid Res (2011) 52 <lb/>(8):1509-16. doi: 10.1194/jlr.M014084 <lb/>190. Griffiths WJ, Crick PJ, Meljon A, Theofilopoulos S, Abdel-Khalik J, Yutuc E, <lb/>et al. Additional pathways of sterol metabolism: Evidence from analysis of <lb/>Cyp27a1-/-mouse brain and plasma. Biochim Biophys Acta Mol Cell Biol <lb/>Lipids (2019) 1864(2):191-211. doi: 10.1016/j.bbalip.2018.11.006 <lb/>191. Bodin K, Andersson U, Rystedt E, Ellis E, Norlin M, Pikuleva I, et al. <lb/>Metabolism of 4 beta -hydroxycholesterol in humans. J Biol Chem (2002) 277 <lb/>(35):31534-40. doi: 10.1074/jbc.M201712200 <lb/>192. Kawashima H, Naganuma T, Kusunose E, Kono T, Yasumoto R, Sugimura K, <lb/>et al. Human fatty acid omega-hydroxylase, CYP4A11: determination of <lb/>complete genomic sequence and characterization of purified recombinant <lb/>protein. Arch Biochem Biophys (2000) 378(2):333-9. doi: 10.1006/ <lb/>abbi.2000.1831 <lb/>193. Shinkyo R, Xu L, Tallman KA, Cheng Q, Porter NA, Guengerich FP. Conversion <lb/>of 7-dehydrocholesterol to 7-ketocholesterol is catalyzed by human cytochrome <lb/>P450 7A1 and occurs by direct oxidation without an epoxide intermediate. J Biol <lb/>Chem (2011) 286(38):33021-8. doi: 10.1074/jbc.M111.282434 <lb/>194. Bjorkhem I, Diczfalusy U, Lovgren-Sandblom A, Starck L, Jonsson M, <lb/>Tallman K, et al. On the formation of 7-ketocholesterol from 7-<lb/>dehydrocholesterol in patients with CTX and SLO. J Lipid Res (2014) 55 <lb/>(6):1165-72. doi: 10.1194/jlr.P048603 <lb/>195. Schwarz M, Lund EG, Lathe R, Bjorkhem I, Russell DW. Identification and <lb/>characterization of a mouse oxysterol 7alpha-hydroxylase cDNA. J Biol <lb/>Chem (1997) 272(38):23995-4001. doi: 10.1074/jbc.272.38.23995 <lb/>196. Gafvels M, Olin M, Chowdhary BP, Raudsepp T, Andersson U, Persson B, <lb/>et al. Structure and chromosomal assignment of the sterol 12alpha-<lb/>hydroxylase gene (CYP8B1) in human and mouse: eukaryotic cytochrome <lb/>P-450 gene devoid of introns. Genomics (1999) 56(2):184-96. doi: 10.1006/ <lb/>geno.1998.5606 <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Hajeyah et al. <lb/>Biosynthesis of Oxidized Lipids <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Endocrinology | www.frontiersin.org <lb/>November 2020 | Volume 11 | Article 591819 <lb/></note>

			<page>27 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>197. Pikuleva IA. Cholesterol-metabolizing cytochromes P450. Drug Metab <lb/>Dispos (2006) 34(4):513-20. doi: 10.1124/dmd.105.008789 <lb/>198. Coulter CL, Jaffe RB. Functional maturation of the primate fetal adrenal in <lb/>vivo: 3. Specific zonal localization and developmental regulation of CYP21A2 <lb/>(P450c21) and CYP11B1/CYP11B2 (P450c11/aldosterone synthase) lead to <lb/>integrated concept of zonal and temporal steroid biosynthesis. Endocrinology <lb/>(1998) 139(12):5144-50. doi: 10.1210/endo.139.12.6333 <lb/>199. Payne AH, Hales DB. Overview of steroidogenic enzymes in the pathway <lb/>from cholesterol to active steroid hormones. Endocr Rev (2004) 25(6):947-<lb/>70. doi: 10.1210/er.2003-0030 <lb/>200. Omdahl JL, Morris HA, May BK. Hydroxylase enzymes of the vitamin D <lb/>pathway: expression, function, and regulation. Annu Rev Nutr (2002) 22 <lb/>(1):139-66. doi: 10.1146/annurev.nutr.22.120501.150216 <lb/>201. White JA, Guo YD, Baetz K, Beckett-Jones B, Bonasoro J, Hsu KE, et al. <lb/>Identification of the retinoic acid-inducible all-trans-retinoic acid 4-<lb/>hydroxylase. J Biol Chem (1996) 271(47):29922-7. doi: 10.1074/ <lb/>jbc.271.47.29922 <lb/>202. Goyal S, Xiao Y, Porter NA, Xu L, Guengerich FP. Oxidation of 7-<lb/>dehydrocholesterol and desmosterol by human cytochrome P450 46A1. J <lb/>Lipid Res (2014) 55(9):1933-43. doi: 10.1194/jlr.M051508 <lb/>203. Lepesheva GI, Waterman MR. Sterol 14alpha-demethylase cytochrome P450 <lb/>(CYP51), a P450 in all biological kingdoms. Biochim Biophys Acta (2007) <lb/>1770(3):467-77. doi: 10.1016/j.bbagen.2006.07.018 <lb/>204. Fer M, Corcos L, Dreano Y, Plee-Gautier E, Salaun JP, Berthou F, et al. <lb/>Cytochromes P450 from family 4 are the main omega hydroxylating <lb/>enzymes in humans: CYP4F3B is the prominent player in PUFA <lb/>metabolism. J Lipid Res (2008) 49(11):2379-89. doi: 10.1194/jlr.M800199-<lb/>JLR200 <lb/>205. Wu CC, Gupta T, Garcia V, Ding Y, Schwartzman ML. 20-HETE and blood <lb/>pressure regulation: clinical implications. Cardiol Rev (2014) 22(1):1-12. <lb/>doi: 10.1097/CRD.0b013e3182961659 <lb/>206. Kikuta Y, Kusunose E, Kusunose M. Prostaglandin and leukotriene omega-<lb/>hydroxylases. Prostaglandins Other Lipid Med (2002) 68-69:345-62. <lb/>doi: 10.1016/s0090-6980(02)00039-4 <lb/>207. Hardwick JP. Cytochrome P450 omega hydroxylase (CYP4) function in fatty <lb/>acid metabolism and metabolic diseases. Biochem Pharmacol (2008) 75 <lb/>(12):2263-75. doi: 10.1016/j.bcp.2008.03.004 <lb/>208. Ohno Y, Nakamichi S, Ohkuni A, Kamiyama N, Naoe A, Tsujimura H, et al. <lb/>Essential role of the cytochrome P450 CYP4F22 in the production of <lb/>acylceramide, the key lipid for skin permeability barrier formation. Proc <lb/>Natl Acad Sci U.S.A. (2015) 112(25):7707-12. doi: 10.1073/pnas.1503491112 <lb/>209. Laethem RM, Balazy M, Falck JR, Laethem CL, Koop DR. Formation of 19 <lb/>(S)-, 19(R)-, and 18(R)-hydroxyeicosatetraenoic acids by alcohol-inducible <lb/>cytochrome P450 2E1. J Biol Chem (1993) 268(17):12912-8. <lb/>210. Oliw EH. bis-Allylic hydroxylation of linoleic acid and arachidonic acid by <lb/>human hepatic monooxygenases. Biochim Biophys Acta (1993) 1166(2-<lb/>3):258-63. doi: 10.1016/0005-2760(93)90106-j <lb/>211. Brash AR, Boeglin WE, Capdevila JH, Yeola S, Blair IA. 7-HETE, 10-HETE, <lb/>and 13-HETE are major products of NADPH-dependent arachidonic acid <lb/>metabolism in rat liver microsomes: analysis of their stereochemistry, and <lb/>the stereochemistry of their acid-catalyzed rearrangement. Arch Biochem <lb/>Biophys (1995) 321(2):485-92. doi: 10.1006/abbi.1995.1421 <lb/>212. Morisseau C. Role of epoxide hydrolases in lipid metabolism. Biochimie <lb/>(2013) 95(1):91-5. doi: 10.1016/j.biochi.2012.06.011 <lb/>213. Snider NT, Kornilov AM, Kent UM, Hollenberg PF. Anandamide <lb/>metabolism by human liver and kidney microsomal cytochrome p450 <lb/>enzymes to form hydroxyeicosatetraenoic and epoxyeicosatrienoic acid <lb/>ethanolamides. J Pharmacol Exp Ther (2007) 321(2):590-7. doi: 10.1124/ <lb/>jpet.107.119321 <lb/>214. Sridar C, Snider NT, Hollenberg PF. Anandamide oxidation by wild-type <lb/>and polymorphically expressed CYP2B6 and CYP2D6. Drug Metab Dispos <lb/>(2011) 39(5):782-8. doi: 10.1124/dmd.110.036707 <lb/>215. McDougle DR, Watson JE, Abdeen AA, Adili R, Caputo MP, Krapf JE, et al. <lb/>Anti-inflammatory w-3 endocannabinoid epoxides. Proc Natl Acad Sci <lb/>(2017) 114(30):E6034-E43. doi: 10.1073/pnas.1610325114 <lb/>216. Watson JE, Kim JS, Das A. Emerging class of omega-3 fatty acid <lb/>endocannabinoids &amp; their derivatives. Prostaglandins Other Lipid Med <lb/>(2019) 143:106337. doi: 10.1016/j.prostaglandins.2019.106337 <lb/>217. Shyadehi AZ, Lamb DC, Kelly SL, Kelly DE, Schunck WH, Wright JN, et al. <lb/>The mechanism of the acyl-carbon bond cleavage reaction catalyzed by <lb/>recombinant sterol 14 alpha-demethylase of Candida albicans (other names <lb/>are: lanosterol 14 alpha-demethylase, P-45014DM, and CYP51). J Biol Chem <lb/>(1996) 271(21):12445-50. doi: 10.1074/jbc.271.21.12445 <lb/>218. Strushkevich N, MacKenzie F, Cherkesova T, Grabovec I, Usanov S, Park <lb/>HW. Structural basis for pregnenolone biosynthesis by the mitochondrial <lb/>monooxygenase system. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A (2011) 108(25):10139-43. <lb/>doi: 10.1073/pnas.1019441108 <lb/>219. Griffiths WJ, Wang Y. Oxysterols as lipid mediators: Their biosynthetic <lb/>genes, enzymes and metabolites. Prostaglandins Other Lipid Med (2020) <lb/>147:106381. doi: 10.1016/j.prostaglandins.2019.106381 <lb/>220. Russell DW. The enzymes, regulation, and genetics of bile acid synthesis. Annu Rev <lb/>Biochem (2003) 72:137-74. doi: 10.1146/annurev.biochem.72.121801.161712 <lb/>221. Cali JJ, Russell DW. Characterization of human sterol 27-hydroxylase. A <lb/>mitochondrial cytochrome P-450 that catalyzes multiple oxidation reaction <lb/>in bile acid biosynthesis. J Biol Chem (1991) 266(12):7774-8. <lb/>222. Lund EG, Guileyardo JM, Russell DW. cDNA cloning of cholesterol 24-<lb/>hydroxylase, a mediator of cholesterol homeostasis in the brain. Proc Natl <lb/>Acad Sci U S A (1999) 96(13):7238-43. doi: 10.1073/pnas.96.13.7238 <lb/>223. Mast N, Norcross R, Andersson U, Shou M, Nakayama K, Bjorkhem I, et al. <lb/>Broad substrate specificity of human cytochrome P450 46A1 which initiates <lb/>cholesterol degradation in the brain. Biochemistry (2003) 42(48):14284-92. <lb/>doi: 10.1021/bi035512f <lb/>224. Bodin K, Andersson U, Rystedt E, Ellis E, Norlin M, Pikuleva I, et al. <lb/>Metabolism of 4 beta -hydroxycholesterol in humans. J Biol Chem (2002) 277 <lb/>(35):31534-40. doi: 10.1074/jbc.M201712200 <lb/>225. Tuckey RC, Cameron KJ. Side-chain specificities of human and bovine <lb/>cytochromes P-450scc. Eur J Biochem (1993) 217(1):209-15. doi: 10.1111/ <lb/>j.1432-1033.1993.tb18235.x <lb/>226. Petrunak EM, DeVore NM, Porubsky PR, Scott EE. Structures of human <lb/>steroidogenic cytochrome P450 17A1 with substrates. J Biol Chem (2014) 289 <lb/>(47):32952-64. doi: 10.1074/jbc.M114.610998 <lb/>227. Jez JM, Flynn TG, Penning TM. A new nomenclature for the aldo-keto <lb/>reductase superfamily. Biochem Pharmacol (1997) 54(6):639-47. <lb/>doi: 10.1016/s0006-2952(97)84253-0 <lb/>228. Hyndman D, Bauman DR, Heredia VV, Penning TM. The aldo-keto <lb/>reductase superfamily homepage. Chem Biol Interact (2003) 143-144:621-<lb/>31. doi: 10.1016/s0009-2797(02)00193-x <lb/>229. Spite M, Baba SP, Ahmed Y, Barski OA, Nijhawan K, Petrash JM, et al. <lb/>Substrate specificity and catalytic efficiency of aldo-keto reductases with <lb/>phospholipid aldehydes. Biochem J (2007) 405(1):95-105. doi: 10.1042/ <lb/>BJ20061743 <lb/>230. O&apos;Connor T, Ireland LS, Harrison DJ, Hayes JD. Major differences exist in <lb/>the function and tissue-specific expression of human aflatoxin B1 aldehyde <lb/>reductase and the principal human aldo-keto reductase AKR1 family <lb/>members. Biochem J (1999) 343 Pt 2(Pt 2):487-504. doi: 10.1042/bj3430487 <lb/>231. Cao D, Fan ST, Chung SS. Identification and characterization of a novel <lb/>human aldose reductase-like gene. J Biol Chem (1998) 273(19):11429-35. <lb/>doi: 10.1074/jbc.273.19.11429 <lb/>232. Endo S, Matsunaga T, Mamiya H, Ohta C, Soda M, Kitade Y, et al. Kinetic <lb/>studies of AKR1B10, human aldose reductase-like protein: endogenous <lb/>substrates and inhibition by steroids. Arch Biochem Biophys (2009) 487 <lb/>(1):1-9. doi: 10.1016/j.abb.2009.05.009 <lb/>233. Huang SP, Palla S, Ruzycki P, Varma RA, Harter T, Reddy GB, et al. Aldo-keto <lb/>reductases in the eye. J Ophthalmol (2010) 2010:521204. doi: 10.1155/2010/521204 <lb/>234. Ruiz FX, Porte S, Pares X, Farres J. Biological role of aldo-keto reductases in <lb/>retinoic Acid biosynthesis and signaling. Front Pharmacol (2012) 3:58:58. <lb/>doi: 10.3389/fphar.2012.00058 <lb/>235. Barski OA, Tipparaju SM, Bhatnagar A. The aldo-keto reductase superfamily <lb/>and its role in drug metabolism and detoxification. Drug Metab Rev (2008) <lb/>40(4):553-624. doi: 10.1080/03602530802431439 <lb/>236. Weber S, Salabei JK, Moller G, Kremmer E, Bhatnagar A, Adamski J, et al. <lb/>Aldo-keto Reductase 1B15 (AKR1B15): a mitochondrial human aldo-keto <lb/>reductase with activity toward steroids and 3-keto-acyl-CoA conjugates. <lb/>J Biol Chem (2015) 290(10):6531-45. doi: 10.1074/jbc.M114.610121 <lb/>237. Byrns MC. Role of aldo-keto reductase enzymes in mediating the timing of <lb/>parturition. Front Pharmacol (2011) 2:92:92. doi: 10.3389/fphar.2011.00092 <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Hajeyah et al. <lb/>Biosynthesis of Oxidized Lipids <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Endocrinology | www.frontiersin.org <lb/>November 2020 | Volume 11 | Article 591819 <lb/></note>

			<page>28 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>238. Penning TM, Burczynski ME, Jez JM, Hung CF, Lin HK, Ma H, et al. Human <lb/>3alpha-hydroxysteroid dehydrogenase isoforms (AKR1C1-AKR1C4) of the <lb/>aldo-keto reductase superfamily: functional plasticity and tissue distribution <lb/>reveals roles in the inactivation and formation of male and female sex hormones. <lb/>Biochem J (2000) 351(Pt 1):67-77. doi: 10.1042/0264-6021:3510067 <lb/>239. Burczynski ME, Sridhar GR, Palackal NT, Penning TM. The reactive oxygen <lb/>species-and Michael acceptor-inducible human aldo-keto reductase <lb/>AKR1C1 reduces the alpha,beta-unsaturated aldehyde 4-hydroxy-2-<lb/>nonenal to 1,4-dihydroxy-2-nonene. J Biol Chem (2001) 276(4):2890-7. <lb/>doi: 10.1074/jbc.M006655200 <lb/>240. Lyon RC, Li D, McGarvie G, Ellis EM. Aldo-keto reductases mediate <lb/>constitutive and inducible protection against aldehyde toxicity in human <lb/>neuroblastoma SH-SY5Y cells. Neurochem Int (2013) 62(1):113-21. <lb/>doi: 10.1016/j.neuint.2012.10.007 <lb/>241. Suzuki-Yamamoto T, Nishizawa M, Fukui M, Okuda-Ashitaka E, Nakajima <lb/>T, Ito S, et al. cDNA cloning, expression and characterization of human <lb/>prostaglandin F synthase. FEBS Lett (1999) 462(3):335-40. doi: 10.1016/ <lb/>s0014-5793(99)01551-3 <lb/>242. Penning TM. Aldo-Keto Reductase (AKR) 1C3 inhibitors: a patent review. <lb/>Expert Opin Ther Pat (2017) 27(12):1329-40. doi: 10.1080/ <lb/>13543776.2017.1379503 <lb/>243. Kondo KH, Kai MH, Setoguchi Y, Eggertsen G, Sjoblom P, Setoguchi T, et al. <lb/>Cloning and expression of cDNA of human delta 4-3-oxosteroid 5 beta-<lb/>reductase and substrate specificity of the expressed enzyme. Eur J Biochem <lb/>(1994) 219(1-2):357-63. doi: 10.1111/j.1432-1033.1994.tb19947.x <lb/>244. Chen M, Drury JE, Penning TM. Substrate specificity and inhibitor analyses <lb/>of human steroid 5beta-reductase (AKR1D1). Steroids (2011) 76(5):484-90. <lb/>doi: 10.1016/j.steroids.2011.01.003 <lb/>245. Nikolaou N, Gathercole LL, Marchand L, Althari S, Dempster NJ, Green CJ, <lb/>et al. AKR1D1 is a novel regulator of metabolic phenotype in human <lb/>hepatocytes and is dysregulated in non-alcoholic fatty liver disease. <lb/>Metabolism (2019) 99:67-80. doi: 10.1016/j.metabol.2019.153947 <lb/>246. Sakuma M, Kametani S, Akanuma H. Purification and some properties of a <lb/>hepatic NADPH-dependent reductase that specifically acts on 1,5-anhydro-<lb/>D-fructose. J Biochem (1998) 123(1):189-93. doi: 10.1093/ <lb/>oxfordjournals.jbchem.a021909 <lb/>247. Azuma Y, Nishinaka T, Ushijima S, Soh J, Katsuyama M, Lu HP, et al. <lb/>Characterization of htAKR, a novel gene product in the aldo-keto reductase <lb/>family specifically expressed in human testis. Mol Hum Reprod (2004) 10 <lb/>(7):527-33. doi: 10.1093/molehr/gah062 <lb/>248. England SK, Uebele VN, Shear H, Kodali J, Bennett PB, Tamkun MM. <lb/>Characterization of a voltage-gated K+ channel beta subunit expressed in <lb/>human heart. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A (1995) 92(14):6309-13. doi: 10.1073/ <lb/>pnas.92.14.6309 <lb/>249. Pan Y, Weng J, Cao Y, Bhosle RC, Zhou M. Functional coupling between the <lb/>Kv1.1 channel and aldoketoreductase Kvbeta1. J Biol Chem (2008) 283 <lb/>(13):8634-42. doi: 10.1074/jbc.M709304200 <lb/>250. Tipparaju SM, Barski OA, Srivastava S, Bhatnagar A. Catalytic mechanism <lb/>and substrate specificity of the beta-subunit of the voltage-gated potassium <lb/>channel. Biochemistry (2008) 47(34):8840-54. doi: 10.1021/bi800301b <lb/>251. Xie Z, Barski OA, Cai J, Bhatnagar A, Tipparaju SM. Catalytic reduction of <lb/>carbonyl groups in oxidized PAPC by Kvbeta2 (AKR6). Chem Biol Interact <lb/>(2011) 191(1-3):255-60. doi: 10.1016/j.cbi.2011.01.032 <lb/>252. Rasband MN, Trimmer JS. Subunit composition and novel localization of K+ <lb/>channels in spinal cord. J Comp Neurol (2001) 429(1):166-76. doi: 10.1002/ <lb/>1096-9861(20000101)429:1&lt;166::aid-cne13&gt;3.0.co;2-y <lb/>253. Leicher T, Bahring R, Isbrandt D, Pongs O. Coexpression of the KCNA3B <lb/>gene product with Kv1.5 leads to a novel A-type potassium channel. J Biol <lb/>Chem (1998) 273(52):35095-101. doi: 10.1074/jbc.273.52.35095 <lb/>254. Ireland LS, Harrison DJ, Neal GE, Hayes JD. Molecular cloning, expression <lb/>and catalytic activity of a human AKR7 member of the aldo-keto reductase <lb/>superfamily: evidence that the major 2-carboxybenzaldehyde reductase from <lb/>human liver is a homologue of rat aflatoxin B1-aldehyde reductase. Biochem <lb/>J (1998) 332( Pt 1):21-34. doi: 10.1042/bj3320021 <lb/>255. Knight LP, Primiano T, Groopman JD, Kensler TW, Sutter TR. cDNA <lb/>cloning, expression and activity of a second human aflatoxin B1-<lb/>metabolizing member of the aldo-keto reductase superfamily, AKR7A3. <lb/>Carcinogenesis (1999) 20(7):1215-23. doi: 10.1093/carcin/20.7.1215 <lb/>256. Matsunaga T, Haga M, Watanabe G, Shinoda Y, Endo S, Kajiwara Y, et al. <lb/>9,10-Phenanthrenequinone promotes secretion of pulmonary aldo-keto <lb/>reductases with surfactant. Cell Tissue Res (2012) 347(2):407-17. <lb/>doi: 10.1007/s00441-011-1304-5 <lb/>257. Luo DX, Huang MC, Ma J, Gao Z, Liao DF, Cao D. Aldo-keto reductase <lb/>family 1, member B10 is secreted through a lysosome-mediated non-classical <lb/>pathway. Biochem J (2011) 438(1):71-80. doi: 10.1042/BJ20110111 <lb/>258. Kelly VP, Sherratt PJ, Crouch DH, Hayes JD. Novel homodimeric and <lb/>heterodimeric rat gamma-hydroxybutyrate synthases that associate with the <lb/>Golgi apparatus define a distinct subclass of aldo-keto reductase 7 family <lb/>proteins. Biochem J (2002) 366(Pt 3):847-61. doi: 10.1042/BJ20020342 <lb/>259. Penning TM, Wangtrakuldee P, Auchus RJ. Structural and Functional <lb/>Biology of Aldo-Keto Reductase Steroid-Transforming Enzymes. Endocr <lb/>Rev (2019) 40(2):447-75. doi: 10.1210/er.2018-00089 <lb/>260. Ma H, Penning TM. Conversion of mammalian 3alpha-hydroxysteroid <lb/>dehydrogenase to 20alpha-hydroxysteroid dehydrogenase using loop <lb/>chimeras: changing specificity from androgens to progestins. Proc Natl <lb/>Acad Sci U S A (1999) 96(20):11161-6. doi: 10.1073/pnas.96.20.11161 <lb/>261. Gulbis JM, Mann S, MacKinnon R. Structure of a voltage-dependent K+ <lb/>channel beta subunit. Cell (1999) 97(7):943-52. doi: 10.1016/s0092-8674(00) <lb/>80805-3 <lb/>262. Liu SQ, Jin H, Zacarias A, Srivastava S, Bhatnagar A. Binding of pyridine <lb/>coenzymes to the beta-subunit of the voltage sensitive potassium channels. <lb/>Chem Biol Interact (2001) 130-132(1-3):955-62. doi: 10.1016/s0009-2797 <lb/>(00)00248-9 <lb/>263. Di Luccio E, Elling RA, Wilson DK. Identification of a novel NADH-specific <lb/>aldo-keto reductase using sequence and structural homologies. Biochem J <lb/>(2006) 400(1):105-14. doi: 10.1042/BJ20060660 <lb/>264. Jez JM, Bennett MJ, Schlegel BP, Lewis M, Penning TM. Comparative <lb/>anatomy of the aldo-keto reductase superfamily. Biochem J (1997) 326Pt <lb/>3)(Pt 3):625-36. doi: 10.1042/bj3260625 <lb/>265. Di Costanzo L, Drury JE, Christianson DW, Penning TM. Structure and <lb/>catalytic mechanism of human steroid 5beta-reductase (AKR1D1). Mol Cell <lb/>Endocrinol (2009) 301(1-2):191-8. doi: 10.1016/j.mce.2008.09.013 <lb/>266. Nagata N, Kusakari Y, Fukunishi Y, Inoue T, Urade Y. Catalytic mechanism <lb/>of the primary human prostaglandin F2alpha synthase, aldo-keto reductase <lb/>1B1-prostaglandin D2 synthase activity in the absence of NADP(H). FEBS J <lb/>(2011) 278(8):1288-98. doi: 10.1111/j.1742-4658.2011.08049.x <lb/>267. Wang C, Yan R, Luo D, Watabe K, Liao DF, Cao D. Aldo-keto reductase <lb/>family 1 member B10 promotes cell survival by regulating lipid synthesis and <lb/>eliminating carbonyls. J Biol Chem (2009) 284(39):26742-8. doi: 10.1074/ <lb/>jbc.M109.022897 <lb/>268. Li D, Ferrari M, Ellis EM. Human aldo-keto reductase AKR7A2 protects <lb/>against the cytotoxicity and mutagenicity of reactive aldehydes and lowers <lb/>intracellular reactive oxygen species in hamster V79-4 cells. Chem Biol <lb/>Interact (2012) 195(1):25-34. doi: 10.1016/j.cbi.2011.09.007 <lb/>269. Li D, Ellis EM. Inducible protection of human astrocytoma 1321N1 cells <lb/>against hydrogen peroxide and aldehyde toxicity by 7-hydroxycoumarin is <lb/>associated with the upregulation of aldo-keto reductases. Neurotoxicology <lb/>(2012) 33(5):1368-74. doi: 10.1016/j.neuro.2012.08.015 <lb/>270. Kabututu Z, Manin M, Pointud JC, Maruyama T, Nagata N, Lambert S, et al. <lb/>Prostaglandin F2alpha synthase activities of aldo-keto reductase 1B1, 1B3 <lb/>and 1B7. J Biochem (2009) 145(2):161-8. doi: 10.1093/jb/mvn152 <lb/>271. Komoto J, Yamada T, Watanabe K, Takusagawa F. Crystal structure of <lb/>human prostaglandin F synthase (AKR1C3). Biochemistry (2004) 43 <lb/>(8):2188-98. doi: 10.1021/bi036046x <lb/>272. Zhou Y, Shaw N, Li Y, Zhao Y, Zhang R, Liu ZJ. Structure-function analysis <lb/>of human l-prostaglandin D synthase bound with fatty acid molecules. <lb/>FASEB J (2010) 24(12):4668-77. doi: 10.1096/fj.10-164863 <lb/>273. Rizner TL, Smuc T, Rupreht R, Sinkovec J, Penning TM. AKR1C1 and <lb/>AKR1C3 may determine progesterone and estrogen ratios in endometrial <lb/>cancer. Mol Cell Endocrinol (2006) 248(1-2):126-35. doi: 10.1016/ <lb/>j.mce.2005.10.009 <lb/>274. Penning TM. Human hydroxysteroid dehydrogenases and pre-receptor <lb/>regulation: insights into inhibitor design and evaluation. J Steroid Biochem <lb/>Mol Biol (2011) 125(1-2):46-56. doi: 10.1016/j.jsbmb.2011.01.009 <lb/>275. Persson B, Kallberg Y, Bray JE, Bruford E, Dellaporta SL, Favia AD, et al. <lb/>(short-chain dehydrogenase/reductase and related enzymes) nomenclature <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Hajeyah et al. <lb/>Biosynthesis of Oxidized Lipids <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Endocrinology | www.frontiersin.org <lb/>November 2020 | Volume 11 | Article 591819 <lb/></note>

			<page>29 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>initiative. Chem Biol Interact (2009) 178(1-3):94-8. doi: 10.1016/ <lb/>j.cbi.2008.10.040 <lb/>276. Dumont M, Luu-The V, Dupont E, Pelletier G, Labrie F. Characterization, <lb/>expression, and immunohistochemical localization of 3 beta-hydroxysteroid <lb/>dehydrogenase/delta 5-delta 4 isomerase in human skin. J Invest Dermatol <lb/>(1992) 99(4):415-21. doi: 10.1111/1523-1747.ep12616131 <lb/>277. Labrie F, Simard J, Luu-The V, Belanger A, Pelletier G. Structure, function <lb/>and tissue-specific gene expression of 3beta-hydroxysteroid dehydrogenase/ <lb/>5-ene-4-ene isomerase enzymes in classical and peripheral intracrine <lb/>steroidogenic tissues. J Steroid Biochem Mol Biol (1992) 43(8):805-26. <lb/>doi: 10.1016/0960-0760(92)90308-6 <lb/>278. Rheaume E, Lachance Y, Zhao HF, Breton N, Dumont M, de Launoit Y, et al. <lb/>Structure and expression of a new complementary DNA encoding the almost <lb/>exclusive 3 beta-hydroxysteroid dehydrogenase/delta 5-delta 4-isomerase in <lb/>human adrenals and gonads. Mol Endocrinol (1991) 5(8):1147-57. <lb/>doi: 10.1210/mend-5-8-1147 <lb/>279. Schwarz M, Wright AC, Davis DL, Nazer H, Bjorkhem I, Russell DW. The <lb/>bile acid synthetic gene 3beta-hydroxy-Delta(5)-C(27)-steroid <lb/>oxidoreductase is mutated in progressive intrahepatic cholestasis. J Clin <lb/>Invest (2000) 106(9):1175-84. doi: 10.1172/JCI10902 <lb/>280. Odermatt A, Arnold P, Stauffer A, Frey BM, Frey FJ. The N-terminal anchor <lb/>sequences of 11beta-hydroxysteroid dehydrogenases determine their <lb/>orientation in the endoplasmic reticulum membrane. J Biol Chem (1999) <lb/>274(40):28762-70. doi: 10.1074/jbc.274.40.28762 <lb/>281. Luu The V, Labrie C, Zhao HF, Couet J, Lachance Y, Simard J, et al. <lb/>Characterization of cDNAs for human estradiol 17 beta-dehydrogenase and <lb/>assignment of the gene to chromosome 17: evidence of two mRNA species <lb/>with distinct 5&apos;-termini in human placenta. Mol Endocrinol (1989) 3 <lb/>(8):1301-9. doi: 10.1210/mend-3-8-1301 <lb/>282. He W, Gauri M, Li T, Wang R, Lin SX. Current knowledge of the <lb/>multifunctional 17beta-hydroxysteroid dehydrogenase type 1 (HSD17B1). <lb/>Gene (2016) 588(1):54-61. doi: 10.1016/j.gene.2016.04.031 <lb/>283. van Grunsven EG, van Berkel E, Ijlst L, Vreken P, de Klerk JB, Adamski J, <lb/>et al. Peroxisomal D-hydroxyacyl-CoA dehydrogenase deficiency: resolution <lb/>of the enzyme defect and its molecular basis in bifunctional protein <lb/>deficiency. Proc Natl Acad Sci U.S.A. (1998) 95(5):2128-33. doi: 10.1073/ <lb/>pnas.95.5.2128 <lb/>284. Nokelainen P, Peltoketo H, Vihko R, Vihko P. Expression cloning of a novel <lb/>estrogenic mouse 17 beta-hydroxysteroid dehydrogenase/17-ketosteroid <lb/>reductase (m17HSD7), previously described as a prolactin receptor-<lb/>associated protein (PRAP) in rat. Mol Endocrinol (1998) 12(7):1048-59. <lb/>doi: 10.1210/mend.12.7.0134 <lb/>285. Marijanovic Z, Laubner D, Moller G, Gege C, Husen B, Adamski J, et al. <lb/>Closing the gap: identification of human 3-ketosteroid reductase, the last <lb/>unknown enzyme of mammalian cholesterol biosynthesis. Mol Endocrinol <lb/>(2003) 17(9):1715-25. doi: 10.1210/me.2002-0436 <lb/>286. Fahy E, Subramaniam S, Murphy RC, Nishijima M, Raetz CR, Shimizu T, <lb/>et al. Update of the LIPID MAPS comprehensive classification system for <lb/>lipids. J Lipid Res (2009) 50 Suppl(Suppl):S9-14. doi: 10.1194/jlr.R800095-<lb/>JLR200 <lb/>287. Sud M, Fahy E, Cotter D, Brown A, Dennis EA, Glass CK, et al. LMSD: LIPID <lb/>MAPS structure database. Nucleic Acids Res (2007) 35(Database issue): <lb/>D527-32. doi: 10.1093/nar/gkl838 <lb/>288. Urquhart P, Nicolaou A, Woodward DF. Endocannabinoids and their <lb/>oxygenation by cyclo-oxygenases, lipoxygenases and other oxygenases. <lb/>Biochim Biophys Acta (2015) 1851(4):366-76. doi: 10.1016/ <lb/>j.bbalip.2014.12.015 <lb/>289. Abraham RT, McKinney MM, Forray C, Shipley GD, Handwerger BS. <lb/>Stimulation of arachidonic acid release and eicosanoid biosynthesis in an <lb/>interleukin 2-dependent T cell line. J Immunopharmacol (1986) 8(2):165-<lb/>204. doi: 10.3109/08923978609028614 <lb/>290. Tang X, Edwards EM, Holmes BB, Falck JR, Campbell WB. Role of <lb/>phospholipase C and diacylglyceride lipase pathway in arachidonic acid <lb/>release and acetylcholine-induced vascular relaxation in rabbit aorta. Am J <lb/>Physiol Heart Circ Physiol (2006) 290(1):H37-45. doi: 10.1152/ <lb/>ajpheart.00491.2005 <lb/>291. Dennis EA, Cao J, Hsu YH, Magrioti V, Kokotos G. Phospholipase A2 <lb/>enzymes: physical structure, biological function, disease implication, <lb/>chemical inhibition, and therapeutic intervention. Chem Rev (2011) 111 <lb/>(10):6130-85. doi: 10.1021/cr200085w <lb/>292. Vasquez AM, Mouchlis VD, Dennis EA. Review of four major distinct types <lb/>of human phospholipase A2. Adv Biol Regul (2018) 67:212-8. doi: 10.1016/ <lb/>j.jbior.2017.10.009 <lb/>293. Clark JD, Lin LL, Kriz RW, Ramesha CS, Sultzman LA, Lin AY, et al. A novel <lb/>arachidonic acid-selective cytosolic PLA2 contains a Ca(2+)-dependent <lb/>translocation domain with homology to PKC and GAP. Cell (1991) 65 <lb/>(6):1043-51. doi: 10.1016/0092-8674(91)90556-e <lb/>294. Hirabayashi T, Murayama T, Shimizu T. Regulatory mechanism and <lb/>physiological role of cytosolic phospholipase A2. Biol Pharm Bull (2004) <lb/>27(8):1168-73. doi: 10.1248/bpb.27.1168 <lb/>295. Strokin M, Sergeeva M, Reiser G. Docosahexaenoic acid and arachidonic acid <lb/>release in rat brain astrocytes is mediated by two separate isoforms of <lb/>phospholipase A2 and is differently regulated by cyclic AMP and Ca2+. Br J <lb/>Pharmacol (2003) 139(5):1014-22. doi: 10.1038/sj.bjp.0705326 <lb/>296. Cheon Y, Kim HW, Igarashi M, Modi HR, Chang L, Ma K, et al. Disturbed brain <lb/>phospholipid and docosahexaenoic acid metabolism in calcium-independent <lb/>phospholipase A(2)-VIA (iPLA(2)beta)-knockout mice. Biochim Biophys Acta <lb/>(2012) 1821(9):1278-86. doi: 10.1016/j.bbalip.2012.02.003 <lb/>297. Fonteh AN, Bass DA, Marshall LA, Seeds M, Samet JM, Chilton FH. <lb/>Evidence that secretory phospholipase A2 plays a role in arachidonic acid <lb/>release and eicosanoid biosynthesis by mast cells. J Immunol (1994) 152 <lb/>(11):5438-46. <lb/>298. Murase R, Sato H, Yamamoto K, Ushida A, Nishito Y, Ikeda K, et al. Group X <lb/>Secreted Phospholipase A2 Releases omega3 Polyunsaturated Fatty Acids, <lb/>Suppresses Colitis, and Promotes Sperm Fertility. J Biol Chem (2016) 291 <lb/>(13):6895-911. doi: 10.1074/jbc.M116.715672 <lb/>299. Murakami M. Lipoquality control by phospholipase A2 enzymes. Proc Jpn <lb/>Acad Ser B Phys Biol Sci (2017) 93(9):677-702. doi: 10.2183/pjab.93.043 <lb/>300. Needleman P, Moncada S, Bunting S, Vane JR, Hamberg M, Samuelsson B. <lb/>Identification of an enzyme in platelet microsomes which generates <lb/>thromboxane A2 from prostaglandin endoperoxides. Nature (1976) 261 <lb/>(5561):558-60. doi: 10.1038/261558a0 <lb/>301. Nusing R, Sauter G, Fehr P, Durmuller U, Kasper M, Gudat F, et al. <lb/>Localization of thromboxane synthase in human tissues by monoclonal <lb/>antibody Tu 300. Virchows Arch A Pathol Anat Histopathol (1992) 421 <lb/>(3):249-54. doi: 10.1007/BF01611182 <lb/>302. Miyata A, Hara S, Yokoyama C, Inoue H, Ullrich V, Tanabe T. Molecular <lb/>cloning and expression of human prostacyclin synthase. Biochem Biophys <lb/>Res Commun (1994) 200(3):1728-34. doi: 10.1006/bbrc.1994.1652 <lb/>303. Urade Y, Hayaishi O. Prostaglandin D synthase: structure and function. <lb/>Vitam Horm (2000) 58:89-120. doi: 10.1016/s0083-6729(00)58022-4 <lb/>304. Joo M, Sadikot RT. PGD synthase and PGD2 in immune resposne. Mediators <lb/>Inflamm (2012) 2012:503128. doi: 10.1155/2012/503128 <lb/>305. Ziganshin AU, Zefirova JT, Zefirova TP, Ziganshina LE, Hoyle CH, <lb/>Burnstock G. Potentiation of uterine effects of prostaglandin F2{alpha} by <lb/>adenosine 5&apos;-triphosphate. Obstet Gynecol (2005) 105(6):1429-36. <lb/>doi: 10.1097/01.AOG.0000161314.50808.dd <lb/>306. Sampey AV, Monrad S, Crofford LJ. Microsomal prostaglandin E synthase-1: <lb/>the inducible synthase for prostaglandin E2. Arthritis Res Ther (2005) 7 <lb/>(3):114-7. doi: 10.1186/ar1748 <lb/>307. Dennis EA, Norris PC. Eicosanoid storm in infection and inflammation. Nat <lb/>Rev Immunol (2015) 15(8):511-23. doi: 10.1038/nri3859 <lb/>308. Schieber A, Frank RW, Ghisla S. Purification and properties of prostaglandin 9-<lb/>ketoreductase from pig and human kidney. Identity with human carbonyl reductase. <lb/>Eur J Biochem (1992) 206(2):491-502. doi: 10.1111/j.1432-1033.1992.tb16952.x <lb/>309. Powell WS, Rokach J. Biosynthesis, biological effects, and receptors of <lb/>hydroxyeicosatetraenoic acids (HETEs) and oxoeicosatetraenoic acids <lb/>(oxo-ETEs) derived from arachidonic acid. Biochim Biophys Acta (2015) <lb/>1851(4):340-55. doi: 10.1016/j.bbalip.2014.10.008 <lb/>310. Powell WS, Gravel S, Halwani F. 5-oxo-6,8,11,14-eicosatetraenoic acid is a <lb/>potent stimulator of L-selectin shedding, surface expression of CD11b, actin <lb/>polymerization, and calcium mobilization in human eosinophils. Am J Respir <lb/>Cell Mol Biol (1999) 20(1):163-70. doi: 10.1165/ajrcmb.20.1.3141 <lb/>311. Hallstrand TS, Henderson WRJr. An update on the role of leukotrienes in <lb/>asthma. Curr Opin Allergy Clin Immunol (2010) 10(1):60-6. doi: 10.1097/ <lb/>ACI.0b013e32833489c3 <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Hajeyah et al. <lb/>Biosynthesis of Oxidized Lipids <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Endocrinology | www.frontiersin.org <lb/>November 2020 | Volume 11 | Article 591819 <lb/></note>

			<page>30 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>312. Capra V, Rovati GE, Mangano P, Buccellati C, Murphy RC, Sala A. <lb/>Transcellular biosynthesis of eicosanoid lipid mediators. Biochim Biophys <lb/>Acta (2015) 1851(4):377-82. doi: 10.1016/j.bbalip.2014.09.002 <lb/>313. Chandrasekharan JA, Sharma-Walia N. Lipoxins: nature&apos;s way to resolve <lb/>inflammation. J Inflammation Res (2015) 8:181-92. doi: 10.2147/JIR.S90380 <lb/>314. Martin TR, Pistorese BP, Chi EY, Goodman RB, Matthay MA. Effects of <lb/>leukotriene B4 in the human lung. Recruitment of neutrophils into the <lb/>alveolar spaces without a change in protein permeability. J Clin Invest (1989) <lb/>84(5):1609-19. doi: 10.1172/JCI114338 <lb/>315. Feltenmark S, Gautam N, Brunnstrom A, Griffiths W, Backman L, Edenius <lb/>C, et al. Eoxins are proinflammatory arachidonic acid metabolites produced <lb/>via the 15-lipoxygenase-1 pathway in human eosinophils and mast cells. Proc <lb/>Natl Acad Sci U.S.A. (2008) 105(2):680-5. doi: 10.1073/pnas.0710127105 <lb/>316. Claesson HE. On the biosynthesis and biological role of eoxins and 15-<lb/>lipoxygenase-1 in airway inflammation and Hodgkin lymphoma. <lb/>Prostaglandins Other Lipid Med (2009) 89(3-4):120-5. doi: 10.1016/ <lb/>j.prostaglandins.2008.12.003 <lb/>317. Nigam S, Patabhiraman S, Ciccoli R, Ishdorj G, Schwarz K, Petrucev B, et al. <lb/>The rat leukocyte-type 12-lipoxygenase exhibits an intrinsic hepoxilin A3 <lb/>synthase activity. J Biol Chem (2004) 279(28):29023-30. doi: 10.1074/ <lb/>jbc.M307576200 <lb/>318. Cronin A, Decker M, Arand M. Mammalian soluble epoxide hydrolase is <lb/>identical to liver hepoxilin hydrolase. J Lipid Res (2011) 52(4):712-9. <lb/>doi: 10.1194/jlr.M009639 <lb/>319. Pace-Asciak CR, Laneuville O, Su WG, Corey EJ, Gurevich N, Wu P, et al. A <lb/>glutathione conjugate of hepoxilin A3: formation and action in the rat central <lb/>nervous system. Proc Natl Acad Sci U.S.A. (1990) 87(8):3037-41. <lb/>doi: 10.1073/pnas.87.8.3037 <lb/>320. Mrsny RJ, Gewirtz AT, Siccardi D, Savidge T, Hurley BP, Madara JL, et al. <lb/>Identification of hepoxilin A3 in inflammatory events: a required role in <lb/>neutrophil migration across intestinal epithelia. Proc Natl Acad Sci U.S.A. <lb/>(2004) 101(19):7421-6. doi: 10.1073/pnas.0400832101 <lb/>321. Serhan CN, Clish CB, Brannon J, Colgan SP, Chiang N, Gronert K. Novel <lb/>functional sets of lipid-derived mediators with antiinflammatory actions <lb/>generated from omega-3 fatty acids via cyclooxygenase 2-nonsteroidal <lb/>antiinflammatory drugs and transcellular processing. J Exp Med (2000) <lb/>192(8):1197-204. doi: 10.1084/jem.192.8.1197 <lb/>322. Arita M, Clish CB, Serhan CN. The contributions of aspirin and microbial <lb/>oxygenase to the biosynthesis of anti-inflammatory resolvins: novel <lb/>oxygenase products from omega-3 polyunsaturated fatty acids. Biochem <lb/>Biophys Res Commun (2005) 338(1):149-57. doi: 10.1016/j.bbrc.2005.07.181 <lb/>323. Tjonahen E, Oh SF, Siegelman J, Elangovan S, Percarpio KB, Hong S, et al. <lb/>Resolvin E2: identification and anti-inflammatory actions: pivotal role of <lb/>human 5-lipoxygenase in resolvin E series biosynthesis. Chem Biol (2006) 13 <lb/>(11):1193-202. doi: 10.1016/j.chembiol.2006.09.011 <lb/>324. Oh SF, Vickery TW, Serhan CN. Chiral lipidomics of E-series resolvins: <lb/>aspirin and the biosynthesis of novel mediators. Biochim Biophys Acta (2011) <lb/>1811(11):737-47. doi: 10.1016/j.bbalip.2011.06.007 <lb/>325. Isobe Y, Arita M, Matsueda S, Iwamoto R, Fujihara T, Nakanishi H, et al. <lb/>Identification and structure determination of novel anti-inflammatory <lb/>mediator resolvin E3, 17,18-dihydroxyeicosapentaenoic acid. J Biol Chem <lb/>(2012) 287(13):10525-34. doi: 10.1074/jbc.M112.340612 <lb/>326. Serhan CN, Levy BD. Resolvins in inflammation: emergence of the pro-<lb/>resolving superfamily of mediators. J Clin Invest (2018) 128(7):2657-69. <lb/>doi: 10.1172/JCI97943 <lb/>327. Dalli J, Zhu M, Vlasenko NA, Deng B, Haeggstrom JZ, Petasis NA, et al. The <lb/>novel 13S,14S-epoxy-maresin is converted by human macrophages to <lb/>maresin 1 (MaR1), inhibits leukotriene A4 hydrolase (LTA4H), and shifts <lb/>macrophage phenotype. FASEB J (2013) 27(7):2573-83. doi: 10.1096/fj.13-<lb/>227728 <lb/>328. Aursnes M, Tungen JE, Colas RA, Vlasakov I, Dalli J, Serhan CN, et al. <lb/>Synthesis of the 16S,17S-Epoxyprotectin Intermediate in the Biosynthesis of <lb/>Protectins by Human Macrophages. J Nat Prod (2015) 78(12):2924-31. <lb/>doi: 10.1021/acs.jnatprod.5b00574 <lb/>329. Jouvene CC, Shay AE, Soens MA, Norris PC, Haeggstrom JZ, Serhan CN. <lb/>Biosynthetic metabolomes of cysteinyl-containing immunoresolvents. <lb/>FASEB J (2019) 33(12):13794-807. doi: 10.1096/fj.201902003R <lb/>330. Hammond VJ, O&apos;Donnell VB. Esterified eicosanoids: generation, <lb/>characterization and function. Biochim Biophys Acta (2012) 1818 <lb/>(10):2403-12. doi: 10.1016/j.bbamem.2011.12.013 <lb/>331. Maskrey BH, Bermudez-Fajardo A, Morgan AH, Stewart-Jones E, Dioszeghy V, <lb/>Taylor GW, et al. Activated platelets and monocytes generate four <lb/>hydroxyphosphatidylethanolamines via lipoxygenase. J Biol Chem (2007) <lb/>282(28):20151-63. doi: 10.1074/jbc.M611776200 <lb/>332. Morgan LT, Thomas CP, Kuhn H, O&apos;Donnell VB. Thrombin-activated <lb/>human platelets acutely generate oxidized docosahexaenoic-acid-<lb/>containing phospholipids via 12-lipoxygenase. Biochem J (2010) 431 <lb/>(1):141-8. doi: 10.1042/BJ20100415 <lb/>333. Thomas CP, Morgan LT, Maskrey BH, Murphy RC, Kuhn H, Hazen SL, et al. <lb/>Phospholipid-esterified eicosanoids are generated in agonist-activated <lb/>human platelets and enhance tissue factor-dependent thrombin <lb/>generation. J Biol Chem (2010) 285(10):6891-903. doi: 10.1074/ <lb/>jbc.M109.078428 <lb/>334. Aldrovandi M, Hammond VJ, Podmore H, Hornshaw M, Clark SR, Marnett <lb/>LJ, et al. Human platelets generate phospholipid-esterified prostaglandins via <lb/>cyclooxygenase-1 that are inhibited by low dose aspirin supplementation. <lb/>J Lipid Res (2013) 54(11):3085-97. doi: 10.1194/jlr.M041533 <lb/>335. Karara A, Dishman E, Falck JR, Capdevila JH. Endogenous <lb/>epoxyeicosatrienoyl-phospholipids. A novel class of cellular glycerolipids <lb/>containing epoxidized arachidonate moieties. J Biol Chem (1991) 266 <lb/>(12):7561-9. <lb/>336. O&apos;Donnell VB, Aldrovandi M, Murphy RC, Krnke G. Enzymatically <lb/>oxidized phospholipids assume center stage as essential regulators of <lb/>innate immunity and cell death. Sci Signaling (2019) 12(574):eaau2293. <lb/>doi: 10.1126/scisignal.aau2293 <lb/>337. Morgan AH, Dioszeghy V, Maskrey BH, Thomas CP, Clark SR, Mathie SA, <lb/>et al. Phosphatidylethanolamine-esterified eicosanoids in the mouse: tissue <lb/>localization and inflammation-dependent formation in Th-2 disease. J Biol <lb/>Chem (2009) 284(32):21185-91. doi: 10.1074/jbc.M109.021634 <lb/>338. Liu GY, Moon SH, Jenkins CM, Sims HF, Guan S, Gross RW. Synthesis of <lb/>oxidized phospholipids by sn-1 acyltransferase using 2-15-HETE <lb/>lysophospholipids. J Biol Chem (2019) 294(26):10146-59. doi: 10.1074/ <lb/>jbc.RA119.008766 <lb/>339. Jenkins CM, Yang K, Liu G, Moon SH, Dilthey BG, Gross RW. Cytochrome c <lb/>is an oxidative stress-activated plasmalogenase that cleaves plasmenylcholine <lb/>and plasmenylethanolamine at the sn-1 vinyl ether linkage. J Biol Chem <lb/>(2018) 293(22):8693-709. doi: 10.1074/jbc.RA117.001629 <lb/>340. Schroepfer GJJr. Oxysterols: modulators of cholesterol metabolism and other <lb/>processes. Physiol Rev (2000) 80(1):361-554. doi: 10.1152/physrev.2000.80.1.361 <lb/>341. Bjorkhem I, Andersson U, Ellis E, Alvelius G, Ellegard L, Diczfalusy U, et al. <lb/>From brain to bile. Evidence that conjugation and omega-hydroxylation are <lb/>important for elimination of 24S-hydroxycholesterol (cerebrosterol) in <lb/>humans. J Biol Chem (2001) 276(40):37004-10. doi: 10.1074/ <lb/>jbc.M103828200 <lb/>342. Tuckey RC, Cameron KJ. Catalytic properties of cytochrome P-450scc <lb/>purified from the human placenta: comparison to bovine cytochrome P-<lb/>450scc. Biochim Biophys Acta (1993) 1163(2):185-94. doi: 10.1016/0167-<lb/>4838(93)90180-y <lb/>343. Mast N, Annalora AJ, Lodowski DT, Palczewski K, Stout CD, Pikuleva IA. <lb/>Structural basis for three-step sequential catalysis by the cholesterol side <lb/>chain cleavage enzyme CYP11A1. J Biol Chem (2011) 286(7):5607-13. <lb/>doi: 10.1074/jbc.M110.188433 <lb/>344. Lund EG, Kerr TA, Sakai J, Li WP, Russell DW. cDNA cloning of mouse and <lb/>human cholesterol 25-hydroxylases, polytopic membrane proteins that <lb/>synthesize a potent oxysterol regulator of lipid metabolism. J Biol Chem <lb/>(1998) 273(51):34316-27. doi: 10.1074/jbc.273.51.34316 <lb/>345. Blanc M, Hsieh WY, Robertson KA, Kropp KA, Forster T, Shui G, et al. The <lb/>transcription factor STAT-1 couples macrophage synthesis of 25-<lb/>hydroxycholesterol to the interferon antiviral response. Immunity (2013) <lb/>38(1):106-18. doi: 10.1016/j.immuni.2012.11.004 <lb/>346. Bauman DR, Bitmansour AD, McDonald JG, Thompson BM, Liang G, <lb/>Russell DW. 25-Hydroxycholesterol secreted by macrophages in response to <lb/>Toll-like receptor activation suppresses immunoglobulin A production. Proc <lb/>Natl Acad Sci U S A (2009) 106(39):16764-9. doi: 10.1073/pnas.0909142106 <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Hajeyah et al. <lb/>Biosynthesis of Oxidized Lipids <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Endocrinology | www.frontiersin.org <lb/>November 2020 | Volume 11 | Article 591819 <lb/></note>

			<page>31 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>347. McDonald JG, Russell DW. Editorial: 25-Hydroxycholesterol: a new life in <lb/>immunology. J Leukoc Biol (2010) 88(6):1071-2. doi: 10.1189/jlb.0710418 <lb/>348. Liu SY, Aliyari R, Chikere K, Li G, Marsden MD, Smith JK, et al. Interferon-<lb/>inducible cholesterol-25-hydroxylase broadly inhibits viral entry by <lb/>production of 25-hydroxycholesterol. Immunity (2013) 38(1):92-105. <lb/>doi: 10.1016/j.immuni.2012.11.005 <lb/>349. Hannedouche S, Zhang J, Yi T, Shen W, Nguyen D, Pereira JP, et al. <lb/>Oxysterols direct immune cell migration via EBI2. Nature (2011) 475 <lb/>(7357):524-7. doi: 10.1038/nature10280 <lb/>350. Liu C, Yang XV, Wu J, Kuei C, Mani NS, Zhang L, et al. Oxysterols direct B-<lb/>cell migration through EBI2. Nature (2011) 475(7357):519-23. doi: 10.1038/ <lb/>nature10226 <lb/>351. Bodin K, Bretillon L, Aden Y, Bertilsson L, Broome U, Einarsson C, et al. <lb/>Antiepileptic drugs increase plasma levels of 4beta-hydroxycholesterol in <lb/>humans: evidence for involvement of cytochrome P450 3A4. J Biol Chem <lb/>(2001) 276(42):38685-9. doi: 10.1074/jbc.M105127200 <lb/>352. Heverin M, Meaney S, Brafman A, Shafir M, Olin M, Shafaati M, et al. Studies <lb/>on the cholesterol-free mouse: strong activation of LXR-regulated hepatic <lb/>genes when replacing cholesterol with desmosterol. Arterioscler Thromb Vasc <lb/>Biol (2007) 27(10):2191-7. doi: 10.1161/ATVBAHA.107.149823 <lb/>353. Pandak WM, Kakiyama G. The acidic pathway of bile acid synthesis: Not just <lb/>an alternative pathway(). Liver Res (2019) 3(2):88-98. doi: 10.1016/ <lb/>j.livres.2019.05.001 <lb/>354. Griffiths WJ, Yutuc E, Abdel-Khalik J, Crick PJ, Hearn T, Dickson A, et al. <lb/>Metabolism of non-enzymatically derived oxysterols: Clues from sterol <lb/>metabolic disorders. Free Radic Biol Med (2019) 144:124-33. doi: 10.1016/ <lb/>j.freeradbiomed.2019.04.020 <lb/>355. Abdel-Khalik J, Crick PJ, Yutuc E, DeBarber AE, Duell PB, Steiner RD, et al. <lb/>Identification of 7alpha,24-dihydroxy-3-oxocholest-4-en-26-oic and <lb/>7alpha,25-dihydroxy-3-oxocholest-4-en-26-oic acids in human <lb/>cerebrospinal fluid and plasma. Biochimie (2018) 153:86-98. doi: 10.1016/ <lb/>j.biochi.2018.06.020 <lb/>356. Vaz FM, Ferdinandusse S. Bile acid analysis in human disorders of bile acid <lb/>biosynthesis. Mol Aspects Med (2017) 56:10-24. doi: 10.1016/j.mam.2017.03.003 <lb/>357. Mazzacuva F, Mills P, Mills K, Camuzeaux S, Gissen P, Nicoli ER, et al. <lb/>Identification of novel bile acids as biomarkers for the early diagnosis of <lb/>Niemann-Pick C disease. FEBS Lett (2016) 590(11):1651-62. doi: 10.1002/ <lb/>1873-3468.12196 <lb/>358. Jiang X, Sidhu R, Mydock-McGrane L, Hsu FF, Covey DF, Scherrer DE, et al. <lb/>Development of a bile acid-based newborn screen for Niemann-Pick disease <lb/>type C. Sci Transl Med (2016) 8(337):337ra63. doi: 10.1126/scitranslmed. <lb/>aaf2326 <lb/>359. Setchell KD, Schwarz M, O&apos;Connell NC, Lund EG, Davis DL, Lathe R, et al. <lb/>Identification of a new inborn error in bile acid synthesis: mutation of the <lb/>oxysterol 7alpha-hydroxylase gene causes severe neonatal liver disease. J Clin <lb/>Invest (1998) 102(9):1690-703. doi: 10.1172/JCI2962 <lb/>360. Sjvall J, Griffiths WJ, Setchell KD, Mano N, Goto J. Analysis of Bile Acids. <lb/>In: H Makin and D Gower, editors. Steroid Analysis. Dordrecht: Springer <lb/>(2010). p. 837-966. doi: 10.1023/b135931_10 <lb/>361. Axelson M, Sjovall J. Potential bile acid precursors in plasma-possible <lb/>indicators of biosynthetic pathways to cholic and chenodeoxycholic acids <lb/>in man. J Steroid Biochem (1990) 36(6):631-40. doi: 10.1016/0022-4731(90) <lb/>90182-R <lb/>362. Rose KA, Stapleton G, Dott K, Kieny MP, Best R, Schwarz M, et al. Cyp7b, a <lb/>novel brain cytochrome P450, catalyzes the synthesis of neurosteroids <lb/>7alpha-hydroxy dehydroepiandrosterone and 7alpha-hydroxy <lb/>pregnenolone. Proc Natl Acad Sci U.S.A. (1997) 94(10):4925-30. doi: <lb/>10.1073/pnas.94.10.4925 <lb/>363. Schwarz M, Lund EG, Russell DW. Two 7 alpha-hydroxylase enzymes in bile <lb/>acid biosynthesis. Curr Opin Lipidol (1998) 9(2):113-8. doi: 10.1097/ <lb/>00041433-199804000-00006 <lb/>364. Shackleton CH. Role of a disordered steroid metabolome in the elucidation <lb/>of sterol and steroid biosynthesis. Lipids (2012) 47(1):1-12. doi: 10.1007/ <lb/>s11745-011-3605-6 <lb/>365. Andrew R. Clinical measurement of steroid metabolism. Best Pract Res Clin <lb/>Endocrinol Metab (2001) 15(1):1-16. doi: 10.1053/beem.2001.0116 <lb/>366. Baulieu EE, Robel P, Schumacher M. Neurosteroids: beginning of the story. <lb/>Int Rev Neurobiol (2001) 46:1-32. doi: 10.1016/s0074-7742(01)46057-0 <lb/>367. Schumacher M, Guennoun R, Mattern C, Oudinet JP, Labombarda F, De <lb/>Nicola AF, et al. Analytical challenges for measuring steroid responses to <lb/>stress, neurodegeneration and injury in the central nervous system. Steroids <lb/>(2015) 103:42-57. doi: 10.1016/j.steroids.2015.08.013 <lb/>368. Storbeck KH, Schiffer L, Baranowski ES, Chortis V, Prete A, Barnard L, et al. <lb/>Steroid Metabolome Analysis in Disorders of Adrenal Steroid Biosynthesis <lb/>and Metabolism. Endocr Rev (2019) 40(6):1605-25. doi: 10.1210/er.2018-<lb/>00262 <lb/>369. Schiffer L, Barnard L, Baranowski ES, Gilligan LC, Taylor AE, Arlt W, et al. <lb/>Human steroid biosynthesis, metabolism and excretion are differentially <lb/>reflected by serum and urine steroid metabolomes: A comprehensive review. <lb/>J Steroid Biochem Mol Biol (2019) 194:105439. doi: 10.1016/ <lb/>j.jsbmb.2019.105439 <lb/>370. Krone N, Hughes BA, Lavery GG, Stewart PM, Arlt W, Shackleton CH. Gas <lb/>chromatography/mass spectrometry (GC/MS) remains a pre-eminent <lb/>discovery tool in clinical steroid investigations even in the era of fast liquid <lb/>chromatography tandem mass spectrometry (LC/MS/MS). J Steroid Biochem <lb/>Mol Biol (2010) 121(3-5):496-504. doi: 10.1016/j.jsbmb.2010.04.010 <lb/></listBibl>

			<div type="annex">Conflict of Interest: The authors declare that the research was conducted in the <lb/>absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a <lb/>potential conflict of interest. <lb/></div>

			<front>Copyright  2020 Hajeyah, Griffiths, Wang, Finch and O&apos;Donnell. This is an open-<lb/>access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution <lb/>License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, <lb/>provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner(s) are credited and that the <lb/>original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic <lb/>practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with <lb/>these terms. <lb/></front>

			<note place="headnote">Hajeyah et al. <lb/>Biosynthesis of Oxidized Lipids <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Endocrinology | www.frontiersin.org <lb/>November 2020 | Volume 11 | Article 591819 <lb/></note>

			<page>32 </page>


	</text>
</tei>