<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>Nonclassical antagonism between human lysozyme and <lb/>AMPs against Pseudomonas aeruginosa <lb/>Ian Blumenthal 1, *, Lydia R. Davis 1 , Chet M. Berman 1 and Karl E. Griswold 1,2 <lb/>1 Thayer School of Engineering, Dartmouth, Hanover, NH, USA <lb/>2 Lyticon LLC, Lebanon, NH, USA <lb/>Keywords <lb/>lysozyme; antimicrobial peptide; synergy; <lb/>antagonism; antibiotic-resistant; <lb/>Pseudomonas aeruginosa <lb/>Correspondence <lb/>K. E. Griswold, Thayer School of <lb/>Engineering, Dartmouth, Hanover, 14 <lb/>Engineering Dr., Hanover, NH 03755, USA <lb/>Tel: 1-603-646-2127 <lb/>E-mail: karl.e.griswold@dartmouth.edu <lb/>* Present address: University of <lb/>Washington, Seattle, WA, USA <lb/>(Received 23 November 2020, revised 25 <lb/>December 2020, accepted 14 January 2021) <lb/>doi:10.1002/2211-5463.13094 <lb/>Edited by Pierre Cosson <lb/></front>

			<body>Combinations of human lysozyme (hLYS) and antimicrobial peptides <lb/>(AMPs) are known to exhibit either additive or synergistic activity, and as <lb/>a result, they have therapeutic potential for persistent and antibiotic-resis-<lb/>tant infections. We examined hLYS activity against Pseudomonas aerugi-<lb/>nosa when combined with six different AMPs. In contrast to prior reports, <lb/>we discovered that some therapeutically relevant AMPs manifest striking <lb/>antagonistic interactions with hLYS across particular concentration ranges. <lb/>We further found that the synthetic AMP Tet009 can inhibit hLYS-medi-<lb/>ated bacterial lysis. To the best of our knowledge, these results represent <lb/>the first observations of antagonism between hLYS and AMPs, and they <lb/>advise that future development of lytic enzyme and AMP combination <lb/>therapies considers the potential for antagonistic interactions. <lb/>Antibiotic-resistant pathogens such as Pseudomonas <lb/>aeruginosa pose a serious and growing threat to <lb/>human health [1]. P. aeruginosa is an opportunistic <lb/>Gram-negative bacterium that can infect numerous <lb/>tissues and organs [2,3]. It is the dominant pathogen <lb/>associated with cystic fibrosis, a genetic disorder in <lb/>which patients suffer from treatment-refractory lung <lb/>infections that typically lead to respiratory failure [4]. <lb/>More generally, P. aeruginosa encodes a diverse array <lb/>of countermeasures against conventional antibacterial <lb/>chemotherapies, and it can rapidly develop resis-<lb/>tance to standard treatment regimens [5,6]. Thus, <lb/>there is an urgent need to develop novel antibacte-<lb/>rial agents to more effectively combat P. aeruginosa <lb/>[7,8]. <lb/>Bacteriolytic enzymes, such as human lysozyme <lb/>(hLYS), have drawn long-standing interest as potential <lb/>treatments for antibiotic-resistant bacteria. These <lb/>agents function by effecting bacterial lysis via catalytic <lb/>hydrolysis of cell wall peptidoglycan, and they are at <lb/>the forefront of next-generation antibiotic development <lb/>[9]. While most studies of bacteriolytic enzymes focus <lb/>on Gram-positive pathogens, there is growing interest <lb/>in anti-Gram-negative enzymes [10,11], including <lb/>hLYS [12-15]. Importantly, however, the outer mem-<lb/>brane of Gram-negative bacteria shields the underlying <lb/>peptidoglycan from ready access by lytic enzymes, and <lb/>enzyme-mediated lysis of Gram-negative bacteria <lb/>therefore necessitates penetrating this outer membrane <lb/>barrier. <lb/></body>

			<front>Abbreviations <lb/>hLYS, human lysozyme; AMP, antimicrobial peptide; PTG1, protegrin 1 AMP; hBD3, human beta defensin 3 AMP; DT, dextrose/tris <lb/>screening buffer; FIC, fractional inhibitory concentration; FICI, fractional inhibitory concentration index; V max , maximum reaction velocity. <lb/>705 <lb/>FEBS Open Bio 11 (2021) 705-713 ª 2021 The Authors. FEBS Open Bio published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of <lb/>Federation of European Biochemical Societies. <lb/>This is an open access article under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits use, <lb/>distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. <lb/></front>

			<body>Antimicrobial peptides (AMPs) are short peptides <lb/>with diverse secondary structure that, along with hLYS, <lb/>comprise important molecular components of animal <lb/>innate immunity. AMPs represent another attractive <lb/>source of antibacterial agents [16-18], due in part to <lb/>their unique mode of action: membrane disruption. A <lb/>well-established body of literature has found antibacte-<lb/>rial synergy between hLYS and most AMPs (Table S1), <lb/>with the remainder of tested combinations exhibiting <lb/>additive interactions. Thus, combinations of hLYS and <lb/>AMPs offer a promising new paradigm for treating <lb/>antibiotic-resistant infections, particularly those caused <lb/>by Gram-negative pathogens. Here, we evaluated a <lb/>small panel of six AMPs combined with hLYS, and in <lb/>contrast to all prior reports, we found that at least two <lb/>of these combinations exhibited striking antagonistic <lb/>activity across specific concentration ranges. <lb/>Materials and methods <lb/>Bacterial strains and antimicrobial agents <lb/>The mucoid bioluminescent P. aeruginosa strain Xen05 was <lb/>purchased from Caliper life Sciences, Inc. The nonmucoid bio-<lb/>luminescent strain H1001 was the kind gift of Robert Hancock <lb/>(University of British Columbia, Vancouver, BC, Canada). <lb/>Both strains were stored as glycerol stocks at À80 °C. Recom-<lb/>binant hLYS and freeze-dried Micrococcus luteus were pur-<lb/>chased from Sigma Millipore (Burlington, MA, USA). <lb/>Protegrin 1 AMP (PTG1) and HB71 peptides (&gt; 95% purity) <lb/>were obtained from Peptide 2.0. LL-37, Melittin, and Tet009 <lb/>peptides (&gt; 95% purity) were purchased from GenScript (Pis-<lb/>cataway, NJ, USA). Human beta defensin 3 AMP (hBD3) pep-<lb/>tide was purchased from AnaSpec. Peptide stock solutions <lb/>were stored at À20 °C. All other reagents and materials were <lb/>purchased from Fisher Scientific (Waltham, MA, USA). <lb/>Antibacterial EC 50 assay <lb/>We analyzed the dose-response potency of each AMP <lb/>against both strains via a well-validated luminescence assay <lb/>[19]. Hundred microlitre of exponential phase cells (5 9 10 6 <lb/>cells/mL) in dextrose/tris (DT) buffer (20 mM dextrose, <lb/>100 mM Tris, pH 7.4) were incubated with a 1 : 2 dilution <lb/>series of each AMP in white, flat-bottomed, 96-well plates at <lb/>37 °C for 4 h. Culture luminescence was then quantified by <lb/>imaging with a CCD camera (Bio-Rad ChemiDoc XRS Sys-<lb/>tem, Hercules, CA, USA). Measurements were normalized <lb/>to the no-treatment controls on the same plate, and potency <lb/>was quantified by a 3-parameter logistic regression of lumi-<lb/>nescence versus AMP concentration, yielding EC 50 values <lb/>(Fig. S1). Importantly, the luminescence of these P. aerugi-<lb/>nosa strains is known to correlate with bacterial viability <lb/>[20]. Assays were done in technical triplicate or quadrupli-<lb/>cate and repeated at least twice. <lb/>Luminescence checkerboard assay <lb/>Checkerboard, or 2-D MIC, assays were performed analo-<lb/>gous to the single agent dose-response studies above, <lb/>except that 1 : 2 serial dilutions of hLYS were made across <lb/>the rows of a 96-well plate, and 1 : 2 serial dilutions of the <lb/>AMP were made down the columns of the same plate, such <lb/>that each well contained a unique concentration mixture of <lb/>the two agents. Controls without treatment (growth con-<lb/>trol) and without bacteria (sterility control) were included <lb/>on all plates. Assays were repeated as three independent tri-<lb/>als (biological replicates), and results are the average of all <lb/>measurements. <lb/>To quantify antibacterial interactions, fractional inhibi-<lb/>tory concentrations (FIC) and FIC index values (FICI) <lb/>were calculated as described elsewhere [21], though in this <lb/>case using EC 50 values in place of conventional growth/no <lb/>growth visual observations. Briefly, the FIC for one agent <lb/>is the ratio of its EC 50 value as a standalone treatment <lb/>(denominator) and the concentration of that agent yielding <lb/>a 50% luminescence reduction in the presence of a fixed <lb/>concentration of a second agent (numerator). The corre-<lb/>sponding FIC values for the two agents in each row and <lb/>column, respectively, of a checkerboard plate may be <lb/>summed, and the lowest FIC sum on the plate is desig-<lb/>nated the FICI. <lb/>Lysozyme kinetic assays with Micrococcus luteus <lb/>hLYS lysis rates for M. luteus were measured using an adap-<lb/>tation of our previously reported methods [22]. Briefly, lytic <lb/>rates were quantified in 96-well plates by tracking M. luteus <lb/>turbidity reduction as a function of time. Reactions, run in <lb/>DT buffer, contained 200 ngÁmL À1 hLYS and freeze-dried <lb/>M. luteus bacterial substrate at concentrations ranging from <lb/>50 to 500 µgÁmL À1 . Initial reaction rates were determined <lb/>from slopes of the linear portions of time course data, and <lb/>pseudo-Michaelis-Menten kinetics (i.e., determination of <lb/>V max and K m kinetic parameters) were analyzed by nonlinear <lb/>regression of initial rates versus M. luteus substrate concen-<lb/>tration. To assess inhibition, Tet009 was added to reactions <lb/>at concentrations ranging from 0 to 200 ngÁmL À1 . Impor-<lb/>tantly, by using freeze-dried M. luteus as a reporter sub-<lb/>strate, we selectivity quantified hLYS-mediated bacteriolysis <lb/>independent of Tet009-mediated membrane disruption and <lb/>cell killing. All reactions were run in triplicate, and the maxi-<lb/>mum reaction velocity (V max ) is reported as the hyperbolic <lb/>asymptote and 95% confidence interval for the best-fit <lb/>regression line to a given data set. <lb/>Results <lb/>Here we sought to evaluate antipseudomonal interac-<lb/>tions between hLYS and six different AMPs, testing <lb/>combinations against mucoid Xen05 and nonmucoid <lb/></body>

			<page>706 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">FEBS Open Bio 11 (2021) 705-713 ª 2021 The Authors. FEBS Open Bio published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of <lb/>Federation of European Biochemical Societies. <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">Nonclassical antagonism between AMPs and Lysozyme <lb/>I. Blumenthal et al. <lb/></note>

			<body>H1001 P. aeruginosa strains. Both Xen05 and H1001 <lb/>have been engineered for bioluminescence via a <lb/>genomically inserted Photorhabdus luminescens lux <lb/>operon, and each has been validated as a tool for <lb/>screening and evaluation of antibacterial agents, <lb/>including biologics such as AMPs [19,23,24]. Impor-<lb/>tantly, the luminescence of these engineered strains has <lb/>been shown to correlate with bacterial viability [20]. <lb/>Determination of single agent potency: EC 50 <lb/>assays <lb/>Our small panel of AMPs were derived from diverse <lb/>origins (human, pig, bee, and purely synthetic), with <lb/>two representatives each from the a-helical, b-sheet, <lb/>and extended AMP structural classes (Table 1). We <lb/>first analyzed dose-response potency of each AMP <lb/>against both strains via a luminescence assay [19] <lb/>(Fig. S1). Most AMPs exhibited similar EC 50 values <lb/>for the mucoid and nonmucoid strains (Table 1), and <lb/>these values were largely consistent with previously <lb/>published MIC values for each peptide [23-33]. <lb/>Evaluation of antibacterial interactions: 2-<lb/>dimensional MIC or &apos;checkerboard&apos; assays <lb/>Based on the EC 50 values of AMP monotherapies, we <lb/>designed checkerboard assays [21] wherein antibacte-<lb/>rial interactions between hLYS and each AMP were <lb/>quantified. Classical drug interactions such as synergy, <lb/>additivity, or antagonism manifest characteristic trends <lb/>across a given checkerboard assay plate, where <lb/>FICI &lt; 0.5 is defined as synergy, 0.5 ≤ FICI &lt; 4 is <lb/>defined as additivity, and FICI ≥ 4 is defined as antag-<lb/>onism [34]. Nonclassical interactions, as observed in <lb/>some of our checkerboard results, might include a con-<lb/>centration-dependent switch from synergy (or additiv-<lb/>ity) to antagonism. In extreme cases, we observed <lb/>inversion of the dose-response curves for specific com-<lb/>binations and concentration ranges of our antibacterial <lb/>agents, as discussed below. <lb/>Classical additive or synergistic activities were <lb/>observed for combinations of hLYS with PTG1, <lb/>HBD3, LL37, and melittin (Table 2), although the <lb/>interactions were not always consistent between <lb/>mucoid and nonmucoid strains. The porcine b-sheet <lb/>AMP PTG1 exhibited synergy with hLYS against both <lb/>P. aeruginosa isolates, similar to prior literature <lb/>reports (Figs 1A and 2A) [35]. The human b-sheet <lb/>AMP HBD3 exhibited additivity with hLYS against <lb/>the mucoid strain Xen05 (Fig. 1B) and synergy with <lb/>hLYS against the nonmucoid strain H1001 (Fig. 2B). <lb/>The human a-helical AMP LL37 exhibited additive <lb/>Table 1. Antimicrobial agents used in this study. <lb/>Agent <lb/>Origin <lb/>Structure <lb/>Net charge <lb/>EC <lb/>50 (lgÁmL À1 <lb/>) <lb/>Sequence <lb/>Source <lb/>Reference <lb/>Xen05 <lb/>H1001 <lb/>hLYS <lb/>Human <lb/>Mixed <lb/>+5 <lb/>990 <lb/>890 <lb/>UniProt-B2R4C5 <lb/>Sigma Millipore (L1667) <lb/>[12] <lb/>LL37 <lb/>Human <lb/>a helix <lb/>+6 <lb/>5.0 <lb/>6.1 <lb/>LLGDFFRKSKEKIGKEFKRIVQRIKDFLRNLVPRTES <lb/>GenScript (&gt; 95%) <lb/>[29] <lb/>hBD3 <lb/>Human <lb/>b sheet <lb/>+11 <lb/>6.0 <lb/>7.0 <lb/>GIINTLQKYYCRVRGGRCAVLSCLPKEEQIGKCSTRGRKCCRRKK <lb/>AnaSpec (AS-60741) <lb/>[27] <lb/>PTG-1 <lb/>Pig <lb/>b sheet <lb/>+6 <lb/>1.1 <lb/>1.7 <lb/>RGGRLCYCRRRFCVCVGR <lb/>Peptide 2.0 (&gt; 95%) <lb/>[25] <lb/>HB71 <lb/>Synthetic <lb/>Extended <lb/>+9 <lb/>1.6 <lb/>2.6 <lb/>FAKKLAKKLKKLAKKLAK <lb/>Peptide 2.0 (&gt; 95%) <lb/>[33] <lb/>Melittin <lb/>Bee <lb/>a helix <lb/>+5 <lb/>4.5 <lb/>3.5 <lb/>GIGAVLKVLTTGLPALISWIKRKRQQ <lb/>GenScript (&gt; 95%) <lb/>[31] <lb/>Tet009 <lb/>Synthetic <lb/>Extended <lb/>+6 <lb/>1.5 <lb/>2.7 <lb/>RRWKIVVIRWRR <lb/>GenScript (&gt; 95%) <lb/>[24] <lb/></body>

			<page>707 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">FEBS Open Bio 11 (2021) 705-713 ª 2021 The Authors. FEBS Open Bio published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of <lb/>Federation of European Biochemical Societies. <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">I. Blumenthal et al. <lb/>Nonclassical antagonism between AMPs and Lysozyme <lb/></note>

			<body>hLYS interactions against both Xen05 and H1001 <lb/>strains (Figs 1C and 2C), although FICI values were <lb/>borderline synergistic (Table 2). Lastly, the a-helical <lb/>bee venom peptide melittin demonstrated hLYS syn-<lb/>ergy against the nonmucoid strain H1001 (Fig. 2D). <lb/>In the remaining hLYS-AMP combinations, we <lb/>observed nonclassical behavior of differing types. <lb/>Against mucoid Xen05, the hLYS dose response at <lb/>high melittin concentrations was inverted, showing <lb/>greater luminescence at higher concentrations of hLYS <lb/>(Fig. 1D). It should be noted, however, that all wells <lb/>exhibited relatively low luminescence at high melittin <lb/>concentrations, indicative of strong overall antibacte-<lb/>rial activity. Against strain H1001, the extended syn-<lb/>thetic peptide HB71 caused a similar inversion of <lb/>hLYS dose response at high AMP concentrations, <lb/>whereas the dose response for HB71 itself was largely <lb/>flattened at intermediate luminescence values when <lb/>combined with high hLYS concentrations (Fig. 2E). <lb/>For mucoid strain Xen05, the hLYS dose response <lb/>was flattened or even inverted at high HB71 concentra-<lb/>tions, though similar to melittin combinations, the <lb/>bacterial luminescence was generally low at high HB71 <lb/>concentrations (Fig. 1E). Perhaps most striking, at <lb/>high hLYS concentrations the Tet009 dose response <lb/>was inverted with both strains (Figs 1F and 2F), where <lb/>the effect was most pronounced with nonmucoid <lb/>H1001. Similarly, we observed that the hLYS dose <lb/>response against both strains was inverted at high <lb/>Tet009 concentrations. As presented here, the various <lb/>inverted dose-response curves are, to the best of our <lb/>knowledge, the first description of nonclassical in vitro <lb/>interactions between hLYS and AMPs. Although this <lb/>panel of AMPs is too small to draw definitive conclu-<lb/>sions, we noted that the AMP-LYS interactions <lb/>loosely correlated with AMP secondary structure: the <lb/>two b-sheet peptides generally exhibited hLYS synergy, <lb/>whereas the two extended peptides generally mani-<lb/>fested nonclassical antagonistic activity. Notably, our <lb/>checkerboard results show that Tet009 and hLYS are <lb/>mutually antagonistic, each inhibiting the other but <lb/>only at higher concentrations. <lb/>Analyzing Tet009 inhibition of hLYS catalytic <lb/>activity <lb/>The strong dose-response inversion observed in the <lb/>hLYS and Tet009 checkerboard assays suggested that <lb/>Tet009 could be interfering with hLYS-mediated pep-<lb/>tidoglycan hydrolysis. To further probe this hypothe-<lb/>sis, we employed a kinetic bacteriolysis assay using <lb/>nonviable M. luteus cells as substrate [22]. Initial <lb/>reaction rates were determined from slopes of the <lb/>linear portions of time course data, and pseudo-<lb/>Michaelis-Menten kinetics <lb/>were <lb/>analyzed by <lb/>nonlinear regression of initial rates versus M. luteus <lb/>substrate concentration (Fig. S2). At Tet009 concen-<lb/>trations from 0.02 to 12.5 ngÁmL À1 , hLYS lytic rates <lb/>(quantified as apparent V max ) accelerated, reaching a <lb/>maximum rate at 12.5 ngÁmL À1 AMP (Fig. 3). How-<lb/>ever, the effect was reversed at Tet009 concentrations <lb/>above 12.5 ngÁmL À1 , with the slowest apparent rate <lb/>at 200 ngÁmL À1 Tet009 (Fig. 3). While these experi-<lb/>ments do not conclusively distinguish between direct <lb/>Tet009 inhibition of hLYS catalysis and Tet009 com-<lb/>petition for hLYS binding sites on M. luteus cell <lb/>walls, the results do reinforce the observed nonclassi-<lb/>cal antagonism observed in the checkerboard assays. <lb/>Specifically, we found complementary activity of the <lb/>two agents up to a threshold Tet009 concentration <lb/>followed by a switch to antagonism above that <lb/>threshold. <lb/>Discussion <lb/>To the best of our knowledge, these results represent <lb/>the first observations of antagonism between hLYS <lb/>and AMPs. Fully assessing the broader significance of <lb/>these results, obtained in a screening medium, will <lb/>require further study. However, we note that similar <lb/>bioluminescence assays in DT buffer have been used <lb/>previously for screening and identification of AMP <lb/>therapeutic candidates [19,24,36]. Our results are there-<lb/>fore directly relevant to screening efforts aimed at <lb/>identifying AMP-enzyme combination therapies. Addi-<lb/>tionally, in a prior publication we made the unex-<lb/>pected observation that, in a murine model of acute <lb/>P. aeruginosa lung infection, Tet009 and hLYS combi-<lb/>nation therapy manifested a weak trend toward <lb/>reduced efficacy compared to hLYS monotherapy [37]. <lb/>Thus, antagonistic interactions may indeed be relevant <lb/>to in vivo environments. Notwithstanding the limita-<lb/>tions of the in vitro methods employed here, our <lb/>results advise that future development of lytic enzyme-<lb/>AMP combinations should carefully consider the <lb/>potential for antagonism. <lb/>Table 2. FICI for AMP-hLYS combinations. N.C., nonclassical <lb/>interaction. See Figs 1 and 2. <lb/>AMP <lb/>FICI Xen05 <lb/>FICI H1001 <lb/>PTG-1 <lb/>0.3 AE 0.2 <lb/>0.4 AE 0.1 <lb/>HBD3 <lb/>1.02 AE 0.09 <lb/>0.3 AE 0.3 <lb/>Melittin <lb/>N.C. <lb/>0.4 AE 0.2 <lb/>LL37 <lb/>0.5 AE 0.2 <lb/>0.5 AE 0.2 <lb/>HB71 <lb/>N.C. <lb/>N.C. <lb/>Tet009 <lb/>N.C. <lb/>N.C. <lb/></body>

			<page>708 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">FEBS Open Bio 11 (2021) 705-713 ª 2021 The Authors. FEBS Open Bio published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of <lb/>Federation of European Biochemical Societies. <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">Nonclassical antagonism between AMPs and Lysozyme <lb/>I. Blumenthal et al. <lb/></note>

			<body>4.5 <lb/>0.56 <lb/>0.07 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1 <lb/>1.5 <lb/>2550 <lb/>318.75 <lb/>39.84 <lb/>HB71 <lb/>Normalized Luminescence <lb/>hLYS <lb/>18 <lb/>2.25 <lb/>0.28 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1 <lb/>1.5 <lb/>2550 <lb/>318.75 <lb/>39.84 <lb/>hBD3 <lb/>Normalized Luminescence <lb/>hLYS <lb/>15 <lb/>1.88 <lb/>0.23 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1 <lb/>1.5 <lb/>2550 <lb/>318.75 <lb/>39.84 <lb/>LL37 <lb/>Normalized Luminescence <lb/>hLYS <lb/>15 <lb/>1.88 <lb/>0.23 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1 <lb/>1.5 <lb/>2550 <lb/>318.75 <lb/>39.84 <lb/>Meliƫn <lb/>Normalized Luminescence <lb/>hLYS <lb/>4 <lb/>0.50 <lb/>0.06 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1 <lb/>1.5 <lb/>2550 <lb/>318.75 <lb/>39.84 <lb/>PTG1 (μg•mL -1 ) <lb/>Normalized Luminescence <lb/>hLYS <lb/>(μg•mL -1 ) <lb/>(μg•mL -1 ) <lb/>(μg•mL -1 ) <lb/>(μg•mL -1 ) <lb/>(μg•mL -1 ) <lb/>(μg•mL -1 ) <lb/>(μg•mL -1 ) <lb/>(μg•mL -1 ) <lb/>(μg•mL -1 ) <lb/>(μg•mL -1 ) <lb/>(μg•mL -1 ) <lb/>4.5 <lb/>0.56 <lb/>0.07 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1 <lb/>1.5 <lb/>2550 <lb/>318.75 <lb/>39.84 <lb/>Tet009 <lb/>Normalized Luminescence <lb/>hLYS <lb/>A <lb/>B <lb/>C <lb/>D <lb/>E <lb/>F <lb/>Fig. 1. 2-D MIC assays (i.e., checkerboard assays) for hLYS and AMPs against mucoid P. aeruginosa strain Xen05. Peptides are (A) PTG1, <lb/>(B) HBD3, (C) LL37, (D) melittin, (E) HB71, and (F) Tet009. Bacterial viability reported as luminescence units, and values are normalized to <lb/>the luminescence of the no-treatment control well. Antimicrobial therapies typically exhibit a dose-response killing curve from low to high <lb/>concentrations, as seen for both PTG1 and hLYS in panel (A). In this study, noncanonical dose-response curves were observed for several <lb/>hLYS-AMP combinations, including (D) melittin, (E) HB71, and (F) Tet009. Shown in each panel are the mean values from three independent <lb/>experiments. <lb/></body>

			<page>709 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">FEBS Open Bio 11 (2021) 705-713 ª 2021 The Authors. FEBS Open Bio published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of <lb/>Federation of European Biochemical Societies. <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">I. Blumenthal et al. <lb/>Nonclassical antagonism between AMPs and Lysozyme <lb/></note>

			<body>7.8 <lb/>0.98 <lb/>0.12 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1 <lb/>1.5 <lb/>2700 <lb/>337.5 <lb/>42.19 <lb/>HB71 <lb/>Normalized Luminescence <lb/>hLYS <lb/>21 <lb/>5.25 <lb/>1.31 <lb/>0.33 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1 <lb/>1.5 <lb/>2700 <lb/>337.5 <lb/>42.19 <lb/>hBD3 <lb/>Normalized Luminescence <lb/>hLYS <lb/>18 <lb/>4.5 <lb/>1.13 <lb/>0.28 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1 <lb/>1.5 <lb/>2700 <lb/>337.5 <lb/>42.19 <lb/>LL37 <lb/>Normalized Luminescence <lb/>hLYS <lb/>15 <lb/>3.75 <lb/>0.94 <lb/>0.23 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1 <lb/>1.5 <lb/>2700 <lb/>337.5 <lb/>42.19 <lb/>Meliƫn <lb/>Normalized Luminescence <lb/>hLYS <lb/>8 <lb/>2 <lb/>0.50 <lb/>0.13 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1 <lb/>2700 <lb/>337.5 <lb/>42.19 <lb/>PTG-1 <lb/>Normalized Luminescence <lb/>hLYS <lb/>(μg•mL -1 ) <lb/>(μg•mL -1 ) <lb/>(μg•mL -1 ) <lb/>(μg•mL -1 ) <lb/>(μg•mL -1 ) <lb/>(μg•mL -1 ) <lb/>(μg•mL -1 ) <lb/>(μg•mL -1 ) <lb/>(μg•mL -1 ) <lb/>(μg•mL -1 ) <lb/>(μg•mL -1 ) <lb/>(μg•mL -1 ) <lb/>8 <lb/>2 <lb/>0.50 <lb/>0.13 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1 <lb/>2700 <lb/>337.5 <lb/>42.19 <lb/>Tet009 <lb/>Normalized Luminescence <lb/>hLYS <lb/>A <lb/>B <lb/>C <lb/>D <lb/>E <lb/>F <lb/>Fig. 2. 2-D MIC assays (i.e., checkerboard assays) for hLYS and AMPs against nonmucoid P. aeruginosa strain H1001. Peptides are (A) <lb/>PTG1, (B) HBD3, (C) LL37, (D) melittin, (E) HB71, and (F) Tet009. Bacterial viability is reported as luminescence units, and values are <lb/>normalized to the luminescence of the no-treatment control wells. Antimicrobial therapies typically exhibit a dose-response killing curve <lb/>from low to high concentrations, as seen for both PTG1 and hLYS in panel (A). In this study, noncanonical dose-response curves were <lb/>observed for several hLYS-AMP combinations, including (E) HB71 and (F) Tet009. Shown in each panel are the mean values from three <lb/>independent experiments. <lb/></body>

			<page>710 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">FEBS Open Bio 11 (2021) 705-713 ª 2021 The Authors. FEBS Open Bio published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of <lb/>Federation of European Biochemical Societies. <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">Nonclassical antagonism between AMPs and Lysozyme <lb/>I. Blumenthal et al. <lb/></note>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgements <lb/>This work was supported in part by the Dartmouth <lb/>Cystic Fibrosis Foundation Research Development <lb/>Program under grant STANTO19R0 and in part by <lb/>an award from the NIH National Institute of Allergy <lb/>and Infectious Diseases under award 1R21AI094391. <lb/>IB was supported by a Federal Work-Study Program. <lb/>LRD was supported by an internship under the Dart-<lb/>mouth E.E. Just Program. CMB was supported by <lb/>R01AI123372 from the NIH National Institute of <lb/>Allergy and Infectious Diseases. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Conflict of interest <lb/>KEG is a cofounder and member-manager of Lyticon <lb/>LLC, which holds a license for rights to engineered <lb/>lysozyme biotherapies. No other authors have a con-<lb/>flict of interest. Potential conflicts of interest for KEG <lb/>are under management at Dartmouth. The authors <lb/>declare that the work presented here is free of any <lb/>bias. <lb/></div>

			<div type="availability">Data Accessibility <lb/>All data will be made available by the corresponding <lb/>author upon reasonable request. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Author contributions <lb/>KEG and IB designed the experiments. IB conducted <lb/>the experiments. IB, LRD, CMB, and KEG analyzed <lb/>the data. LRD, CMB, and KEG wrote the manuscript. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>1 Cosgrove SE (2005) The relationship between <lb/>antimicrobial resistance and patient outcomes: <lb/>mortality, length of hospital stay, and health care costs. <lb/>Clin Infect Dis 42, S82-S89. <lb/>2 Bhagirath AY, Li Y, Somayajula D, Dadashi M, Badr <lb/>S and Duan K (2016) Cystic fibrosis lung environment <lb/>and Pseudomonas aeruginosa infection. BMC Pulm Med <lb/>16, 174. <lb/>3 Brandenburg KS Jr, Weaver AJ, Karna SLR, You T, <lb/>Chen P, Stryk SV, Qian L, Pineda U, Abercrombie JJ <lb/>and Leung KP (2019) Formation of Pseudomonas <lb/>aeruginosa biofilms in full-thickness scald burn wounds <lb/>in rats. Sci Rep 9, 13627. <lb/>4 Høiby N, Ciofu O and Bjarnsholt T (2010) <lb/>Pseudomonas aeruginosa biofilms in cystic fibrosis. <lb/>Future Microbiol 5, 1163-1674. <lb/>5 Klockgether J, Cramer N, Wiehlmann L, Davenport <lb/>CF and T€ ummler B (2011) Pseudomonas aeruginosa <lb/>genomic structure and diversity. Front Microbiol 2, 150. <lb/>6 Stover CK, Pham XQ, Erwin AL, Mizoguchi SD, <lb/>Warrener P, Hickey MJ, Brinkman FSL, Hufnagle WO, <lb/>Kowalik DJ, Lagrou M et al. (2000) Complete genome <lb/>sequence of Pseudomonas aeruginosa PA01, an <lb/>opportunistic pathogen. Nature 406, 959-964. <lb/>7 Lister PD, Wolter DJ and Hanson ND (2009) <lb/>Antibacterial-resistant Pseudomonas aeruginosa: clinical <lb/>impact and complex regulation of chromosomally <lb/>encoded resistance mechanisms. Clin Microbiol Rev 22, <lb/>582-610. <lb/>8 CDC (2019) Antibiotic Resistance Threats in the United <lb/>States. U.S. Department of Health and Human <lb/>Services, Atlanta, GA. <lb/>9 Wittekind M and Schuch R (2016) Cell wall hydrolases <lb/>and antibiotics: exploiting synergy to create efficacious <lb/>new antimicrobial treatments. Curr Opin Microbiol 33, <lb/>18-24. <lb/>10 Heselpoth RD, Euler CW, Schuch R and Fischetti VA <lb/>(2019) Lysocins: bioengineered antimicrobials that <lb/>deliver lysins across the outer membrane of gram-<lb/>negative bacteria. Antimicrob Agents Chemother 63, <lb/>e0034-19. <lb/></listBibl>

			<body>0 .02 1.56 12.5 50 200 <lb/>0.0000 <lb/>0.0002 <lb/>0.0004 <lb/>0.0006 <lb/>0.0008 <lb/>Tet009 (ng•mL -1 ) <lb/>V <lb/>max (ΔOD/sec) <lb/>Fig. 3. V max values from pseudo-Michaelis-Menten kinetic analysis <lb/>of hLYS lytic rates. V max values at different concentrations of <lb/>Tet009 AMP reveal a nonclassical inhibitory effect manifested only <lb/>at high Tet009 concentrations. All kinetic runs were evaluated in <lb/>triplicate and shown are the means and 95% confidence intervals <lb/>for V max , derived from the best curve fits. The hyperbolic curve fits <lb/>for all reactions were compared, and it was found that the V max <lb/>values differed significantly among the data sets (P &lt; 0.0001, extra <lb/>sum of squares F test). Initial rates from linear regression of time <lb/>course light scattering experiments at different substrate <lb/>concentrations are shown in Fig. S2, as are best-fit hyperbolas by <lb/>nonlinear regression. <lb/></body>

			<page>711 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">FEBS Open Bio 11 (2021) 705-713 ª 2021 The Authors. FEBS Open Bio published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of <lb/>Federation of European Biochemical Societies. <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">I. Blumenthal et al. <lb/>Nonclassical antagonism between AMPs and Lysozyme <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>11 Brier Y, Walmagh M, Puyenbroeck VV, Cornelissen A, <lb/>Cenens W, Aertsen A, Oliveira H, Azeredo J, Verween <lb/>G, Pirnay J-P et al. (2014) Engineered endolysin-based <lb/>&quot;Artilysins&quot; to combat multidrug-resistant gram-<lb/>negative pathogens. MBio 5, e01379-14. <lb/>12 Ragland SA and Criss AK (2017) From bacterial <lb/>killing to immune modulation: recent insights into the <lb/>functions of lysozyme. PLOS Pathog 13, e1006512. <lb/>13 Scanlon TC, Teneback CC, Gill A, Bement JL, Weiner <lb/>JA, Lamppa JW, Leclair LW and Griswold KE (2010) <lb/>Enhanced antimicrobial activity of engineered human <lb/>lysozyme. ACS Chem Biol 5, 809-818. <lb/>14 Teneback CC, Scanlon TC, Wargo MJ, Bement JL, <lb/>Griswold KE and Leclair LW (2013) Bioengineered <lb/>lysozyme reduces bacterial burden and inflammation in a <lb/>murine model of mucoid Pseudomonas aeruginosa lung <lb/>infection. Antimicrob Agents Chemother 57, 5559-5564. <lb/>15 Thallinger B, Prasetyo EN, Nyanhongo GS and <lb/>Guebitz GM (2013) Antimicrobial enzymes: an <lb/>emerging strategy to fight microbes and microbial <lb/>biofilms. Biotechnol J 8, 97-109. <lb/>16 Hancock REW and Diamond G (2000) The role of <lb/>cationic antimicrobial peptides in innate host defences. <lb/>Trends Microbiol 8, 402-410. <lb/>17 Mookherjee N and Hancock R (2007) Cationic host <lb/>defence peptides: innate immune regulatory peptides as <lb/>a novel approach for treating infections. Cell Mol Life <lb/>Sci 64, 922-933. <lb/>18 Ruden S, Rieder A, Chis Ster I, Schwartz T, Mikut R <lb/>and Hilpert K (2019) Synergy pattern of short cationic <lb/>antimicrobial peptides against multidrug-resistant <lb/>Pseudomonas aeruginosa. Front Microbiol 10, 2740. <lb/>19 Hilpert K and Hancock REW (2007) Use of <lb/>luminescent bacteria for rapid screening and <lb/>characterization of short cationic antimicrobial peptides <lb/>synthesized on cellulose using peptide array technology. <lb/>Nat Protoc 2, 1652-1660. <lb/>20 Hilpert K, Volkmer-Engert R, Walter T and Hancock <lb/>REW (2005) High-throughput generation of small <lb/>antibacterial peptides with improved activity. Nat <lb/>Biotechnol 23, 1008-1012. <lb/>21 Singh PK, Tack BF Jr, McCray PB and Welsh MJ <lb/>(2000) Synergistic and additive killing by antimicrobial <lb/>factors found in human airway surface liquid. Am J <lb/>Physiol Lung Cell Mol Physiol 279, L799-L805. <lb/>22 Gill A, Scanlon TC, Osipovitch DC, Madden DR and <lb/>Griswold KE (2011) Crystal structure of a charge <lb/>engineered human lysozyme having enhanced <lb/>bactericidal activity. PLoS One 6, e16788. <lb/>23 Bucki R, Leszczy nska K, Byfield FJ, Fein DE, Won E, <lb/>Cruz K, Namiot A, Kułakowska A, Namiot Z, Savage <lb/>PB et al. (2010) Combined antibacterial and anti-<lb/>inflammatory activity of a cationic disubstituted <lb/>dexamethasone-spermine conjugate. Antimicrob Agents <lb/>Chemother 54, 2525-2533. <lb/>24 Hilpert K, Elliott M, Jenssen H, Kindrachuk J, Fjell <lb/>CD, K€ orner J, Winkler DF, Weaver LL, Henklein P, <lb/>Ulrich AS et al. (2009) Screening and characterization <lb/>of surface-tethered cationic peptides for antimicrobial <lb/>activity. Chem Biol 16, 58-69. <lb/>25 Steinberg DA, Hurst MA, Fujii CA, Kung AH, Ho J, <lb/>Cheng F, Loury DJ and Fiddes JC (1997) Protegrin-1: <lb/>a broad-spectrum, rapidly microbicidal peptide with <lb/>in vivo activity. Antimicrob Agents Chemother 41, 1738-<lb/>1742. <lb/>26 Hoover DM, Wu Z, Tucker K, Lu W and Lubkowski J <lb/>(2003) Antimicrobial characterization of human beta-<lb/>defensin 3 derivatives. Antimicrob Agents Chemother 47, <lb/>2804-2809. <lb/>27 Harder J, Bartels J, Christophers E and Schr€ oder J-M <lb/>(2001) Isolation and characterization of human beta-<lb/>defensin-3, a novel human inducible peptide antibiotic. <lb/>J Biol Chem 276, 5707-5713. <lb/>28 Lin P, Li Y, Dong K and Li Q (2015) The antibacterial <lb/>effects of an antimicrobial peptide human beta-defensin 3 <lb/>fused with carbohydrate-binding domain on Pseudomonas <lb/>aeruginosa PA14. Curr Microbiol 71, 170-176. <lb/>29 Wnorowska U, Niemirowicz K, Myint M, Diamond <lb/>SL, Wr oblewska M, Savage PB, Janmey PA and Bucki <lb/>R (2015) Bactericidal activities of cathelicidin LL-37 <lb/>and select cationic lipids against the hypervirulent <lb/>Pseudomonas aeruginosa strain LESB58. Antimicrob <lb/>Agents Chemother 59, 3808-3815. <lb/>30 Mohammed I, Said DG, Nubile M, Mastropasqua L <lb/>and Dua HS (2019) Cathelicidin-derived synthetic <lb/>peptide improves therapeutic potential of vancomycin <lb/>against Pseudomonas aeruginosa. Front Microbiol 10, <lb/>2190. <lb/>31 Maiden MM, Zachos MP and Waters CM (2019) <lb/>Hydrogels embedded with melittin and tobramycin are <lb/>effective against Pseudomonas aeruginosa biofilms in an <lb/>animal wound model. Front Microbiol 10, 1348. <lb/>32 Hilpert K, Elliott MR, Volkmer-Engert R, Henklein P, <lb/>Donini O, Zhou Q, Winkler DF and Hancock RE <lb/>(2006) Sequence requirements and an optimization <lb/>strategy for short antimicrobial peptides. Chem Biol 13, <lb/>1101-1107. <lb/>33 Zhang L, Parente J, Harris SM, Woods DE, Hancock <lb/>RE and Falla TJ (2005) Antimicrobial peptide <lb/>therapeutics for cystic fibrosis. Antimicrob Agents <lb/>Chemother 49, 2921-2927. <lb/>34 Odds FC (2003) Synergy, antagonism, and what the <lb/>chequerboard puts between them. J Antimicrob <lb/>Chemother 52, 1. <lb/>35 Yan H and Hancock REW (2001) Synergistic <lb/>interactions between mammalian antimicrobial defense <lb/>peptides. Antimicrob Agents Chemother 45, 1558-1560. <lb/>36 Cherkasov A, Hilpert K, Jenssen H, Fjell CD, <lb/>Waldbrook M, Mullaly SC, Volkmer R and Hancock <lb/>REW (2008) Use of artificial intelligence in the design <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Nonclassical antagonism between AMPs and Lysozyme <lb/>I. Blumenthal et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>712 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">FEBS Open Bio 11 (2021) 705-713 ª 2021 The Authors. FEBS Open Bio published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of <lb/>Federation of European Biochemical Societies. <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>of small peptide antibiotics effective against a broad <lb/>spectrum of highly antibiotic-resistant superbugs. ACS <lb/>Chem Biol 4, 65-74. <lb/>37 Griswold KE, Bement JL, Teneback CC, Scanlon TC, <lb/>Wargo MJ and Leclair LW (2014) Bioengineered <lb/>lysozyme in combination therapies for Pseudomonas <lb/>aeruginosa lung infections. Bioengineered 5, 143-147. <lb/></listBibl>

			<div type="annex">Supporting information <lb/>Additional supporting information may be found <lb/>online in the Supporting Information section at the end <lb/>of the article. <lb/>Fig. S1. Dose-response curves of each antimicrobial <lb/>agent against P. aeruginosa strains Xen05 (A-F, M) <lb/>and H1001 (G-L, N). 95% confidence intervals for <lb/>EC 50 values in µgÁmL À1 : (A) 1.4-1.5; (B) 5.5-6.5; (C) <lb/>1.4-1.8; (D) 3.8-5.4; (E) 1.1-1.2; (F) 4.8-5.1; (G) 2.5-<lb/>2.9; (H) 6.9-7.1; (J) 3.4-3.6; (K) 1.6-1.8; (L) 5.7-6.6; <lb/>(M) 800-1200; (N) 700-1100. Experiments were con-<lb/>ducted as technical triplicate or quadruplicate mea-<lb/>surements and were repeated at least twice. <lb/>Fig. S2. Pseudo-Michaelis-Menten kinetic analysis of <lb/>hLYS lytic rates toward Gram-positive M. luteus bac-<lb/>teria in the presence of the specified concentration of <lb/>Tet009 AMP. All reactions were evaluated in triplicate <lb/>and shown are the means and standard deviation of <lb/>the initial rate at each bacterial substrate concentra-<lb/>tion. The best-fit hyperbola for each data set is shown, <lb/>and V max values from the regressions are provided in <lb/>Fig. 3. <lb/>Table S1. Literature Review of AMP Interactions with <lb/>Lysozyme. <lb/></div>

			<page>713 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">FEBS Open Bio 11 (2021) 705-713 ª 2021 The Authors. FEBS Open Bio published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of <lb/>Federation of European Biochemical Societies. <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">I. Blumenthal et al. <lb/>Nonclassical antagonism between AMPs and Lysozyme </note>


	</text>
</tei>