<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>Asian Pacific Journal of Cancer Prevention, Vol 21 <lb/>411 <lb/>DOI:10.31557/APJCP.2020.21.2.411 <lb/>Design, One Pot Synthesis and Molecular Docking Studies <lb/>Asian Pac J Cancer Prev, 21 (2), 411-421 <lb/></front>

			<body>Introduction <lb/>Cancer is one of the leading causes of death worldwide <lb/>and accounts for almost 13% deaths than any other <lb/>infectious diseases (Thun et al., 2010). According to <lb/>World Health Organization (WHO), projections of <lb/>cancer prevalence is expected to raise by 21.7 million <lb/>cases of oncological patients and 13 million deaths by <lb/>2030 (El-Azab et al., 2017; Boussari et al., 2018). With <lb/>the increase in prevalence of cancer and thereby rapidly <lb/>escalating costs, there are still types of cancer with massive <lb/>unmet medical needs (Kummar and Takimoto, 2018). <lb/>Therefore, the development of novel chemotherapeutic <lb/>agents to fight against this deadly disease is needed <lb/>urgently (Chakraborty and Rahman, 2012). Nitrogen <lb/>containing heterocyclic compounds like quinolines and <lb/>pyridines core rings plays a very important role in drug <lb/>discovery and development on cancer. (Taylor et al., <lb/>2016; Jabir et al., 2018) Some of the marketed drugs have <lb/>core structure of quinazoline which includes Afatinib (I, <lb/></body>

			<front>Abstract <lb/>Objective: The present study focused to build pyridine and quinazoline rings in a single molecule and designed a new <lb/>fused Pyrido[2,1-b] quinazoline to have a better pharmacological activity. Material and Methods: A three component, <lb/>one-pot synthesis of substituted-1H-Pyrido[2,1-b] quinazoline derivatives has been described by conventional and <lb/>microwave synthesis using triflic acid as catalyst. These compounds were screened for in vitro cytotoxic activity <lb/>against the panel of cancer cell lines A549, NCI-H460, HT-29, HCT-15, DU-145, and HFL. Results: Among the <lb/>tested compounds, 11-(1-benzyl-1H-indol-3-y1)-2, 3, 4, 11-tetrahydro-1H-pyrido[2,1-b] quinazoline (4i) showed most <lb/>potent cytotoxicity against A549 and NCI-H460 lung cancer cell lines with IC 50 values 4.57±0.25 and 5.53±0.49 µM, <lb/>respectively. Moreover, compound 4i was found to be most potent considerable cell growth inhibition with GI 50 values <lb/>of 2.70±0.18 and 3.24±0.40 µM against A549 and NCI-H460 cell lines, respectively. In addition, induction of apoptosis <lb/>for compound 4i on A549 was investigated by morphological changes, Acridine orange/ethidium bromide (AO/EB) and <lb/>DAPI staining. Furthermore, a strong anti-clonogenic effect of compound 4i on lung cancer cells was observed. The <lb/>flow cytometric analysis investigation reveals that compound 4i arrests the A549 cancer cell lines at the G0/G1 phase of <lb/>the cell cycle. Molecular docking were also performed on 4i, 4j, and erlotinib to predict the binding mode towards the <lb/>EGFR kinase (PDB code: 1M17) and the compounds have displayed similar interactions and compared with erlotinib. <lb/>Conclusion: Overall, these findings could suggest that the compound 4i would be an ideal lead as an anticancer agent. <lb/>Keywords: One Pot-quinazoline-molecular docking-cytotoxicity-anticancer. <lb/></front>

			<body>RESEARCH ARTICLE <lb/>Design, One Pot Synthesis and Molecular Docking <lb/>Studies of Substituted-1H-Pyrido[2,1-b] Quinazolines as <lb/>Apoptosis-Inducing Anticancer Agents <lb/>Raju Bathula 1 , Shobha Rani Satla 1 *, Ramadevi Kyatham 2 , Kiran Gangarapu 2 <lb/>as metastatic non-small cell lung cancer) (Shagufta and <lb/>Ahmad, 2017), Barasertib (II, acute myeloid leukemia) <lb/>(Helfrich et al., 2016), Tandutinib (III, Antisolid <lb/>tumors) (Motyckova and Stone, 2015) and Cediranib <lb/>(IV, Hematological cancers). (Fiedler et al., 2010) The <lb/>structural moieties of quinazoline exhibit broad range of <lb/>biological activities viz., anticancer (Zaki et al., 2018), <lb/>analgesic (Samiksha and Gupta, 2018), antimalarial(Gupta <lb/>et al., 2018), anti-inflammatory (Moussa et al., 2018) <lb/>and anticonvulsant activities. (Oluwaseye et al., 2018) <lb/>Moreover, Pyridine derivatives have known as antifungal, <lb/>antiviral, anticancer, antidepressant and anti-inflammatory <lb/>properties (Kurumurthy et al., 2014; Helal et al., 2015) <lb/>(Figure 1). <lb/>Pyrido [2,1-b]quinazoline (V) is a nitrogen containing <lb/>fused heterocyclic compound and widely distributed <lb/>in many bioactive compounds, natural products with <lb/>interesting biological activities (Tilley et al., 1987; <lb/>Mikhalev et al., 1995; Gálvez et al., 2018; Samiksha <lb/>and Gupta, 2018). Pyrido [2,1-b] quinazolines have <lb/></body>

			<front>Editorial Process: Submission:07/18/2019 Acceptance:12/20/2019 <lb/>1 <lb/>Centre for Pharmaceutical Sciences, Institute of Science and Technology, JNTUH, Kukatpally, Hyderabad, 2 Department of <lb/>Pharmacy, Anurag Group of Institutions, Venkatapur, Ghatkaser, Medchal, Hyderabad, Telangana, India. *For Correspondence: <lb/>satlashobharani@gmail.com <lb/></front>

			<note place="headnote">Raju Bathula et al <lb/>Asian Pacific Journal of Cancer Prevention, Vol 21 <lb/></note>

			<page>412 <lb/></page>

			<body>been discovered for their anticancer, antidepressant, <lb/>anti-inflammatory, analgesic, antiulcer activities. Recent <lb/>years fused heterocyclic compounds have gained a renewed <lb/>attention because of their significant biological activities, <lb/>some of them Pyrido [2,1-b]quinazoline carboxamide <lb/>motifs as antiplatelet activity, pyrido [2&apos;,3&apos;:3,4] pyrazolo <lb/>[1, 5-a] quinazoline (VI) as anticancer and antimicrobial <lb/>activity (Kumar et al., 2018b) have been reported in the <lb/>literature. Pyrazolo[3, 4-b]pyridine derivative (VII) have <lb/>known to possess antitumor, antiviral, antimicrobial and <lb/>anti-inflammatory activities (Nagender et al., 2014; Zhao <lb/>et al., 2016) (Figure 1). Previously, many reports have <lb/>known for versatile one pot, three component reaction <lb/>of aminopyrimidine, ketone and aldehydes leading to <lb/>synthesis of diverse fused heterocyclic rings such as <lb/>Pyrido [2,1-b]quinazoline by using different catalyst <lb/>(Yang et al., 2013; Sagir et al., 2016). Thus, the present <lb/>study focused to build pyridine and quinazoline rings in a <lb/>single molecule and designed a new fused Pyrido [2,1-b] <lb/>quinazoline to have a better pharmacological activity. The <lb/>resulting moieties were screened for in vitro cytotoxicity <lb/>by MTT assay and the potent analogs were evaluated for <lb/>cell growth inhibition assay, Flow cytometric analysis, <lb/>clonogenic growth inhibition assay, Annexin-V assay for <lb/>apoptosis. <lb/>Results <lb/>Chemistry <lb/>A three component, one pot synthesis of Substituted-<lb/>1H-Pyrido[2,1-b] Quinazoline derivatives by condensation <lb/>of 2-aminopyrimidines, substituted aromatic aldehydes <lb/>and ketones in the presence of ethanol by conventional <lb/>reflux or by microwave synthesis using triflic acid as <lb/>catalyst were described in Scheme 1. All the synthesized <lb/>compounds were purified by column chromatography <lb/>and characterized by 1 H, 13 C NMR and Mass spectral data. <lb/>The physical data of all the synthesized compounds were <lb/>shown in Table S1 and were compared and authenticated <lb/>with the previously reported literature. <lb/>To assess the cytotoxic activity of the synthesized <lb/>compounds in human cancer cells, A549, NCI-H460, <lb/>HT-29, HCT-15, DU-145 cancer cell lines and HFL-1 <lb/>normal lung fibroblasts cell lines were employed by using <lb/>3-(4,5-dimethylthiazol-2-yl)-2,5-diphenyltetrazolium <lb/>bromide (MTT) assay. The in vitro cytotoxicity studies <lb/>disclosed that the synthesized compounds manifested <lb/>assorted anticancer properties referred in Table 1. From <lb/>the closer analysis of the IC 50 values, it was observed that <lb/>compound 4i was more prominent in inducing cytotoxicity <lb/>in all cancer cells and found to be most potent in A549 lung <lb/>cancer cell line with IC 50 value 4.57±0.25 µM whereas, <lb/>in NCI-H460 cell line 50% inhibition was observed <lb/>at 5.53±0.49 µM, which indicates that compound <lb/>has specificity towards lung cancer cell lines, thus we <lb/>compared the cytotoxicity in normal lung fibroblast <lb/>cell line HFL-1 where it showed IC 50 value 8.70±0.36 <lb/>µM respectively (Figure 2). Hence, the compound was <lb/>found to have approximately 2-fold selectivity towards <lb/>the cancer cells. While the compound 4j also exhibited <lb/>remarkable cytotoxicity with IC 50 value 7.25±0.38 µM <lb/>against the colon cancer cell line HT-29, Among the series <lb/>the compound 4f also showed considerable cytotoxicity <lb/>and selectivity towards lung cancer with IC 50 12.84±1.50 <lb/>and 12.64±0.35 µM in A549 and NCI-H460 cancer cells. <lb/>These results of biological screening could give a positive <lb/>hope in anticancer studies that may lead to the origination <lb/>of novel cytotoxic agents with better activity. <lb/>In vitro growth inhibitory activity <lb/>The synthesized derivatives were further examined <lb/>for their growth inhibition on potential in human cancer <lb/>cell lines and normal cell line by MTT assay. The GI 50 <lb/>(µM) values (concentration required to inhibit 50% <lb/>Figure 1. Anticancer Drugs Containing Quinazoline as Core Structural Unit <lb/>Scheme 1. Synthesis of Substituted-1H-Pyrido [2,1-b]Quinazoline <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">Asian Pacific Journal of Cancer Prevention, Vol 21 </note>

			<page>413 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">DOI:10.31557/APJCP.2020.21.2.411 <lb/>Design, One Pot Synthesis and Molecular Docking Studies <lb/></note>

			<body>µM in A549 and NCI-H460 cell lines with selectivity <lb/>towards lung cancer cells consistent with 50% inhibitory <lb/>potential, and also have selectivity towards colon cancer <lb/>cells with significant GI 50 5.98±0.18, 6.27±0.19µM in <lb/>HT-29 and HCT-15 cells (Figure 2). Furthermore, the other <lb/>compounds examined among the series for potential cell <lb/>growth inhibition, the compounds 4f, 4g, and 4j exhibited <lb/>growth of cancer cells) of the tested compounds were <lb/>listed in Table 2. It is seen from the results that some of <lb/>the compounds have shown moderate to potent growth <lb/>inhibition against the tested cancer cell lines. Among this <lb/>series, from GI 50 analysis, the compound 4i was found <lb/>to be the most potent with considerable cell growth <lb/>inhibition with GI 50 values of 2.70±0.18 and 3.24±0.40 <lb/>Figure 2. A) Cytospecificity of compound 4i towards lung cancer (A549, NCI-H460) cells compared to normal <lb/>fibroblasts HFL-1; B) Cytotoxicity and growth inhibitory potential of compound 4i towards lung cancer cells compared <lb/>to normal fibroblasts HFL-1. Data was expressed as mean ± S.E.M. (n=3). ***p&lt;0.001, **p&lt;0.01, versus normal <lb/>HFL-1 cell line. <lb/>Cell line <lb/>A549 a <lb/>NCI-H460 b <lb/>HT-29 c <lb/>HCT-15 d <lb/>DU-145 e <lb/>HFL-1 f <lb/>4a <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>4b <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>4c <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>4d <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>4e <lb/>43.08±2.43 <lb/>43.18±2.58 <lb/>39.48±1.40 <lb/>40.91±0.55 <lb/>23.25±0.25 <lb/>84.96±3.80 <lb/>4f <lb/>12.84±1.50 <lb/>12.64±0.35 <lb/>15.40±0.11 <lb/>19.26±1.16 <lb/>16.08±0.14 <lb/>15.23±0.30 <lb/>4g <lb/>25.54±3.98 <lb/>41.51±1.27 <lb/>41.33±1.43 <lb/>28.59±1.96 <lb/>32.86±3.77 <lb/>63.09±1.79 <lb/>4h <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>4i <lb/>4.57±0.25 <lb/>5.53±0.49 <lb/>11.57±0.04 <lb/>11.31±0.25 <lb/>9.15±0.09 <lb/>8.70±0.36 <lb/>4j <lb/>8.98±0.32 <lb/>9.27±0.54 <lb/>7.25±0.38 <lb/>10.88±0.40 <lb/>12.57±0.23 <lb/>9.31±0.32 <lb/>Table 1. In vitro Inhibitory Concentration (IC 50 µM) Against Human Cancer Cell Lines <lb/>Figure 3. A) Morphological changes observed in Lung cancer cells with compound 4i treatment. A549 cells were <lb/>treated with and without compound 4i at concentrations 0.5,1, 2.5 and 5 µM. After 72 h the images were captured with <lb/>a phase contrast microscope at 200X magnification; B) Apoptotic morphology detection by acridine orange-ethidium <lb/>bromide (AO/EB) fluorescent staining of lung cancer cells after AO and EB staining. Untreated A549 cells showed <lb/>normal structure without prominent apoptosis and necrosis, cells treated with compound 4i at various concentrations <lb/>0.5, 1, 2.5 and 5 µM for 72 h showed prominent apoptotic features like membrane blebbing, nuclear condensation, <lb/>fragmented nuclei. The images were captured with fluorescence microscope at 200X. <lb/>a <lb/>A549, adenocarcinoma; b lung carcinoma; c colorectal cancer; d colon cancer cell line; e prostate cancer cell line; f non-small cell lung cancer <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Raju Bathula et al <lb/>Asian Pacific Journal of Cancer Prevention, Vol 21 <lb/></note>

			<page>414 <lb/></page>

			<body>promising growth inhibition. The rest compounds were <lb/>found to be moderately active in inhibiting growth of <lb/>cancer cells. Hence the compound 4i was further selected <lb/>for mechanistic studies to unveil the mechanism of cell <lb/>growth inhibition at the molecular level in A549 cell line. <lb/>These encouraging results may offer promising support <lb/>in further mechanistic studies. <lb/>Morphological observations using phase contrast <lb/>microscope <lb/>The induction of apoptosis and apoptotic cell residues <lb/>formation is one of the imperative goals in anti-cancer <lb/>Cell line <lb/>A549 a <lb/>NCI-H460 b <lb/>HT-29 c <lb/>HCT-15 d <lb/>DU-145 e <lb/>HFL-1 f <lb/>4a <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>4b <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>4c <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>4d <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>4e <lb/>29.53±0.79 <lb/>20.83±1.82 <lb/>15.75±0.97 <lb/>23.44±0.20 <lb/>17.7±0.13 <lb/>68.64±3.20 <lb/>4f <lb/>8.64±0.40 <lb/>9.62±0.41 <lb/>11.43±0.06 <lb/>12.94±0.73 <lb/>11.35±0.34 <lb/>11.63±0.17 <lb/>4g <lb/>9.23±0.93 <lb/>17.48±2.05 <lb/>20.81±3.74 <lb/>10.03±0.97 <lb/>7.37±2.50 <lb/>41.69±0.98 <lb/>4h <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>4i <lb/>2.70±0.18 <lb/>3.24±0.40 <lb/>5.98±0.18 <lb/>6.27±0.19 <lb/>9.64±0.37 <lb/>4.54±0.59 <lb/>4j <lb/>5.79±0.14 <lb/>7.10±0.19 <lb/>4.40±0.20 <lb/>7.81±0.65 <lb/>8.10±0.10 <lb/>7.67±0.22 <lb/>Table 2. In vitro Growth Inhibitory Concentration (GI 50 µM) Against Human Cancer Cell Lines <lb/>Figure 4. A) Nuclear changes in lung cancer cells after DAPI staining. A549 cells were treated with and without <lb/>compound 4i at various concentrations 0.5, 1, 2.5 and 5 µM for 72 h then stained with DAPI and compared with control. <lb/>The treatment showed intact nucleus in untreated cells whereas, altered nuclear architecture with clear apoptotic <lb/>changes such as bright stain, condensed nuclei were captured with fluorescence microscope at 200X; B) Effect of <lb/>compound 4i on survival of A549 cell colonies in colony formation assay. A549 cells were treated with compound 4i <lb/>at 1, 2.5 and 5 µM. After 7 days the colonies were fixed in crystal violet stain, and then cells were counted in Vilber <lb/>fusion chemdoc imaging system. The picture clearly depicts the strong anti-clonogenic effect of compound 4q on lung <lb/>cancer cells. The graphical representation illustrates the percent colony forming ability. <lb/>Compounds <lb/>Human <lb/>intestinal <lb/>absorption (%) <lb/>in vitro <lb/>Caco-2 cell <lb/>permeability (nm/sec) <lb/>in vitro <lb/>MDCK cell <lb/>permeability <lb/>(nm/sec) <lb/>in vitro <lb/>Plasma protein <lb/>binding <lb/>(%) <lb/>in vivo blood-<lb/>brain barrier <lb/>penetration <lb/>(C.brain/C.blood) <lb/>Skin <lb/>Permeability <lb/>4a <lb/>100.00 <lb/>47.55 <lb/>22.36 <lb/>90.03 <lb/>1.65 <lb/>-2.95 <lb/>4b <lb/>100.00 <lb/>54.46 <lb/>12.36 <lb/>99.22 <lb/>2.73 <lb/>-3.03 <lb/>4c <lb/>98.45 <lb/>1.68 <lb/>7.35 <lb/>91.26 <lb/>0.19 <lb/>-3.26 <lb/>4d <lb/>100.00 <lb/>57.96 <lb/>25.05 <lb/>92.43 <lb/>0.57 <lb/>-3.31 <lb/>4e <lb/>100.00 <lb/>35.84 <lb/>19.16 <lb/>89.60 <lb/>2.28 <lb/>-2.93 <lb/>4f <lb/>100.00 <lb/>47.91 <lb/>8.35 <lb/>100.00 <lb/>3.68 <lb/>-3.07 <lb/>4g <lb/>100.00 <lb/>55.03 <lb/>26.92 <lb/>100.00 <lb/>2.53 <lb/>-3.42 <lb/>4h <lb/>97.60 <lb/>56.83 <lb/>220.12 <lb/>88.73 <lb/>0.10 <lb/>3.70 <lb/>4i <lb/>100.00 <lb/>32.34 <lb/>13.75 <lb/>100.00 <lb/>2.17 <lb/>-2.41 <lb/>4j <lb/>94.39 <lb/>27.22 <lb/>17.45 <lb/>93.52 <lb/>9.38 <lb/>-3.59 <lb/>Table 3. In Silico ADME Properties Predicted for 20 Novel Compounds <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">Asian Pacific Journal of Cancer Prevention, Vol 21 </note>

			<page>415 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">DOI:10.31557/APJCP.2020.21.2.411 <lb/>Design, One Pot Synthesis and Molecular Docking Studies <lb/></note>

			<body>therapeutics (Ward et al., 2008). To examine whether the <lb/>treatment with the most active compound 4i could lead <lb/>to the apoptosis induction, A549 cells were treated with <lb/>the compound 4i, after 72 h of incubation images were <lb/>captured in phase contrast microscope which delineate <lb/>the shrinkage of cells and resulted in increased number <lb/>of dead cells with increase in concentration, whereas <lb/>these characteristic morphological features were absent in <lb/>control cells and exhibited healthy morphology as shown <lb/>in Figure 3. <lb/>Acridine orange/ethidium bromide (AO/EB) staining <lb/>Acridine orange/ethidium bromide (AO/EB) staining <lb/>assay was performed to differentiate among live, apoptotic <lb/>and necrotic cells. AO can penetrate the intact cell <lb/>membrane and stain the nuclei green, whereas EB can only <lb/>stain the nuclei of cells that have lost membrane integrity <lb/>and stain orange. Necrotic cells display red fluorescence <lb/>with no indication of chromatin fragmentation, and the <lb/>cells also appear swollen (Riyasdeen et al., 2014). It <lb/>can be inferred from Figure-3B that the control cells <lb/>exhibited normal cell morphology and appeared green. <lb/>Whereas, the compound 4i treatment dose dependently <lb/>clearly induced the apoptotic morphological changes such <lb/>as cell shrinkage, chromatin condensation, membrane <lb/>blebbing and apoptotic body formation, indicating that <lb/>the compound 4i had induced apoptosis in A549 lung <lb/>cancer cells. <lb/>DAPI staining <lb/>Apoptosis can be demarcated from necrosis by their <lb/>pronounced change in nuclear appearance. With DAPI <lb/>staining the untreated cells appeared normally with intact <lb/>nucleus. <lb/>A549 cells treatment with the compound 4i showed <lb/>chromatin condensation, nuclear fragmentation, and horse <lb/>shoe shaped nucleus and bright chromatin due to which <lb/>are clear morphological indicators of apoptosis as shown <lb/>Figure 5. A) Compound 4i reduced ΔΨm in lung cancer cells. A549 cells were treated with various concentrations <lb/>of compound 4i for 72 h. The control represents the cells without compound 4i treatment. P1 indicates formation of <lb/>J-aggregates in healthy mitochondria whereas, P2 represents depolarized mitochondria in cells due to the presence <lb/>of J-monomers; Cell cycle analysis of lung cancer cells following Compound 4i treatment. A549 cells were grown <lb/>and treated with compound 4i at different concentrations 0.5, 1, 2.5 and 5 µM for 72 h. The cells were harvested, <lb/>stained with propidium iodide and DNA content was quantified by flow cytometry. Histogram showing the percentage <lb/>of cells in the Sub G1, G0/G1, G1, S and G2/M phase of the cell cycle obtained after FACS analysis. 10,000 cells <lb/>were acquired for each sample. B) Apoptosis induction by Compound 4i in lung cancer cells using annexin V FITC/ <lb/>PI staining. A549 cells were cultured and treated with compound 4i ranging from 0.5 to 5µM concentration and <lb/>incubated for 72 h and processed for annexin V-FITC/ PI double-staining. Quantification of cells undergoing apoptosis <lb/>or necrosis was carried out with 10,000 cells from each sample and were analyzed by flowcytometry. The percentage <lb/>of cells positive for Annexin V-FITC and/or Propidium iodide is represented inside the quadrants. Cells in the upper <lb/>left quadrant (Q1-UL; AV-/PI+): necrotic cells; lower left quadrant (Q2-LL; AV-/PI-): live cells; lower right quadrant <lb/>(Q3-LR; AV+/PI-): early apoptotic cells and upper right quadrant (Q4-UR; AV+/PI +): late apoptotic cells. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Raju Bathula et al <lb/>Asian Pacific Journal of Cancer Prevention, Vol 21 <lb/></note>

			<page>416 <lb/></page>

			<body>in the Figure 4A. <lb/>Effect of compound 4q on the formation of colonies by <lb/>Clonogenic assay <lb/>The assay mainly tests ability to undergo &quot;unlimited&quot; <lb/>division by every cell in the population and the hindrance <lb/>of colony formation by compound 4i was determined in <lb/>exponentially growing A549 cells by culturing 100-150 <lb/>cells per well. Treatment with compound 4i was given at <lb/>different concentrations (1, 2.5 and 5µM), then colonies <lb/>formation was observed in 7 days&apos; time period. Then, <lb/>formed colonies were fixed with glutaraldehyde (6.0% <lb/>v/v), stained with crystal violet (0.5% w/v). The treatment <lb/>clearly retained the capacity to produce colonies in lung <lb/>cancer cell population in a concentration dependent <lb/>manner. Reductions in the number of colonies were <lb/>observed as shown in Figure 4B. Hence, these results <lb/>denote the importance of compound 4i in inhibiting the <lb/>potential of colony formation. The total colonies were <lb/>counted by molecular imaging system Vilber Fusion Fx <lb/>software and the values were represented as a percent <lb/>colony forming ability. <lb/>Flow-cytometry analysis <lb/>Effect of compound 4i on mitochondrial membrane <lb/>depolarization <lb/>The fluorescent orange-red staining is indicative of the <lb/>presence of polarized mitochondria. On depolarization, <lb/>there is usually a reduction in orange-red staining occurs. <lb/>The mitochondria play a fundamental role in initiating <lb/>the intrinsic pathway of apoptosis in response to many <lb/>triggers, as it is the leading target of cellular oxidative <lb/>stress, which impede the electron transport chain, which <lb/>generate reactive oxygen species (ROS) (Bustamante <lb/>et al., 2004). Therefore, to test the impact of compound <lb/>4i on mitochondria, the ΔΨ m was measured. A549 cells <lb/>treatment with compound 4i caused significant collapse in <lb/>the ΔΨ m compared to control cells as shown in the Figure <lb/>5A. The compound 4i prompted the depolarisation of ΔΨ m <lb/>dose-dependently leading to the disruption of electron <lb/>transport. <lb/>Effect of compound 4q on Cell cycle distribution <lb/>From the in vitro screening results, it was evident <lb/>that the compound 4i showed remarkable toxicity against <lb/>lung cancer cell line respectively. Hence, in order to <lb/>reveal whether this cytotoxicity may be due to the phase <lb/>arrest, cell cycle determination was performed which <lb/>was parallel with increased percentages of cell death <lb/>(Żuryń et al., 2016). Cells were treated with compound <lb/>4i at concentrations ranging from 0.5 to 5 µM for 48 h, <lb/>and then the cells were stained with propidium iodide <lb/>and analyzed by using flow analyzer. The results from <lb/>Figure 5A indicated that the A549 untreated control cells <lb/>showed 63.53% cells in G0/G1 phase, whereas compound <lb/>4i treatment resulted in significant elevation in G0/G1 <lb/>population from 63.53% to 80.02% which gradually <lb/>increased with increase in doses, which implies G0/G1 <lb/>arrest of the cell cycle The G0/G1 phase arrest was more <lb/>prominent at 2.5 and 5 µM concentrations. <lb/>Annexin V Dead cell apoptosis assay <lb/>To determine whether the cytotoxicity by compound <lb/>4i treatment could induce early apoptotic or late apoptotic <lb/>cell death, Annexin V-FITC/PI flow cytometry was <lb/>performed. As appeared in Figure-5B, compound 4i <lb/>fundamentally exhibited significant early apoptosis, the <lb/>population of early apoptotic cells increased from 4.08 % <lb/>(control) to 26.90% concentration. While at 2.5 and 5 μM <lb/>concentration evidenced both early and late apoptosis. <lb/>Molecular Docking <lb/>The docking of compounds 4i and 4j on EGFR <lb/>kinase was investigated into the putative binding site of <lb/>EGFR kinase. Both analogs 4i and 4j were docked using <lb/>MOE software into the active site of EGFR kinase along <lb/>with the crystal ligand erlotinib (PDB code: 1M17). All <lb/>docking calculations were performed and interactions <lb/>were predicted. The interaction energies of compounds <lb/>4i, 4j and erlotinib, docked into the active site of EGFR, <lb/>were -17.47, -16.57 and -22.34 kcal/mol, respectively <lb/>Table S2; <lb/>The docking study of the most active compound <lb/>4i revealed that the indole ring typically overlaid the <lb/>corresponding ring of erlotinib without clashing with the <lb/>surrounding amino acids. The 6-ring and 5-ring of indole <lb/>nucleus of compound 4i have bound with Val702 with <lb/>pi-H interaction with distances 3.71 and 4.28 respectively <lb/>with energies -1.0 and -0.8 kcal/mol respectively. The <lb/>compound 4i also shows hydrophobic interactions with <lb/>Figure 6. 3D and 2D Interactions of Erlotinib with <lb/>the EGFR Kinase and Overlay Complex with Crystal <lb/>Ligand; 3D and 2D interactions of compound 4i with <lb/>the EGFR kinase with pi-H interactions with Val 702: <lb/>3D and 2D interactions of compound 4j with the EGFR <lb/>kinase with pi-H interactions with Val 702 and Lys 721. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">Asian Pacific Journal of Cancer Prevention, Vol 21 </note>

			<page>417 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">DOI:10.31557/APJCP.2020.21.2.411 <lb/>Design, One Pot Synthesis and Molecular Docking Studies <lb/></note>

			<body>Phe 699, Leu 694, Met 742 and Leu 764. <lb/>The indole ring is the main moiety affecting the <lb/>binding mode of compound 4i in both activation and <lb/>catalytic loop Figure 6. <lb/>In contrast, compound 4j was bound in similar manner, <lb/>where the pi-H interaction is observed with quinoline <lb/>nucleus with Val 702 with -0.6 kcal/mol. Pi-H interactions <lb/>with Lys 721 indole nucleus with -0.7 kcal/mol. The <lb/>compound 4j have shown similar hydrophobic interactions <lb/>with Phe 699, Leu 694, Met 742 and Leu 764. The dock <lb/>score for 4i, 4j and erlotinib by interactions with EGFR <lb/>kinase was found to be -6.34, -5.96 and -7.29 respectively. <lb/>It is clear that the results of the molecular docking can be <lb/>used to design novel quinoline derivatives with potential <lb/>anticancer activity and binding to EGFR target. <lb/>ADME predictions <lb/>The major parameters for pharmacokinetics are <lb/>absorption, distribution, metabolism and excretion. The <lb/>in silico ADME properties of substituted 1H-pyrido[2,1-b] <lb/>quinazoline (4) compounds have shown satisfactory <lb/>results. Among the evaluated 18 compounds have showed <lb/>good intestinal absorption. Almost all compounds have <lb/>shown moderate permeability for in vitro Caco-2 cells <lb/>except 4c and 4i have shown low permeability and low <lb/>to moderate permeability for in vitro MDCK cells except <lb/>4h showed 220.117 with high permeability. Predicted <lb/>In vivo blood-brain barrier penetration demonstrated <lb/>that compound 4j has high penetration in to CNS and <lb/>4c, 4d, and 4h have less penetration ability into CNS. <lb/>All compounds have strong plasma protein binding <lb/>the value more than 90% indicates strongly bound and <lb/>also showed maximum skin permeability. The in silico <lb/>predicted ADME properties and their values are shown <lb/>in the Table 3. <lb/>Discussion <lb/>In conclusion, we developed substituted 1H-pyrido <lb/>[2,1-b]quinazoline (4) derivates from the various <lb/>2-aminopyrimidines, substituted aromatic aldehydes <lb/>and ketones by using recyclable and it under go one <lb/>pot the component system to formation of Pyrido[2,1-b] <lb/>quinazoline (4) compounds are more efficient and <lb/>simple method for the organic chemistry synthesis. <lb/>The synthesized compounds were screened for in vitro <lb/>cytotoxicity by MTT assay against the panel of human <lb/>cancer cell lines A549, NCI-H460, HT-29, HCT-15, <lb/>DU-145 cancer cell lines and HFL-1 normal lung <lb/>fibroblasts cell line. Among the tested compounds, <lb/>11-(1-benzyl-1H-indol-3-y1)-2, 3, 4, 11-tetrahydro-1H-<lb/>pyrido [2,1-b] Quinazoline (4i) showed potent cytotoxicity <lb/>in A549 and NCI-H460 lung cancer cell lines with IC 50 <lb/>values 4.57±0.25 and 5.53±0.49 µM, respectively. The <lb/>induction of apoptosis was examined by morphological <lb/>changes of compound 4i in A549 cancer cells and showed <lb/>microscopically shrinkage of cells with increased number <lb/>of dead cells in dose dependent manner. AO/EB and DAPI <lb/>staining studies revealed at compound 4i treatment dose <lb/>dependently clearly induced the apoptotic morphological <lb/>changes such as cell shrinkage, chromatin condensation, <lb/>membrane blebbing and apoptotic body formation, <lb/>indicating that the compound 4i had induced apoptosis in <lb/>A549 lung cancer cells. Colony formation in A549 was <lb/>inhibited by compound 4i in a concentration dependent <lb/>manner. Furthermore, the flow cytometric investigation <lb/>using compound 4i in A549 cell line in a dose dependent <lb/>manner gave the following illustrations, 1) Cancer cells <lb/>were arrested at the G0/G1 Phase of cell cycle.2) Evidence <lb/>of the depolarization of ΔΨ m dose-dependently leading <lb/>to the disruption of electron transport chain. 3)Annexin <lb/>V-FITC/PI flow cytometry exhibited significant early <lb/>apoptosis. The molecular docking studies on EGFR kinase <lb/>results indicated that two compounds 4i and 4j of binding <lb/>interactions strongly correlated with crystal ligand. <lb/>Overall, these findings could suggest that these compounds <lb/>would be an ideal motif&apos;s as an anticancer agent. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgment <lb/>The authors are thankful to Director, CPS, IST, JNTUH <lb/>for providing the necessary facilities and also thankful to <lb/>UGC for financial support. <lb/></div>

			<body>Experimental <lb/>Chemistry <lb/>All chemicals and reagents were obtained from Aldrich <lb/>Lancaster (Alfa Aeser, Johnson Matthey Company, Ward <lb/>Hill, MA, USA), or Spectrochem Pvt. Ltd. (Mumbai, <lb/>India) and were used without further purification. <lb/>Reactions were performed by TLC on silica gel glass plate <lb/>containing 60 GF-254, and visualization was achieved <lb/>by UV light or iodine indicator. 1 H and 13 C NMR spectra <lb/>were determined in CDCl 3 by using Varian and Avance <lb/>instruments of 400Hz. Chemical shifts are expressed in <lb/>parts per million ( <lb/>in ppm) downfield from internal <lb/>TMS and coupling constants are expressed in Hz. 1 H NMR <lb/>spectroscopic data coupling constants in Hz, number of <lb/>protons. ESI mass spectra were recorded on a Micro mass <lb/>Quattro LC using ESI+ software with capillary voltage <lb/>3.98 kV and an ESI mode positive ion trap detector. <lb/>Melting points were determined with an Electro thermal <lb/>melting point apparatus. <lb/>General procedure <lb/>Preparation of Pyrido [2,1-b]quinazoline (4) <lb/>A One-pot and three component reaction were <lb/>employed for the preparation of final compound (4) briefly, <lb/>2-aminopyridine (1, 1.0 mmol), aldehydes (2, 1.0 mmol) <lb/>and ketones (2.0 mmol) was dissolved in EtOH in presence <lb/>of CF 3 SO 3 H as a catalyst under nitrogen condition the <lb/>reaction mixture was stirred with reflux for 5 hours at 70 o C <lb/>by conventional method or 35 minutes under microwave <lb/>irradiation, the completion of reaction was monitored by <lb/>the TLC. Then solvent was removed from the reaction by <lb/>rotavaccum pressure. Resultant reaction mixture extracted <lb/>with ethyl acetate and water, the organic layer washed <lb/>with sodium sulphate then it is evaporated to obtain solid <lb/>compound later purified by the column chromatography <lb/>by using Ethyl acetate and Hexane (80:20) as mobile phase <lb/>to afford a final desired product. <lb/>δ <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Raju Bathula et al <lb/>Asian Pacific Journal of Cancer Prevention, Vol 21 <lb/></note>

			<page>418 <lb/></page>

			<body>Spectral data <lb/>11-Phenyl-2, 3, 4, 11-tetrahydro-1H-pyrido [2, 1-b] <lb/>quinazoline (4a) <lb/>m.p: 154-156 o C; 1 H NMR: δ 7.36-7.28 (m, 5H), 6.89 <lb/>(t, 1H, J = 7.8), 6.73-6.69 (m, 2H), 5.98 (t, 1H, J = 6.6), <lb/>5.37 (s, 1H), 2.38-2.24 (m, 2H), 1.74-1.59 (m, 6H); 13 C <lb/>NMR: δ 148.7, 142.6, 136.8, 135.3, 133.1, 128.7, 128.2, <lb/>126.8, 123.6, 108.1, 106.6, 68.3, 30.3, 26.6, 23.1, 22.6; <lb/>MS: m/z 263.0 [M + H+]. <lb/>11-(4-Chlorophenyl)-2, 3, 4, 11-tetrahydro-IH-pyrido [2, <lb/>1-b] quinazoline (4b) <lb/>mp: 88-93 0 C; 1 H NMR: δ 7.50-7.21 (m, 7H), 6.62 (t, <lb/>1H, J = 6.0), 5.64 (s, 1H), 2.47-2.36 (m, 2H), 1.88-1.61 <lb/>(m, 6H); 13 C NMR: δ 148.8, 141.9, 137.5, 135.2, 134.5, <lb/>133.0, 129.4, 128.3, 123.6, 108.3, 106.8, 67.8, 29.6, 26.4, <lb/>23.0, 22.6; MS: m/z 297.0 [M + H+]. <lb/>11-(4-Nitrophenyl)-2, 3, 4, 11-tetrahydro-1H-pyrido[2,1-b] <lb/>quinazoline (4c) <lb/>mp: 150-151 o C; 1 H NMR: δ 8.25-8.22 (m, 2H), <lb/>7.54-7.45 (m, 3H), 7.34-7.29 (m, 1H), 7.07 (d, 1H, J = <lb/>6.3), 6.46 (t, 1H, J = 6.3), 5.72 (s, 1H), 2.53-2.37 (m, 2H), <lb/>1.91-1.61 (m, 6H); MS: m/z 308.12 [M + H+]. <lb/>11-(4-Methoxyphenyl)-2, 3, 4, 11-tetrahydro-1H-<lb/>pyrido[2,1-b]quinazoline (4d) <lb/>mp: 88-89 o C; 1 H NMR: δ 7.27-7.21 (m, 2H), 6.88-<lb/>6.84 (m, 3H), 6.76-6.68 (m, 2H), 5.99 (t, 1H, J = 6.6), <lb/>5.32 (s, 1H), 3.79 (s, 3H), 2.39-2.29 (m, 2H), 1.77-1.57 <lb/>(m, 6H); 13 C NMR: δ 159.7, 148.9, 136.6, 135.4, 135.1, <lb/>133.4, 128.3,123.5, 114.2, 108.6, 107.0, 67.9, 55.3, 30.2, <lb/>26.7, 23.2, 22.8; MS: m/z 295.0 [M+ H+]. <lb/>(p-Tolyl)-2, 3, 4,11-tetrahydro-1H-pyrido[2,1-b] <lb/>quinazoline (4e) <lb/>mp: 125-126 o C; 1 H NMR: δ 7.24-7.11 (m, 4H), 6.87 <lb/>(t, 1H, J = 7.8), 6.73-6.65 (m, 2H), 5.96 (t, 1H, J = 6.6), <lb/>5.32 (s, 1H), 2.32-2.30 (m, 5H), 1.79-1.58 (m, 6H); 13 C <lb/>NMR: δ 148.9, 139.8, 138.2, 136.5, 135.4, 133.4, 129.6, <lb/>126.9, 123.5, 108.5, 106.9, 66.2, 30.2, 26.7, 23.2, 22.7, <lb/>21.2; MS: m/z 276.9 [M + H+]. <lb/>8-Chloro-11-(4-chlorophenyl)-2, 3, 4, 11-tetrahydro-1H-<lb/>pyrido [2, 1-b] quinazoline (4f) <lb/>mp: 131-132 o C; 1 H NMR: δ 7.35-7.32 (m, 2H), <lb/>7.27-7.22 (m, 2H), 6.89-6.85 (m, 1H), 6.78 (s, 1H), 6.75 <lb/>(d, 1H, J = 2.1), 5.32 (s, 1H), 2.34-2.23 (m, 2H), 1.77-1.59 <lb/>(m, 6H); 13 C NMR: δ 146.8, 140.4, 136.6, 134.9,134.8, <lb/>132.5, 129.4, 128.3, 124.6, 115.3, 107.4, 68.0, 29.9, 26.6, <lb/>22.9, 22.5; MS: m/z 330.8 [M + H+]. <lb/>8-chloro-11-(4-fluorophenyl)-2,3,4,11-tetrahydro-1H-<lb/>pyrido[2,1-b]quinazoline (4g) <lb/>mp: 88-93 0 C; 1 H NMR: δ 7.50-7.21 (m, 7H), 6.62 (t, <lb/>1H, J = 6.0), 5.64 (s, 1H), 2.47-2.36 (m, 2H), 1.88-1.61 <lb/>(m, 6H); 13 C NMR: δ 148.8, 141.9, 137.5, 135.2, 134.5, <lb/>133.0, 129.4, 128.3, 123.6, 108.3, 106.8, 67.8, 29.6, 26.4, <lb/>23.0, 22.6; MS: m/z 314.0 [M + H+]. <lb/>11-(4-trimethoxyphenyl)-2, 3, 4, 11-tetrahydro-1H-<lb/>pyrido[2,1-b] quinazoline (4h) <lb/>mp: 89-92 o C; 1 H NMR: δ 7.32-7.28 (m, 2H), 7.10-<lb/>6.85 (m, 3H), 6.75-6.65 (m, 2H), 6.10 (s, 1H), 5.75 (d, <lb/>1H, J = 2.1), 3.85 (s, 3H), 2.34-2.23 (m, 2H), 1.77-1.59 <lb/>(m, 6H); 13 C NMR: δ 160.0, 147.2, 135.7, 134.6, 134.1, <lb/>132.5, 127.5, 124.5, 115.2, 107.6, 106.8, 66.8, 56., 30.6, <lb/>27.0, 24.0, 23.6; MS: m/z 295.5 [M + H+]. <lb/>11-(1-benzyl-1H-indol-3-yl)-2, 3, 4, 11-tetrahydro-1H-<lb/>pyrido [2, 1-b] quinazoline (4i) <lb/>mp: 185-186 o C; 1 H NMR: δ 8.20-7.80(m, 3H), 7.50-<lb/>7.35 (m, 4H), 7.20-7.05 (m, 5H), 6.65 (s, 1H), 6.47 (1H, <lb/>dd, J = 8.3, 1.9 Hz), 5.99 (1H, d, J = 10.1 Hz), 5.55-5.25 <lb/>(s, 2H), 2.21-2.94 (m, 3H), 2.00 (m, 1H), δ 1.56-1.85 <lb/>(m,4H). 13 C NMR: δ 156.8, 147.8, 137.4, 134.9,134.8, <lb/>132.5, 129.4, 128.3, 124.6, 115.3, 107.4, 68.0, 29.9, 26.6, <lb/>22.9, 22.5; MS: m/z 392.46 [M + H+]. <lb/>11-(1H-indol-3-yl)-2, 3, 4, 11-tetrahydro-1H-pyrido [2,1-<lb/>b]quinazoline (4j) <lb/>mp: 180-182 o C; 1 H NMR: δ 7.89-7.32 (m, 4H), <lb/>7.27-7.22 (m, 3H), 6.89-6.85 (m, 2H), 6.78 (s, 1H), 6.75 <lb/>(d, 1H, J = 2.1), 2.34-2.23 (m, 2H), 1.77-1.59 (m, 6H); <lb/>13 C NMR: δ 146.8, 140.4, 136.6, 134.9,134.8, 132.5, <lb/>129.4, 128.3, 124.6, 115.3, 107.4, 68.0, 29.9, 26.6, 22.9, <lb/>22.5; MS: m/z 301.25 [M + H+]. <lb/>Biological Activity <lb/>Materials and Methods <lb/>Cell culture <lb/>Various cancer cells were used to screen anticancer <lb/>activity of newly synthesized compounds. Lung (A549 <lb/>and NCI-H460), colon (HCT-15 and HT-29), prostate <lb/>(DU-145) cancer cells maintained in RPMI-1640 media <lb/>while normal lung fibroblasts cell line (HFL-1) were <lb/>maintained in F-12 k medium supplemented with 10% <lb/>fetal bovine serum (FBS) with 1% antibiotic-antimycotic <lb/>solution (Sigma). Cells were maintained in 5% CO2 with <lb/>98% relative humidity at 37oC in incubator. When 80-90% <lb/>of confluency is reached, they were sub-cultured using <lb/>0.25% trypsin/1 mM EDTA solution for further passage. <lb/>The compounds in this series were dissolved in DMSO <lb/>(1 %) to prepare the stock solution of 10 mM. Further <lb/>dilutions were made accordingly with respective media <lb/>to obtain the required concentrations. <lb/>Cytotoxicity assay <lb/>MTT assay measures the reduction of MTT <lb/>(3-(4,5-dimethylthiazol-2-yl)-2,5-diphenyl tetrazolium <lb/>bromide) by mitochondrial succinate dehydrogenase <lb/>enzyme to insoluble formazan crystals. Since reduction <lb/>of MTT occurs only in metabolically active cells, the <lb/>level of activity is the measure of the viability of the cells. <lb/>(Pordeli et al., 2017). Briefly, cells were plated in 96-well <lb/>plates at a density of 3,000 to 6,000 cells per well in 100 <lb/>µl of complete medium and allowed to grow overnight. <lb/>Then the cells were treated with different concentrations <lb/>of the synthesized compounds and incubated for 72 h. <lb/>After the treatment, 100 µl of MTT (0.5 mg/ml) was <lb/>added and incubated at 37 o C for 4 h. Then MTT reagent <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">Asian Pacific Journal of Cancer Prevention, Vol 21 </note>

			<page>419 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">DOI:10.31557/APJCP.2020.21.2.411 <lb/>Design, One Pot Synthesis and Molecular Docking Studies <lb/></note>

			<body>was aspirated and formazan crystals formed were <lb/>dissolved by the addition of 200 µL of DMSO for 20 min <lb/>at 37 o C. The formazan product quantity was measured <lb/>by using a spectrophotometric microtiter plate reader <lb/>(Spectra Max, M4 Molecular devices, USA) at 570 nm <lb/>wavelength(Nekkanti et al., 2017). <lb/>Cell Growth inhibition assay <lb/>Briefly, the cells were seeded on to a 96-well plate <lb/>in 100 µl of medium. Following 24 h MTT reagent was <lb/>added in few wells and day 0 absorbance was analyzed, <lb/>and then cells were treated with compounds and incubated <lb/>for an additional 72 h. After the treatment, 100 µl of MTT <lb/>(0.5 mg/ml) was added and incubated at 37 o C for 4 h. <lb/>Then MTT reagent was suctioned, the insoluble formazan <lb/>crystals were dissolved in DMSO and formazan product <lb/>formed is measured at 570 nm wavelength. The day 0 <lb/>absorbance was subtracted from the 72 h incubated plates <lb/>and data were plotted as a percentage of untreated control <lb/>(Dai et al., 2011). <lb/>Morphological observation <lb/>A549 cells were plated in 12 well culture plates with a <lb/>cell density of 1.2x10 5 cells/ml and allowed to adhere for <lb/>24 h. Then the cells were incubated with 0.5, 1, 2.5 and 5 <lb/>µM concentrations of compound 4q. After 72 h treatment, <lb/>cells were monitored for the morphological changes <lb/>and the images were captured under a phase contrast <lb/>microscope (Nikon, Inc. Japan) at 200X magnification. <lb/>Acridine orange ethidium bromide (AO/EB) staining <lb/>A549 cells were seeded at a concentration of 1.2x10 5 <lb/>cells/ml and treated with various concentrations of <lb/>compound 4q and the plates were incubated for 72 h. <lb/>Then, 100 µl from fluorescent dyes comprising both <lb/>Acridine Orange (Helfrich et al., 2016) and Ethidium <lb/>Bromide (Vundru et al., 2013) were added into each well <lb/>in equal volumes (10 µg/ml) respectively (Nekkanti et al., <lb/>2017), then the cells were Immediately visualized under <lb/>fluorescence microscope with excitation (488 nm) and <lb/>emission (550 nm) at 200X magnification. <lb/>4′,6-diamidino-2-phenylindole nucleic acid staining <lb/>(DAPI) <lb/>Morphological changes in the nucleus by the <lb/>cytotoxic compound 4q treatment were observed with <lb/>the DAPI staining as per the method described with <lb/>small modifications. After treatment with compound 4q <lb/>for 72 h, lung cancer cell line A549 were washed with <lb/>PBS then fixed with 4% formaldehyde for 10 min and <lb/>then permeabilized with 0.1% Tween 20 followed by <lb/>staining with 1 µM DAPI. Control and treated cells were <lb/>observed under fluorescence microscope with excitation <lb/>at 359 nm and emission at 461 nm using DAPI filter at <lb/>200X magnification (Sgorbati et al., 1986). <lb/>Flow cytometric analysis <lb/>Measurement of mitochondrial membrane potential <lb/>The cyanine dye JC-1 (5,5′,6,6′-tetrachloro-1,1′,3,3′-<lb/>tetraethylbenzimidazolylcarbocyanine iodide) is <lb/>a cell-penetrating dye that facilitates discrimination of <lb/>energized and de energized mitochondria thus, high <lb/>mitochondrial potential shifts its emission fluorescence <lb/>from green to red (Vundru et al., 2013).This phenomenon <lb/>was assessed by flow cytometry (FACS). A549 cells <lb/>(1.5x10 6 cells/ml) were seeded in 12 well plates and <lb/>allowed to adhere for overnight. Then the cells were <lb/>incubated with compound 4q at 0.5, 1, 2.5 and 5 µM <lb/>concentrations for 72 h. Cells were collected and washed <lb/>with PBS and resuspended in solution of JC-1 (1 µM) <lb/>and incubated for 30 min in incubator at 37 o C. The cells <lb/>were washed twice with PBS and cells were trypsinized, <lb/>centrifuged and 10,000 events were analyzed by flow <lb/>cytometer (BD FACSVerse™, USA). <lb/>Cell cycle analysis <lb/>In order to reveal whether arrest of cell cycle was <lb/>mechanistically responsible for sensitizing lung cancer <lb/>cells towards apoptosis, the flow cytometric analysis was <lb/>performed to analyse the distribution of the cell population <lb/>in various cell cycle phases (Mani et al., 2017). Here, <lb/>A549 cancer cells were incubated with compound 4q at <lb/>various concentrations ranging from 0.5 to 5 µM for 48 <lb/>h. Untreated and treated cells were harvested, washed and <lb/>fixed overnight in 70% ethanol in PBS at -20 o C. Fixed cells <lb/>were pelleted and stained with cell cycle analysis reagent <lb/>propidium iodide (50 μg/ml) with RNase A for 20 min at <lb/>37 o C in dark and about 10,000 events were acquired and <lb/>analyzed on a flow cytometer (Kumar et al., 2018a). <lb/>Annexin assay <lb/>A fundamental part of apoptosis is the flipping of <lb/>phosphatidyl serine (PS) from the inner surface to the outer <lb/>surface of the plasma layer of the cells. PS is a component <lb/>of phospholipid usually located on the cytoplasmic surface <lb/>of the cell layer in viable cells. When the apoptotic <lb/>condition is initiated in a cell, PS is no more restricted <lb/>to the cytosolic region and will flip on the surface of the <lb/>cell. Translocation of PS is considered to be a hall mark <lb/>of apoptosis (Zhu et al., 2015). To experimentally address <lb/>this phenomenon briefly, 1 X 10 5 cells were seeded in a <lb/>12-well plate and treated with different concentration <lb/>of compound 4q and incubated for 72 h. Then untreated <lb/>and treated cells were harvested and the cells were <lb/>processed with annexin V-FITC and Propidium Iodide (PI) <lb/>staining (Bio Legend), according to the manufacturer&apos;s <lb/>instructions. Further, early/late apoptosis and necrosis <lb/>parameters were analyzed with quadrant statistics on <lb/>propidium iodide-negative cells, fluorescein positive cells <lb/>and propidium iodide-positive cells, respectively. <lb/>Clonogenic growth inhibition assay <lb/>Lung cancer cells A549 at exponentially phase were <lb/>seeded into 12-well culture plates and kept overnight and <lb/>treated with the compound 4q. Every 2 days the medium <lb/>was replaced with the fresh medium. After 7 days of <lb/>incubation, the colonies formed were fixed and stained <lb/>with 1 % crystal violet in methanol for 3 h. The number <lb/>of stained colonies were counted under chemdoc imaging <lb/>system (Vilber Fusion Fx, France). Colony formation was <lb/>calculated as a percentage to untreated control cultures <lb/>(Moghaddam et al., 2009). <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Raju Bathula et al <lb/>Asian Pacific Journal of Cancer Prevention, Vol 21 <lb/></note>

			<page>420 <lb/></page>

			<body>Molecular Docking Studies <lb/>In this molecular docking study were carried out to <lb/>examine the possible interactions with target enzyme using <lb/>Dock Methodology of computational DOCK software. <lb/>The docking methodology consists of many parameters <lb/>such as target selection and preparation, isolation of <lb/>binding cavity with site finder, preparation of ligands, <lb/>and finally docking to its receptor. The crystal structure <lb/>of a-amylase was retrieved from Protein Data Bank (PDB <lb/>ID: 1M17) having a co-crystal ligand erlotinib and water <lb/>molecules are removed and protein structure were energy <lb/>minimized using default settings. The ligands are built <lb/>using builder in Marvin sketch and energy minimized <lb/>using MMFF94x force field. The docking protocol was <lb/>carried out with ligand mbd file, Triangle Matcher as <lb/>Placement, Rescoring using London dG scoring and <lb/>finally optimized poses are ranked using GBVI/WSA <lb/>DG score. The docking poses were browsed visually and <lb/>best interactions were isolated and computed with ligand <lb/>interactions (El-Azab et al., 2017). <lb/>ADME Predictions <lb/>The in silico ADME properties of these synthesized <lb/>compounds were calculated by using the online server <lb/>preADMET (http://preadmet.bmdrc.org/). The ADMET <lb/>properties, human intestinal absorption (HIA), Caco-2 <lb/>cell permeability, Maden Darby Canine Kidney (MDCK) <lb/>cell permeability, plasma protein binding and blood brain <lb/>barrier penetration (BBB) were predicted using this <lb/>program. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgments <lb/>The authors are thankful to Director, Institute of <lb/>Science and Technology, JNTUH Hyderabad for providing <lb/>the laboratory facilities and also thankful to UGC, New <lb/>Delhi for providing funding for carrying out this work. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Conflict of interest <lb/>The authors declare no conflict of interest. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>Boussari O, Romain G, Remontet L, et al (2018). A new approach <lb/>to estimate time-to-cure from cancer registries data. Cancer <lb/>Epidemiol, 53, 72-80. <lb/>Bustamante J, Lopes EC, Garcia M, et al (2004). Disruption of <lb/>mitochondrial membrane potential during apoptosis induced <lb/>by PSC 833 and CsA in multidrug-resistant lymphoid <lb/>leukemia. Toxicol Appl Pharmacol, 199, 44-51. <lb/>Chakraborty S, Rahman T (2012). The difficulties in cancer <lb/>treatment. Ecancermedicalscience, 6, ed16. <lb/>Dai Y, Hogan S, Schmelz EM, et al (2011). Selective growth <lb/>inhibition of human breast cancer cells by graviola fruit <lb/>extract in vitro and in vivo involving downregulation of <lb/>EGFR expression. Nutr Cancer, 63, 795-801. <lb/>El-Azab AS, Al-Dhfyan A, Abdel-Aziz AA-M, et al (2017). <lb/>Synthesis, anticancer and apoptosis-inducing activities of <lb/>quinazoline-isatin conjugates: epidermal growth factor <lb/>receptor-tyrosine kinase assay and molecular docking <lb/>studies. J Enzyme Inhib Med Chem, 32, 935-44. <lb/>Fiedler W, Mesters R, Heuser M, et al (2010). An open-label, <lb/>Phase I study of cediranib (RECENTIN™) in patients with <lb/>acute myeloid leukemia. Leukemia Res, 34, 196-202. <lb/>Gálvez J, Polo S, Insuasty B, et al (2018). Design, facile <lb/>synthesis, and evaluation of novel spiro-and pyrazolo [1, 5-c] <lb/>quinazolines as cholinesterase inhibitors: Molecular docking <lb/>and MM/GBSA studies. Comput Biol Chem, 74, 218-29. <lb/>Gupta T, Rohilla A, Pathak A, et al (2018). Current perspectives <lb/>on quinazolines with potent biological activities: A review. <lb/>Synth Commun, 48, 1099-127. <lb/>Helal M, El-Awdan S, Salem M, et al (2015). Synthesis, <lb/>biological evaluation and molecular modeling of novel series <lb/>of pyridine derivatives as anticancer, anti-inflammatory and <lb/>analgesic agents. Spectrochim Acta A Mol Biomol Spectrosc, <lb/>135, 764-73. <lb/>Helfrich BA, Kim J, Gao D, et al (2016). Barasertib (AZD1152), <lb/>a small molecule aurora B inhibitor, inhibits the growth of <lb/>SCLC cell lines in vitro and in vivo. Mol Cancer Ther, 50, <lb/>2314-22. <lb/>Jabir NR, Firoz CK, Bhushan A, et al (2018). The use of <lb/>Azoles containing natural products in cancer prevention <lb/>and treatment: An overview. Anticancer Agents Med Chem, <lb/>18, 6-14. <lb/>Kumar NP, Thatikonda S, Tokala R, et al (2018a). Sulfamic <lb/>acid promoted one-pot synthesis of phenanthrene <lb/>fused-dihydrodibenzo-quinolinones: Anticancer activity, <lb/>tubulin polymerization inhibition and apoptosis inducing <lb/>studies. Bioorg Med Chem, 26, 1996-2008. <lb/>Kumar NR, Swaroop DK, Punna N, et al (2018b). Synthesis <lb/>of Novel Pyrido [2′, 3′: 3, 4] Pyrazolo [1, 5-a] Quinazoline <lb/>Derivatives, their biological evaluation and molecular <lb/>modelling studies. ChemistrySelect, 3, 7813-21. <lb/>Kummar S, Takimoto C (2018). Novel designs of early phase <lb/>trials for cancer therapeutics, Academic Press.1-3 <lb/>Kurumurthy C, Veeraswamy B, Rao PS, et al (2014). Synthesis <lb/>of novel 1, 2, 3-triazole tagged pyrazolo [3, 4-b] pyridine <lb/>derivatives and their cytotoxic activity. Bioorg Med Chem <lb/>Lett, 24, 746-9. <lb/>Mani GS, Shaik SP, Tangella Y, et al (2017). A facile I 2-catalyzed <lb/>synthesis of imidazo [1, 2-a] pyridines via sp 3 C-H <lb/>functionalization of azaarenes and evaluation of anticancer <lb/>activity. Org Biomol Chem, 15, 6780-91. <lb/>Mikhalev AI, Kon&apos;shin ME, Ovodenko LA, et al (1995). <lb/>Synthesis, anti-inflammatory and analgesic activity of <lb/>pyrido[2,1-b]quinazoline derivatives. Pharm Chem J, 29, <lb/>124-6. <lb/>Moghaddam S, Barta P, Mirabolfathinejad S, et al (2009). <lb/>Curcumin inhibits COPD-like airway inflammation and lung <lb/>cancer progression in mice. Carcinogenesis, 30, 1949-56. <lb/>Motyckova G, Stone RM (2015). Development of midostaurin <lb/>as a tyrosine kinase inhibitor. In &apos;Targeted Therapy of Acute <lb/>Myeloid Leukemia&apos;, Eds Springer, pp 201-14 <lb/>Moussa G, Alaaeddine R, Alaeddine LM, et al (2018). Novel <lb/>click modifiable thioquinazolinones as anti-inflammatory <lb/>agents: Design, synthesis, biological evaluation and docking <lb/>study. Eur J Med Chem, 144, 635-50. <lb/>Nagender P, Reddy GM, Kumar RN, et al (2014). Synthesis, <lb/>cytotoxicity, antimicrobial and anti-biofilm activities of novel <lb/>pyrazolo [3, 4-b] pyridine and pyrimidine functionalized 1, <lb/>2, 3-triazole derivatives. Bioorg Med Chem Lett, 24, 2905-8. <lb/>Nekkanti S, Pooladanda V, Veldandi M, et al (2017). Synthesis <lb/>of 1, 2, 3-Triazolo-fused-tetrahydro-β-carboline Derivatives <lb/>via 1, 3-Dipolar Cycloaddition Reaction: Cytotoxicity <lb/>Evaluation and DNA-Binding studies. ChemistrySelect, 2, <lb/>7210-21. <lb/>Oluwaseye A, Uzairu A, Shallangwa G, et al (2018). Qsar <lb/>studies on derivatives of Quinazoline-4 (3h)-Ones with <lb/>anticonvulsant activities. J Eng Exact Sci, 4, 0255-64. <lb/>Pordeli M, Nakhjiri M, Safavi M, et al (2017). Anticancer <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="footnote">Asian Pacific Journal of Cancer Prevention, Vol 21 </note>

			<page>421 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">DOI:10.31557/APJCP.2020.21.2.411 <lb/>Design, One Pot Synthesis and Molecular Docking Studies <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>effects of synthetic hexahydrobenzo [g] chromen-4-one <lb/>derivatives on human breast cancer cell lines. Breast Cancer, <lb/>24, 299-311. <lb/>Riyasdeen A, Senthilkumar R, Periasamy VS, et al (2014). <lb/>Antiproliferative and apoptosis-induction studies of a <lb/>metallosurfactant in human breast cancer cell MCF-7. RSC <lb/>Advances, 4, 49953-9. <lb/>Sagir H, Rai P, Neha S, et al (2016). S-Nanoparticle/SDS: <lb/>an efficient and recyclable catalytic system for synthesis <lb/>of substituted 4H-pyrido[1,2-a]pyrimidines in aqueous <lb/>admicellar medium. RSC Advances, 6, 73924-32. <lb/>Samiksha M, Gupta P (2018). Novel chemical synthesis and <lb/>medicinal aspects of some quinazoline and pyrimidine <lb/>derivatives. Int J Res, 5, 1855-71. <lb/>Sgorbati S, Levi M, Sparvoli E, et al (1986). Cytometry and flow <lb/>cytometry of 4′, 6-diamidino-2-phenylindole (DAPI)-stained <lb/>suspensions of nuclei released from fresh and fixed tissues <lb/>of plants. Physiol Plant, 68, 471-6. <lb/>Shagufta, Ahmad I (2017). An insight into the therapeutic <lb/>potential of quinazoline derivatives as anticancer agents. <lb/>Med Chem Comm, 8, 871-85. <lb/>Taylor AP, Robinson RP, Fobian YM, et al (2016). Modern <lb/>advances in heterocyclic chemistry in drug discovery. Org <lb/>Biomol Chem, 14, 6611-37. <lb/>Thun MJ, DeLancey JO, Center MM, et al (2010). The global <lb/>burden of cancer: priorities for prevention. Carcinogenesis, <lb/>31, 100-10. <lb/>Tilley JW, Levitan P, Lind J, et al (1987). N-(heterocyclic alkyl) <lb/>pyrido[2,1-b]quinazoline-8-carboxamides as orally active <lb/>antiallergy agents. J Med Chem, 30, 185-93. <lb/>Vundru SS, Kale RK, Singh RP (2013). β-Sitosterol induces G1 <lb/>arrest and causes depolarization of mitochondrial membrane <lb/>potential in breast carcinoma MDA-MB-231 cells. BMC <lb/>Complem Altern M, 13, 280. <lb/>Ward TH, Cummings J, Dean E, et al (2008). Biomarkers of <lb/>apoptosis. Br J Cancer, 99, 841. <lb/>Yang K, Xiang J, Bao G, et al (2013). Synthesis of Highly <lb/>Substituted 4H-Pyrido[1,2-a]pyrimidines via a one-Pot <lb/>three-component condensation reaction. ACS Comb Sci, <lb/>15, 519-24. <lb/>Zaki YH, Al-Gendey MS, Abdelhamid AO (2018). A facile <lb/>synthesis, and antimicrobial and anticancer activities of <lb/>some pyridines, thioamides, thiazole, urea, quinazoline, <lb/>β-naphthyl carbamate, and pyrano [2, 3-d] thiazole <lb/>derivatives. Chem Cent J, 12, 70. <lb/>Zhao B, Li Y, Xu P, et al (2016). Discovery of substituted 1 <lb/>H-pyrazolo [3, 4-b] pyridine derivatives as potent and <lb/>selective FGFR kinase inhibitors. ACS Med Chem Lett, 7, <lb/>629-34. <lb/>Zhu YY, Huang HY, Wu YL (2015). Anticancer and apoptotic <lb/>activities of oleanolic acid are mediated through cell cycle <lb/>arrest and disruption of mitochondrial membrane potential <lb/>in HepG2 human hepatocellular carcinoma cells. Mol Med <lb/>Rep, 12, 5012-8. <lb/>Żuryń A, Litwiniec A, Safiejko-Mroczka B, et al (2016). The <lb/>effect of sulforaphane on the cell cycle, apoptosis and <lb/>expression of cyclin D1 and p21 in the A549 non-small cell <lb/>lung cancer cell line. Int J Oncol, 48, 2521-33. <lb/>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-<lb/>Non Commercial 4.0 International License. </listBibl>


	</text>
</tei>