<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>Vol.:(0123456789) 1 3 <lb/>Natural Products and Bioprospecting (2020) 10:57-66 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1007/s13659-020-00235-3 <lb/>ORIGINAL ARTICLE <lb/>Artificial Erythrina Alkaloids from Three Erythrina Plants, E. variegata, <lb/>E. crista-galli and E. arborescens <lb/>Bing-Jie Zhang 1,2 • Jing Wu 1 • Mei-Fen Bao 1,2 • Fang Wang 1,3 • Xiang-Hai Cai 1,3 <lb/>Received: 7 January 2020 / Accepted: 19 February 2020 / Published online: 4 March 2020 <lb/>© The Author(s) 2020 <lb/>Abstract <lb/>Fourteen unprecedented artificial Erythrina alkaloids were isolated from the Erythrina variegata, E. crista-galli and E. <lb/>arborescens (Fabaceae). The structures of these alkaloids were determined by spectroscopic analyses. Their possible forma-<lb/>tions were proposed. All isolated compounds showed no cytotoxicity and hypoglycemic activity at cell screening bioassay. <lb/>Keywords Fabaceae • Erythrina variegata • E. crista-galli • E. arborescens • Artificial products • Erythrina alkaloids <lb/></front>

			<body>1 Introduction <lb/>The Erythrina-type alkaloids with 6/5/6/6 spirocycle sys-<lb/>tems and stable 5S-chiral center are derived from two <lb/>tyrosine units via oxidative coupling and intramolecular <lb/>rearrangement. Since the first phytochemical research on <lb/>Erythrina alkaloid in 1930s [1], the total number now stands <lb/>at well over 110 alkaloids reported from plants of Erythrina <lb/>genus [2]. Bioassay screening of these alkaloids showed <lb/>anxiolytic-like actitivity [3], induced sleep [4], anticonvul-<lb/>sant actitivity [5], neuronal nicotinic acetylcholine recep-<lb/>tor antagonism [6], leishmanicidal [7], anticataract [7], and <lb/>antifeedant activity [8]. Our previous research disclosed <lb/>natural dimeric [9, 10] and trimeric [11] Erythrina alka-<lb/>loids, alkaloidal glucosides [10], and complex monomers <lb/>[12-14]. However, during the extraction and separation <lb/>of Erythrina alkaloids, some artificial products would be <lb/>produced. Consideration of the NMR spectra characteristics <lb/>and potential activities of Erythrina alkaloid, we here sys-<lb/>tematically summarized these artifacts from E. arborescens, <lb/>E. crista-galli and E. variegata (Fig. 1). Their cytotoxicity <lb/>against three cancer cells and hypoglycemic activity on 3T3-<lb/>L1 myoblasts cell were screened. This paper will describe <lb/>their isolation, structure determination and possible mecha-<lb/>nism of formation. <lb/>2 Results and Discussion <lb/>Alkaloid 1 was obtained as white amorphous powder. Its IR <lb/>absorption bands at 3441, 1640, 1503, 1480 cm -1 indicated <lb/>the presence of the hydroxyls and aromatic rings. Moreo-<lb/>ver, the UV absorptions at 204, 239 and 290 nm indicated <lb/>a tetrahydroisoquinoline chromophore [15]. These spectra <lb/>were consistent with the characteristics of an Erythrina <lb/>alkaloid. Alkaloid 1 had a molecular formula C 39 H 40 N 2 O 9 <lb/>as established by the HRESIMS m/z at 681.2811 [M+H] + , <lb/>together with the 1 H and 13 C NMR spectroscopic data. In <lb/>the 1 H NMR spectrum of 1 (Table 1), four aromatic singlet <lb/>proton (δ H 7.08, 7.01, 6.74 × 2), two pairs of olefin [δ H 7.16 <lb/>(dd, J = 10.2, 4.2 Hz), 5.92 (d, J = 10.2 Hz), and 6.56 (dd, <lb/>J = 10.2, 2.4 Hz), 6.06 (d, J = 10.2 Hz)], two methylenedi-<lb/>oxy group (δ H 5.96, 5.94, 5.93 and 5.92), and two methoxyl <lb/>group (δ H 3.29 and 3.24) signals indicated that 1 might be an <lb/>Erythrina alkaloid dimer. In comparison with the reported <lb/>dimer, erythrivarine A [9], alkaloid 1 had three more sig-<lb/>nals at δ C 208.1, 47.5 and 31.2 in the 13 C NMR spectra and <lb/>56 mass units higher in molecular weight, which showed <lb/>Bing-Jie Zhang and Jing Wu have contributed equally to this work. <lb/>Dedicated to Professor Han-Dong Sun on the occasion of his <lb/>80th birthday. <lb/></body>

			<front>* Xiang-Hai Cai <lb/>xhcai@mail.kib.ac.cn <lb/>1 <lb/>State Key Laboratory of Phytochemistry and Plant <lb/>Resources in West China, Kunming Institute of Botany, <lb/>Chinese Academy of Sciences, Kunming 650201, China <lb/>2 <lb/>University of Chinese Academy of Sciences, Beijing 100049, <lb/>China <lb/>3 <lb/>Yunnan Key Laboratory of Natural Medicinal Chemistry, <lb/>Kunming 650201, China <lb/></front>

			<page>58 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">B.-J. Zhang et al. <lb/>1 3 <lb/></note>

			<body>an extra 2-oxopropyl group in 1. In the HMBC spectrum, <lb/>correlations of δ H 4.20 (H-8) with δ C 53.9 (C-10), δ C 136.2 <lb/>(C-7) and δ C 208.1 (C=O) indicated the 2-oxopropyl group <lb/>at C-8. Further analysis of the 2D NMR revealed that the <lb/>other parts of compound 1 were consistent with those of <lb/>erythrivarine A. <lb/>Alkaloids 2 and 3 showed the same molecular formula <lb/>C 40 H 42 N 2 O 9 as established by HRESIMS (m/z 695.2968 <lb/>[M+H] + in 2; m/z 695.2970 [M+H] + in 3). In the 1 H and <lb/>13 C NMR spectra, the chemical shifts of 2 and 3 showed <lb/>good agreement with those of 1, except those signals around <lb/>the C-11′ position (C-10′/11′/12′). The C-11′ carbon of 1 <lb/>was resonated at δ 64.9, however, signals of the same carbon <lb/>were observed at δ 74.7 and δ 74.5 in 2 and 3, respectively. <lb/>In addition, an extra methoxyl group (δ H 3.54 in 2, δ H 3.36 <lb/>in 3) was observed, which indicated that both 2 and 3 had a <lb/>methoxyl group at the C-11′ position instead of a hydroxyl <lb/>group in 1. Chemical shifts of H-10′, H-11′ and H-17′ pro-<lb/>tons (Table 1) of 2 and 3 implied the configuration of 11′-<lb/>OCH 3 in 2 and 3 were different. In the ROESY spectrum, <lb/>the NOE correlation of H-3′β/H-4′β and H-11′/H-4′α in 3 <lb/>suggested its 11′-OCH 3 was in β-orientation. The NOE cor-<lb/>relation of H-11′/H-4′β in 2 suggested its 11′-OCH 3 was in <lb/>α-orientation. <lb/>The HRESIMS of 4 showed the pseudomolecular ion at <lb/>m/z 370.1651 [M+H] + (calc. for C 21 H 23 NO 5 , 370.1652). The <lb/>13 C NMR spectrum of 4 showed a methine at 64.7 ppm, <lb/>which indicated the existence of hydroxy substituent. The <lb/>HMBC correlation between δ H 7.05 (H-17) with δ C 64.7 <lb/>suggested the hydroxy at C-11. Through detailed compari-<lb/>son of the 1D and 2D NMR spectrum, 4 was basically the <lb/>same as erythranine [16] except for the 2-oxopropyl sub-<lb/>stituent (δ C 207.9, 47.8 and 30.8). The HMBC spectrum <lb/>showed correlations from δ H 3.98 (H-8) to δ C 52.6 (C-10), <lb/>δ C 127.6 (C-7) and δ C 207.9 (C=O) disclosed 4 to be <lb/>8-(2-oxopropyl)-erythranine. <lb/>Alkaloid 5 displayed a hydrogen adduct ion at m/z <lb/>354.1709 [M+H] + (calc. for C 21 H 23 NO 4 , 354.1707). The <lb/>1D NMR spectroscopic data of compound 5 were similar to <lb/>those of 4 except for the following differentiations: in the 1 H <lb/>NMR spectrum, the signal displayed at δ H 4.72 in 4 which <lb/>was assigned to the active hydrogen in the hydroxy was <lb/>disappeared in compound 5. Correspondingly, the methine <lb/>signal at δ C 64.7 (C-11) in compound 4 was replaced with <lb/>a methylene (δ C 26.0) in 5. Thus, compound 5 was an ana-<lb/>logue of 4 without the hydroxy moiety and determined to be <lb/>8-(2-oxopropyl)-erythraline. <lb/>The HRESIMS of 6 gave a hydrogen adduct ion at m/z <lb/>384.1806 [M+H] + , indicative of a molecular formula of <lb/>C 22 H 25 NO 5 . In comparing with those of 4, the 1 H NMR <lb/>spectrum of 6 gave signal of an addional methyoxyl group <lb/>(δ H 3.55, s, 3H), and its 13 C NMR spectrum showed an <lb/>downfield chemical shift δ C 74.8. These findings suggested <lb/>the C-11 of 6 was substituted by a methoxy rather than <lb/>a hydroxy. Thus, the structure of 6 was determined to be <lb/>8-(2-oxopropyl))-11-methoxy-erythraline. <lb/>Fig. 1 Chemical structures of 14 artificial Erythrina alkaloids <lb/></body>

			<page>59 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Artificial Erythrina Alkaloids from Three Erythrina Plants, E. variegata, E. crista-galli… <lb/></note>

			<page>1 3 <lb/></page>

			<body>Table 1 1 H and 13 C NMR <lb/>spectroscopic data for 1-3 in <lb/>acetone-d 6 (δ in ppm and J in <lb/>Hz) <lb/>1 H NMR recorded at 600 MHz, 13 C NMR recorded at 150 MHz <lb/>Enrty <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>δ H <lb/>δ C <lb/>δ H <lb/>δ C <lb/>δ H <lb/>δ C <lb/>1 <lb/>7.16, dd (10.2, 4.2) 124.6 d 7.16, d (10.2) <lb/>124.8 d 7.06, overlap <lb/>124.7 d <lb/>2 <lb/>5.92, d (10.2) <lb/>132.1 d 6.00, d (10.2) <lb/>132.2 d 6.00, d (10.2) <lb/>132.2 d <lb/>3 <lb/>3.68, m <lb/>76.9 d 3.73, m <lb/>76.8 d 3.73, m <lb/>77.0 d <lb/>4 <lb/>2.38, dd (11.4, 6.0) <lb/>43.6 t 2.44, dd (10.8, 6.0) <lb/>42.9 t 2.40, dd (10.8, 6.0) <lb/>43.0 t <lb/>1.68, t (11.4) <lb/>1.69, t (10.8) <lb/>1.70, t (10.8) <lb/>5 <lb/>69.2 s <lb/>68.9 s <lb/>69.2 s <lb/>6 <lb/>139.6 s <lb/>139.7 s <lb/>138.2 s <lb/>7 <lb/>136.2 d <lb/>136.8 d <lb/>135.6 d <lb/>8 <lb/>4.20, m <lb/>69.7 d 4.30, m <lb/>68.3 d 4.23, br s <lb/>69.2 d <lb/>10 <lb/>3.48, dd (11.4, 5.4) <lb/>53.9 t 3.34, dd (11.4, 4.8) <lb/>50.7 t 3.47, dd (11.4, 4.8) <lb/>53.2 t <lb/>2.51, overlap <lb/>2.77, br d (11.4) <lb/>2.61, overlap <lb/>11 <lb/>4.65, m <lb/>64.7 d 4.66, m <lb/>64.7 d 4.75, m <lb/>64.8 d <lb/>12 <lb/>134.1 s <lb/>133.9 s <lb/>133.9 s <lb/>13 <lb/>132.2 s <lb/>132.6 s <lb/>132.6 s <lb/>14 <lb/>6.74, s <lb/>106.1 d 6.73, s <lb/>105.8 d 6.90, s <lb/>106.1 d <lb/>15 <lb/>147.7 s <lb/>147.3 s <lb/>147.3 s <lb/>16 <lb/>147.2 s <lb/>147.3 s <lb/>147.3 s <lb/>17 <lb/>7.01, s <lb/>108.7 d 7.01, s <lb/>108.6 d 7.06, s <lb/>107.3 d <lb/>OCH 2 O <lb/>5.96, s <lb/>101.8 t 5.96, s <lb/>101.8 t 5.96, s <lb/>102.0 t <lb/>5.94, s <lb/>5.95, s <lb/>5.95, s <lb/>3-OCH 3 <lb/>3.29, s <lb/>56.3 q 3.26, s <lb/>56.2 q 3.25, s <lb/>56.2 q <lb/>11-OH <lb/>4.63, d (5.4) <lb/>CH 2 COCH 3 3.21, overlap <lb/>47.5 t 3.42, m <lb/>47.1 t 3.35, m <lb/>47.5 t <lb/>2.71, m <lb/>2.71, m <lb/>2.64, m <lb/>CH 2 COCH 3 <lb/>208.1 s <lb/>207.8 s <lb/>208.2 s <lb/>CH 2 COCH 3 2.14, s <lb/>31.2 q 2.13, s <lb/>31.0 q 2.13, s <lb/>31.2 q <lb/>1′ <lb/>6.56, dd (10.2, 2.4) 125.5 d 6.55, dd (10.2, 1.8) 125.5 d 6.54, dd (10.2, 1.8) 125.7 d <lb/>2′ <lb/>6.06, d (10.2) <lb/>133.6 d 6.06, d (10.2) <lb/>133.6 d 6.09, d (10.2) <lb/>133.6 d <lb/>3′ <lb/>3.32, m <lb/>76.8 d 3.93, m <lb/>76.8 d 4.06, m <lb/>76.6 d <lb/>4′ <lb/>2.46, dd (11.4, 5.4) <lb/>41.6 t 2.44, dd (10.8, 6.0) <lb/>41.6 t 2.49, dd (10.8, 6.0) <lb/>40.9 t <lb/>1.79, t (11.4) <lb/>1.79, t (10.8) <lb/>1.77, t (10.8) <lb/>5′ <lb/>68.2 s <lb/>68.4 s <lb/>68.3 s <lb/>6′ <lb/>142.8 s <lb/>143.2 s <lb/>143.4 s <lb/>7′ <lb/>5.58, s <lb/>127.3 d 5.57, s <lb/>127.4 d 5.58, s <lb/>127.4 d <lb/>8′ <lb/>4.92, s <lb/>66.4 d 4.90, s <lb/>64.6 d 4.92, s <lb/>64.5 d <lb/>10′ <lb/>3.36, dd (13.2, 4.8) <lb/>50.5 t 3.42, dd (13.2, 4.0) <lb/>47.0 t 3.21, m <lb/>43.2 t <lb/>2.83, overlap <lb/>2.83, dd (13.2, 5.0) <lb/>3.15, m <lb/>11′ <lb/>4.78, m <lb/>64.9 d 4.24, s <lb/>74.7 d 4.00, s <lb/>74.5 d <lb/>12′ <lb/>132.5 s <lb/>129.2 s <lb/>129.2 s <lb/>13′ <lb/>133.4 s <lb/>132.6 s <lb/>132.6 s <lb/>14′ <lb/>6.74, s <lb/>105.9 d 6.78, s <lb/>106.0 t 6.75, s <lb/>105.8 d <lb/>15′ <lb/>147.3 s <lb/>147.3 s <lb/>148.4 s <lb/>16′ <lb/>147.2 s <lb/>147.3 s <lb/>147.3 s <lb/>17′ <lb/>7.08, s <lb/>106.8 d 6.92, s <lb/>108.1 d 7.37, s <lb/>110.3 d <lb/>OC&apos;H 2 O <lb/>5.93, s <lb/>101.7 t 5.95, s <lb/>101.8 t 5.95, s <lb/>101.8 t <lb/>5.92, s <lb/>5.94, s <lb/>5.94, s <lb/>3′-OCH 3 <lb/>3.24, s <lb/>56.2 q 3.29, s <lb/>56.2 q 3.35, s <lb/>56.3 q <lb/>11′-OCH 3 <lb/>3.54, s <lb/>58.1 q 3.36, s <lb/>58.0 q <lb/></body>

			<page>60 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">B.-J. Zhang et al. <lb/>1 3 <lb/></note>

			<body>The molecular formula of 7 was determined to be <lb/>C 21 H 25 NO 5 from the HRESIMS m/z at 394.1626 [M+Na] + . <lb/>Its 1 H NMR spectrum showed two aromatic singlet protons <lb/>(δ H 6.84 and 6.76), three conjugate olefin signals (δ H 6.60, <lb/>6.10 and 5.67), and four methoxy groups (δ H 3.28, 3.70, 3.78 <lb/>and 3.97). The 13 C NMR spectrum of 7 showed three meth-<lb/>ylenes (δ C 24.6, 43.3, 44.4), two methines (δ C 76.9 and 70.5) <lb/>and a carbonyl (δ C 172.1). These data suggested 7 might be <lb/>a carbomethoxyl derivative of erysotrine [17]. The HMBC <lb/>correlations from δ H 3.78 (OCH 3 ) and δ H 4.33(H-8) to δ C <lb/>172.1 (C=O) assigned the carbomethoxy at C-8. The molec-<lb/>ular formula of 8 was determined to be C 20 H 21 NO 6 from the <lb/>HRESIMS m/z at 372.1444 [M+H] + . The 1 H and 13 C NMR <lb/>the structural pattern of 8 was identical to that of 5, and the <lb/>additional carbomethoxyl moiety was identical to that of 7. <lb/>Accordingly, the structures of 7 and 8 were determined to be <lb/>8-carbomethoxyerysotrine and 8-carbomethoxyerythranine, <lb/>respectively. <lb/>Alkaloid 9 showed molecular ion peaks at m/z 370.1652 <lb/>[M+H] + , suggesting the molecular formulae C 21 H 24 NO 5 . In <lb/>comparing with compound 5, the 1 H and 13 C NMR signal of <lb/>δ H 2.13 (CH 3 ) and δ C 207.7(CH 2 COCH 3 ) in 5 were changed <lb/>to δ H 3.61 (OCH 3 ) and δ C 172.5(CH 2 COOCH 3 ) in 9, respec-<lb/>tively. The remaining NMR data were almost identical to <lb/>those of 5. Thus, the structure of 9 was determined to be <lb/>8-acetatemethoxyerythraline. <lb/>The molecular formulas of compounds 10 and 11 <lb/>were deduced to be C 21 H 23 NO 6 and C 22 H 25 NO 6 from the <lb/>HRESIMS at m/z 386.1599 [M+H] + and 400.1758 [M+H] + , <lb/>respectively. The 1 H and 13 C NMR data of both 10 and 11 <lb/>are very similar to those of 9 except that the methylene sig-<lb/>nal was replaced by an oxymethine signal at the C-11 posi-<lb/>tion. Further, in the 13 C NMR, the signal for C-11 appeared <lb/>at 64.8 and 74.7 ppm for compounds 10 and 11, similar <lb/>to that of 4 and 6, respectively. Thus, 10 was identified as <lb/>8-acetatemethoxyerythranine. 11 had an extra methoxy and <lb/>was identified as 8-acetatemethoxy-10β-methoxyerythraline. <lb/>The molecular formula 12 was established as C 22 H 27 NO 5 <lb/>based on the HRESIMS m/z = 386.1964 [M+H] + . From the <lb/>1 H and 13 C NMR data, the structure of 12 was very similar <lb/>to 9 except for the replacement of methylenedioxy group by <lb/>two methoxys at C-15 and C-16. This was confirmed from <lb/>the HMBC and HSQC spectra. Alkaloid 12 was thus identi-<lb/>fied as 8-acetatemethoxyerysotrine. <lb/>The HRESIMS m/z at 394.1628 [M+Na] + of 13 assigned <lb/>the molecular formula to be C 21 H 25 NO 5 , 58 mass units <lb/>higher than that of erysotrine. Its 13 C NMR spectrum gave <lb/>an additional methylene (δ C 34.9) and a carbonyl (δ C 172.3) <lb/>signals, indicating the existence of an acetyl group. The <lb/>HMBC correlations from δ H 2.51 (CH 2 CO) and δ H 4.14 <lb/>(H-8) to δ C 172.3 (C=O) suggested that the acetyl group was <lb/>located at C-8. Accordingly, the structure of 13 was deter-<lb/>mined to be 8-acetylerythsotrine. The molecular formula of <lb/>14 was dirermined to be C 20 H 21 NO 5 by the HRESIMS m/z <lb/>at 378.1313 [M+Na] + . The 1D NMR spectrum gave signals <lb/>similar to that of erythraline expect for the replacement of a <lb/>methylene by an acetyl group (δ C 35.4 and δ C 172.3). In the <lb/>HMBC spectrum, the correlations from δ H 4.07 (H-8) to δ C <lb/>172.3 (COOH) and δ H 2.74 (CH 2 COOH) to δ C 65.4 (C-8) <lb/>and δ C 172.3 (COOH) confirmed that 14 was an 8-acetyl <lb/>derivative of erythraline. <lb/>The configurations of H-8 for compound 1-14 were deter-<lb/>mined to be β based on ROESY experiments with correla-<lb/>tions of H-3β/H-4 eq , H-4 eq /H-10 ax and H-10 eq /H-8 (Fig. 2). <lb/>Further, together with 5S-configuration in all Erythrina <lb/>alkaloids [18], so absolute configuration of alkaloids 1-14 <lb/>could be determined. <lb/>Since N-containing compounds were main candicates of <lb/>anticancer and hypoglycemic drugs, so alkaloids 1-14 were <lb/>evaluated for their cytotoxicity against human A-549 lung <lb/>cancer, SGC-7901 gastric cancer, and HeLa cell lines using <lb/>the MTT method. In addition, their hypoglycemic activity on <lb/>3T3-L1 myoblasts cell were screened. Unfortunately, none <lb/>of them showed positive activity. Alkaloids 1-14 possessed <lb/>acetonyl, acetyl methyl, acetate, or methyl formate groups, <lb/>which indicated they were artificial products. Without con-<lb/>sidering the artifitial units, these alkaloids are known. Duing <lb/>the extraction and isolation, methanol, acetone, petroleum <lb/>ether, especial ethyl acetate, were used as solvents. Accord-<lb/>ingly, acetone and residual of acetic acid, methyl acetate <lb/>and methyl formate in above solvents would become reac-<lb/>tion reagents. Alkaloids 1-6 and 9-14 were formed firstly <lb/>through an iminium immediate by oxidation, then by nucle-<lb/>ophilic attack from carbanion of acetone, acetic acid, and <lb/>methyl acetate in base condition. On the other hand, the <lb/>iminium immediate could be tautomerized to inmine and <lb/>Fig. 2 Selected NOE interaction of alkaloid 9 <lb/></body>

			<page>61 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Artificial Erythrina Alkaloids from Three Erythrina Plants, E. variegata, E. crista-galli… <lb/>1 3 <lb/></note>

			<body>attacked to methyl formate, generating the carbomethoxy <lb/>substitued products (7-8) (Fig. 3). <lb/>3 Experimental Section <lb/>3.1 General Experimental Procedures <lb/>Optical rotations were measured with a Jasco p-1020 digi-<lb/>tal polarimeter. UV spectra were recorded on a Shimadzu <lb/>2401PC spectrophotometer. IR spectra were obtained on <lb/>a Bruker Tensor 27 infrared spectrophotometer with KBr <lb/>pellets. 1 H, 13 C and 2D NMR spectra were obtained on <lb/>Bruker AV-600, AVANCE III-500 and 400 MHz spectrom-<lb/>eters with SiMe 4 as an internal standard. Chemical shifts <lb/>(δ) were expressed in ppm with reference to the solvent <lb/>signals. MS data were recorded on an UPLC-IT-TOF MS. <lb/>Column chromatography (CC) was performed on either <lb/>silica gel (200-300 mesh, Qingdao Marine Chemical Co., <lb/>Ltd., Qingdao, China) or RP-18 silica gel (20-45 μm, Fuji <lb/>Silysia Chemical Ltd., Japan). Fractions were monitored by <lb/>TLC on silica gel plates (GF254, Qingdao Marine Chemi-<lb/>cal Co., Ltd., Qingdao, China), and spots were visualized <lb/>with Dragendorff&apos;s reagent spray. MPLC was performed <lb/>using a Buchi pump system coupled with RP-18 silica gel-<lb/>packed glass columns (15 × 230 and 26 × 460 mm, respec-<lb/>tively). HPLC was performed using Waters 1525 pumps <lb/>coupled with analytical or preparative Sunfire C 18 columns <lb/>(4.6 × 150 and 19 × 250 mm, respectively). The HPLC <lb/>system employed a Waters 2998 photodiode array detector <lb/>and a Waters fraction collector III. <lb/>3.2 Plant Material <lb/>Flowers of E. variegata Linn and E. crista-galli Linn were <lb/>collected in February and April, respectively, 2014 in <lb/>Simao of Yunnan Province, People&apos;s Republic of China. <lb/>Leaves and flowers of Erythrina arborescens Roxb. Hort. <lb/>Beng were collected in October 2014 in Jianshui of Yun-<lb/>nan Province. These plant samples were identified by Dr. <lb/>Chun-Xia Zeng. The voucher specimens (Cai20140207, <lb/>Cai20140407, Cai20141003 and Cai20141004) have been <lb/>deposited in the State Key Laboratory of Phytochemistry <lb/>and Plant Resources in West China, Kunming Institute of <lb/>Botany, the Chinese Academy of Sciences. <lb/>3.3 Extraction and Isolation <lb/>The dried and powdered flowers of E. variegata (10.0 kg) <lb/>were extracted with 90% MeOH (25 L) for three times. The <lb/>extracts were concentrated under reduced pressure, and then <lb/>dissolved in 2% acetic acid to adjust pH to 2-3 and then par-<lb/>titioned twice with EtOAc. The aqueous layers were basified <lb/>with NH 3 •H 2 O to adjust pH to 8-9 and then extracted with <lb/>EtOAc to give a crude alkaloid fraction (110 g). The crude <lb/>alkaloid was subjected to column chromatography (CC) over <lb/>silica gel with gradient CHCl 3 -Acetone (1:0 to 1:1) to afford <lb/>seven fractions (Fr. I-Fr. VII). Fr. I (6.1 g) was divided into <lb/>2 subfractions (Fr. I-1-Fr. I-2) by using RP-MPLC eluting <lb/>Fig. 3 Possible formation of two typically artificial Erythrina alkaloids <lb/></body>

			<page>62 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">B.-J. Zhang et al. <lb/>1 3 <lb/></note>

			<body>with MeOH-H 2 O (50-100%). Fr. I-2 was isolated by pre-<lb/>parative C 18 HPLC column with a gradient of MeOH-H 2 O <lb/>(60:40-70:30, v/v) to obtain 9 (35 mg) and 11 (41 mg). Fr. II <lb/>(4.5 g) was separated using C 18 MPLC column with a gradi-<lb/>ent of MeOH-H 2 O (40:60-90:40, v/v) to afford 10 (35 mg) <lb/>and 8 (13 mg). Fr. IV (8.5 g) was fractionated by C 18 MPLC <lb/>column with a gradient of MeOH-H 2 O (10:90-90:10, v/v) <lb/>to give six subfractions (Fr. IV-1-Fr. IV-6). Fr. IV-2 was <lb/>subjected to a preparative C 18 HPLC column with a gradient <lb/>of MeOH-H 2 O (50:50-60:40, v/v) to afford 6 (20 mg) and <lb/>5 (32 mg) Fr. IV-4 was subjected to a preparative C 18 HPLC <lb/>column with a gradient of MeOH-H 2 O (70:30-80:20, v/v) <lb/>to give 1 (5 mg). Fr. V (12 g) was chromatographed on a <lb/>C 18 MPLC column eluted with a gradient of MeOH-H 2 O <lb/>(10:80-100:0, v/v) to give six subfractions (Fr. V-1-Fr.V-<lb/>6). 2 (29 mg) and 3 (21 mg) was obtained from Fr.V-5 <lb/>using a preparative C 18 HPLC column with a gradient of <lb/>MeOH-H 2 O (65:35-25:75, v/v). <lb/>Flowers of E. crista-galli (11 kg) were powdered and <lb/>extracted with 90% MeOH (25 L) for three times. The <lb/>extract was concentrated in vacuo to give a brown residue. <lb/>The crude alkaloid (90 g) were obtained using the same <lb/>acid-base treatment method described above, and then sub-<lb/>jected to column chromatography (CC) over silica gel and <lb/>eluted with gradient CHCl 3 -Acetone (1:0 to 1:1) to afford <lb/>four fractions (Fr. I-Fr. IV). Fr. I (12.1 g) was further chro-<lb/>matographed on a C 18 MPLC column eluted with a gradient <lb/>of MeOH-H 2 O (50:50-100:0, v/v) to give the two subfrac-<lb/>tions (Fr. I-1-Fr. I-2). Alkaloid 12 (51 mg) was obtained <lb/>from Fr. I-1 using a column chromatography (CC) over silica <lb/>gel and eluted with petroleum ether-acetone (4:1). <lb/>Crude alkaloid extract (85.2 g) and (62.5 g) were obtained <lb/>from the leaves (15.8 kg) and flowers (6.5 kg) of Eryth-<lb/>rina arborescens, respectively. The crude alkaloid of leaves <lb/>was divided into nine fractions (Fr. I-Fr. IX). Fr. V (7.1 g) <lb/>was fractionated by C 18 MPLC column with a gradient of <lb/>MeOH-H 2 O (20:80-80:20, v/v) to give three subfractions <lb/>(Fr. V-1-Fr. V-3). Fr. V-3 was subjected to a preparative C 18 <lb/>HPLC column with a gradient of MeOH-H 2 O (60:40-70:30, <lb/>v/v) to afford 4 (1 mg) and 14 (5 mg). The crude alkaloid <lb/>of flowers was divided into seven fractions (Fr. I-Fr. VII). 7 <lb/>was obtained from Fr. II by C 18 MPLC column with a gradi-<lb/>ent of MeOH-H 2 O (40:60-100:0, v/v) and then purified by <lb/>preparative C 18 HPLC column with a gradient MeOH-H 2 O <lb/>(50:50-60:40, v/v). Fr. IV (4.5 g) was chromatographed on <lb/>a C 18 MPLC column eluted with a gradient of MeOH-H 2 O <lb/>(20:80-70:30, v/v) to give four subfractions (Fr. IV-1-Fr. <lb/>IV-4). Fr. IV-3 was further purified by a preparative C 18 <lb/>HPLC column with a gradient of MeCN-H 2 O (25:75-35:65, <lb/>v/v) to afford 13 (20 mg). <lb/>8α-(2-oxopropyl)-erythrivarine A (1): white powder; <lb/>[ ] 20 <lb/>D -121.2 (c 0.2, MeOH); UV (MeOH) λ max (log ε) <lb/>204 (4.26), 239 (3.88) and 290 (3.46) nm; IR (KBr) ν max <lb/>3441, 2924, 1640, 1503, 1480, 1226, 1100, 1041 cm -1 ; 1 H <lb/>(600 MHz) and 13 C NMR (150 MHz) data (acetone-d 6 ), see <lb/>Table 1; positive HRESIMS m/z 681.2811 [M+H] + (calcd. <lb/>for C 39 H 41 N 2 O 9 , 681.2110). <lb/>8α-(2-oxopropyl)-11′-O-methyl-erythrivarine A (2): <lb/>white powder; [ ] 20 <lb/>D -114.1 (c 0.1, MeOH); UV (MeOH) <lb/>λ max (log ε) 203 (4.12), 238 (3.66) and 289 (3.43) nm; IR <lb/>(KBr) ν max 3441, 1639, 1490, 1234, 1101, 1040 cm -1 ; 1 H <lb/>(600 MHz) and 13 C NMR (150 MHz) data (acetone-d 6 ), see <lb/>Table 1; positive HRESIMS m/z 695.2968 [M+H] + (calcd. <lb/>for C 40 H 43 N 2 O 9 , 695.2969). <lb/>8α-(2-oxopropyl)-11′-epi-O-methyl-erythrivarine A <lb/>(3): white powder; [ ] 20 <lb/>D -165.2 (c 0.1, MeOH); UV (MeOH) <lb/>λ max (log ε) 204 (4.22), 238 (3.88) and 289 (3.46) nm; IR <lb/>(KBr) ν max 3441, 2924, 1629, 1503, 1482, 1234, 1100, <lb/>1040 cm -1 ; 1 H (600 MHz) and 13 C NMR (150 MHz) data <lb/>(acetone-d 6 ), see Table 1; positive HRESIMS m/z 695.2970 <lb/>[M+H] + (calcd. for C 40 H 43 N 2 O 9 , 695.2969). <lb/>8α-(2-oxopropyl)-erythrinine (4): white powder; <lb/>[ ] 20 <lb/>D + 133.0 (c 0.2, MeOH); UV (MeOH) λ max (log ε) <lb/>204 (4.71), 239 (3.63) and 289 (3.32) nm; IR (KBr) ν max <lb/>2930, 1630, 1503, 1489 cm -1 ; 1 H (600 MHz) and 13 C NMR <lb/>(150 MHz) data (acetone-d 6 ), see Tables 2 and 4; positive <lb/>HRESIMS m/z 370.1651 [M+H] + (calcd. for C 21 H 24 NO 5 , <lb/>370.1652). <lb/>8α-(2-oxopropyl)-erythraline (5): white powder; <lb/>[ ] 23 <lb/>D + 80.5 (c 0.10, MeOH); UV(MeOH) λ max (log ε) 201 <lb/>(4.11), 238 (2.37), 289(1.29) nm; IR (KBr) ν max 1712, 1480, <lb/>1423 cm -1 ; 1 H (600 MHz) and 13 C NMR (150 MHz) data <lb/>(acetone-d 6 ), see Tables 2 and 4; positive HRESIMS m/z <lb/>354.1709 [M+H] + (calcd. for C 21 H 23 NO 4 , 354.1707). <lb/>8α-(2-oxopropyl)-11-methoxy-erythraline (6): white <lb/>powder; [ ] 20 <lb/>D + 95.3 (c 0.1, MeOH); UV (MeOH) λ max <lb/>(log ε) 204 (4.76), 238 (3.74) and 288 (3.48) nm; IR (KBr) <lb/>ν max 1631, 1504, 1483 cm -1 ; 1 H (600 MHz) and 13 C NMR <lb/>(150 MHz) data (acetone-d 6 ), see Tables 2 and 4; positive <lb/>HRESIMS m/z 384.1806 [M+H] + (calcd. for C 22 H 26 NO 5 , <lb/>384.1805). <lb/>8α-carbomethoxyerysotrine (7): white powder; <lb/>[ ] 22 <lb/>D + 74.0 (c 0.21, CH 3 OH); UV (CH 3 OH) λ max (log ε) <lb/>203 (3.79), 225 (3.45) and 277 (3.05) nm; 1 H (400 Hz) and <lb/>13 C (125 Hz) NMR data (acetone-d 6 ), Tables 2 and 4; Posi-<lb/>tive ESIMS m/z 394 [M+Na] +. , HRESIMS m/z. 394.1626 <lb/>[M+Na] + ; (calcd. for C 21 H 25 NO 5 Na, 394.1625). <lb/>8α-carbomethoxyerythrinine (8): white powder; <lb/>[ ] 20 <lb/>D + 118.3 (c 0.1, MeOH); UV (MeOH) λ max (log ε) <lb/>205 (4.69), 239 (3.79) and 289 (3.51) nm; IR (KBr) ν max <lb/>2923, 1630, 1503, 1488 cm -1 ; 1 H (600 MHz) and 13 C NMR <lb/>(150 MHz) data (acetone-d 6 ), see Tables 2 and 4; positive <lb/>HRESIMS m/z 372.1444 [M+H] + (calcd. for C 20 H 22 NO 6 , <lb/>372.1443). <lb/>8α-acetatemethoxyerythraline (9): white powder; <lb/>[ ] 20 <lb/>D + 171 (c 0.1, MeOH); UV (MeOH) λ max (log ε) 204 <lb/></body>

			<page>63 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Artificial Erythrina Alkaloids from Three Erythrina Plants, E. variegata, E. crista-galli… <lb/></note>

			<page>1 3 <lb/></page>

			<body>(4.78), 239 (3.88) and 290 (3.52) nm; IR (KBr) ν max 1628, <lb/>1501, 1489 cm -1 ; 1 H (600 MHz) and 13 C NMR (150 MHz) <lb/>data (acetone-d 6 ), see Tables 3 and 4; positive HRESIMS <lb/>m/z 370.1652 [M+H] + (calcd. for C 21 H 24 NO 5 , 370.1653). <lb/>8α-acetatemethoxyerythrinine (10): white powder; <lb/>[ ] 20 <lb/>D + 89.4 (c 0.1, MeOH); UV (MeOH) λ max (log ε) 204 <lb/>(4.65), 238 (3.68) and 290 (3.33) nm; IR (KBr) ν max 2924, <lb/>1628, 1488 cm -1 ; 1 H (600 MHz) and 13 C NMR (150 MHz) <lb/>data (acetone-d 6 ), see Tables 3 and 4; positive HRESIMS <lb/>m/z 386.1599 [M+H] + (calcd. for C 21 H 24 NO 6 , 386.1598). <lb/>8α-acetatemethoxy-11β-methoxyerythraline (11): <lb/>white powder; [ ] 20 <lb/>D + 154.2 (c 0.2, MeOH); UV (MeOH) <lb/>λ max (log ε) 204 (4.62), 238 (3.74) and 289 (3.41) nm; IR <lb/>(KBr) ν max 1630, 1503, 1484 cm -1 ; 1 H (600 MHz) and <lb/>13 C NMR (150 MHz) data (acetone-d 6 ), see Tables 3 and <lb/>4; positive HRESIMS m/z 400.1758 [M+H] + (calcd. for <lb/>C 22 H 26 NO 6 , 400.1757). <lb/>8α-acetatemethoxyerysotrine (12): white powder; <lb/>[ ] 20 <lb/>D + 113.3 (c 0.1, MeOH); UV (MeOH) λ max (log ε) 204 <lb/>(4.72), 239 (3.66) and 288 (3.51) nm; IR (KBr) ν max 1628, <lb/>1503, 1488 cm -1 ; 1 H (600 MHz) and 13 C NMR (150 MHz) <lb/>data (acetone-d 6 ), see Tables 3 and 4; positive HRESIMS <lb/>m/z 386.1964 [M+H] + (calcd. for C 22 H 28 NO 5 , 386.1965). <lb/>8α-acetylerythsotrine (13): white powder; C 21 H 25 NO 5 ; <lb/>[ ] 22 <lb/>D + 5.2 (c 0.18, CH 3 OH); UV (CH 3 OH) λ max (log ε) 203 <lb/>(3.90), 229 (3.56) and 282 (2.93) nm; 1 H (400 Hz) and 13 C <lb/>(125 Hz) NMR data (acetone-d 6 ), Tables 3 and 4; Posi-<lb/>tive ESIMS m/z 394 [M+Na] +. , HRESIMS m/z. 394.1628 <lb/>[M+Na] + ; (calcd. for C 21 H 25 NO 5 Na, 394.1625). <lb/>8α-acetylerythraline (14): white powder; [ ] 20 <lb/>D + 105 <lb/>(c 0.1, MeOH); UV (MeOH) λ max (log ε) 204 (4.71), 249 <lb/>(3.72) and 289 (3.62) nm; IR (KBr) ν max 3341, 1639, 1503, <lb/>1442 cm -1 ; 1 H (600 MHz) and 13 C NMR (150 MHz) data <lb/>(acetone-d 6 ), see Tables 3 and 4; positive HRESIMS m/z <lb/>378.1313 [M+H] + (calcd. for C 20 H 22 NO 5 , 378.1314). <lb/>3.4 Cytotoxicity <lb/>The human A-549 lung cancer, SGC-7901 gastric cancer, <lb/>and HeLa cell lines were used in the cytotoxic assay. These <lb/>cells were grown in DMEM media (HyClone, USA) sup-<lb/>plemented with 10% fetal bovine serum (HyClone, USA) <lb/>at 37 °C in 5% CO 2 . The cytotoxicity of all alkaloids were <lb/>Table 2 1 H NMR spectroscopic data for 4-8 in acetone-d 6 (δ in ppm and J in Hz) <lb/>a1 H NMR recorded in 600 MHz <lb/>b1 H NMR recorded in 400 MH <lb/>Entry <lb/>δ H (4) a <lb/>δ H (5) a <lb/>δ H (6) a <lb/>δ H (7) b <lb/>δ H (8) a <lb/>1 <lb/>6.55, dd (10.2, 2.4) <lb/>6.72, dd (10.2, 2.4) <lb/>6.55, dd (10.2, 1.8) <lb/>6.60 dd (10.2, 1.9) <lb/>6.59, dd (10.2, 2.4) <lb/>2 <lb/>6.01, d (10.2) <lb/>6.68, d (10.2) <lb/>6.03, d (10.2) <lb/>6.10, d (10.2) <lb/>6.07, d (10.2) <lb/>3 <lb/>3.79, m <lb/>3.85, m <lb/>3.92, m <lb/>3.97, m <lb/>3.85, m <lb/>4 <lb/>2.38, dd (11.4, 5.4) <lb/>2.48, dd (11.4,5.6) <lb/>2.46, dd (11.4, 5.4) <lb/>2.53, dd (11.2, 5.7) <lb/>2.45, dd (11.4, 5.4) <lb/>1.65, t (11.4) <lb/>1.68, t (11.4) <lb/>1.66, t (11.4) <lb/>1.78, t (11.2) <lb/>1.73, t (11.4) <lb/>7 <lb/>5.67, s <lb/>5.63, s <lb/>5.64, s <lb/>5.67, s <lb/>5.71, s <lb/>8 <lb/>4.20, m <lb/>3.98, m <lb/>4.33, m <lb/>4.33, s <lb/>4.68, s <lb/>10 <lb/>3.48, dd (13.8, 4.8) <lb/>3.38, m <lb/>3.39, dd (13.8, 4.2) <lb/>3.49, m <lb/>3.57, dd (13.2, 4.8) <lb/>2.68, dd (13.8, 6,6) <lb/>2.77 (overlap) <lb/>3.09, dd (13.8, 4.2) <lb/>3.02 dd (12.9, 5.7) <lb/>2.92, dd (13.2, 4.8) <lb/>11 <lb/>4.75, m <lb/>2.77 (overlap) <lb/>4.18, t (4.2) <lb/>2.93, m <lb/>4.77, m <lb/>2.65, m <lb/>264, m <lb/>14 <lb/>6.70, s <lb/>6.72, s <lb/>6.74, s <lb/>6.84, s <lb/>6.73, s <lb/>17 <lb/>7.05, s <lb/>6.68, s <lb/>6.89, s <lb/>6.76, s <lb/>7.04, s <lb/>3-OCH 3 <lb/>3.25, s <lb/>3.28, s <lb/>3.28, s <lb/>3.28, s <lb/>3.23, s <lb/>11-OCH 3 <lb/>3.55, s <lb/>11-OH <lb/>4.72, d (4.8) <lb/>4.64, br s <lb/>15-OCH 3 <lb/>3.70, s <lb/>16-OCH 3 <lb/>3.97, s <lb/>OCH 2 O <lb/>6.01, s <lb/>5.92, s <lb/>5.96, s <lb/>5.95, s <lb/>5.99, s <lb/>5.90, s <lb/>5.94, s <lb/>5.94, s <lb/>CH 2 COCH 3 <lb/>2.90, dd (15.6, 4.8) <lb/>2.85 (overlap) <lb/>2.94, overlap <lb/>2.55, dd (15.6, 4.8) <lb/>2.58, dd (16.8, 8.0) <lb/>2.55, dd (15.6, 9.0) <lb/>CH 2 COCH 3 <lb/>2.13, s <lb/>2.13, s <lb/>2.12, s <lb/>COOCH 3 <lb/>3.78, s <lb/>3.72, s <lb/></body>

			<page>64 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">B.-J. Zhang et al. <lb/>1 3 <lb/></note>

			<body>determined based on the MTT method in 96-well micro-<lb/>plates. In short, 100 µL adherent cells were seeded into <lb/>each well and incubated for 12 h before the addition of the <lb/>test alkaloids/drug. At the same time, the suspended cells <lb/>were seeded at an initial density of 1 × 10 5 cells/mL just <lb/>before the addition of the alkaloids/drug. Each tumor cell <lb/>line was exposed to a test compound at concentration 20 μM <lb/>in DMSO in triplicate for 48 h, with camptothecin as the <lb/>positive control. After treatment, cell viability was assessed. <lb/>3.5 Hypoglycemic Activity <lb/>3T3-L1 myoblasts cells were purchased from American Type <lb/>Culture Collection (Manassas, VA). Cells were maintained <lb/>in DMEM supplemented with 10% FBS or CS (for 3T3-L1 <lb/>cells), 100 units/ml penicillin and 100 mg/ml streptomycin <lb/>in 10 cm diameter dishes in a humidified atmosphere of 95% <lb/>air and 5% CO 2 at 37 °C. Cells were maintained in continu-<lb/>ous passages by trypsinization of subconfluent cultures and <lb/>fed fresh medium every 48 h. For differentiation, L6 myo-<lb/>blasts were transferred to DMEM with 2% FCS in tissue <lb/>culture plates for 5-6 days, 3T3-L1 cells were exposed to <lb/>0.5 mM IBMX, 1 mM dexamethasone, 1 mM rosiglitazone <lb/>and 1 mg/mL insulin for 3 days, and 1 mg/ml insulin for <lb/>the other day. For glucose uptake assay, cells were serum <lb/>starved for 4 h in 96-well plates, followed by incubated with <lb/>insulin and alkaloids 1-14 for 24 h. Finally, the supernatants <lb/>of cultured cells were collected and subjected to glucose <lb/>assay using a commercially kit. The quantified values were <lb/>normalized based on the results of the MTS assay. <lb/>Table 3 1 H NMR spectroscopic data for 9-14 in acetone-d 6 (δ in ppm, J in Hz) <lb/>a1 H NMR recorded in 600 MHz <lb/>b1 H NMR recorded in 400 MH <lb/>Entry <lb/>δ H (9) a <lb/>δ H (10) a <lb/>δ H (11) a <lb/>δ H (12) a <lb/>δ H (13) b <lb/>δ H (14) a <lb/>1 <lb/>6.54, dd (10.2, 2.4) 6.55, dd (10.2, 2.4) 6.56, dd (10.2, 1.8) 6.57, dd (10.2, 2.4) 6.60, d (10.2) <lb/>6.58, dd (10.2, 2.2) <lb/>2 <lb/>6.00, d (10.2) <lb/>5.99, d (10.2) <lb/>6.04, d (10.2) <lb/>6.05, d (10.2) <lb/>6.14, d (10.20 <lb/>6.11, d (10.2) <lb/>3 <lb/>3.8, m <lb/>3.77, m <lb/>3.91, m <lb/>4.01, m <lb/>4.09, m <lb/>3.92, m <lb/>4 <lb/>2.48, dd (11.4, 5.4) 2.38, overlap <lb/>2.46, dd (11.4, 5.4) 2.50, m <lb/>2.63, dd (10.9, 5.7) 2.66, dd (11.4, 5.5) <lb/>1.69, t (11.4) <lb/>1.64, t (11.4) <lb/>1.66, t (11.4) <lb/>1.69, t (10.8) <lb/>1.78, t (10.9) <lb/>1.77, t (11.4) <lb/>7 <lb/>5.66, s <lb/>5.70, s <lb/>5.69, s <lb/>5.64, s <lb/>5.68, s <lb/>5.72, s <lb/>8 <lb/>3.94, m <lb/>4.16, m <lb/>4.31, m <lb/>4.05, m <lb/>4.14, m <lb/>4.07, m <lb/>10 <lb/>3.40, m <lb/>3.50, dd (12.0, 5.4) 3.39, dd (13.8, 4.2) 3.37, m <lb/>3.49, m <lb/>3.53, m <lb/>2.75, m <lb/>2.65, dd (12.0, 6.6) 3.06, dd (13.8, 4.2) 2.95, m <lb/>3.16, m <lb/>3.03, m <lb/>11 <lb/>2.84, overlap <lb/>4.77, m <lb/>4.19, t (4.2) <lb/>2.96, m <lb/>3.03, m <lb/>2.98, m <lb/>2.65, overlap <lb/>2.57, m <lb/>2.72, overlap <lb/>2.84, m <lb/>14 <lb/>6.70, s <lb/>6.69, s <lb/>6.90, s <lb/>6.83, s <lb/>6.84, s <lb/>6.73, s <lb/>17 <lb/>6.68, s <lb/>7.05, s <lb/>6.74, s <lb/>6.81, s <lb/>6.78, s <lb/>6.74, s <lb/>3-OCH 3 <lb/>3.25, s <lb/>3.23, s <lb/>3.29, s <lb/>3.28, s <lb/>3.31, s <lb/>3.30, s <lb/>11-OCH 3 <lb/>3.55, s <lb/>11-OH <lb/>4.60, d (5.4) <lb/>15-OCH 3 <lb/>3.78, s <lb/>3.68, s <lb/>16-OCH 3 <lb/>3.67, s <lb/>3.79, s <lb/>OCH 2 O <lb/>5.91, s <lb/>5.95, s <lb/>5.96, s <lb/>5.96, s <lb/>5.89, s <lb/>5.94, s <lb/>5.94, s <lb/>5.95, s <lb/>CH 2 COO-<lb/>2.68, dd (15.0, 4.8) 2.73, dd (15.0, 4.8) 2.81, dd (15, 4.2) <lb/>2.72, dd (15.0, 4.8) 2.76, overlap <lb/>2.74, dd (16.8, 5.8) <lb/>2.39, dd (15.0, 7.8) 2.36, overlap <lb/>2.36, dd (15, 6.0) <lb/>2.41, dd (15.0, 7.8) 2.51, dd (16.5,2.8) 2.51, dd (16.8, 1.8) <lb/>CH 2 COOCH 3 3.61, s <lb/>3.60, s <lb/>3.62, s <lb/>3.63, s <lb/></body>

			<page>65 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Artificial Erythrina Alkaloids from Three Erythrina Plants, E. variegata, E. crista-galli… <lb/></note>

			<page>1 3 <lb/></page>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgements This project is supported in part by the National <lb/>Natural Science Foundation of China (31872677). The authors are <lb/>grateful to Dr. Chun-Xia Zeng for identification of plant samples. <lb/>Compliance with Ethical Standards <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Conflicts of interest The authors declare no conflict of interest. <lb/>Open Access This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attri-<lb/>bution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adapta-<lb/>tion, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long <lb/>as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, <lb/>provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes <lb/>were made. The images or other third party material in this article are <lb/>included in the article&apos;s Creative Commons licence, unless indicated <lb/>otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in <lb/>the article&apos;s Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not <lb/>permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will <lb/>need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a <lb/>copy of this licence, visit http://creat iveco mmons .org/licen ses/by/4.0/. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>1. K. Folkers, R.T. Major, J. Am. Chem. Soc. 59, 1580-1581 (1937) <lb/>2. A.F. Parsons, M.J. Palframan, Alkaloids 68, 39-81 (2010). https <lb/>://doi.org/10.1016/S1099 -4831(10)06802 -1 <lb/>3. O. Flausino, L.D. Santos, H. Verli, A.M. Pereira, V.D. Bolzani, <lb/>R.L. Nunes-de-Souza, J. Nat. Prod. 70, 48-53 (2007) <lb/>4. M. Ozawa, K. Honda, I. Nakai, A. Kishida, A. Ohsaki, Bioorg. <lb/>Med. Chem. Lett. 18, 3992-3994 (2008) <lb/>5. S.A. Faggion, A.O.S. Cunha, H.A. Fachim, A.S. Gavin, W.F. <lb/>dos Santos, A.M.S. Pereira, R.O. Beleboni, Epilepsy Behav. 20, <lb/>441-446 (2011) <lb/>6. F. Crestey, A.A. Jensen, M. Borch, J.T. Andreasen, J. Andersen, <lb/>T. Balle, J.L. Kristensen, J. Med. Chem. 56, 9673-9682 (2013) <lb/>7. D.R. Callejon, T.B. Riul, L.G.P. Feitosa, T. Guaratini, D.B. Silva, <lb/>A. Adhikari, R.L. Shrestha, L.M.M. Marques, M.D. Baruffi, J.L.C. <lb/>Lopes, N.P. Lopes, Molecules 19, 5692-5703 (2014) <lb/>8. W.W. Cornelius, T. Akeng&apos;a, G.O. Obiero, K.P. Lutta, Rec. Nat. <lb/>Prod. 3, 96-103 (2009) <lb/>9. B.J. Zhang, M.F. Bao, C.X. Zeng, X.H. Zhong, L. Ni, Y. Zeng, <lb/>X.H. Cai, Org. Lett. 16, 6400-6403 (2014) <lb/></listBibl>

			<body>Table 4 13 C NMR spectroscopic data from 4 to 14 in acetone-d 6 (δ in ppm) <lb/>a13 C NMR recorded in 150 MHz <lb/>b13 C NMR recorded in 125 MHz <lb/>Entry <lb/>δ C (4) a <lb/>δ C (5) a <lb/>δ C (6) a <lb/>δ C (7) b <lb/>δ C (8) a <lb/>δ C (9) a <lb/>δ C (10) a <lb/>δ C (11) a <lb/>δ C (12) a <lb/>δ C (13) b <lb/>δ C (14) a <lb/>1 <lb/>125.4 d <lb/>125.6 d <lb/>125.7 d <lb/>125.3 d <lb/>125.2 d <lb/>125.4 d <lb/>125.3 d <lb/>125.5 d <lb/>125.6 d <lb/>125.1 d <lb/>125.0 d <lb/>2 <lb/>133.1 d <lb/>133.1 d <lb/>133.1 d <lb/>134.0 d <lb/>134.2 d <lb/>133.1 d <lb/>133.2 d <lb/>133.1 d <lb/>133.2 d <lb/>134.1 d <lb/>134.1 d <lb/>3 <lb/>76.9 d <lb/>77.0 d <lb/>76.8 d <lb/>76.9 d <lb/>76.8 d <lb/>76.8 d <lb/>76.9 d <lb/>76.7 d <lb/>77.0 d <lb/>76.6 d <lb/>76.5 d <lb/>4 <lb/>43.3 t <lb/>43.8 t <lb/>42.7 t <lb/>43.3 t <lb/>43.1 t <lb/>43.8 t <lb/>43.6 t <lb/>42.7 t <lb/>43.4 t <lb/>42.3 t <lb/>42.7 t <lb/>5 <lb/>69.3 s <lb/>69.3 s <lb/>68.6 s <lb/>69.4 s <lb/>69.7 s <lb/>69.6 s <lb/>69.7 s <lb/>68.9 s <lb/>68.9 s <lb/>69.1 s <lb/>69.7 s <lb/>6 <lb/>142.3 s <lb/>142.6 s <lb/>142.4 s <lb/>144.4 s <lb/>144.2 s <lb/>142.7 s <lb/>142.4 s <lb/>142.4 s <lb/>142.9 s <lb/>143.1 s <lb/>143.0 s <lb/>7 <lb/>127.6 d <lb/>127.6 d <lb/>127.9 d <lb/>121.7 d <lb/>122.4 d <lb/>126.9 d <lb/>127.1 d <lb/>127.3 d <lb/>126.7 d <lb/>125.2 d <lb/>125.6 d <lb/>8 <lb/>67.7 d <lb/>65.1 d <lb/>65.8 d <lb/>70.5 d <lb/>73.2 d <lb/>66.1 d <lb/>68.5 d <lb/>66.4 d <lb/>64.4 d <lb/>63.9 d <lb/>65.4 d <lb/>10 <lb/>52.6 t <lb/>43.9 t <lb/>45.2 t <lb/>44.4 t <lb/>53.1 t <lb/>44.2 t <lb/>53.0 t <lb/>45.4 t <lb/>42.6 t <lb/>40.8 t <lb/>42.3 t <lb/>11 <lb/>64.7 d <lb/>26.0 t <lb/>74.8 d <lb/>24.6 t <lb/>65.1 d <lb/>26.0 t <lb/>64.8 t <lb/>74.7 d <lb/>24.6 t <lb/>24.1 t <lb/>25.5 t <lb/>12 <lb/>132.2 s <lb/>129.4 s <lb/>130.1 s <lb/>128.0 s <lb/>133.3 s <lb/>129.4 s <lb/>133.5 s <lb/>130.0 s <lb/>127.7 s <lb/>126.8 s <lb/>128.7 s <lb/>13 <lb/>133.4 s <lb/>134.0 s <lb/>133.0 s <lb/>132.2 s <lb/>131.9 s <lb/>133.9 s <lb/>132.2 s <lb/>132.9 s <lb/>132.7 s <lb/>130.9 s <lb/>132.2 s <lb/>14 <lb/>105.9 d <lb/>106.5 d <lb/>105.9 d <lb/>110.6 d <lb/>105.8 d <lb/>106.4 d <lb/>105.8 d <lb/>105.7 d <lb/>110.6 d <lb/>110.4 d <lb/>106.4 d <lb/>15 <lb/>147.3 s <lb/>146.7 s <lb/>148.0 s <lb/>148.2 s <lb/>147.6 s <lb/>146.6 s <lb/>147.3 s <lb/>147.8 s <lb/>148.9 s <lb/>148.5 s <lb/>147.0 s <lb/>16 <lb/>147.2 s <lb/>147.0 s <lb/>147.2 s <lb/>149.1 s <lb/>147.5 s <lb/>146.9 s <lb/>147.3 s <lb/>147.1 s <lb/>148.1 s <lb/>149.4 s <lb/>147.5 s <lb/>17 <lb/>107.4 d <lb/>109.4 d <lb/>109.0 d <lb/>113.1 d <lb/>108.1 d <lb/>109.3 d <lb/>107.2 d <lb/>108.8 d <lb/>113.0 d <lb/>113.1 d <lb/>109.5 d <lb/>3-OCH 3 <lb/>56.2 q <lb/>56.3 q <lb/>56.3 q <lb/>56.0 q <lb/>56.3 q <lb/>56.1 q <lb/>56.1 q <lb/>56.2 q <lb/>56.0 q <lb/>55.9 q <lb/>56.4 q <lb/>11-OCH 3 <lb/>57.9 q <lb/>57.7 q <lb/>56.0 q <lb/>15-OCH 3 <lb/>56.1 q <lb/>56.1 q <lb/>56.3 q <lb/>16-OCH 3 <lb/>56.1 q <lb/>55.9 q <lb/>OCH 2 O <lb/>101.7 t <lb/>101.7 t <lb/>101.9 t <lb/>101.9 t <lb/>101.5 t <lb/>101.7 t <lb/>101.7 t <lb/>101.9 t <lb/>CH 2 COCH 3 <lb/>47.8 t <lb/>48.1 t <lb/>47.4 t <lb/>34.9 t <lb/>35.4 t <lb/>CH 2 COCH 3 <lb/>207.9 s <lb/>207.7 s <lb/>207.7 s <lb/>172.3 s <lb/>172.3 s <lb/>CH 3 COCH 3 <lb/>30.8 q <lb/>30.9 q <lb/>30.8 q <lb/>(CH 2 )COOCH 3 <lb/>39.5 t <lb/>39.3 t <lb/>38.8 t <lb/>39.3 t <lb/>(CH 2 )COOCH 3 <lb/>172.1 s <lb/>172.2 s <lb/>172.5 s <lb/>172.4 s <lb/>172.3 s <lb/>172.9 s <lb/>(CH 2 )COOCH 3 <lb/>52.0 q <lb/>52.1 q <lb/>51.5 q <lb/>51.5 q <lb/>51.5 q <lb/>51.6 q <lb/></body>

			<page>66 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">B.-J. Zhang et al. <lb/>1 3 <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>10. B.J. Zhang, W.N. Xiao, J. Chen, M.F. Bao, J. Schinnerl, Q. <lb/>Wang, X.H. Cai, Tetrahedron (2019). https ://doi.org/10.1016/j. <lb/>tet.2019.13051 5 <lb/>11. B.J. Zhang, B. Wu, M.F. Bao, L. Ni, X.H. Cai, RSC Adv. 6, <lb/>87863-87868 (2016) <lb/>12. J. Wu, B.J. Zhang, W.N. Xiao, M.F. Bao, X.H. Cai, RSC Adv. 7, <lb/>51245-51251 (2017) <lb/>13. J. Wu, B.J. Zhang, M.F. Bao, X.H. Cai, Nat. Prod. Res. 33, 2004-<lb/>2010 (2019) <lb/>14. H.E. Zhao, J. Wu, F.Q. Xu, M.F. Bao, C.S. Jin, X.H. Cai, Nat. <lb/>Prod. Res. 33, 1298-1303 (2019) <lb/>15. K. Ito, H. Furukawa, H. Tanaka, J. Chem. Soc. Chem. Commun. <lb/>17, 1076-1077 (1970) <lb/>16. K. Ito, H. Furukawa, H. Tanaka, Yakugaku Zasshi 93, 1215-1217 <lb/>(1973) <lb/>17. A.S. Chawla, S. Chunchatprasert, A.H. Jackson, Org. Magn. <lb/>Reson. 21, 39-41 (1983) <lb/>18. Y. Tsuda, T. Sano, Alkaloids 48, 249-337 (1996). https ://doi. <lb/>org/10.1016/S1099 -4831(08)60032 -2 </listBibl>


	</text>
</tei>