<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>molecules <lb/>Article <lb/>Liquid-Crystal and Fire-Retardant Properties of New <lb/>Hexasubstituted Cyclotriphosphazene Compounds <lb/>with Two Schiff Base Linking Units <lb/>Zuhair Jamain 1,2, * , Melati Khairuddean 2, * and Tay Guan-Seng 3 <lb/>1 <lb/>Faculty of Science and Natural Resources, Universiti Malaysia Sabah (UMS), Kota Kinabalu 88400, Malaysia <lb/>2 <lb/>School of Chemical Sciences, Universiti Sains Malaysia (USM), Penang 11800, Malaysia <lb/>3 <lb/>School of Industrial Technology, Universiti Sains Malaysia (USM), Penang 11800, Malaysia; taygs@usm.my <lb/>* Correspondence: zuhairjamain@ums.edu.my (Z.J.); melati@usm.my (M.K.) <lb/>Received: 5 April 2020; Accepted: 22 April 2020; Published: 1 May 2020 <lb/>Abstract: A series of new hexasubstituted cyclotriphosphazene compounds (4a-j) consisting of <lb/>two Schiff base linking units and different terminal substituents was successfully synthesized <lb/>and characterized. The structures of these compounds were confirmed using Fourier Transform <lb/>Infra-Red (FTIR), Nuclear Magnetic Resonance (NMR), and CHN elemental analysis. Polarized optical <lb/>microscopy (POM) was used to determine their liquid-crystal behavior, which was then further <lb/>confirmed using differential scanning calorimetry (DSC). Compounds 4a-i with heptyl, nonyl, <lb/>decyl, dodecyl, tetradecyl, hydroxy, 4-carboxyphenyl, chloro, and nitro terminal ends, respectively, <lb/>showed the liquid-crystal properties, whereas compound 4j with the amino group was found to be <lb/>non-mesogenic. The attachment of an electron-donating group in 4j eventually give a non-mesogenic <lb/>product. The study of the fire-retardant properties of these compounds was done using the limiting <lb/>oxygen index (LOI). In this study, polyester resin (PE) was used as a matrix for moulding, and the <lb/>LOI value of pure PE was 22.53%. The LOI value increased to 24.71% when PE was incorporated <lb/>with 1 wt.% of hexachlorocyclotriphosphazene (HCCP), thus indicating that HCCP has a good <lb/>fire-retardant properties. The result showed that all the compounds have good agreement in their <lb/>LOI values. Compound 4i with a nitro terminal group gave the highest LOI value of 28.37%. <lb/>Keywords: schiff base; cyclotriphosphazene; liquid-crystal; fire-retardant; non-mesogenic <lb/></front>

			<body>1. Introduction <lb/>Hexachlorocyclotriphosphazene (HCCP) is an inorganic phosphorus-nitrogen compound <lb/>consisting of alternating phosphorus and nitrogen atoms, bound to each other through alternating <lb/>single and double bonds [1]. HCCP derivatives are excellent models for structure-activity studies <lb/>and their multiarmed rigid ring allows the exploration of new discotic molecules in the field of liquid <lb/>crystals [2,3]. Liquid crystal is an intermediate phase between liquid and solid, a state of matter that has <lb/>both the properties of isotropic liquid and of solid crystal. As temperature increases, the solid absorbs <lb/>some heat and melts into a liquid-crystal phase whereby molecules can move freely, disrupting the <lb/>positional order without changing the orientational order [4]. <lb/>To study the behavior of the HCCP compound, which consists of inorganic backbones as <lb/>well as organic side chains, small changes in the structure must be made [5,6]. Due to the high <lb/>reactivity of the P-Cl bond, the corresponding substitution method allows the introduction of a <lb/>wide range of substituents [7,8] and hence provides substituted cyclotriphosphazene derivatives <lb/>with different chemical and physical properties [9,10]. Such compounds have been used in <lb/>commercial applications [11-14] especially in liquid-crystal and fire-retardant materials, where it has <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">Molecules 2020, 25, 2122; doi:10.3390/molecules25092122 <lb/>www.mdpi.com/journal/molecules <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">Molecules 2020, 25, 2122 <lb/></note>

			<page>2 of 26 <lb/></page>

			<body>been proved that phosphazene-based compounds exhibit effective flame-retardant properties [15]. <lb/>Jae Shin et al. (2010) reported the application of cyclotriphosphazene derivatives as fire retardants [16]. <lb/>Phosphorus-based materials are thermally quite stable and versatile in their fire-retardant activity. <lb/>Interestingly, compounds with a phosphorus atom often exhibit both condensed and gas phase <lb/>state [17]. The chemical reactions that take place in the condensed phase at elevated temperature, <lb/>such as hydrolysis, dehydration, and chain scission, produce carbonaceous char residues on the surface <lb/>of the phosphorus-based materials, which retards the material from further burning [18,19]. <lb/>Even though extensive research has focused on the use of substituted cyclotriphosphazene <lb/>derivatives on fire retardants, the study of cyclophosphazene-based compounds on liquid crystal <lb/>has still not being fully explored [20,21]. The HCCP molecule is a well-known compound with good <lb/>thermal stability and fire retardancy, which is due to the hexa-functionality and high phosphorus <lb/>content. Modification of the HCCP core system with organic side arms allows the exploration of <lb/>new discotic molecules in the field of liquid crystals with fire-retardant properties. The incorporation <lb/>of HCCP into organic compounds with a Schiff base linking unit is done to increase the resistance <lb/>of the material towards ignition. The different terminal substituents in the side arms will gain a <lb/>better insight of the structure-properties relationship of these types of compounds. The research into <lb/>liquid-crystal materials with fire-retardant properties with flexible ordered structures has led to the <lb/>discovery of new properties and applications such as advanced technological devices or composite <lb/>applications. Extensive exploration of these materials can detect small changes in temperature, <lb/>electromagnetic radiation, mechanical stress, and chemical environment [22-24]. <lb/>This research focused on the preparation of a series of hexasubstituted cyclotriphosphazene <lb/>derivatives with two Schiff base linking units. Schiff base contains carbon double bonds with nitrogen <lb/>atoms connected to an alkyl or aryl group but not the hydrogen. These Schiff base molecules provide a <lb/>stepped core structure that can maintain the molecular linearity. This linearity will provide high stability <lb/>and enable mesophase formation [25]. Moreover, Schiff base linking units were found to enhance <lb/>the fire-retardant properties of polyester resin due to their thermal stability [26]. During the burning <lb/>process, this molecule can transform into a cross-linked structure, which promotes the formation of char <lb/>on the surface in the condensed phase. These char layers shield the surface of the polyester resin from <lb/>combustion [27]. Therefore, both liquid-crystal and fire-retardant properties of the cyclotriphosphazene <lb/>core system attached to a Schiff base linking unit were investigated in this study. <lb/>In this work, polyester resin (PE) was used as a matrix for moulding in order to study the <lb/>fire-retardant properties of these compounds. PE is an unsaturated synthetic resin and can be <lb/>considered to be a combustible material [28]. This resin produces a lot of heat during combustion, <lb/>due to low thermal stability, and becomes a potential fire risk. Thus, the modification of polyester resin <lb/>by mixing with cyclotriphosphazene-based compounds with fire-retardant properties is necessary to <lb/>overcome this problem. <lb/>2. Results and Discussion <lb/>2.1. Synthesis of the Intermediates and Final Compounds <lb/>Intermediates 1a-e were synthesized using the alkylation reaction of 4-hydroxybenzaldehyde <lb/>with different alkyl bromides (heptyl, nonyl, decyl, dodecyl, and tetradecyl). Intermediates 2a-i were <lb/>formed from the condensation reaction of 1a-e and other commercially para-substituted benzaldehydes <lb/>(-OH, -COOH, -Cl, and -NO 2 ), respectively. Reaction of hexachlorocyclotriphosphazene, HCCP, <lb/>with 4-hydroxybenzaldehyde gave intermediate 3, which was then used for further reaction to yield <lb/>the final compounds 4a-i. Finally, the reduction of compound 4i afforded compound 4j. The overall <lb/>synthesis pathway for hexasubstituted cyclotriphosphazene compounds with different terminal ends <lb/>in the side arms bearing two Schiff base linking units is shown in Schemes 1-3. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Molecules 2020, 25, 2122 <lb/></note>

			<page>3 of 26 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Molecules 2020, 25, x FOR PEER REVIEW <lb/></note>

			<page>3 of 26 <lb/></page>

			<body>Scheme 1. Alkylation reaction of intermediates 1a-e [29]. <lb/>Scheme 2. Formation of intermediates (2a-i and 3) and hexasubstituted cyclotriphosphazene <lb/>compounds, 4a-i [30-33]. <lb/>Scheme 3. Reduction of compound 4i-j [34]. <lb/>H <lb/>O <lb/>OH <lb/>R-Br <lb/>K 2 CO 3 , KI <lb/>DMF <lb/>reflux, 12h <lb/>H <lb/>O <lb/>OR <lb/>R = C 7 H 15 ; C 9 H 19 ; C 10 H 21 ; C 12 H 25 ; C 14 H 29 <lb/>a <lb/>b <lb/>c <lb/>d <lb/>e <lb/>1a-e <lb/>H <lb/>O <lb/>X <lb/>N <lb/>P N <lb/>P <lb/>N <lb/>P <lb/>A 1 A 1 <lb/>A 1 <lb/>A 1 <lb/>O <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>X <lb/>N <lb/>P N <lb/>P <lb/>N <lb/>P <lb/>Cl Cl <lb/>Cl <lb/>Cl <lb/>Cl <lb/>Cl <lb/>A 1 <lb/>A 1 <lb/>HO <lb/>N <lb/>P N <lb/>P <lb/>N <lb/>P <lb/>A A <lb/>A <lb/>A <lb/>O <lb/>A <lb/>O <lb/>H 2 N <lb/>N <lb/>X <lb/>+ <lb/>H <lb/>Glacial acetic acid, MeOH <lb/>reflux, 24h <lb/>H <lb/>O <lb/>+ <lb/>Et 3 N, Acetone <lb/>rt, 4 days <lb/>A <lb/>H 2 N <lb/>NH 2 + <lb/>2a-i <lb/>3 <lb/>MeOH <lb/>rt, 2h <lb/>4a-i <lb/>X = OC 7 H 15 ; OC 9 H 19 ; OC 10 H 21 ; OC 12 H 25 ; OC 14 H 29 ; OH; COOH; Cl; NO 2 <lb/>a <lb/>b <lb/>c <lb/>d <lb/>e <lb/>f <lb/>g <lb/>h i <lb/>HCCP <lb/>N <lb/>P N <lb/>P <lb/>N <lb/>P <lb/>A 10 A 10 <lb/>A 10 <lb/>O <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>NO 2 <lb/>A 10 <lb/>A <lb/>4i <lb/>A <lb/>10 <lb/>10 <lb/>N <lb/>P N <lb/>P <lb/>N <lb/>P <lb/>A 11 A 11 <lb/>A 11 <lb/>O <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>NH 2 <lb/>A 11 <lb/>A <lb/>4j <lb/>A <lb/>11 <lb/>11 <lb/>Na 2 S.9H 2 O, EtOH <lb/>reflux, 12h <lb/>Scheme 1. Alkylation reaction of intermediates 1a-e [29]. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Molecules 2020, 25, x FOR PEER REVIEW <lb/></note>

			<page>3 of 26 <lb/></page>

			<body>Scheme 1. Alkylation reaction of intermediates 1a-e [29]. <lb/>Scheme 2. Formation of intermediates (2a-i and 3) and hexasubstituted cyclotriphosphazene <lb/>compounds, 4a-i [30-33]. <lb/>Scheme 3. Reduction of compound 4i-j [34]. <lb/>H <lb/>O <lb/>OH <lb/>R-Br <lb/>K 2 CO 3 , KI <lb/>DMF <lb/>reflux, 12h <lb/>H <lb/>O <lb/>OR <lb/>R = C 7 H 15 ; C 9 H 19 ; C 10 H 21 ; C 12 H 25 ; C 14 H 29 <lb/>a <lb/>b <lb/>c <lb/>d <lb/>e <lb/>1a-e <lb/>H <lb/>O <lb/>X <lb/>N <lb/>P N <lb/>P <lb/>N <lb/>P <lb/>A 1 A 1 <lb/>A 1 <lb/>A 1 <lb/>O <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>X <lb/>N <lb/>P N <lb/>P <lb/>N <lb/>P <lb/>Cl Cl <lb/>Cl <lb/>Cl <lb/>Cl <lb/>Cl <lb/>A 1 <lb/>A 1 <lb/>HO <lb/>N <lb/>P N <lb/>P <lb/>N <lb/>P <lb/>A A <lb/>A <lb/>A <lb/>O <lb/>A <lb/>O <lb/>H 2 N <lb/>N <lb/>X <lb/>+ <lb/>H <lb/>Glacial acetic acid, MeOH <lb/>reflux, 24h <lb/>H <lb/>O <lb/>+ <lb/>Et 3 N, Acetone <lb/>rt, 4 days <lb/>A <lb/>H 2 N <lb/>NH 2 + <lb/>2a-i <lb/>3 <lb/>MeOH <lb/>rt, 2h <lb/>4a-i <lb/>X = OC 7 H 15 ; OC 9 H 19 ; OC 10 H 21 ; OC 12 H 25 ; OC 14 H 29 ; OH; COOH; Cl; NO 2 <lb/>a <lb/>b <lb/>c <lb/>d <lb/>e <lb/>f <lb/>g <lb/>h i <lb/>HCCP <lb/>N <lb/>P N <lb/>P <lb/>N <lb/>P <lb/>A 10 A 10 <lb/>A 10 <lb/>O <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>NO 2 <lb/>A 10 <lb/>A <lb/>4i <lb/>A <lb/>10 <lb/>10 <lb/>N <lb/>P N <lb/>P <lb/>N <lb/>P <lb/>A 11 A 11 <lb/>A 11 <lb/>O <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>NH 2 <lb/>A 11 <lb/>A <lb/>4j <lb/>A <lb/>11 <lb/>11 <lb/>Na 2 S.9H 2 O, EtOH <lb/>reflux, 12h <lb/>Scheme 2. Formation of intermediates (2a-i and 3) and hexasubstituted cyclotriphosphazene <lb/>compounds, 4a-i [30-33]. <lb/></body>

			<note>Molecules 2020, 25, x FOR PEER REVIEW <lb/></note>

			<page>3 of 26 <lb/></page>

			<body>Scheme 1. Alkylation reaction of intermediates 1a-e [29]. <lb/>Scheme 2. Formation of intermediates (2a-i and 3) and hexasubstituted cyclotriphosphazene <lb/>compounds, 4a-i [30-33]. <lb/>Scheme 3. Reduction of compound 4i-j [34]. <lb/>H <lb/>O <lb/>OH <lb/>R-Br <lb/>K 2 CO 3 , KI <lb/>DMF <lb/>reflux, 12h <lb/>H <lb/>O <lb/>OR <lb/>R = C 7 H 15 ; C 9 H 19 ; C 10 H 21 ; C 12 H 25 ; C 14 H 29 <lb/>a <lb/>b <lb/>c <lb/>d <lb/>e <lb/>1a-e <lb/>H <lb/>O <lb/>X <lb/>N <lb/>P N <lb/>P <lb/>N <lb/>P <lb/>A 1 A 1 <lb/>A 1 <lb/>A 1 <lb/>O <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>X <lb/>N <lb/>P N <lb/>P <lb/>N <lb/>P <lb/>Cl Cl <lb/>Cl <lb/>Cl <lb/>Cl <lb/>Cl <lb/>A 1 <lb/>A 1 <lb/>HO <lb/>N <lb/>P N <lb/>P <lb/>N <lb/>P <lb/>A A <lb/>A <lb/>A <lb/>O <lb/>A <lb/>O <lb/>H 2 N <lb/>N <lb/>X <lb/>+ <lb/>H <lb/>Glacial acetic acid, MeOH <lb/>reflux, 24h <lb/>H <lb/>O <lb/>+ <lb/>Et 3 N, Acetone <lb/>rt, 4 days <lb/>A <lb/>H 2 N <lb/>NH 2 + <lb/>2a-i <lb/>3 <lb/>MeOH <lb/>rt, 2h <lb/>4a-i <lb/>X = OC 7 H 15 ; OC 9 H 19 ; OC 10 H 21 ; OC 12 H 25 ; OC 14 H 29 ; OH; COOH; Cl; NO 2 <lb/>a <lb/>b <lb/>c <lb/>d <lb/>e <lb/>f <lb/>g <lb/>h i <lb/>HCCP <lb/>N <lb/>P N <lb/>P <lb/>N <lb/>P <lb/>A 10 A 10 <lb/>A 10 <lb/>O <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>NO 2 <lb/>A 10 <lb/>A <lb/>4i <lb/>A <lb/>10 <lb/>10 <lb/>N <lb/>P N <lb/>P <lb/>N <lb/>P <lb/>A 11 A 11 <lb/>A 11 <lb/>O <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>NH 2 <lb/>A 11 <lb/>A <lb/>4j <lb/>A <lb/>11 <lb/>11 <lb/>Na 2 S.9H 2 O, EtOH <lb/>reflux, 12h <lb/>Scheme 3. Reduction of compound 4i-j [34]. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Molecules 2020, 25, 2122 <lb/></note>

			<page>4 of 26 <lb/></page>

			<body>All the synthesized intermediates (1a-e, 2a-i, and 3) and final compounds 4a-j were then <lb/>characterized using Fourier Transform Infra-Red (FTIR), Nuclear Magnetic Resonance (NMR), and CHN <lb/>elemental analysis. Liquid-crystal properties of these compounds were determined using polarized <lb/>optical microscope (POM) and further confirmed using differential scanning calorimetry (DSC). In this <lb/>study, the limiting oxygen index (LOI) test is used to determine the minimum amount of oxygen <lb/>required to support the combustion of a sample. The compact data of these intermediates and <lb/>compounds are summarized in Section 3.3. <lb/>2.2. FTIR Spectral Data of the Intermediates and Final Compounds <lb/>The IR data for intermediates 1a-e with heptyl, nonyl decyl, dodecyl, and tetradecyl chains, <lb/>respectively, showed a similar pattern to the absorption bands at 2850 and 2930 cm -1 for the symmetrical <lb/>and asymmetrical Csp 3 -H stretching, 2733 cm -1 for the C-H stretching of the aldehyde, 1690 cm -1 for <lb/>C=O stretching, 1600 cm -1 for C=C aromatic stretching, and 1250 cm -1 for C-O stretching. The absence <lb/>of the O-H stretching at 3300 cm -1 indicated that the insertion of the alkyl groups was a success. <lb/>These intermediates 1a-e and other commercially available aldehydes such as 4-hydroxybenzald <lb/>ehyde, 4-formylbenzoic acid, 4-chlorobenzaldehyde, and 4-nitrobenzaldehyde were used in the reaction <lb/>with 1,4-phenylenediamine to form the Schiff base intermediates, 2a-i. The IR data of intermediates <lb/>2a-i showed similar absorption bands with two bands at 3320 and 3450 cm -1 for the N-H stretching. <lb/>Other bands at 1610, 1550, and 1165 cm -1 were assigned to the C=N, C=C, and C-N stretching, respectively. <lb/>The absorption band for C-O stretching at 1250 cm -1 can also be observed for intermediates 2a-g. <lb/>Only intermediates 2a-e displayed the absorption bands of asymmetrical and asymmetrical Csp 3 -H <lb/>stretching at 2850 and 2920 cm -1 , while intermediates 2f and 2g showed a band at 3210 cm -1 for O-H <lb/>stretching. An additional band at 1698 cm -1 for C=O stretching was observed for 2g and band at 790 cm -1 <lb/>for C-Cl stretching for 2h. The band for aldehydic C-H stretching was not observed in any of the <lb/>intermediates, 2a-i, which confirmed the success of the condensation reaction. <lb/>The substitution reaction of HCCP with p-hydroxybenzaldehyde formed intermediate 3. The main <lb/>absorption bands for 3 were observed at 2730 (H-C=O), 1700 (C=O), 1595 (C=C), and 1205 cm -1 (C-O). <lb/>The absorption bands from the cyclotriphosphazene ring, P=N stretching, appeared at 1151 cm -1 <lb/>while P-O-C bending was located at 944 cm -1 . Intermediate 3 was reacted with 2a-i to afford final <lb/>compounds with two Schiff base linking units, 4a-i. <lb/>According to the IR spectra of compounds 4a-j (Figure 1), the presence of the alkoxy moieties in <lb/>compounds 4a-e was substantiated by the appearance of the absorption bands at 2851 and 2920 cm -1 <lb/>(Csp 3 -H stretching). The absorption bands at 1168, 1248, and 1509 cm -1 were assigned to the <lb/>stretching of C-N, C-O, and aromatic C=C, respectively. The stretching of P=N and P-O-C bending <lb/>of the cyclotriphosphazene ring in the compound was observed at 1192 and 983 cm -1 , respectively. <lb/>Only compound 4g showed the absorption band for carbonyl (C=O) of the 4-carboxyphenyl substituent <lb/>at 1673 cm -1 , while C-Cl bending at 823 cm -1 was observed in compound 4h. On the other hand, <lb/>the reduction reaction of compound 4i to form 4j was completed with the appearance of two absorption <lb/>bands at 3312 and 3478 cm -1 for the N-H stretching in the amino group. The stretching corresponding <lb/>to C=N linkage at 1616 cm -1 in the IR spectra of compounds 4a-j indicated that the Schiff base <lb/>formation was successful. <lb/>2.3. NMR Spectral Data of Final Compounds <lb/>Compound 4a was used to represent the structure confirmation in the series. The structure of <lb/>compound 4a with complete atomic numbering is shown in Figure 2. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Molecules 2020, 25, 2122 <lb/></note>

			<page>5 of 26 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Molecules 2020, 25, x FOR PEER REVIEW <lb/></note>

			<page>5 of 26 <lb/></page>

			<body>Figure 1. Fourier Transform Infra-Red (FTIR) spectra overlay of compounds 4a-j. <lb/>2.3. NMR Spectral Data of Final Compounds <lb/>Compound 4a was used to represent the structure confirmation in the series. The structure of <lb/>compound 4a with complete atomic numbering is shown in Figure 2. <lb/>Figure 2. Structure of compound 4a with complete atomic numbering. <lb/>1 H NMR spectrum of compound 4a (Figure 3) showed two different azomethine proton signals, <lb/>which were observed in the downfield region at δ 8.66 (H5) and δ 8.55 ppm (H10), respectively. Six <lb/>doublets integrating to 12 aromatic protons appeared in the range of δ 7.03-7.95 ppm and were <lb/>assigned to the para-substituted aromatic protons. The presence of the azomethine groups caused the <lb/>signals of H3 and H12 to be the most deshielded aromatic protons. Meanwhile, the signals for H7 <lb/>and H8 almost overlapped as the protons experienced similar chemical environment. Moreover, <lb/>proton signals of the aliphatic chains were observed in the upfield region, with the oxymethylene <lb/>protons (H15) more deshielded among other methylene protons due to their close proximity to the <lb/>N <lb/>P N <lb/>P <lb/>N <lb/>P <lb/>A 2 A 2 <lb/>A 2 <lb/>O <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>O <lb/>A 2 <lb/>A <lb/>A <lb/>2 <lb/>2 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>6 <lb/>7 8 <lb/>9 <lb/>10 <lb/>11 <lb/>12 13 <lb/>14 <lb/>15 <lb/>16 <lb/>17 <lb/>18 <lb/>19 <lb/>20 <lb/>21 <lb/>Figure 1. Fourier Transform Infra-Red (FTIR) spectra overlay of compounds 4a-j. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Molecules 2020, 25, x FOR PEER REVIEW <lb/></note>

			<page>5 of 26 <lb/></page>

			<body>Figure 1. Fourier Transform Infra-Red (FTIR) spectra overlay of compounds 4a-j. <lb/>2.3. NMR Spectral Data of Final Compounds <lb/>Compound 4a was used to represent the structure confirmation in the series. The structure of <lb/>compound 4a with complete atomic numbering is shown in Figure 2. <lb/>Figure 2. Structure of compound 4a with complete atomic numbering. <lb/>1 H NMR spectrum of compound 4a (Figure 3) showed two different azomethine proton signals, <lb/>which were observed in the downfield region at δ 8.66 (H5) and δ 8.55 ppm (H10), respectively. Six <lb/>doublets integrating to 12 aromatic protons appeared in the range of δ 7.03-7.95 ppm and were <lb/>assigned to the para-substituted aromatic protons. The presence of the azomethine groups caused the <lb/>signals of H3 and H12 to be the most deshielded aromatic protons. Meanwhile, the signals for H7 <lb/>and H8 almost overlapped as the protons experienced similar chemical environment. Moreover, <lb/>proton signals of the aliphatic chains were observed in the upfield region, with the oxymethylene <lb/>protons (H15) more deshielded among other methylene protons due to their close proximity to the <lb/>N <lb/>P N <lb/>P <lb/>N <lb/>P <lb/>A 2 A 2 <lb/>A 2 <lb/>O <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>O <lb/>A 2 <lb/>A <lb/>A <lb/>2 <lb/>2 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>6 <lb/>7 8 <lb/>9 <lb/>10 <lb/>11 <lb/>12 13 <lb/>14 <lb/>15 <lb/>16 <lb/>17 <lb/>18 <lb/>19 <lb/>20 <lb/>21 <lb/>Figure 2. Structure of compound 4a with complete atomic numbering. <lb/>1 H NMR spectrum of compound 4a (Figure 3) showed two different azomethine proton signals, <lb/>which were observed in the downfield region at δ 8.66 (H5) and δ 8.55 ppm (H10), respectively. <lb/>Six doublets integrating to 12 aromatic protons appeared in the range of δ 7.03-7.95 ppm and were <lb/>assigned to the para-substituted aromatic protons. The presence of the azomethine groups caused <lb/>the signals of H3 and H12 to be the most deshielded aromatic protons. Meanwhile, the signals for <lb/>H7 and H8 almost overlapped as the protons experienced similar chemical environment. Moreover, <lb/>proton signals of the aliphatic chains were observed in the upfield region, with the oxymethylene <lb/>protons (H15) more deshielded among other methylene protons due to their close proximity to the <lb/>neighboring electronegative oxygen atom. Therefore, the signal of these protons appeared at δ 4.07 ppm <lb/>as a triplet while that of the other methylene protons (H16-H20) were observed in the region of δ <lb/>1.30-1.79 ppm. A triplet in the most upfield (δ 0.89 ppm) region was assigned to H21. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Molecules 2020, 25, 2122 <lb/></note>

			<page>6 of 26 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Molecules 2020, 25, x FOR PEER REVIEW <lb/></note>

			<page>6 of 26 <lb/></page>

			<body>neighboring electronegative oxygen atom. Therefore, the signal of these protons appeared at δ 4.07 <lb/>ppm as a triplet while that of the other methylene protons (H16-H20) were observed in the region of <lb/>δ 1.30-1.79 ppm. A triplet in the most upfield (δ 0.89 ppm) region was assigned to H21. <lb/>Figure 3. 1 H Nuclear Magnetic Resonance (NMR) spectrum of compound 4a. <lb/>The 13 C NMR spectrum of compound 4a as shown in Figure 4a indicates that 4a has 21 carbon <lb/>signals in the side arms. These signals consist of two azomethine, six aromatics, six quaternary, six <lb/>methylene, and one methyl carbons. Further complete assignment of all carbons was done using <lb/>DEPT experiments. DEPT 90 gave information on methine carbon (CH) and DEPT 135 gave <lb/>information on the methylene carbon (CH2) which appeared as the negative signal while methine <lb/>(CH) and methyl (CH3) carbon showed positive signals. <lb/>Figure 4. (a) 13 C NMR, (b) DEPT 90 and (c) DEPT 135 spectra of compound 4a. <lb/>Figure 3. 1 H Nuclear Magnetic Resonance (NMR) spectrum of compound 4a. <lb/>The 13 C NMR spectrum of compound 4a as shown in Figure 4a indicates that 4a has 21 carbon <lb/>signals in the side arms. These signals consist of two azomethine, six aromatics, six quaternary, <lb/>six methylene, and one methyl carbons. Further complete assignment of all carbons was done using <lb/>DEPT experiments. DEPT 90 gave information on methine carbon (CH) and DEPT 135 gave information <lb/>on the methylene carbon (CH 2 ) which appeared as the negative signal while methine (CH) and methyl <lb/>(CH 3 ) carbon showed positive signals. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Molecules 2020, 25, x FOR PEER REVIEW <lb/></note>

			<page>6 of 26 <lb/></page>

			<body>neighboring electronegative oxygen atom. Therefore, the signal of these protons appeared at δ 4.07 <lb/>ppm as a triplet while that of the other methylene protons (H16-H20) were observed in the region of <lb/>δ 1.30-1.79 ppm. A triplet in the most upfield (δ 0.89 ppm) region was assigned to H21. <lb/>Figure 3. 1 H Nuclear Magnetic Resonance (NMR) spectrum of compound 4a. <lb/>The 13 C NMR spectrum of compound 4a as shown in Figure 4a indicates that 4a has 21 carbon <lb/>signals in the side arms. These signals consist of two azomethine, six aromatics, six quaternary, six <lb/>methylene, and one methyl carbons. Further complete assignment of all carbons was done using <lb/>DEPT experiments. DEPT 90 gave information on methine carbon (CH) and DEPT 135 gave <lb/>information on the methylene carbon (CH2) which appeared as the negative signal while methine <lb/>(CH) and methyl (CH3) carbon showed positive signals. <lb/>Figure 4. (a) 13 C NMR, (b) DEPT 90 and (c) DEPT 135 spectra of compound 4a. <lb/>Figure 4. (a) 13 C NMR, (b) DEPT 90 and (c) DEPT 135 spectra of compound 4a. <lb/>Based on the DEPT 90 spectrum (Figure 4b), peaks at δ 159.38 and 158.83 ppm were assigned to two <lb/>azomethine carbons, C5 and C10. The aromatic carbon signals were observed at δ 115.46, 122.13, 122.32, <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Molecules 2020, 25, 2122 <lb/></note>

			<page>7 of 26 <lb/></page>

			<body>129.28, 130.53, and 130.81 ppm which can be assigned to C12, C8, C7, C3, C13, and C2, respectively. <lb/>Six carbon signals, which were absent in the DEPT 90 spectrum were assigned for the quaternary <lb/>carbons (C1, C4, C6, C9, C11, and C14). C1 and C14 were in the most deshielded region at δ 162.09 <lb/>and 162.02 ppm, respectively, due to electronegativity effect of the oxygen atom. On the other hand, <lb/>C4 and C11 were assigned at δ 136.49 and 135.76 ppm, respectively, as these carbons were attached to <lb/>the less electronegative atoms among other quaternary carbons. The two carbons attached to nitrogen <lb/>atoms, C6 and C9, were assigned to peaks at δ 150.63 and 149.14 ppm, respectively. Six methylene <lb/>carbons of the heptyl chains (C15-C20) showed negative signals in the DEPT 135 spectrum (Figure 4c). <lb/>C15 adjacent to the oxygen atom was observed at δ 68.64 ppm. Five methylene carbons of the aliphatic <lb/>chains showed signals at δ 22.31 (C20), 25.88 (C19), 28.76 (C18), 29.16 (C17), and 31.58 ppm (C15). <lb/>The signal at δ 13.91 ppm disappeared in the DEPT 90 spectrum but appeared in the positive region of <lb/>DEPT 135 spectrum, confirming that this carbon signal belongs to the methyl carbon (C21). <lb/>The assignment of all proton ( 1 H-1 H) correlations between proton and neighboring proton was <lb/>further confirmed using a COSY ( 1 H-1 H) NMR experiment. According to the COSY ( 1 H-1 H) spectrum <lb/>(Figure 5), H5 and H6 did not show any correlation with other protons, which indicated that there <lb/>are the azomethine protons. The correlation of the aromatic protons can be seen between H2 and H3, <lb/>H7 and H8, and H12 and H13, respectively. However, the correlations between methylene protons of <lb/>the heptyl chains could be observed between H15 and H16, H16, and H17, and H18-H21. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Molecules 2020, 25, x FOR PEER REVIEW <lb/></note>

			<page>7 of 26 <lb/></page>

			<body>Based on the DEPT 90 spectrum (Figure 4b), peaks at δ 159.38 and 158.83 ppm were assigned to <lb/>two azomethine carbons, C5 and C10. The aromatic carbon signals were observed at δ 115.46, 122.13, <lb/>122.32, 129.28, 130.53, and 130.81 ppm which can be assigned to C12, C8, C7, C3, C13, and C2, <lb/>respectively. Six carbon signals, which were absent in the DEPT 90 spectrum were assigned for the <lb/>quaternary carbons (C1, C4, C6, C9, C11, and C14). C1 and C14 were in the most deshielded region <lb/>at δ 162.09 and 162.02 ppm, respectively, due to electronegativity effect of the oxygen atom. On the <lb/>other hand, C4 and C11 were assigned at δ 136.49 and 135.76 ppm, respectively, as these carbons <lb/>were attached to the less electronegative atoms among other quaternary carbons. The two carbons <lb/>attached to nitrogen atoms, C6 and C9, were assigned to peaks at δ 150.63 and 149.14 ppm, <lb/>respectively. Six methylene carbons of the heptyl chains (C15-C20) showed negative signals in the <lb/>DEPT 135 spectrum (Figure 4c). C15 adjacent to the oxygen atom was observed at δ 68.64 ppm. Five <lb/>methylene carbons of the aliphatic chains showed signals at δ 22.31 (C20), 25.88 (C19), 28.76 (C18), <lb/>29.16 (C17), and 31.58 ppm (C15). The signal at δ 13.91 ppm disappeared in the DEPT 90 spectrum <lb/>but appeared in the positive region of DEPT 135 spectrum, confirming that this carbon signal belongs <lb/>to the methyl carbon (C21). <lb/>The assignment of all proton ( 1 H-1 H) correlations between proton and neighboring proton was <lb/>further confirmed using a COSY ( 1 H-1 H) NMR experiment. According to the COSY ( 1 H-1 H) spectrum <lb/>(Figure 5), H5 and H6 did not show any correlation with other protons, which indicated that there <lb/>are the azomethine protons. The correlation of the aromatic protons can be seen between H2 and H3, <lb/>H7 and H8, and H12 and H13, respectively. However, the correlations between methylene protons <lb/>of the heptyl chains could be observed between H15 and H16, H16, and H17, and H18-H21. <lb/>Figure 5. COSY ( 1 H-1 H) spectrum of compound 4a. <lb/>Figure 5. COSY ( 1 H-1 H) spectrum of compound 4a. <lb/>Assignment of the protonated carbons in compound 4a was done using HSQC NMR experiment <lb/>(Figure 6). The azomethine protons at δ 8.66 (H5) and δ 8.55 ppm (H10), showed correlations with the <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Molecules 2020, 25, 2122 <lb/></note>

			<page>8 of 26 <lb/></page>

			<body>carbons at δ 159.38 (C5) and 158.83 (C10) ppm, respectively. The 1 H-13 C connectivity in the aromatic <lb/>region could be observed between H2 and C2 at δ 130.81 ppm; H3 and C3 at δ 129.28 ppm; H7 and C7 <lb/>at δ 122.32 ppm; H8 and C8 at δ 122.13 ppm; H12 and C12 at δ 115.56 ppm; and H13 with C13 at δ <lb/>130.53 ppm. Moreover, H15 at δ 4.07 ppm was correlated with C15 at δ 68.64 ppm. The connectivity of <lb/>methylene protons (H16-H20) with their corresponding carbons (C16-C20) was also observed in the <lb/>HSQC spectrum. A triplet at δ 0.89 ppm assigned to H21 for the methyl protons showed connectivity <lb/>with its methyl carbon (C21) at δ 14.06 ppm in the most upfield region. All the data obtained from the <lb/>COSY ( 1 H-1 H) and HSQC ( 1 H-13 C) spectra are summarized in Table 1. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Molecules 2020, 25, x FOR PEER REVIEW <lb/></note>

			<page>8 of 26 <lb/></page>

			<body>Assignment of the protonated carbons in compound 4a was done using HSQC NMR experiment <lb/>(Figure 6). The azomethine protons at δ 8.66 (H5) and δ 8.55 ppm (H10), showed correlations with <lb/>the carbons at δ 159.38 (C5) and 158.83 (C10) ppm, respectively. The 1 H-13 C connectivity in the <lb/>aromatic region could be observed between H2 and C2 at δ 130.81 ppm; H3 and C3 at δ 129.28 ppm; <lb/>H7 and C7 at δ 122.32 ppm; H8 and C8 at δ 122.13 ppm; H12 and C12 at δ 115.56 ppm; and H13 with <lb/>C13 at δ 130.53 ppm. Moreover, H15 at δ 4.07 ppm was correlated with C15 at δ 68.64 ppm. The <lb/>connectivity of methylene protons (H16-H20) with their corresponding carbons (C16-C20) was also <lb/>observed in the HSQC spectrum. A triplet at δ 0.89 ppm assigned to H21 for the methyl protons <lb/>showed connectivity with its methyl carbon (C21) at δ 14.06 ppm in the most upfield region. All the <lb/>data obtained from the COSY ( 1 H-1 H) and HSQC ( 1 H-13 C) spectra are summarized in Table 1. <lb/>Figure 6. HSQC ( 1 H-13 C) spectrum of compound 4a. <lb/>Table 1. 1 H, COSY, and HSQC NMR data of compound 4a. <lb/>Proton <lb/>1 H [δ (ppm), Multiplicity, Coupling <lb/>Constant (Hz)] <lb/>COSY <lb/>( 1 H-1 H) <lb/>Correlation <lb/>HSQC <lb/>( 1 H-13 C) <lb/>Correlation (ppm) <lb/>H2 <lb/>7.55 (d, J = 5.0 Hz) <lb/>H3 <lb/>C2 (129.28) <lb/>H3 <lb/>7.95 (d, J = 5.0 Hz) <lb/>H2 <lb/>C3 (136.49) <lb/>H5 <lb/>8.66 (s, 1H) <lb/>-<lb/>C5 (159.38) <lb/>H7 <lb/>7.33 (d, J = 10.0 Hz) <lb/>H8 <lb/>C7 (122.32) <lb/>H8 <lb/>7.28 (d, J = 20.0 Hz) <lb/>H7 <lb/>C8 (122.13) <lb/>H10 <lb/>8.55 (s, 1H) <lb/>-<lb/>C10 (158.83) <lb/>H12 <lb/>7.87 (d, J = 10.0 Hz) <lb/>H13 <lb/>C12 (135.76) <lb/>H13 <lb/>7.03 (d, J = 5.0 Hz) <lb/>H12 <lb/>C13 (115.46) <lb/>H15 <lb/>4.07 (t, J = 5.0 Hz) <lb/>H16 <lb/>C15 (68.64) <lb/>Figure 6. HSQC ( 1 H-13 C) spectrum of compound 4a. <lb/>Table 1. 1 H, COSY, and HSQC NMR data of compound 4a. <lb/>Proton <lb/>1 H [δ (ppm), Multiplicity, <lb/>Coupling Constant (Hz)] <lb/>COSY ( 1 H-1 H) <lb/>Correlation <lb/>HSQC ( 1 H-13 C) <lb/>Correlation (ppm) <lb/>H2 <lb/>7.55 (d, J = 5.0 Hz) <lb/>H3 <lb/>C2 (129.28) <lb/>H3 <lb/>7.95 (d, J = 5.0 Hz) <lb/>H2 <lb/>C3 (136.49) <lb/>H5 <lb/>8.66 (s, 1H) <lb/>-<lb/>C5 (159.38) <lb/>H7 <lb/>7.33 (d, J = 10.0 Hz) <lb/>H8 <lb/>C7 (122.32) <lb/>H8 <lb/>7.28 (d, J = 20.0 Hz) <lb/>H7 <lb/>C8 (122.13) <lb/>H10 <lb/>8.55 (s, 1H) <lb/>-<lb/>C10 (158.83) <lb/>H12 <lb/>7.87 (d, J = 10.0 Hz) <lb/>H13 <lb/>C12 (135.76) <lb/>H13 <lb/>7.03 (d, J = 5.0 Hz) <lb/>H12 <lb/>C13 (115.46) <lb/>H15 <lb/>4.07 (t, J = 5.0 Hz) <lb/>H16 <lb/>C15 (68.64) <lb/>H16-H20 <lb/>1.32-1.79 (m) <lb/>H15-H21 <lb/>C16-C20 (22.31-31.58) <lb/>H21 <lb/>0.89 (t, J = 7.5 Hz) <lb/>H20 <lb/>C21 (14.06) <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Molecules 2020, 25, 2122 <lb/></note>

			<page>9 of 26 <lb/></page>

			<body>The 31 P NMR spectrum of compound 4a (Figure 7a) showed only a singlet at δ 8.20 ppm. <lb/>The peak of this compound was shifted to the upfield region as compared to that of HCCP with <lb/>six electron-withdrawing chlorine atoms (Figure 7b), indicating that all the phosphorus had been <lb/>substituted with the same side arms. The 31 P NMR spectrum showed the chemical shifts of the <lb/>hexasubstituted cyclotriphosphazene series experience more shielding. This behavior was attributed <lb/>to the molecular structure of the hexa-series that contains six side arms with high electron density. As a <lb/>result, greater shielding effect was observed. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Molecules 2020, 25, x FOR PEER REVIEW <lb/></note>

			<page>9 of 26 <lb/></page>

			<body>H16-<lb/>H20 <lb/>1.32-1.79 (m) <lb/>H15-H21 <lb/>C16-C20 (22.31-<lb/>31.58) <lb/>H21 <lb/>0.89 (t, J = 7.5 Hz) <lb/>H20 <lb/>C21 (14.06) <lb/>The 31 P NMR spectrum of compound 4a (Figure 7a) showed only a singlet at δ 8.20 ppm. The <lb/>peak of this compound was shifted to the upfield region as compared to that of HCCP with six <lb/>electron-withdrawing chlorine atoms (Figure 7b), indicating that all the phosphorus had been <lb/>substituted with the same side arms. The 31 P NMR spectrum showed the chemical shifts of the <lb/>hexasubstituted cyclotriphosphazene series experience more shielding. This behavior was attributed <lb/>to the molecular structure of the hexa-series that contains six side arms with high electron density. <lb/>As a result, greater shielding effect was observed. <lb/>Figure 7. 31 P NMR spectrum of (a) compound 4a and (b) HCCP. <lb/>Furthermore, other homologues with alkylated terminal chains (compounds 4b-e) showed <lb/>similar splitting patterns and chemical shifts in the 1 H and 13 C NMR spectra with compound 4a but <lb/>only differed in terms of the number of protons and carbons in the alkyl chains. Compounds 4f-j <lb/>with small terminal substituents (OH, Cl, COOH, NO2, and NH2) showed two singlets of azomethine <lb/>and six doublets for aromatic protons in the 1 H NMR spectra. There was a slight difference in the <lb/>chemical shift values of the signals of each compound due to the chemical environment, <lb/>Figure 7. 31 P NMR spectrum of (a) compound 4a and (b) HCCP. <lb/>Furthermore, other homologues with alkylated terminal chains (compounds 4b-e) showed similar <lb/>splitting patterns and chemical shifts in the 1 H and 13 C NMR spectra with compound 4a but only <lb/>differed in terms of the number of protons and carbons in the alkyl chains. Compounds 4f-j with small <lb/>terminal substituents (OH, Cl, COOH, NO 2 , and NH 2 ) showed two singlets of azomethine and six <lb/>doublets for aromatic protons in the 1 H NMR spectra. There was a slight difference in the chemical <lb/>shift values of the signals of each compound due to the chemical environment, electronegativity effect, <lb/>and bond angles. Only compounds 4f and 4g showed the hydroxyl and carboxyl proton peaks in the <lb/>1 H NMR spectra. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Molecules 2020, 25, 2122 <lb/></note>

			<page>10 of 26 <lb/></page>

			<body>2.4. Determination of Liquid-Crystal Properties Using POM <lb/>The phase textures of intermediate and final compounds were determined using POM. In this <lb/>study, all the intermediates (1a-e, 2a-j, and 3) were found to be non-mesogenic with no liquid-crystal <lb/>behavior. Meanwhile, compounds 4a-i with two Schiff base linking units were found to exhibit <lb/>liquid-crystal phase while compound 4j was found to be non-mesogenic. Observation under POM <lb/>(Figure 8) showed that compound 4a exhibited the thread-like nematic phase with four-point brushes <lb/>in the cooling cycle. Further cooling changed the nematic phase into SmA phase before it became a <lb/>crystal phase. <lb/>liquid-crystal phase while compound 4j was found to be non-mesogenic. Observation under POM <lb/>(Figure 8) showed that compound 4a exhibited the thread-like nematic phase with four-point brushes <lb/>in the cooling cycle. Further cooling changed the nematic phase into SmA phase before it became a <lb/>crystal phase. <lb/>The phase transitions of compounds 4b-d showed the focal conic fan texture of SmA phase in <lb/>the heating and cooling cycles, as illustrated in Figure 9. Meanwhile, compound 4e exhibited two <lb/>different types of phase transition in both heating and cooling cycles. Upon cooling, a focal conic fan <lb/>of SmA phase was formed from the isotropic phase and further cooling resulted in the formation of <lb/>a broken focal conic fan of SmC phase which might be due to the stacking of molecules. The texture <lb/>is illustrated in Figure 10. <lb/>For compounds 4f-i, schlieren texture of the nematic phase with four-point brushes was clearly <lb/>observed under POM (Figures 11 and 12) in the heating and cooling cycles. Upon cooling, compound <lb/>4f showed the formation of droplets from the isotropic phase which became the nematic phase with <lb/>a thread-like texture, as shown in Figure 11. However, compound 4j without any liquid-crystal <lb/>properties only displays the phase transition of crystal to isotropic phase in heating cycle and <lb/>isotropic to crystal phase in cooling cycle. <lb/>(a) <lb/>(b) <lb/>Figure 8. The optical photomicrographs of compound 4a in the cooling cycle: (a) focal conic fans of <lb/>SmA phase at 190.57 °C, and (b) thread-like schlieren texture of nematic phase at 223.98 °C <lb/>(Magnification of 20 × 0.50). <lb/>Figure 8. The optical photomicrographs of compound 4a in the cooling cycle: (a) focal conic fans of SmA <lb/>phase at 190.57 • C, and (b) thread-like schlieren texture of nematic phase at 223.98 • C (Magnification of <lb/>20 × 0.50). <lb/>The phase transitions of compounds 4b-d showed the focal conic fan texture of SmA phase in <lb/>the heating and cooling cycles, as illustrated in Figure 9. Meanwhile, compound 4e exhibited two <lb/>different types of phase transition in both heating and cooling cycles. Upon cooling, a focal conic fan of <lb/>SmA phase was formed from the isotropic phase and further cooling resulted in the formation of a <lb/>broken focal conic fan of SmC phase which might be due to the stacking of molecules. The texture is <lb/>illustrated in Figure 10. <lb/>For compounds 4f-i, schlieren texture of the nematic phase with four-point brushes was clearly <lb/>observed under POM (Figures 11 and 12) in the heating and cooling cycles. Upon cooling, compound 4f <lb/>showed the formation of droplets from the isotropic phase which became the nematic phase with <lb/>a thread-like texture, as shown in Figure 11. However, compound 4j without any liquid-crystal <lb/>properties only displays the phase transition of crystal to isotropic phase in heating cycle and isotropic <lb/>to crystal phase in cooling cycle. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Molecules 2020, 25, 2122 <lb/></note>

			<page>11 of 26 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Molecules 2020, 25, x FOR PEER REVIEW <lb/></note>

			<page>11 of 26 <lb/></page>

			<body>(a) <lb/>(b) <lb/>(c) <lb/>Figure 9. The optical photomicrographs of compounds 4b-d in the heating cycle showing the focal <lb/>conic fans of SmA phase: (a) 4b at 188.15 °C, (b) 4c at 179.33 °C, and (c) 4d at 180.48 °C (Magnification <lb/>of 20 × 0.50). <lb/>(a) <lb/>(b) <lb/>Figure 10. The optical photomicrographs of compound 4e in the cooling cycle, (a) SmA at 175.34 °C <lb/>and (b) SmC at 143.76 °C (Magnification of 20 × 0.25). <lb/>Figure 9. The optical photomicrographs of compounds 4b-d in the heating cycle showing the focal <lb/>conic fans of SmA phase: (a) 4b at 188.15 • C, (b) 4c at 179.33 • C, and (c) 4d at 180.48 • C (Magnification of <lb/>20 × 0.50). <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Molecules 2020, 25, x FOR PEER REVIEW <lb/></note>

			<page>11 of 26 <lb/></page>

			<body>(a) <lb/>(b) <lb/>(c) <lb/>Figure 9. The optical photomicrographs of compounds 4b-d in the heating cycle showing the focal <lb/>conic fans of SmA phase: (a) 4b at 188.15 °C , (b) 4c at 179.33 °C , and (c) 4d at 180.48 °C (Magnification <lb/>of 20 × 0.50). <lb/>(a) <lb/>(b) <lb/>Figure 10. The optical photomicrographs of compound 4e in the cooling cycle, (a) SmA at 175.34 °C <lb/>and (b) SmC at 143.76 °C (Magnification of 20 × 0.25). <lb/>Figure 10. The optical photomicrographs of compound 4e in the cooling cycle, (a) SmA at 175.34 • C <lb/>and (b) SmC at 143.76 • C (Magnification of 20 × 0.25). <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Molecules 2020, 25, 2122 <lb/></note>

			<page>12 of 26 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Molecules 2020, 25, x FOR PEER REVIEW <lb/></note>

			<page>12 of 26 <lb/></page>

			<body>(a) <lb/>(b) <lb/>Figure 11. The optical photomicrographs of compound 4f in the cooling cycle: (a) droplets at 211.38 <lb/>°C, and (b) thread-like schlieren texture of nematic phase at 215.88 °C (Magnification of 20 × 0.25). <lb/>(a) <lb/>(b) <lb/>(c) <lb/>Figure 12. The optical photomicrographs of compounds 4g-i in the cooling cycle showing the thread-<lb/>like schlieren texture of nematic phase: (a) 4g at 210.33 °C, (b) 4h at 211.45 °C, and (c) 4i at198.67 °C <lb/>(Magnification of 20 × 0.25). <lb/>Figure 11. The optical photomicrographs of compound 4f in the cooling cycle: (a) droplets at 211.38 • C, <lb/>and (b) thread-like schlieren texture of nematic phase at 215.88 • C (Magnification of 20 × 0.25). <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Molecules 2020, 25, x FOR PEER REVIEW <lb/></note>

			<page>12 of 26 <lb/></page>

			<body>(a) <lb/>(b) <lb/>Figure 11. The optical photomicrographs of compound 4f in the cooling cycle: (a) droplets at 211.38 <lb/>°C, and (b) thread-like schlieren texture of nematic phase at 215.88 °C (Magnification of 20 × 0.25). <lb/>(a) <lb/>(b) <lb/>(c) <lb/>Figure 12. The optical photomicrographs of compounds 4g-i in the cooling cycle showing the thread-<lb/>like schlieren texture of nematic phase: (a) 4g at 210.33 °C, (b) 4h at 211.45 °C, and (c) 4i at198.67 °C <lb/>(Magnification of 20 × 0.25). <lb/>Figure 12. The optical photomicrographs of compounds 4g-i in the cooling cycle showing the thread-like <lb/>schlieren texture of nematic phase: (a) 4g at 210.33 • C, (b) 4h at 211.45 • C, and (c) 4i at 198.67 • C <lb/>(Magnification of 20 × 0.25). <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Molecules 2020, 25, 2122 <lb/></note>

			<page>13 of 26 <lb/></page>

			<body>2.5. Determination of Thermal Transitions Using DSC <lb/>Texture observation under POM with controlled temperature helped to determine the type of <lb/>mesophases present in the molecules. Only compounds exhibiting mesophase(s) were sent for DSC <lb/>measurements. The DSC thermograms are used to confirm the phase transition temperatures and <lb/>enthalpy change involved during the transition in the heating and cooling cycles. The phase transitions <lb/>and its corresponding enthalpy change of compounds 4a-i with two Schiff base linking units is <lb/>summarized in Table 2. <lb/>Table 2. Phase transitional properties of compounds 4a-i upon heating and cooling cycles. <lb/>Cpd Mode <lb/>Transition Temperature ( • C) <lb/>Enthalpy, ∆H (kJ/mol) <lb/>4a <lb/>H Cr <lb/>SmC <lb/>SmA <lb/>N <lb/>I <lb/>• <lb/>156.33 <lb/>48.30 <lb/>• <lb/>210.97 <lb/>32.42 <lb/>• <lb/>235.89 <lb/>15.74 <lb/>• <lb/>C <lb/>I <lb/>N <lb/>SmA <lb/>SmC <lb/>Cr <lb/>• <lb/>232.89 <lb/>-12.16 <lb/>• <lb/>202.65 <lb/>-28.05 <lb/>• <lb/>144.82 <lb/>-27.92 <lb/>• <lb/>4b <lb/>H Cr <lb/>SmC <lb/>SmA <lb/>N <lb/>I <lb/>• <lb/>152.47 <lb/>9.25 <lb/>• <lb/>206.81 <lb/>7.68 <lb/>• <lb/>C <lb/>I <lb/>N <lb/>SmA <lb/>SmC <lb/>Cr <lb/>• <lb/>200.53 <lb/>-7.57 <lb/>• <lb/>144.76 <lb/>-7.16 <lb/>• <lb/>4c <lb/>H Cr <lb/>SmC <lb/>SmA <lb/>N <lb/>I <lb/>• <lb/>151.60 <lb/>36.70 <lb/>• <lb/>201.38 <lb/>19.81 <lb/>• <lb/>C <lb/>I <lb/>N <lb/>SmA <lb/>SmC <lb/>Cr <lb/>• <lb/>192.87 <lb/>-10.25 <lb/>• <lb/>140.08 <lb/>-28.35 <lb/>• <lb/>4d <lb/>H Cr <lb/>SmC <lb/>SmA <lb/>N <lb/>I <lb/>• <lb/>149.69 <lb/>19.02 <lb/>• <lb/>198.44 <lb/>12.79 <lb/>• <lb/>C <lb/>I <lb/>N <lb/>SmA <lb/>SmC <lb/>Cr <lb/>• <lb/>193.87 <lb/>-9.04 <lb/>• <lb/>136.91 <lb/>-26.59 <lb/>• <lb/>4e <lb/>H Cr <lb/>SmC <lb/>SmA <lb/>N <lb/>I <lb/>• <lb/>147.75 <lb/>34.59 <lb/>• <lb/>174.33 <lb/>31.48 <lb/>• <lb/>197.81 <lb/>22.18 <lb/>• <lb/>C <lb/>I <lb/>N <lb/>SmA <lb/>SmC <lb/>Cr <lb/>• <lb/>195.64 <lb/>-14.34 <lb/>• <lb/>148.24 <lb/>-38.11 <lb/>• <lb/>132.86 <lb/>-34.60 <lb/>• <lb/>4f <lb/>H Cr <lb/>SmC <lb/>SmA <lb/>N <lb/>I <lb/>• <lb/>182.54 <lb/>97.20 <lb/>• <lb/>231.49 <lb/>44.93 <lb/>• <lb/>C <lb/>I <lb/>N <lb/>SmA <lb/>SmC <lb/>Cr <lb/>• <lb/>220.43 <lb/>-51.10 <lb/>• <lb/>167.83 <lb/>-66.25 <lb/>• <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Molecules 2020, 25, 2122 <lb/></note>

			<page>14 of 26 <lb/></page>

			<body>Table 2. Cont. <lb/>Cpd Mode <lb/>Transition Temperature ( • C) <lb/>Enthalpy, ∆H (kJ/mol) <lb/>4g <lb/>H Cr <lb/>SmC <lb/>SmA <lb/>N <lb/>I <lb/>• <lb/>172.62 <lb/>15.15 <lb/>• <lb/>243.79 <lb/>10.22 <lb/>• <lb/>C <lb/>I <lb/>N <lb/>SmA <lb/>SmC <lb/>Cr <lb/>• <lb/>240.96 <lb/>-33.81 <lb/>• <lb/>167.81 <lb/>-18.90 <lb/>• <lb/>4h <lb/>H Cr <lb/>SmC <lb/>SmA <lb/>N <lb/>I <lb/>• <lb/>166.47 <lb/>19.71 <lb/>• <lb/>226.30 <lb/>15.71 <lb/>• <lb/>C <lb/>I <lb/>N <lb/>SmA <lb/>SmC <lb/>Cr <lb/>• <lb/>223.55 <lb/>-8.00 <lb/>• <lb/>149.33 <lb/>-18.74 <lb/>• <lb/>4i <lb/>H Cr <lb/>SmC <lb/>SmA <lb/>N <lb/>I <lb/>• <lb/>157.47 <lb/>7.25 <lb/>• <lb/>219.11 <lb/>4.98 <lb/>• <lb/>C <lb/>I <lb/>N <lb/>SmA <lb/>SmC <lb/>Cr <lb/>• <lb/>211.47 <lb/>-5.94 <lb/>• <lb/>157.26 <lb/>-5.67 <lb/>• <lb/>Note: Cpd = Compound, H = Heating, C = Cooling, Cr = Crystal, SmC = Smectic C, SmA = Smectic A, N = Nematic, <lb/>I = Isotropic. <lb/>The DSC thermogram of compounds 4a and 4e shows three endotherms or curves with their <lb/>enthalpy values, in both heating and cooling cycles. Upon heating of compound 4a, the curves <lb/>were attributed to the phase transitions from crystal to SmA and nematic before reaching a clearing <lb/>temperature at 235.89 • C. Similar phase transitions were also observed in the reversed order of the <lb/>cooling cycle. For compound 4e, the phase transitions were from the crystal to SmC and then SmA <lb/>before it became the isotropic phase with the melting point observed at 147.75 • C and the clearing <lb/>temperature at 197.81 • C. <lb/>Compounds 4b-d and 4f-i exhibited only two curves in the DSC thermogram which indicates <lb/>that these compounds have only one liquid-crystal phase. The DSC thermogram of compounds 4b-d <lb/>displayed the transition from crystal to SmA and isotropic phase in the heating cycle. Meanwhile, <lb/>compounds 4f-i with substituents such as hydroxy, 4-carboxyphenyl, chloro, and nitro terminal <lb/>chains in the side arms also showed two curves in the DSC thermogram, the transition from crystal <lb/>to the thread-like nematic, and isotropic phase. In the cooling cycle, these two curves of phase <lb/>transitions were also observed in the reverse order. The DSC thermogram of compound 4f is shown <lb/>in Figure 13. In addition, the DSC thermogram of compounds 4a-e and 4g-i are provided in the <lb/>Supplementary Materials Section. The existence of endotherm appears in the DSC thermogram for <lb/>each of the mesophase transition, which corresponds to the texture of liquid crystal, which is observed <lb/>under POM. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Molecules 2020, 25, 2122 <lb/></note>

			<page>15 of 26 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Molecules 2020, 25, x FOR PEER REVIEW <lb/></note>

			<page>15 of 26 <lb/></page>

			<body>Figure 13. DSC thermogram of compound 4f. <lb/>2.6. Structure-Properties Relationship <lb/>The study on the relationship between structure and liquid-crystal mesophase behavior is very <lb/>important in designing new liquid-crystal materials with desirable properties for future applications. <lb/>Based on the POM observation, all the final compounds in the series with a Schiff base linking <lb/>unit that bore a different terminal alkoxy function were mesogenic and the wider of the thermal <lb/>mesomorphic range increased with increasing chain length. Compound 4a with heptyl chains <lb/>showed smectic and nematic phases with the texture of thread-like four-point brushes. As the length <lb/>of the alkyl chain increased, the tendency for formation of the nematic phase was reduced. This trend <lb/>was observed for compounds 4b-e which exhibited only the smectic phase since the flexibility of the <lb/>long chains tends to decrease the clearing temperatures, Tc. Smectic phases are more ordered than <lb/>the nematic phase. Nematic phase has the positional order but no orientational order and closest to <lb/>the isotropic phase. Hence, effective molecular packing is essential for the formation of stable phases. <lb/>Moreover, the polarisability of the molecules also increased with an increase of the alkoxy chain <lb/>length in the compounds. This enhanced the cohesive forces between the sides and the core of the <lb/>molecules, thus increased the tendency to form the smectic layer [35]. Molecules with smectic phase <lb/>behavior are likely to favor a lamellar packing, which is due to higher Van der Waals interactions <lb/>and intertwining possibility between the alkoxy chains. Thus, the nematic orientation cannot be <lb/>adopted as the chain length increased and resulted in only a smectic phase in compounds 4b-e. <lb/>In this work, compounds 4a-e exhibited the smectic A phase while compound 4e showed an <lb/>additional of smectic C. The presence of smectic C phase in compound 4e is due to the tilted analogue <lb/>of the smectic A phase [36]. In smectic C, molecules are aligned with their long axes tilted relative to <lb/>the layer normal in which the molecules are stacked. Meanwhile, molecules in smectic A are arranged <lb/>in layers, with long axes perpendicular to the layers which can slide over one another [37]. <lb/>Small terminal substituents, such as hydroxy or carboxy, do not always induce liquid-crystal <lb/>behavior [38]. In contrast, Sudhakar et al. (2000) reported that small molecules often exhibit one or <lb/>more liquid crystalline phases since these molecules have geometrical anisotropy and high <lb/>polarisability [39]. In this study, compound 4f with the -OH terminal group and compound 4g with <lb/>-COOH substituent showed the formation of the nematic phase. Meanwhile, compound 4h with <lb/>Figure 13. DSC thermogram of compound 4f. <lb/>2.6. Structure-Properties Relationship <lb/>The study on the relationship between structure and liquid-crystal mesophase behavior is very <lb/>important in designing new liquid-crystal materials with desirable properties for future applications. <lb/>Based on the POM observation, all the final compounds in the series with a Schiff base linking <lb/>unit that bore a different terminal alkoxy function were mesogenic and the wider of the thermal <lb/>mesomorphic range increased with increasing chain length. Compound 4a with heptyl chains showed <lb/>smectic and nematic phases with the texture of thread-like four-point brushes. As the length of the <lb/>alkyl chain increased, the tendency for formation of the nematic phase was reduced. This trend was <lb/>observed for compounds 4b-e which exhibited only the smectic phase since the flexibility of the long <lb/>chains tends to decrease the clearing temperatures, T c . Smectic phases are more ordered than the <lb/>nematic phase. Nematic phase has the positional order but no orientational order and closest to the <lb/>isotropic phase. Hence, effective molecular packing is essential for the formation of stable phases. <lb/>Moreover, the polarisability of the molecules also increased with an increase of the alkoxy chain length <lb/>in the compounds. This enhanced the cohesive forces between the sides and the core of the molecules, <lb/>thus increased the tendency to form the smectic layer [35]. Molecules with smectic phase behavior are <lb/>likely to favor a lamellar packing, which is due to higher Van der Waals interactions and intertwining <lb/>possibility between the alkoxy chains. Thus, the nematic orientation cannot be adopted as the chain <lb/>length increased and resulted in only a smectic phase in compounds 4b-e. <lb/>In this work, compounds 4a-e exhibited the smectic A phase while compound 4e showed an <lb/>additional of smectic C. The presence of smectic C phase in compound 4e is due to the tilted analogue <lb/>of the smectic A phase [36]. In smectic C, molecules are aligned with their long axes tilted relative to <lb/>the layer normal in which the molecules are stacked. Meanwhile, molecules in smectic A are arranged <lb/>in layers, with long axes perpendicular to the layers which can slide over one another [37]. <lb/>Small terminal substituents, such as hydroxy or carboxy, do not always induce liquid-crystal <lb/>behavior [38]. In contrast, Sudhakar et al. (2000) reported that small molecules often exhibit one or more <lb/>liquid crystalline phases since these molecules have geometrical anisotropy and high polarisability [39]. <lb/>In this study, compound 4f with the -OH terminal group and compound 4g with -COOH substituent <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Molecules 2020, 25, 2122 <lb/></note>

			<page>16 of 26 <lb/></page>

			<body>showed the formation of the nematic phase. Meanwhile, compound 4h with chlorine at the terminal <lb/>end also exhibited the nematic phase. The result agreed with the literature data which demonstrated <lb/>that compounds with the polar group are more likely to exhibit nematic phase compared to compounds <lb/>with a methyl group or hydrogen atom at the terminal chain [40]. Chlorine is a polar substituent <lb/>which possesses a strong dipole moment, thus enhances the stability of the lattice and melting <lb/>temperatures [41]. <lb/>The effect of the NO 2 and NH 2 groups at the terminal end in promoting the mesophase properties <lb/>was also highlighted. The nematic phase exhibited by compound 4i was due to the high polarity <lb/>of NO 2 group which increases the molecular aromaticity and polarisability of the molecules [42]. <lb/>On the other hand, compound 4j was found to be non-mesogenic. This phenomenon might be due <lb/>to the properties of the NH 2 group as an electron-donating group, which increases the repulsive <lb/>interactions between adjacent aromatic rings. As a result, the mesophase transitions cannot be induced. <lb/>Galewski and Coles (1999) also reported that the attachment of an electron withdrawing at the terminal <lb/>end of a compound induces the liquid-crystal properties, while compounds with electron-donating <lb/>groups did not show any liquid-crystal properties [43]. <lb/>In this research, the effect of the Schiff base (-C=N-) linking unit was also studied. When the <lb/>Schiff base linking unit conjugated with the phenylene rings, the length of the molecules increased <lb/>which enhanced the anisotropic polarisability and the flexibility of the compounds [44,45]. Thus, <lb/>the rigidity and linearity of its constituents were maintained and impart various property alterations <lb/>to mesomorphic materials. <lb/>The Schiff base linkage provides a stepped core structure which can maintain the linearity of <lb/>the molecules to provide high stability [46]. This induces mesophase formation whereby the phase <lb/>transition temperatures and the physical properties are usually governed by the linking group [47]. <lb/>This was proven when all the compounds, 4a-i in this series (two Schiff base linking units) except for <lb/>compound 4j with the terminal NH 2 substituent, showed liquid-crystal behavior. Schiff base offers <lb/>the possibility of controlling the alignment and orientation of their molecules which can generate <lb/>liquid-crystal materials [48]. The POM observation of compounds 4a-j is summarized in Table 3. <lb/>Table 3. POM observation of compounds 4a-j. <lb/>Material <lb/>POM Observation <lb/>Material <lb/>POM Observation <lb/>Compound 4a <lb/>Smectic A and Nematic <lb/>Compound 4f <lb/>Nematic <lb/>Compound 4b <lb/>Smectic A <lb/>Compound 4g <lb/>Nematic <lb/>Compound 4c <lb/>Smectic A <lb/>Compound 4h <lb/>Nematic <lb/>Compound 4d <lb/>Smectic A <lb/>Compound 4i <lb/>Nematic <lb/>Compound 4e <lb/>Smectic A and C <lb/>Compound 4j <lb/>Non-mesogenic <lb/>2.7. Determination of Fire-Retardant Properties Using LOI Testing <lb/>All the hexasubstituted cyclotriphosphaze compounds 4a-j were further tested for their <lb/>fire-retardant properties. All the samples were prepared using 1 wt.% to achieve the highest fire <lb/>retardancy with less additive usage. Their effect is to reduce the initiation of a fire by delaying the <lb/>spread of flame and provide resistance to ignition. LOI was used to determine the fire-retardant <lb/>properties of the sample. This test was conducted by suspending the sample vertically inside a closed <lb/>chamber where this chamber was equipped with oxygen and nitrogen gas inlets so that the atmosphere <lb/>in the chamber can be controlled. The sample was then ignited from the top and the atmosphere was <lb/>adjusted to determine the minimum amount of oxygen required to burn a sample at a certain time. <lb/>In this study, polyester resin has been used as a matrix for moulding. As shown in Table 4, the LOI <lb/>value of pure polyester resin was determined as 22.53%. When the polyester resin was incorporated <lb/>with 1 wt.% of HCCP in the matrix, the LOI value increased to 24.71%. HCCP material is well known <lb/>as the compound that has high thermal stability and fire retardancy. This behavior was due to its <lb/>hexa-functionality and high phosphorus content [49]. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Molecules 2020, 25, 2122 <lb/></note>

			<page>17 of 26 <lb/></page>

			<body>Table 4. LOI test results. <lb/>Material <lb/>LOI Value (%) <lb/>Material <lb/>LOI Value (%) <lb/>Pure polyester resin <lb/>22.53 (± 0.00) <lb/>Polyester resin + 1 wt.% of HCCP <lb/>24.71 (± 0.00) <lb/>Compound 4a <lb/>26.90 (± 0.00) <lb/>Compound 4f <lb/>27.54 (± 0.01) <lb/>Compound 4b <lb/>26.71 (± 0.00) <lb/>Compound 4g <lb/>27.73 (± 0.03) <lb/>Compound 4c <lb/>26.71 (± 0.00) <lb/>Compound 4h <lb/>27.90 (± 0.00) <lb/>Compound 4d <lb/>26.53 (± 0.00) <lb/>Compound 4i <lb/>28.37 (± 0.00) <lb/>Compound 4e <lb/>26.37 (± 0.00) <lb/>Compound 4j <lb/>27.28 (± 0.00) <lb/>All compounds showed good agreement in the LOI results where they could be considered to <lb/>be fire-retardant materials. Generally, materials with LOI value above 26% are considered to have <lb/>fire-retardant property and will show self-extinguishing behavior [50,51]. The best result was achieved <lb/>for compound 4i with nitro (-NO 2 ) and compound 4h with chlorine (-Cl) groups at the terminal end, <lb/>with LOI values of 28.37% and 27.90%, respectively. This might be due to the electron-withdrawing <lb/>properties of both the nitro and chlorine groups which induced the properties of fire retardancy. <lb/>These groups can release the electron from their resonance effects due to their corresponding P-N <lb/>bonds. Thus, the P-N synergistic effect was enhanced, and they exhibited both the condensed and gas <lb/>phase action [52]. Similar trends can be observed for the compounds attached to hydroxy, carboxy, <lb/>and amino groups at the terminal end. However, the LOI values decreased as the alkyl chain length <lb/>increased. Moreover, the LOI values of the alkylated compounds were lower compared to those of <lb/>compounds with the hydroxy, carboxy, and amino groups at the terminal end. The longer the alkyl <lb/>tails are attached to the cyclotriphosphazene ring, the more combustible the target materials [53,54]. <lb/>3. Materials and Methods <lb/>3.1. Chemicals <lb/>The chemicals and solvents used in this study are 1-bromoheptane, 1-bromononane, 1-bromodecane, <lb/>1-bromododecane, 1-bromotetradecane, 4-hydroxybenzaldehyde, 4-chlorobenzaldehyde, 4-nitrobenzalde <lb/>hyde, 4-formylbenzoic acid, 1,4-phenylenediamine, phosphonitrilic chloride trimer, sodium sulphide <lb/>hydrate, potassium carbonate, potassium iodide, anhydrous sodium sulphate, glacial acetic acid, <lb/>methanol, ethanol, acetone, N,N-dimethylformamide, dichloromethane, n-hexane, ethyl acetate, <lb/>and triethylamine. All the chemicals and solvents were used as received without further purification <lb/>and purchased from Merck (Darmstadt, Germany), Qrëc (Asia) (Selangor, Malaysia), Sigma-Aldrich <lb/>(Steinheim, Germany), Acros Organics (Geel, Belgium), Fluka (Shanghai, China), and BDH (British Drug <lb/>Houses) (Nichiryo, Japan). <lb/>3.2. Instruments <lb/>In this research, Thin Layer Chromatography (TLC) is used to monitor a reaction progress and <lb/>identify a product in a mixture. The ratios used were 5:95, 10:90, 15:85, 20:80, and 25:75 of ethyl <lb/>acetate:hexane. Meanwhile, all the synthesized intermediates and compounds were characterized <lb/>using FTIR spectroscopy (PerkinElmer, Waltham, MA, USA), NMR spectroscopy (Bruker, Coventry, <lb/>UK), and CHN elemental analysis (PerkinElmer, Waltham, MA, USA). Moreover, the mesophase texture <lb/>of these compounds was determined using POM (Linkam, London, UK) and their transition was <lb/>further confirmed using DSC (PerkinElmer, Waltham, MA, USA). In addition, LOI (S.S. Instruments <lb/>Pvt. Ltd., Delhi, India) was used to determine the minimum amount of oxygen needed to support <lb/>the combustion of a sample. The sample was prepared by mixing 1 wt.% of the final compound with <lb/>polyester resin. About 1 wt.% of methyl ethyl ketone peroxide (MEKP) curing agent was added to the <lb/>mixture and stirred until the sample is homogeneous and then poured into the moulds. The samples <lb/>were cured for 5 h in an oven at 60 • C and left overnight at room temperature before it was burned <lb/>using LOI testing. The LOI test was performed using an FTT oxygen index, according to BS 2782: <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Molecules 2020, 25, 2122 <lb/></note>

			<page>18 of 26 <lb/></page>

			<body>Part 1: Method 141 and ISO 4589 with the dimension of 120 mm × 10 mm × 4 mm. The minimum <lb/>value of oxygen obtained was expressed as a percentage and the LOI results were calculated according <lb/>to the equation given below: <lb/>LOI = C F + (k × d) <lb/>(1) <lb/>where: C F is the oxygen concentration of the final test, k is the factor obtained from the manual book <lb/>Fire Testing Technology (ISO 4589), and d is the oxygen concentration increment. <lb/>3.3. Syntheses <lb/>3.3.1. Synthesis of 4-Alkoxybenzaldehyde, 1a-e <lb/>4-Heptyloxybenzaldehyde, 1a: 4-Hydroxybenzaldehyde (12.21 g, 0.10 mol) was dissolved in N,N-dime <lb/>thylformamide, DMF (20 mL) while 1-bromoheptane (17.89 g, 0.10 mol) was dissolved in DMF <lb/>(20 mL), separately. Both solutions were mixed in a 250 mL round bottom flask. Potassium carbonate <lb/>(20.73 g, 0.15 mol) and potassium iodide (1.66 g, 0.01 mol) were added to the mixture and was then <lb/>refluxed for 12 h. The reaction progress was monitored using TLC. Upon completion, the mixture was <lb/>poured into 500 mL cold water and was extracted using dichloromethane (3 × 30 mL). The organic <lb/>layers were collected, dried with anhydrous sodium sulphate, filtered, and evaporated overnight <lb/>to form a yellowish oil. The same method was used to synthesis 1b-e. Yield: 18.71 g (85.05%), <lb/>light-yellow oil. FTIR (cm -1 ): 2929 and 2857 (Csp 3 -H stretching), 2738 (H-C=O aldehydic stretching), <lb/>1687 (C=O stretching), 1601 (C=C stretching), 1254 (C-O stretching). 1 H-NMR (500 MHz, CDCl 3 ) δ, <lb/>ppm: 9.81 (s, 1H), 7.76 (d, J = 10.0 Hz, 2H), 6.93 (d, J = 10.0 Hz, 2H), 3.97 (t, J = 5.0 Hz, 2H), 1.72-1.78 (m, <lb/>2H), 1.37-1.43 (m, 2H), 1.23-1.34 (m, 6H), 0.84 (t, J = 7.5 Hz, 3H). 13 C-NMR (125 MHz, CDCl 3 ) δ, ppm: <lb/>190.61, 164.24, 131.88, 129.76, 114.71, 68.38, 31.71, 29.03, 28.96, 25.89, 22.54, 14.01. <lb/>4-Nonyloxybenzaldehyde, 1b: Yield: 20.11 g (81.09%), light-yellow oil. FTIR (cm -1 ): 2924 and 2854 <lb/>(Csp 3 -H stretching), 2733 (H-C=O aldehydic stretching), 1689 (C=O stretching), 1601 (C=C stretching), <lb/>1254 (C-O stretching). 1 H-NMR (500 MHz, CDCl 3 ) δ, ppm: 9.79 (s, 1H), 7.73 (d, J = 5.0 Hz, 2H), 6.90 (d, <lb/>J = 5.0 Hz, 2H), 3.95 (t, J = 7.50 Hz, 2H), 1.70-1.76 (m, 2H), 1.36-1.42 (m, 2H), 1.20-1.32 (m, 10H), 0.82 (t, <lb/>J = 5.0 Hz, 3H). 13 C-NMR (125 MHz, CDCl 3 ) δ, ppm: 190.56, 164.24, 131.87, 129.77, 114.71, 68.37, 31.83, <lb/>29.47, 29.32, 29.21, 29.04, 25.93, 22.62, 14.04. <lb/>4-Decyloxybenzaldehyde, 1c: Yield: 21.32 g (81.37%), light-yellow oil. FTIR (cm -1 ): 2924 and 2854 <lb/>(Csp 3 -H stretching), 2733 (H-C=O aldehydic stretching), 1689 (C=O stretching), 1601 (C=C stretching), <lb/>1254 (C-O stretching). 1 H-NMR (500 MHz, CDCl 3 ) δ, ppm: 9.83 (s, 1H), 7.77 (d, J = 10.0 Hz, 2H), <lb/>6.94 (d, J = 10.0 Hz, 2H), 3.99 (t, J = 7.50 Hz, 2H), 1.74-1.79 (m, 2H), 1.39-1.45 (m, 2H), 1.21-1.33 (m, <lb/>12H), 0.84 (t, J = 7.5 Hz, 3H). 13 C-NMR (125 MHz, CDCl 3 ) δ, ppm: 190.65, 164.27, 131.92, 129.78, 114.74, <lb/>68.41, 31.87, 29.52, 29.32, 29.29, 29.05, 25.95, 22.65, 14.06. <lb/>4-Dodecyloxybenzaldehyde, 1d: Yield: 23.56 g (83.25%), light-yellow oil. FTIR (cm -1 ): 2921 and 2854 <lb/>(Csp 3 -H stretching), 2733 (H-C=O aldehydic stretching), 1692 (C=O stretching), 1601 (C=C stretching), <lb/>1254 (C-O stretching). 1 H-NMR (500 MHz, CDCl 3 ) δ, ppm: 9.82 (s, 1H), 7.77 (d, J = 10.0 Hz, 2H), <lb/>6.94 (d, J = 10.0 Hz, 2H), 3.98 (t, J = 7.50 Hz, 2H), 1.74-1.79 (m, 2H), 1.39-1.45 (m, 2H), 1.22-1.33 (m, <lb/>16H), 0.84 (t, J = 7.5 Hz, 3H). 13 C-NMR (125 MHz, CDCl 3 ) δ, ppm: 190.63, 164.26, 131.91, 129.78, 114.73, <lb/>68.41, 31.90, 29.64, 29.62, 29.57, 29.53, 29.33, 29.05, 25.95, 22.67, 14.07. <lb/>4-Tetradecyloxybenzaldehyde, 1e: Yield: 24.75 g (79.58%), mp: 56.6-58.7 • C, white powder. FTIR (cm -1 ): <lb/>2916 and 2845 (Csp 3 -H stretching), 2733 (H-C=O aldehydic stretching), 1689 (C=O stretching), <lb/>1601 (C=C stretching), 1251 (C-O stretching). 1 H-NMR (500 MHz, CDCl 3 ) δ, ppm: 9.85 (s, 1H), <lb/>7.80 (d, J = 10.0 Hz, 2H), 6.96 (d, J = 10.0 Hz, 2H), 4.01 (t, J = 7.50 Hz, 2H), 1.76-1.81 (m, 2H), <lb/>1.41-1.47 (m, 2H), 1.23-1.36 (m, 20H), 0.86 (t, J = 7.5 Hz, 3H). 13 C-NMR (125 MHz, CDCl 3 ) δ, ppm: <lb/>190.76, 164.29, 131.97, 129.79, 114.76, 68.45, 31.92, 29.68, 29.66 29.64, 29.57, 29.53, 29.34, 29.33, 29.06, <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Molecules 2020, 25, 2122 <lb/></note>

			<page>19 of 26 <lb/></page>

			<body>25.95, 22.67, 14.09. CHN elemental analysis: Calculated for C 21 H 34 O 2 : C: 79.19%, H: 10.76%; Found: <lb/>C: 78.91%, H: 10.66%. <lb/>3.3.2. Synthesis of N-(4-Substitutedbenxylidene)benzene-1,4-diamine, 2a-i <lb/>N-(4-heptyloxybenxylidene)benzene-1,4-diamine, 2a: A mixture of 1,4-phenylenediamine (1.08 g, <lb/>0.01 mol) and intermediate 1a (1.54 g, 0.007 mol) was dissolved in 15 mL methanol in a 100 mL <lb/>round bottom flask. The reaction was stirred at room temperature for 2 h. The reaction progress <lb/>was monitored by TLC. Upon completion, the mixture was cooled in ice water and the precipitate <lb/>formed was filtered and dried. The precipitate was recrystallised from ethanol to yield a yellow <lb/>powder. The same method was used to synthesis 2b-i. Yield = 1.85 g (85.25%), mp: 136.5-138.3 • C, <lb/>yellow powder. FTIR (cm -1 ): 3462 and 3336 (N-H stretching), 2927 and 2857 (Csp 3 -H stretching), <lb/>1603 (C=N stretching), 1509 (aromatic C=C stretching), 1248 (C-O stretching), 1168 (C-N stretching). <lb/>1 H-NMR (500 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) δ, ppm: 8.47 (s, 1H), 7.79 (d, J = 10.0 Hz, 2H), 7.06 (d, J = 5.0 Hz, 2H), <lb/>7.00 (d, J = 10.0 Hz, 2H), 6.64 (d, J = 10.0 Hz, 2H), 6.42 (s, 2H), 4.06 (t, J = 7.50 Hz, 2H), 1.73-1.78 (m, 2H), <lb/>1.43-1.48 (m, 2H), 1.28-1.40 (m, 6H), 0.90 (t, J = 7.5 Hz, 3H). 13 C-NMR (125 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) δ, ppm: <lb/>161.32, 154.63, 147.57, 141.36, 139.43, 130.03, 122.37, 115.38, 115.07, 68.58, 31.57, 29.18, 28.74, 25.88, 22.30, <lb/>14.07. CHN elemental analysis: Calculated for C 20 H 26 N 2 O: C: 77.38%, H: 8.44%, N: 9.02%; Found: <lb/>C: 77.05%, H: 8.47%, N: 8.95%. <lb/>N-(4-nonyloxybenxylidene)benzene-1,4-diamine, 2b: Yield = 1.95 g (82.42%), mp: 135.6-137.7 • C, <lb/>yellow powder. FTIR (cm -1 ): 3459 and 3330 (N-H stretching), 2921 and 2851 (Csp 3 -H stretching), <lb/>1606 (C=N stretching), 1509 (aromatic C=C stretching), 1248 (C-O stretching), 1170 (C-N stretching). <lb/>1 H-NMR (500 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) δ, ppm: 8.47 (s, 1H), 7.79 (d, J = 10.0 Hz, 2H), 7.06 (d, J = 10.0 Hz, 2H), <lb/>7.00 (d, J = 5.0 Hz, 2H), 6.65 (d, J = 10.0 Hz, 2H), 6.43 (s, 2H), 4.05 (t, J = 7.50 Hz, 2H), 1.72-1.77 (m, 2H), <lb/>1.42-1.46 (m, 2H), 1.24-1.37 (m, 10H), 0.88 (t, J = 7.5 Hz, 3H). 13 C-NMR (125 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) δ, ppm: <lb/>161.33, 154.65, 147.52, 141.40, 139.43, 130.03, 122.37, 115.37, 115.09, 68.57, 31.63, 29.28, 29.16, 29.12, 28.94, <lb/>25.90, 22.36, 14.07. CHN elemental analysis: Calculated for C 22 H 30 N 2 O: C: 78.06%, H: 8.93%, N: 8.28%; <lb/>Found: C: 77.83%, H: 8.89%, N: 8.19%. <lb/>N-(4-decyloxybenxylidene)benzene-1,4-diamine, 2c: Yield = 2.11 g (85.63%), mp: 134.3-136.1 • C, <lb/>white powder. FTIR (cm -1 ): 3457 and 3336 (N-H stretching), 2919 and 2851 (Csp 3 -H stretching), <lb/>1603 (C=N stretching), 1509 (aromatic C=C stretching), 1251 (C-O stretching), 1170 (C-N stretching). <lb/>1 H-NMR (500 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) δ, ppm: 8.47 (s, 1H), 7.79 (d, J = 5.0 Hz, 2H), 7.05 (d, J = 10.0 Hz, 2H), <lb/>7.00 (d, J = 5.0 Hz, 2H), 6.64 (d, J = 5.0 Hz, 2H), 6.42 (s, 2H), 4.05 (t, J = 7.50 Hz, 2H), 1.72-1.77 (m, 2H), <lb/>1.42-1.48 (m, 2H), 1.25-1.38 (m, 12H), 0.88 (t, J = 5.0 Hz, 3H). 13 C-NMR (125 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) δ, ppm: <lb/>161.32, 154.61, 147.55, 141.37, 139.43, 130.02, 122.36, 115.38, 115.06, 68.58, 31.64, 29.31, 29.27, 29.16, 29.10, <lb/>28.98, 25.90, 22.35, 14.07. CHN elemental analysis: Calculated for C 23 H 32 N 2 O: C: 78.36%, H: 9.15%, <lb/>N: 7.95%; Found: C: 78.13%, H: 9.19%, N: 7.99%. <lb/>N-(4-dodecyloxybenxylidene)benzene-1,4-diamine, 2d: Yield = 2.15 g (80.83%), mp: 128.5-133.3 • C, <lb/>yellow powder. FTIR (cm -1 ): 3462 and 3333 (N-H stretching), 2919 and 2851 (Csp 3 -H stretching), <lb/>1606 (C=N stretching), 1509 (aromatic C=C stretching), 1248 (C-O stretching), 1170 (C-N stretching). <lb/>1 H-NMR (500 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) δ, ppm: 8.47 (s, 1H), 7.79 (d, J = 5.0 Hz, 2H), 7.05 (d, J = 10.0 Hz, 2H), <lb/>7.00 (d, J = 10.0 Hz, 2H), 6.64 (d, J = 5.0 Hz, 2H), 6.43 (s, 2H), 4.06 (t, J = 7.50 Hz, 2H), 1.72-1.78 (m, 2H), <lb/>1.42-1.48 (m, 2H), 1.25-1.39 (m, 16H), 0.88 (t, J = 7.5 Hz, 3H). 13 C-NMR (125 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) δ, ppm: <lb/>161.32, 154.62, 147.55, 141.36, 139.26, 130.02, 122.37, 115.38, 115.06, 68.57, 31.64, 29.35, 29.33, 29.31, 29.29, <lb/>29.15, 29.08, 28.99, 25.88, 22.35, 14.07. CHN elemental analysis: Calculated for C 25 H 36 N 2 O: C: 78.90%, <lb/>H: 9.53%, N: 7.36%; Found: C: 78.11%, H: 9.51%, N: 7.43%. <lb/>N-(4-tetradecyloxybenxylidene)benzene-1,4-diamine, 2e: Yield = 2.32 g (81.23%), mp: 126.6-128.8 • C, <lb/>yellow powder. FTIR (cm -1 ): 3459 and 3320 (N-H stretching), 2919 and 2849 (Csp 3 -H stretching), <lb/>1609 (C=N stretching), 1512 (aromatic C=C stretching), 1254 (C-O stretching), 1170 (C-N stretching). <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Molecules 2020, 25, 2122 <lb/></note>

			<page>20 of 26 <lb/></page>

			<body>1 H-NMR (500 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) δ, ppm: 8.47 (s, 1H), 7.77 (d, J = 10.0 Hz, 2H), 7.06 (d, J = 10.0 Hz, 2H), <lb/>6.99 (d, J = 10.0 Hz, 2H), 6.58 (d, J = 10.0 Hz, 2H), 5.10 (s, 2H), 4.00 (t, J = 7.50 Hz, 2H), 1.68-1.73 (m, 2H), <lb/>1.37-1.42 (m, 2H), 1.18-1.33 (m, 20H), 0.83 (t, J = 7.5 Hz, 3H). 13 C-NMR (125 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) δ, ppm: <lb/>161.32, 154.62, 147.55, 141.36, 139.24, 130.02, 122.36, 115.38, 115.06, 68.57, 31.64, 29.36, 29.35, 29.34, 29.33, <lb/>29.30, 29.29, 29.15, 29.08, 28.99, 25.88, 22.35, 14.07. CHN elemental analysis: Calculated for C 27 H 40 N 2 O: <lb/>C: 79.36%, H: 9.87%, N: 6.86%; Found: C: 78.56%, H: 9.80%, N: 6.79%. <lb/>N-(4-hydroxybenxylidene)benzene-1,4-diamine, 2f: Yield = 2.23 g (75.08%), mp: 186.2-188.4 • C, <lb/>yellow powder. FTIR (cm -1 ): 3100-3350 and 3285 (N-H stretching), 3198 (O-H stretching), <lb/>1603 (C=N stretching), 1504 (aromatic C=C stretching), 1221 (C-O stretching), 1162 (C-N stretching). <lb/>1 H-NMR (500 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) δ, ppm: 10.00 (s, 1H), 8.42 (s, 1H), 7.69 (d, J = 10.0 Hz, 2H), 7.04 (d, <lb/>J = 5.0 Hz, 2H), 6.84 (d, J = 10.0 Hz, 2H), 6.58 (d, J = 10.0 2H), 5.08 (s, 2H). 13 C-NMR (125 MHz, <lb/>DMSO-d 6 ) δ, ppm: 160.55, 157.38, 156.12, 143.68, 130.63, 128.37, 122.59, 116.11, 116.03. CHN elemental <lb/>analysis: Calculated for C 13 H 12 N 2 O: C: 73.56%, H: 5.70%, N: 13.20%; Found: C: 74.00%, H: 5.75%, <lb/>N: 13.09%. <lb/>N-(4-carboxybenxylidene)benzene-1,4-diamine, 2g: Yield = 2.57 g (76.49%), mp: 178.3-180.4 • C, <lb/>yellow powder. FTIR (cm -1 ): 3150-3350 and 3309 (N-H stretching), 3210 (O-H stretching), <lb/>1698 (C=O stretching), 1593 (C=N stretching), 1536 (aromatic C=C stretching), 1385 (C-O stretching), <lb/>1149 (C-N stretching). 1 H-NMR (500 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) δ, ppm: 8.67 (s, 1H), 8.02 (d, J = 5.0 Hz, 2H), <lb/>7.95 (d, J = 10.0 Hz, 2H), 7.19 (d, J = 10.0 Hz, 2H), 6.62 (d, J = 5.0 Hz, 2H). 13 C-NMR (125 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) <lb/>δ, ppm: 167.54, 153.36, 148.96, 141.05, 139.42, 130.12, 129.52, 128.32, 123.33, 114.61. CHN elemental <lb/>analysis: Calculated for C 14 H 12 N 2 O 2 : C: 69.99%, H: 5.03%, N: 11.66%; Found: C: 69.36%, H: 5.06%, <lb/>N: 11.52%. <lb/>N-(4-chlorobenxylidene)benzene-1,4-diamine, 2h: Yield = 2.78 g (86.07%), mp: 196.7-198.3 • C, <lb/>yellow powder. FTIR (cm -1 ): 3328 and 3217 (N-H stretching), 1617 (C=N stretching), 1504 (aromatic C=C <lb/>stretching), 1168 (C-N stretching), 790 (C-Cl bending). 1 H-NMR (500 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) δ, ppm: 8.59 (s, <lb/>1H), 7.87 (d, J = 5.0 Hz, 2H), 7.52 (d, J = 5.0 Hz, 2H), 7.15 (d, J = 5.0 Hz, 2H), 6.61 (d, J = 10.0 Hz, 2H), <lb/>5.26 (s, 2H). 13 C-NMR (125 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) δ, ppm: 153.20, 148.68, 139.54, 136.20, 135.23, 129.94, 129.25, <lb/>123.11, 114.59. CHN elemental analysis: Calculated for C 13 H 11 N 2 : C: 67.68%, H: 4.81%, N: 12.14%; <lb/>Found: C: 67.61%, H: 4.82%, N: 12.05%. <lb/>N-(4-nitrobenxylidene)benzene-1,4-diamine, 2i: Yield = 4.34 g (85.75%), mp: 172.1-174.5 • C, red powder. <lb/>FTIR (cm -1 ): 3484 and 3384 (N-H stretching), 1625 (C=N stretching), 1504 (aromatic C=C stretching), <lb/>1160 (C-N stretching). 1 H-NMR (500 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) δ, ppm: 8.76 (s, 1H), 8.31 (d, J = 5.0 Hz, 2H), <lb/>8.09 (d, J = 5.0 Hz, 2H), 7.25 (d, J = 5.0 Hz, 2H), 6.63 (d, J = 5.0 Hz, 2H), 5.44 (s, 2H). 13 C-NMR (125 MHz, <lb/>DMSO-d 6 ) δ, ppm: 151.66, 149.62, 148.40, 143.19, 138.85, 129.09, 124.43, 123.80, 114.50. CHN elemental <lb/>analysis: Calculated for C 13 H 11 N 3 O 2 : C: 64.72%, H: 4.60%, N: 17.42%; Found: C: 64.62%, H: 4.62%, <lb/>N: 17.21%. <lb/>3.3.3. Synthesis of Hexakis(4-Formlyphenoxy)cyclotriphosphazene, 3 <lb/>4-Hydroxybenzaldehyde (9.77 g, 0.08 mol) and triethylamine (10.12 g, 0.1 mol) were dissolved <lb/>in 150 mL acetone and the mixture was cooled to 0 • C in an ice bath. The mixture was <lb/>stirred for 30 min. Then, a solution of hexachlorocyclotriphosphazene (3.48 g, 0.01 mol) in <lb/>50 mL acetone was added dropwise to the mixture. A white salt began to precipitate within <lb/>few minutes. After 2 h at 0 • C, the reaction was allowed to attain at room temperature <lb/>and was continued to stir for an additional 94 h. The reaction was monitored using TLC. <lb/>Upon completion, the mixture was poured into 250 mL of cold water and left overnight in the <lb/>fridge. The precipitate formed was then filtered, washed with water, and dried. The precipitate <lb/>was recrystallised from methanol. Yield: 8.11 g (94.19%), mp: 200.8-204.2 • C, white powder. <lb/>FTIR (cm -1 ): 2730 (H-C=O), 1699 (C=O stretching), 1595 (C=C stretching), 1205 (C-O stretching), <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Molecules 2020, 25, 2122 <lb/></note>

			<page>21 of 26 <lb/></page>

			<body>1151 (P=N stretching), 944 (P-O-C stretching). 1 H-NMR (500 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) δ, ppm: 9.90 (s, <lb/>1H), 7.78 (d, J = 10.0 Hz, 2H), 7.16 (d, J = 10.0 Hz, 2H). 13 C-NMR (125 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) δ, ppm: 191.69, <lb/>153.59, 133.55, 131.46, 121.03. 31 P-NMR (500 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) δ, ppm: 7.60 (s, 1P). CHN elemental <lb/>analysis: Calculated for C 42 H 30 N 3 O 12 P 3 : C: 58.55%, H: 3.51%, N: 4.88%; Found: C: 58.28%, H: 3.48%, <lb/>N: 4.83%. <lb/>3.3.4. Synthesis of Hexakis{4-((E)-((4-(((E)-4-substituted-benzylidene)amino)phenyl)imino)methyl) <lb/>phenoxy}triazaphosphazene, 4a-i <lb/>Hexakis{4-((E)-((4-(((E)-4-heptyloxy-benzylidene)amino)phenyl)imino)methyl)phenoxy} <lb/>triazaphosphazene, 4a: Intermediate 3 (0.50 g, 0.58 mmol) and intermediate 2a (1.26 g, 4.07 mmol) <lb/>were mixed in 25 mL methanol in a 100 mL round bottom flask. A few drops of glacial acetic acid was <lb/>added to the mixture which was stirred and refluxed for 24 h. The reaction progress was monitored by <lb/>TLC. Upon completion, the mixture was cooled in an ice bath. The precipitate formed was filtered, <lb/>washed with cold methanol, and dried. The crude was recrystallised from ethanol. The same method <lb/>was used to synthesize 4b-i. Yield: 1.12 g (73.68%), mp: 130.5-133.1 • C, yellow powder. FTIR (cm -1 ): <lb/>2924 and 2857 (Csp 3 -H stretching), 1613 (C=N stretching), 1509 (C=C stretching), 1248 (C-O stretching), <lb/>1192 (P=N stretching), 1168 (C-N stretching), 983 (P-O-C stretching). 1 H-NMR (500 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) <lb/>δ, ppm: 8.66 (s, 1H) 8.55 (s, 1H), 7.95 (d, J = 10.0 Hz, 2H), 7.87 (d, J = 10.0 Hz, 2H), 7.55 (d, J = 5.0 Hz, <lb/>2H), 7.33 (d, J = 10.0 Hz, 2H), 7.28 (d, J = 15.0 Hz, 2H), 7.04 (d, J = 5.0 Hz, 2H), 4.07 (t, J = 5.0 Hz, 2H), <lb/>1.73-1.79 (m, 2H), 1.42-1.48 (m, 2H), 1.27-1.38 (m, 6H), 0.90 (t, J = 7.5 Hz, 3H). 13 C-NMR (125 MHz, <lb/>DMSO-d 6 ) δ, ppm: 162.09, 162.02, 159.38, 158.83, 150.63, 149.14, 136.49, 135.76, 130.81, 130.53, 129.28, <lb/>122.32, 122.13, 115.46, 68.64, 31.58, 29.16, 28.76, 25.88, 22.31, 14.06. 31 P-NMR (500 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) δ, <lb/>ppm: 8.20 (s, 1P). CHN elemental analysis: Calculated for C 162 H 174 N 15 O 12 P 3 : C: 74.37%, H: 6.70%, <lb/>N: 8.03%; Found: C: 74.29%, H: 6.68%, N: 7.95%. <lb/>Hexakis{4-((E)-((4-(((E)-4-nonyloxy-benzylidene)amino)phenyl)imino)methyl)phenoxy} <lb/>triazaphosphazene, 4b: Yield: 1.13 g (70.19%), mp: 128.1-130.5 • C, yellow powder. FTIR (cm -1 ): <lb/>2919 and 2851 (Csp 3 -H stretching), 1616 (C=N stretching), 1509 (C=C stretching), 1254 (C-O stretching), <lb/>1195 (P=N stretching), 1168 (C-N stretching), 981 (P-O-C stretching). 1 H-NMR (500 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) <lb/>δ, ppm: 8.66 (s, 1H) 8.55 (s, 1H), 7.95 (d, J = 10.0 Hz, 2H), 7.87 (d, J = 5.0 Hz, 2H), 7.55 (d, J = 10.0 Hz, <lb/>2H), 7.33 (d, J = 10.0 Hz, 2H), 7.28 (d, J = 15.0 Hz, 2H), 7.04 (d, J = 5.0 Hz, 2H), 4.07 (t, J = 5.0 Hz, 2H), <lb/>1.73-1.78 (m, 2H), 1.42-1.48 (m, 2H), 1.26-1.38 (m, 10H), 0.88 (t, J = 5.0 Hz, 3H). 13 C-NMR (125 MHz, <lb/>DMSO-d 6 ) δ, ppm: 162.09, 162.02, 159.06, 158.48, 150.63, 149.14, 136.48, 135.77, 130.81, 130.54, 129.29, <lb/>122.32, 122.09, 115.46, 68.63, 31.64, 29.29, 29.14, 28.94, 25.90, 22.36, 14.08. 31 P-NMR (500 MHz, <lb/>DMSO-d 6 ) δ, ppm: 8.18 (s, 1P). CHN elemental analysis: Calculated for C 174 H 198 N 15 O 12 P 3 : C: 75.05%, <lb/>H: 7.17%, N: 7.55%; Found: C: 74.88%, H: 7.10%, N: 7.48%. <lb/>Hexakis{4-((E)-((4-(((E)-4-decyloxy-benzylidene)amino)phenyl)imino)methyl)phenoxy} <lb/>triazaphosphazene, 4c: Yield = 1.15 g (69.28%), mp: 125.7-127.4 • C, yellow powder. FTIR (cm -1 ): <lb/>2919 and 2851 (Csp 3 -H stretching), 1613 (C=N stretching), 1509 (C=C stretching), 1251 (C-O stretching), <lb/>1195 (P=N stretching), 1168 (C-N stretching), 983 (P-O-C stretching). 1 H-NMR (500 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) <lb/>δ, ppm: 8.66 (s, 1H) 8.55 (s, 1H), 7.96 (d, J = 5.0 Hz, 2H), 7.87 (d, J = 5.0 Hz, 2H), 7.55 (d, J = 10.0 Hz, <lb/>2H), 7.33 (d, J = 10.0 Hz, 2H), 7.28 (d, J = 15.0 Hz, 2H), 7.04 (d, J = 10.0 Hz, 2H), 4.07 (t, J = 7.5 Hz, 2H), <lb/>1.73-1.79 (m, 2H), 1.43-1.48 (m, 2H), 1.26-1.38 (m, 12H), 0.88 (t, J = 7.5 Hz, 3H). 13 C-NMR (125 MHz, <lb/>DMSO-d 6 ) δ, ppm: 162.09, 162.02, 159.06, 158.48, 150.63, 149.15, 136.48, 135.76, 130.75, 130.54, 129.29, <lb/>122.33, 122.09, 115.46, 68.63, 31.64, 29.29, 29.15, 29.13, 28.94, 25.90, 22.36, 14.08. 31 P-NMR (500 MHz, <lb/>DMSO-d 6 ) δ, ppm: 8.20 (s, 1P). CHN elemental analysis: Calculated for C 180 H 210 N 15 O 12 P 3 : C: 75.37%, <lb/>H: 7.38%, N: 7.32%; Found: C: 75.12%, H: 7.31%, N: 7.27%. <lb/>Hexakis{4-((E)-((4-(((E)-4-dodecyloxy-benzylidene)amino)phenyl)imino)methyl)phenoxy} <lb/>triazaphosphazene, 4d: Yield = 1.23 g (69.89%), mp: 121.2-123.7 • C, yellow powder. FTIR (cm -1 ): <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Molecules 2020, 25, 2122 <lb/></note>

			<page>22 of 26 <lb/></page>

			<body>2919 and 2849 (Csp 3 -H stretching), 1616 (C=N stretching), 1509 (C=C stretching), 1248 (C-O stretching), <lb/>1192 (P=N stretching), 1168 (C-N stretching), 980 (P-O-C stretching). 1 H-NMR (500 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) <lb/>δ, ppm: 8.67 (s, 1H) 8.56 (s, 1H), 7.96 (d, J = 5.0 Hz, 2H), 7.87 (d, J = 10.0 Hz, 2H), 7.56 (d, J = 10.0 Hz, <lb/>2H), 7.34 (d, J = 15.0 Hz, 2H), 7.28 (d, J = 10.0 Hz, 2H), 7.05 (d, J = 5.0 Hz, 2H), 4.08 (t, J = 7.5 Hz, 2H), <lb/>1.73-1.79 (m, 2H), 1.43-1.49 (m, 2H), 1.26-1.38 (m, 16H), 0.88 (t, J = 5.0 Hz, 3H). 13 C-NMR (125 MHz, <lb/>DMSO-d 6 ) δ, ppm: 162.09, 162.03, 159.48, 158.56, 149.82, 149.15, 136.57, 135.76, 130.83, 130.56, <lb/>129.31, 122.34, 122.15, 115.49, 68.64, 31.64, 29.31, 29.26, 29.13, 29.11, 29.09, 28.97, 25.88, 22.35, 14.08. <lb/>31 P-NMR (500 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) δ, ppm: 8.19 (s, 1P). CHN elemental analysis: Calculated for <lb/>C 192 H 234 N 15 O 12 P 3 : C: 75.93%, H: 7.77%, N: 6.92%; Found: C: 75.77%, H: 7.73%, N: 6.88%. <lb/>Hexakis{4-((E)-((4-(((E)-4-tetradecyloxy-benzylidene)amino)phenyl)imino)methyl)phenoxy} <lb/>triazaphosphazene, 4e: Yield = 1.36 g (74.73%), mp: 118.8-120.5 • C, yellow powder. FTIR (cm -1 ): <lb/>2916 and 2849 (Csp 3 -H stretching), 1616 (C=N stretching), 1512 (C=C stretching), 1251 (C-O stretching), <lb/>1195 (P=N stretching), 1170 (C-N stretching), 973 (P-O-C stretching). 1 H-NMR (500 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) <lb/>δ, ppm: 8.66 (s, 1H) 8.54 (s, 1H), 7.95 (d, J = 10.0 Hz, 2H), 7.87 (d, J = 10.0 Hz, 2H), 7.54 (d, J = 10.0 Hz, <lb/>2H), 7.33 (d, J = 5.0 Hz, 2H), 7.27 (d, J = 10.0 Hz, 2H), 7.03 (d, J = 10.0 Hz, 2H), 4.08 (t, J = 7.5 Hz, 2H), <lb/>1.73-1.79 (m, 2H), 1.43-1.49 (m, 2H), 1.23-1.40 (m, 16H), 0.88 (t, J = 10.0 Hz, 3H). 13 C-NMR (125 MHz, <lb/>DMSO-d 6 ) δ, ppm: 162.18, 162.14, 159.33, 158.38, 150.70, 159.04, 136.54, 135.86, 130.74, 130.54, 129.28, <lb/>122.31, 122.07, 115.56, 68.77, 31.68, 29.38, 29.34, 29.20, 29.18, 29.14, 29.12, 29.02, 29.00, 25.92, 22.34, <lb/>14.01. 31 P-NMR (500 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) δ, ppm: 8.21 (s, 1P). CHN elemental analysis: Calculated for <lb/>C 204 H 258 N 15 O 12 P 3 : C: 76.44%, H: 8.11%, N: 6.55%; Found: C: 76.32%, H: 8.07%, N: 6.49%. <lb/>Hexakis{4-((E)-((4-(((E)-4-hydroxy-benzylidene)amino)phenyl)imino)methyl)phenoxy} <lb/>triazaphosphazene, 4f: Yield = 1.21 g (73.33%), mp: 212.5-215.5 • C, light brown powder. <lb/>FTIR (cm -1 ): 3221 (OH stretching), 1617 (C=N stretching), 1493 (C=C stretching), 1264 (C-O stretching), <lb/>1189 (P=N stretching), 1160 (C-N stretching), 981 (P-O-C stretching). 1 H-NMR (500 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) <lb/>δ, ppm: 10.11 (s, 1H), 8.71 (s, 1H) 8.51 (s, 1H), 7.97 (d, J = 10.0 Hz, 2H), 7.78 (d, J = 10.0 Hz, 2H), <lb/>7.61 (d, J = 5.0 Hz, 2H), 7.37 (d, J = 15.0 Hz, 2H), 7.28 (d, J = 20.0 Hz, 2H), 6.88 (d, J = 10.0 Hz, 2H). <lb/>13 C-NMR (125 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) δ, ppm: 156.64, 156.50, 155.77, 155.64, 142.33, 142.19, 135.42, 135.32, <lb/>129.90, 129.76, 128.79, 122.72, 122.59, 115.71. 31 P-NMR (500 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) δ, ppm: 8.24 (s, 1P). <lb/>CHN elemental analysis: Calculated for C 120 H 90 N 15 O 12 P 3 : C: 71.10%, H: 4.48%, N: 10.37%; Found: <lb/>C: 70.76%, H: 4.44%, N: 10.28%. <lb/>Hexakis{4-((E)-((4-(((E)-4-carboxy-benzylidene)amino)phenyl)imino)methyl)phenoxy} <lb/>triazaphosphazene, 4g: Yield = 1.23 g (69.10%), mp: 195.2-197.1 • C, yellow powder. FTIR (cm -1 ): <lb/>3219 (OH stretching), 1673 (C=O stretching), 1619 (C=N stretching), 977 (C=C stretching), <lb/>1291 (C-O stretching), 1195 (P=N stretching), 1173 (C-N stretching), 1012 (P-O-C stretching). <lb/>1 H-NMR (500 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) δ, ppm: 10.14 (s, 1H), 8.69 (s, 1H) 8.51 (s, 1H), 7.90 (d, J = 5.0 Hz, 2H), <lb/>7.78 (d, J = 10.0 Hz, 2H), 7.74 (d, J = 10.0 Hz, 2H), 7.37 (d, J = 15.0 Hz, 2H), 7.28 (d, J = 20.0 Hz, 2H), <lb/>6.88 (d, J = 10.0 Hz, 2H). 13 C-NMR (125 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) δ, ppm: 164.41, 164.40, 157.70, 155.10, 148.79, <lb/>142.55, 142.11, 140.04, 129.51, 126.59, 124.36, 123.57, 116.31, 116.22. 31 P-NMR (500 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) δ, <lb/>ppm: 8.23 (s, 1P). CHN elemental analysis: Calculated for C 126 H 90 N 15 O 18 P 3 : C: 68.94%, H: 4.13%, <lb/>N: 9.57%; Found: C: 68.77%, H: 4.09%, N: 9.48%. <lb/>Hexakis{4-((E)-((4-(((E)-4-chloro-benzylidene)amino)phenyl)imino)methyl)phenoxy} <lb/>triazaphosphazene, 4h: Yield = 1.33 g (76.44%), mp: 201.1-204.4 • C, yellow powder. FTIR (cm -1 ): <lb/>1618 (C=N stretching), 1515 (C=C stretching), 1273 (C-O stretching), 1192 (P=N stretching), <lb/>1165 (C-N stretching), 983 (P-O-C stretching), 823 (C-Cl bending). 1 H-NMR (500 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) δ, <lb/>ppm: 8.80 (s, 1H) 8.64 (s, 1H), 8.30 (d, J = 10.0 Hz, 2H), 8.17 (d, J = 10.0 Hz, 2H), 7.93 (d, J = 10.0 Hz, <lb/>2H), 7.53 (d, J = 10.0 Hz, 2H), 7.41 (d, J = 15.0 Hz, 2H), 7.34 (d, J = 15.0 Hz, 2H). 13 C-NMR (125 MHz, <lb/>DMSO-d 6 ) δ, ppm: 159.28, 158.94, 158.53, 158.17, 142.22, 142.15, 136.70, 135.52, 130.64, 129.98, 129.32, <lb/>124.22, 122.67, 122.42. 31 P-NMR (500 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) δ, ppm: 8.25 (s, 1P). CHN elemental analysis: <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Molecules 2020, 25, 2122 <lb/></note>

			<page>23 of 26 <lb/></page>

			<body>Calculated for C 120 H 84 Cl 6 N 15 O 6 P 3 : C: 67.42%, H: 3.96%, N: 9.83%; Found: C: 67.33%, H: 3.92%, <lb/>N: 9.78%. <lb/>Hexakis{4-((E)-((4-(((E)-4-nitro-benzylidene)amino)phenyl)imino)methyl)phenoxy} <lb/>triazaphosphazene, 4i: Yield = 3.06 g (79.90%), mp: 183.7-186.7 • C, orange powder. FTIR (cm -1 ): <lb/>1618 (C=N stretching), 1520 (C=C stretching), 1273 (C-O stretching), 1195 (P=N stretching), <lb/>1165 (C-N stretching), 981 (P-O-C stretching). 1 H-NMR (500 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) δ, ppm: 8.85 (s, 1H) <lb/>8.68 (s, 1H), 8.34 (d, J = 5.0 Hz, 2H), 8.21 (d, J = 5.0 Hz, 2H), 7.97 (d, J = 5.0 Hz, 2H), 7.57 (d, J = 5.0 Hz, <lb/>2H), 7.44 (d, J = 15.0 Hz, 2H), 7.37 (d, J = 15.0 Hz, 2H). 13 C-NMR (125 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) δ, ppm: <lb/>166.30, 157.70, 155.10, 150.40, 148.78, 142.55, 142.09, 136.98, 131.11, 129.51, 124.36, 124.09, 123.57, <lb/>116.30. 31 P-NMR (500 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) δ, ppm: 8.20 (s, 1P). CHN elemental analysis: Calculated for <lb/>C 120 H 84 N 21 O 18 P 3 : C: 65.48%, H: 3.85%, N: 13.36%; Found: C: 65.37%, H: 3.88%, N: 13.29%. <lb/>3.3.5. Synthesis of Hexakis{4-((E)-((4-(((E)-4-amino-benzylidene)amino)phenyl)imino)methyl)phenoxy} <lb/>triazaphosphazene, 4j <lb/>Compound 4i (2.50 g, 1.14 mmol) was dissolved in 20 mL methanol and a solution of <lb/>sodium sulphide hydrate, Na 2 S.9H 2 0 (0.89 g, 0.01 mol) in 20 mL ethanol was mixed in <lb/>100 mL round bottom flask. The mixture was stirred and refluxed for 12 h. The reaction <lb/>was monitored using TLC. Upon completion, the mixture was cooled in an ice bath and <lb/>the precipitate formed was filtered, washed with cold ethanol, and dried overnight to give <lb/>a red precipitate. Yield: 1.14 g (49.57%), mp: 198.2-200.8 • C, red powder. FTIR (cm -1 ): <lb/>3478 and 3312 (N-H stretching), 1617 (C=N stretching), 1493 (C=C stretching), 1273 (C-O stretching), <lb/>1186 (P=N stretching), 1162 (C-N stretching), 1002 (P-O-C stretching). 1 H-NMR (500 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) <lb/>δ, ppm: 8.67 (s, 1H) 8.50 (s, 1H), 7.89 (d, J = 10.0 Hz, 2H), 7.78 (d, J = 10.0 Hz, 2H), 7.72 (d, J = 10.0 Hz, <lb/>2H), 7.34 (d, J = 15.0 Hz, 2H), 7.27 (d, J = 15.0 Hz, 2H), 6.90 (d, J = 10.0 Hz, 2H). 13 C-NMR (125 MHz, <lb/>DMSO-d 6 ) δ, ppm: 160.55, 158.83, 158.68, 149.43, 149.27, 135.46, 131.81, 130.43, 130.34, 127.89, 124.84, <lb/>121.94, 121.57, 115.70. 31 P-NMR (500 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) δ, ppm: 8.22 (s, 1P). CHN elemental analysis: <lb/>Calculated for C 120 H 96 N 21 O 6 P 3 : C: 71.31%, H: 4.79%, N: 14.55%; Found: C: 70.99%, H: 4.77%, N: 14.42%. <lb/>4. Conclusions <lb/>Intermediates 1a-e, 2a-i, and 3, and final compounds 4a-j, with two Schiff base linking units were <lb/>successfully synthesized and characterized. All the intermediates and compound 4j were found to be <lb/>non-mesogenic, whereas other final compounds 4a-i were mesogenic molecules. Compound 4a showed <lb/>smectic A and nematic phases while compounds 4b-d exhibited only smectic A in heating and cooling <lb/>cycles. In addition, compound 4e exhibited smectic C and smectic A phases in both cycles. Meanwhile, <lb/>all the other compounds with a small substituent such as hydroxy, carboxy, chloro, and nitro groups at <lb/>the terminal end were found to exhibit a nematic phase. Further study on the fire-retardant properties <lb/>of the hexasubstituted cyclotriphosphazene compounds was done using LOI testing. Interestingly, <lb/>all the final compounds showed LOI values higher compared to that of polyester resin incorporated <lb/>with HCCP. The highest LOI value obtained was 28.37%, which belonged to compound 4i with the <lb/>nitro terminal group. The presence of the NO 2 group as an electron-withdrawing side arm of the <lb/>cyclotriphosphazene compound reduces the exothermicity of the materials, which enhanced the <lb/>fire-retardant property of the polyester resin. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Molecules 2020, 25, 2122 <lb/></note>

			<page>24 of 26 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">Supplementary Materials: The following are available online, Figure S1-S9: DSC thermogram of compounds <lb/>4a-i, respectively. <lb/>Author Contributions: Conceptualization, Z.J. and M.K.; methodology, Z.J.; validation, Z.J., M.K. and T.G.-S.; <lb/>formal analysis, Z.J.; investigation, Z.J.; resources, M.K. and T.G.-S.; data curation, Z.J.; writing-original draft <lb/>preparation, Z.J.; writing-review and editing, M.K.; visualization, Z.J.; supervision, M.K. and T.G.-S.; <lb/>funding acquisition, Z.J. and M.K. All authors have read and agreed to the published version of the manuscript. <lb/></div>

			<div type="funding">Funding: This research was funded by Universiti Malaysia Sabah, grant number SGA0037-2019; Universiti Sains <lb/>Malaysia, grant number 1001/PKIMIA/811332 and The APC was funded by Universiti Malaysia Sabah. <lb/></div>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgments: The authors would like to thank the Universiti Malaysia Sabah (UMS) and Universiti Sains <lb/>Malaysia (USM) for the lab facilities. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Conflicts of Interest: The authors declare no conflict of interest. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>1. <lb/>Allcock, H.R. Recent advances in phosphazene (phosphonitrilic) chemistry. Chem. Rev. 1972, 72, 315-356. <lb/>[CrossRef] <lb/>2. <lb/>Joaquín, B.; Manuel, B.; Josefina, J.; Antonio, L.; Pilar, M.M.; Luis, O.; José, L.S.; Irene, Z. Columnar mesomorphic <lb/>organisations in cyclotriphosphazene. J. Am. Chem. Soc. 2005, 127, 8994-9002. <lb/>3. <lb/>He, Q.; Dai, H.; Tan, X.; Cheng, X.; Liu, F.; Tschierske, C. Synthesis and characterisation of room temperature <lb/>columnar mesogens of cyclotriphosphazene with Schiff base unit. J. Mater. Chem. C 2013, 43, 7148-7154. <lb/>[CrossRef] <lb/>4. <lb/>Chandrasekhar, S. Liquid Crystals, 2nd ed.; Cambridge University Press: Cambridge, UK, 1992; <lb/>ISBN 0-521-41747-3. <lb/>5. <lb/>Allcock, H.R. Phosphorus-Nitrogen Compounds; Academic Press: New York, NY, USA, 1972. <lb/>6. <lb/>Moriya, K.; Suzuki, T.; Kawanishi, Y.; Masuda, T.; Mizusaki, H.; Nakagawa, S.; Ikematsu, H.; Mizuno, K.; <lb/>Yano, S.; Kajiwara, M. Liquid-crystalline phase transition in organophosphazene. Appl. Organomet. Chem. <lb/>1998, 12, 771-779. [CrossRef] <lb/>7. <lb/>Zhu, L.; Zhu, Y.; Pan, Y.; Huang, Y.W.; Huang, X.B.; Tang, X.Z. Fully cross-linked poly[-cyclotriphosphazene-<lb/>co-(4, 40-sulfonyldiphenol)] microspheres via precipitation polymerisation and their superior thermal <lb/>properties. Macromol. React. Eng. 2007, 1, 45-52. [CrossRef] <lb/>8. <lb/>Lejeune, N.; Dez, I.; Jaffres, P.A.; Lohier, J.F.; Madec, P.J.; Santos, J.S.O. Synthesis, crystal structure and thermal <lb/>properties of phosphorylated cyclotriphosphazenes. Eur. J. Inorg. Chem. 2008, 1, 138-143. [CrossRef] <lb/>9. <lb/>Allcock, H.R. The crucial role of inorganic ring chemistry in the development of new polymers. <lb/>Phosphorus Sulfur Silicon Relat. Elem. 2004, 179, 661-671. [CrossRef] <lb/>10. Barberá, J.; Bardají, M.; Jiménez, J.; Laguna, A.; Martínez, M.P.; Oriol, L.; Serrano, J.L.; Zaragozano, I. <lb/>Columnar mesomorphic organizations in cyclotriphosphazenes. J. Am. Chem. Soc. 2005, 127, 8994-9002. <lb/>[CrossRef] <lb/>11. Heal, H.G. The Inorganic Heterocyclic Chemistry of Sulphur, Nitrogen and Phosphorus; Academic Press: New York, <lb/>NY, USA, 1980; p. 214. <lb/>12. Allen, C.W. The Chemistry of Inorganic Homo-and Heterocycles; Haiduc, I., Sowerby, D.B., Eds.; Academic Press: <lb/>New York, NY, USA, 1987; p. 2. <lb/>13. Allen, C.W. Organophosphorus Chemistry; Hutchinson, D.W., Walker, B.J., Eds.; Royal Society of Chemistry: <lb/>London, UK, 1990; Volume 21, p. 368. <lb/>14. Allcock, H.R. Chemistry and Applications of Polyphosphazenes; Wiley Interscience: New York, NY, USA, 2003. <lb/>15. Chen-Yang, Y.W.; Lee, H.F.; Yuan, C.Y. A Flame-retardant phosphate and cyclotriphosphazene containing <lb/>epoxy resin: Synthesis and properties. J. Polym. Sci. A Polym. Chem. 2000, 38, 972-981. [CrossRef] <lb/>16. Shin, Y.J.; Ham, Y.R.; Kim, S.H.; Lee, D.H.; Kim, S.B.; Park, C.S.; Yoo, Y.M.; Kim, J.G.; Kwon, S.H.; Shin, J.S. <lb/>Application of cyclotriphosphazene derivatives as flame retardants for ABS. J. Ind. Eng. Chem. 2010, 16, <lb/>364-367. [CrossRef] <lb/>17. Salmeia, K.A.; Gaan, S.; Malucelli, G. Recent advances for flame retardancy of textiles based on phosphorus <lb/>chemistry. Polymers 2016, 8, 319. [CrossRef] [PubMed] <lb/>18. Wendels, S.; Chavez, T.; Bonnet, M.; Salmeia, K.A.; Gaan, S. Recent development in organophosphorus flame <lb/>retardants containing P-C bond and their applications. Materials 2017, 10, 784. [CrossRef] [PubMed] <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Molecules 2020, 25, 2122 <lb/></note>

			<page>25 of 26 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>19. Senthil, S.; Kannan, P. Ferrocene-based organophosphorus liquid-crystalline polymers: Synthesis and <lb/>characterization. J. Polym. Sci. A Polym. Chem. 2001, 39, 2396-2403. [CrossRef] <lb/>20. Kim, C.; Allcock, H.R. A liquid crystalline poly (organophosphazene). Macromolecules 1987, 20, 1726-1727. <lb/>[CrossRef] <lb/>21. Allcock, H.R.; Kim, C. Liquid crystalline phosphazenes. High polymeric and cyclic trimeric systems with <lb/>aromatic azo side groups. Macromolecules 1989, 22, 2596-2602. [CrossRef] <lb/>22. Singh, S. Phase transitions in liquid crystals. Phys. Rep. 2000, 324, 107-269. [CrossRef] <lb/>23. Iqbal, D.; Samiullah, M.S. Photo-responsive shape-memory and shape-changing liquid-crystal polymer <lb/>networks. Materials 2013, 6, 116-142. [CrossRef] <lb/>24. Balakrishnan, V.; Phan, H.P.; Dinh, T.; Dao, D.V.; Nguyen, N.T. Thermal flow sensors for harsh environments. <lb/>Sensors 2017, 17, 2061. [CrossRef] <lb/>25. Selvarasu, C.; Kannan, O. Effect of azo and ester linkages on rod shapd Schiff base liquid crystals and their <lb/>photophysical investigations. J. Mol. Struct. 2016, 1125, 234-240. [CrossRef] <lb/>26. El-Wahab, H.S. Synthesis and characterisation of the flame retardant properties and corrosion resistance <lb/>of Schiff&apos;s base compounds incorporated into organic coating. Pigment. Resin Technol. 2015, 44, 101-108. <lb/>[CrossRef] <lb/>27. Gouri, M.E.; Bachiri, A.E.; Hegazi, S.E.; Ziraoui, R.; Rafik, M.; Harfi, A.E. Thermal degradation of a reactive <lb/>flame retardant based on cyclotriphosphazene and its blend with DGEBA epoxy resin. Polym. Degrad. Stab. <lb/>2009, 94, 2101-2106. [CrossRef] <lb/>28. Habib, T.; Morteza, J.; Azam, N. Mechanical and thermo-gravimetric properties of unsaturated polyester <lb/>resin blended with FGD gypsum. Constr. Build. Mater. 2018, 163, 438-445. <lb/>29. Boyce, R.S.; Cherian, J.; Calanasan, C.; Sihombing, M.S.A. Lipopeptide Compounds and Their Use. PCT Int. <lb/>Appl. Patent No. WO2010062264A1, 3 June 2010. <lb/>30. Raghuwanshi, P.B.; Malalle, P.V. Synthesis and substituted Schiff&apos;s bases and their antimicrobial activity. <lb/>Pharma Chem. 2014, 6, 262-266. <lb/>31. Rong, Y.; Wentian, H.; Liang, X.; Yan, S.; Jinchun, L. Synthesis, mechanical and fire behaviours of rigid <lb/>polyurethane foam with a reactive flame retardant containing phosphazene and phosphate. Polym. Degrad. Stab. <lb/>2015, 122, 102-109. <lb/>32. Jamain, Z.; Khairuddean, M.; Saidin, S.A. Synthesis and characterisation of 1, 4-phenylenediamine derivatives <lb/>containing hydroxyl and cyclotriphosphazene as terminal group. J. Mol. Struct. 2019, 1186, 293-302. <lb/>[CrossRef] <lb/>33. Fang, Z.; Liu, Y.; Zhang, Y.; Cao, Z. Phosphorus-Containing Schiff Base Derivative Expanded Flame Retardant <lb/>and Its Preparation. Patent No. CN102732041A, 17 October 2012. <lb/>34. Deyan, Z.; Yangyang, W.; Jiong, J.; Wenzhu, Y.; Baofeng, Q.; Xia, L.; Xuan, S. H-Bonding and charging <lb/>mediated affregation and emission for fluorescene turn-on detection of hydrazine hydrate. Chem. Comm. <lb/>2015, 51, 10656-10659. <lb/>35. Thaker, B.T.; Patel, P.H.; Vansadiya, A.D.; Kanojiya, J.B. Substitution effects on the liquid crystalline properties <lb/>of thermotropic liquid crystals containing Schiff base chalcone linkages. Mol. Cryst. Liq. Cryst. 2009, 515, <lb/>135-147. [CrossRef] <lb/>36. Khoo, I.C. Liquid Crystals, 2nd ed.; John Wiley &amp; Sons, Inc.: Hoboken, NJ, USA, 2007; pp. 60-65. <lb/>37. Andrienko, D. Introduction to liquid crystals. J. Mol. Liq. 2018, 267, 520-541. [CrossRef] <lb/>38. Kelker, H.; Hatz, R. Handbook of Liquid Crystals; Verlag Chemie: Weinheim, Germany; Deerfield Beach, FL, <lb/>USA, 1980. <lb/>39. Sudhakar, S.; Narasimhaswamy, T.; Srinivasan, K.S.V. Towards the molecular-statistical modelling of the <lb/>optically isotropic mesophase in neat systems: From the thermodynamic point of view. Liq. Cryst. 2000, 27, <lb/>1525-1559. [CrossRef] <lb/>40. Sakagami, S.; Nakamizo, M. Liquid crystalline properties of N-(alkoxybenzylidene)-4-halogenoanilines. <lb/>Bull. Chem. Soc. Jpn. 1980, 53, 265-266. [CrossRef] <lb/>41. Singh, S.; Dunmur, D.A. Liquid Crystals: Fundamentals; World Scientific Publishing Co. Pte. Ltd.: London, <lb/>UK, 2002. <lb/>42. Sharma, V.S.; Patel, R.B. Effect of alkyl chain in the terminal ester group on mesomorphic properties of <lb/>new rod like homologous series: Synthesis and characterization. Mol. Cryst. Liq. Cryst. 2017, 643, 62-75. <lb/>[CrossRef] <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Molecules 2020, 25, 2122 <lb/></note>

			<page>26 of 26 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>43. Galewski, Z.; Coles, H.J. Liquid crystalline properties and phase situations in 4-chlorobenzylidene-4 -alkylanilines. <lb/>J. Mol. Liq. 1999, 79, 77-87. [CrossRef] <lb/>44. Frenkel, D.; Mulder, B.M. The hard ellipsoid-of-revolution fluid: I. Monte Carlo stimulations. Mol. Phys. <lb/>1985, 55, 1171-1192. [CrossRef] <lb/>45. Demus, D.; Goodby, J.; Gray, G.W.; Spiess, H.-W.; Vill, V. Handbook of Liquid Crystals, Low Molecular Weight <lb/>Liquid Crystals I; Wiley-VCH: New York, NY, USA, 1998; Volume 2A. <lb/>46. Jamain, Z.; Khairuddean, M.; Zulbaharen, N.N.; Chung, T.K. Synthesis, characterisation and determination <lb/>of mesophase transition of azo-azomethine derivatives with different terminal chain lengths. Malays. J. Chem. <lb/>2019, 22, 73-85. <lb/>47. Thaker, B.T.; Kanojiya, J.B.; Tandel, R.S. Effects of different terminal substituent on the mesomorphic behavior <lb/>of some azo-Schiff base and azo-ester-based liquid crystals. Mol. Cryst. Liq. Cryst. 2010, 528, 120-137. <lb/>[CrossRef] <lb/>48. Prajapati, A.K.; Pandya, H.M. Effect of a lateral chloro group on azomesogens containing the naphthalene <lb/>moiety. Mol. Cryst. Liq. Cryst. 2003, 393, 31-39. [CrossRef] <lb/>49. Rong, Y.; Bo, W.; Xiaofeng, H.; Binbin, M.; Jinchun, L. Synthesis and characterisation of flame retardant rigid <lb/>polyurethane foam based on a reactive flame retardant containing phosphazene and cyclotriphosphazene. <lb/>Polym. Degrad. Stab. 2017, 144, 62-69. <lb/>50. Liu, Y.L.; Chiu, Y.C.; Chen, T.Y. Phosphorus-containing polyaryloxydiphenylsilanes with high flame <lb/>retardance arising from a phosphorus-silicon synergic effect. Polym. Int. 2003, 52, 1256-1261. [CrossRef] <lb/>51. Faghihi, K.; Hagibeygi, M. New aromatic polyamide with azo and phosphine oxide groups in the main chain. <lb/>Turk. J. Chem. 2007, 31, 65-73. <lb/>52. Zahra, S.; Nasrin, J.; Shahla, S. Flame retardant cotton fibres produced using novel synthesised halogen-free <lb/>phosphoramide nanoparticles. Carbohydr. Polym. 2015, 118, 183-198. <lb/>53. Bian, X.C.; Chen, L.; Wang, J.S.; Wang, Y.Z. A novel thermotropic liquid crystalline copolyester containing <lb/>phosphorus and aromatic ether moiety toward high flame retardancy and low mesophase temperature. <lb/>J. Polym. Sci. A Polym. Chem. 2010, 48, 1182-1189. [CrossRef] <lb/>54. Mequanint, K.; Sanderson, R.; Pasch, H. Thermogravimetric study of phosphated polyurethane ionomers. <lb/>Polym. Degrad. Stab. 2002, 77, 121-128. [CrossRef] <lb/></listBibl>

			<front>Sample Availability: Samples of the compounds are not available from the authors. <lb/>© 2020 by the authors. Licensee MDPI, Basel, Switzerland. This article is an open access <lb/>article distributed under the terms and conditions of the Creative Commons Attribution <lb/>(CC BY) license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/). </front>


	</text>
</tei>