<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>Vol.:(0123456789) 1 3 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1007/s00109-021-02124-9 <lb/>ORIGINAL ARTICLE <lb/>The recurrent missense mutation p.(Arg367Trp) in YARS1 causes <lb/>a distinct neurodevelopmental phenotype <lb/>Luisa Averdunk 1,2 • Heinrich Sticht 3 • Harald Surowy 1 • Hermann-Josef Lüdecke 1 • Margarete Koch-Hogrebe 4 • <lb/>Hessa S. Alsaif 5 • Kimia Kahrizi 6 • Hamad Alzaidan 5 • Bashayer S. Alawam 5 • Mohamed Tohary 5 • Cornelia Kraus 7 • <lb/>Sabine Endele 7 • Erin Wadman 8 • Julie D. Kaplan 8 • Stephanie Efthymiou 9 • Hossein Najmabadi 5 • André Reis 7 • <lb/>Fowzan S. Alkuraya 5 • Dagmar Wieczorek 1 <lb/>Received: 12 March 2021 / Revised: 21 July 2021 / Accepted: 30 July 2021 <lb/>© The Author(s) 2021 <lb/>* Dagmar Wieczorek <lb/>dagmar.wieczorek@hhu.de <lb/>Extended author information available on the last page of the article <lb/>Abstract <lb/>Pathogenic variants in aminoacyl-tRNA synthetases (ARS1) <lb/>cause a diverse spectrum of autosomal recessive disorders. <lb/>Tyrosyl tRNA synthetase (TyrRS) is encoded by YARS1 <lb/>(cytosolic, OMIM*603,623) and is responsible of coupling <lb/>tyrosine to its specific tRNA. Next to the enzymatic domain, <lb/>TyrRS has two additional functional domains (N-Terminal <lb/>TyrRS Mini and C-terminal EMAP-II-like domain) which <lb/>confer cytokine-like functions. Mutations in YARS1 have <lb/>been associated with autosomal-dominant Charcot-Marie-<lb/>Tooth (CMT) neuropathy type C and a heterogenous group <lb/>of autosomal recessive, multisystem diseases. We iden-<lb/>tified 12 individuals from 6 families with the recurrent <lb/>homozygous missense variant c.1099C &gt; T;p.(Arg367Trp) <lb/>(NM_003680.3) in YARS1. This variant causes a multisys-<lb/>tem disorder with developmental delay, microcephaly, fail-<lb/>ure to thrive, short stature, muscular hypotonia, ataxia, brain <lb/>anomalies, microcytic anemia, hepatomegaly, and hypo-<lb/>thyroidism. In silico analyses show that the p.(Arg367Trp) <lb/>does not affect the catalytic domain responsible of enzy-<lb/>matic coupling, but destabilizes the cytokine-like C-termi-<lb/>nal domain. The phenotype associated with p.(Arg367Trp) <lb/>is distinct from the other biallelic pathogenic variants that <lb/>reside in different functional domains of TyrRS which <lb/>all show some common, but also divergent clinical signs <lb/>[(e.g., p.(Phe269Ser)-retinal anomalies, p.(Pro213Leu)/p. <lb/>(Gly525Arg)-mild ID, p.(Pro167Thr)-high fatality)]. <lb/>The diverse clinical spectrum of ARS1-associated disorders <lb/>is related to mutations affecting the various non-canonical <lb/>domains of ARS1, and impaired protein translation is likely <lb/>not the exclusive disease-causing mechanism of YARS1-and <lb/>ARS1-associated neurodevelopmental disorders. <lb/>Key messages <lb/>• The missense variant p.(Arg367Trp) in YARS1 causes a <lb/>distinct multisystem disorder. <lb/>• p.(Arg367Trp) affects a non-canonical domain with <lb/>cytokine-like functions. <lb/>• Phenotypic heterogeneity associates with the different <lb/>affected YARS1 domains. <lb/>• Impaired protein translation is likely not the exclusive <lb/>mechanism of ARS1-associated disorders. <lb/>Keywords Functional protein domains • Phenotypic <lb/>heterogeneity • Aminoacyl-tRNA synthetases (ARS1) • <lb/>Novel disease genes • Neurodevelopmental disorders • <lb/>Multisystem diseases <lb/></front>

			<body>Introduction <lb/>Pathogenic variants in aminoacyl-tRNA synthetases (ARS1) <lb/>have been implicated in neurodevelopmental disorders and mul-<lb/>tisystem diseases affecting many different tissues. Aminoacyl-<lb/>tRNA synthetases catalyze the attachment of specific amino <lb/>acids to their corresponding tRNA. ARS1 proteins are cytoplas-<lb/>mic proteins, whereas ARS2 proteins act in the mitochondria. <lb/>YARS1 encodes the cytosolic tyrosyl-tRNA synthetase <lb/>(TyrRS), that is, responsible of linking tyrosine to its specific <lb/>tRNA and requires homodimerization for enzyme activity. <lb/>Already in 1999, it was shown that apart from its enzy-<lb/>matic function, TyrRS has acquired at least two additional <lb/>functional motifs in higher eukaryotes during evolution <lb/>[1]. The N-terminal ELR motif was identified to play an <lb/>important role as an interleukin-8 (IL-8)-like cytokine by <lb/>binding to CXCR1, and to induce angiogenesis and throm-<lb/>bopoiesis [2, 3]. The C-terminal endothelial monocyte-<lb/>activating polypeptide II (EMAP-II)-like domain exerts <lb/></body>

			<front>/ Published online: 18 September 2021 <lb/>Journal of Molecular Medicine (2021) 99:1755-1768 <lb/></front>

			<page>1 3 <lb/></page>

			<body>cytokine functions, e.g., by inducing the migration of leu-<lb/>kocytes (macrophages, granulocytes) and the expression <lb/>and release of tumor necrosis factor-(TNF-), tissue fac-<lb/>tor or myeloperoxidase [1, 4, 5]. While the cytokine-like <lb/>functions of TyrRS are inactive in the dimeric full-length <lb/>protein, secretion, dissociation into monomers and cleavage <lb/>by proteases (elastase or plasmin) activates the secondary <lb/>functions of the N-and C-terminal fragments [6]. <lb/>The spectrum of diseases associated with ARS1 is very <lb/>broad. Pathogenic variants in all ARS1 coding genes have <lb/>been implicated in autosomal recessive disorders, many <lb/>of them presenting as early onset, severe multisystem dis-<lb/>eases, while six of these (GARS1, AARS1, KARS1, HARS1, <lb/>MARS1, YARS1) have also been implicated in autosomal-<lb/>dominant, late-onset neuropathies [7-13]. <lb/>Heterozygous pathogenic variants in YARS1 have been <lb/>first identified to cause autosomal-dominant Charcot-<lb/>Marie-Tooth (CMT) neuropathy type C (OMIM #608,323) <lb/>[7, 10]. Recently, five different biallelic variants in YARS <lb/>have been published to cause autosomal recessive disor-<lb/>ders [14-18]. However, the disorders attributed to bial-<lb/>lelic pathogenic variants in YARS in these five families are <lb/>heterogeneous ranging from severe intellectual disability <lb/>(ID) with infant mortality to milder conditions without ID <lb/>primarily affecting the sensory system [17]. <lb/>The goal of this study was to delineate the clinical pheno-<lb/>types associated with biallelic pathogenic variants in YARS1 in <lb/>order to improve disease recognition and health surveillance. <lb/>Via GeneMatcher and international collaborations, <lb/>we identified and characterized a set of twelve patients <lb/>with developmental delay and multisystem diseases <lb/>that were all homozygous for the specific variant <lb/>NM_003680.3:c.1099C &gt; T, p.(Arg367Trp). We review <lb/>all individuals with biallelic YARS1 pathogenic vari-<lb/>ants reported in the literature and search for the common <lb/>denominator and major discrepancies in clinical presenta-<lb/>tion of distinct YARS1 variations. <lb/>By in silico analysis, we study the predicted effect of <lb/>p.(Arg367Trp) on the protein structure and stability and dis-<lb/>cuss the impact on the canonical enzyme function of TyrRS <lb/>and on the non-canonical, secondary functions of TyrRS. <lb/>We suggest that an impaired protein synthesis is not the <lb/>primary mechanism underlying YARS1-(and ARS1-) associ-<lb/>ated disorders, but that they arise from defective non-canon-<lb/>ical, secondary functional domains. <lb/>Materials and methods <lb/>Patient recruitment and clinical assessment <lb/>The study was performed according to the Declaration of <lb/>Helsinki. The study was approved by the institutional ethical <lb/>review boards (King Faisal Specialist Hospital and Research <lb/>Center; Ref. No # 2,121,053 and 2,080,006; University Hos-<lb/>pital Erlangen Ref. No. 253_15B). Patients with multisys-<lb/>tem diseases and biallelic pathogenic variants in YARS1 <lb/>were recruited for the study. Ten of the 12 individuals with <lb/>homozygous p.(Arg367Trp) YARS1 variants were identi-<lb/>fied newly in-hospital or by international partners. Written <lb/>informed consent for publishing of clinical, genetic data, <lb/>and photographs was obtained from the patients and their <lb/>legal guardians. Two (J:II-1 and K:II-2) of the 12 individuals <lb/>had been identified within a large cohort of consanguine-<lb/>ous families with ID before and clinical data that had not <lb/>been published were provided after additional follow-up <lb/>investigations and in depth review of medical records [15]. <lb/>Clinical and laboratory findings of all patients were centrally <lb/>reviewed, categorized and summarized. <lb/>Identification of biallelic YARS1 pathogenic variants <lb/>by exome sequencing and Sanger sequencing <lb/>Genetic testing preceding exome sequencing including <lb/>cytogenetic and chromosomal microarray analyses did not <lb/>reveal any causative genetic aberrations. Exome sequenc-<lb/>ing was performed according to standard methods (supple-<lb/>mentary material). Sanger sequencing was performed for <lb/>confirmation of reported variants. <lb/>Review of published individuals <lb/>A literature search was performed in PubMed (search terms <lb/>YARS, tyrosyl-tRNA synthetase deficiency). All clinical <lb/>details and laboratory results were retrieved from the manu-<lb/>scripts, categorized and summarized. <lb/>In silico variant prediction, protein modeling, <lb/>and structural prediction <lb/>Effects of the p.(Arg367Trp) variant were predicted using <lb/>PROVEAN, SIFT, PolyPhen-2, and MutationTaster [19]. <lb/>Structural analysis of the p.(Arg367Trp) variant was based <lb/>on a crystal structure of the C-terminal domain of human <lb/>TyrRS (PDB code:1NTG) [20]. The effect of the pathogenic <lb/>variant was modeled using Missense3D [21]. RasMol was <lb/>used for visualization [22]. Multiple species protein align-<lb/>ment was done with Uniprot [23]. The impact of published <lb/>recessive variants on protein structure and stability was ana-<lb/>lyzed using the VIPUR algorithm [24]. A VIPUR score &gt; 0.5 <lb/>indicates a critical destabilization of protein structure. <lb/></body>

			<page>1756 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Journal of Molecular Medicine (2021) 99:1755-1768 <lb/></note>

			<page>1 3 <lb/></page>

			<body>Results <lb/>Identification and in silico analysis of YARS1 <lb/>c.1099C &gt; T, p.(Arg367Trp) <lb/>In all included patients, homozygosity of the variant <lb/>NM_003680.3(YARS1):c.1099C &gt; T, p.(Arg367Trp) <lb/>([GRCH38/hg38] chr1:g.32,781,089G &gt; A) in exon 10 of <lb/>YARS1 was identified by exome sequencing. No other likely <lb/>pathogenic variant of clinical significance was identified <lb/>in any patient. The haplotypes of the individuals originat-<lb/>ing from Saudi Arabia (C-I) differs from the haplotypes of <lb/>individuals A + B (from Turkey) and L (from Puerto Rico) <lb/>(Supplementary Table S1). While this finding does not rule <lb/>out a founder effect common to the Saudi patients (C-I), it <lb/>is less likely that also p.(Arg367Trp) of A + B and L traces <lb/>back to the same, shared founder. The homozygous variant <lb/>was absent from internal control databases but reported in <lb/>dbSNP (rs376054085). The allele frequency in the gnomAD <lb/>v2.1.1 population database is 3.89 × 10 -5 , with 11 known <lb/>heterozygotes among 141,403 individuals, of which 10 have <lb/>Latino and 1 has South Asian ancestry. The variant affects an <lb/>arginine residue at position 367 (Arg367) of human TyrRS, <lb/>in the C-terminal EMAP-II-like domain (residues 364-528) <lb/>and is located three amino acids away from the tRNA anti-<lb/>codon-binding domain (Fig. 1A). In silico tools predict del-<lb/>eterious effects on protein structure and function (predic-<lb/>tion scores: PROVEAN: -5.642, SIFT: 0.03, PolyPhen-2: <lb/>HumDiv 1.000/HumVar 0.953, MutationTaster: &quot;disease <lb/>causing&quot;). Arginine in position 367 is highly conserved in <lb/>mammals and down to Drosophila melanogaster, but not in <lb/>Xenopus tropicalis (western clawed frog) and Caenorhab-<lb/>ditis elegans (Fig. 1E). Given the PS4, PP1, PP2, and PP3 <lb/>ACMG/AMP criteria being fulfilled and the consistent phe-<lb/>notype in 12 individuals of 6 families, the p.(Arg367Trp) in <lb/>YARS1 was considered to be the causative genetic alteration <lb/>in the patients [25]. <lb/>In silico protein modeling and structural prediction <lb/>The p.(Arg367Trp) variant is located in the C-terminal <lb/>EMAP-II-like domain (residues 364-528) of TyrRS. In sil-<lb/>ico analysis of the wildtype structure reveals that arginine <lb/>in position 367 (Arg367) forms tight electrostatic interac-<lb/>tions with the oppositely charged aspartic acid in position <lb/>478 (Asp478), thereby stabilizing the domain structure <lb/>(Fig. 1C). In the mutant, the bulkier and uncharged tryp-<lb/>tophan (Trp367) cannot form this interaction resulting in <lb/>a rearrangement of the sidechains and a reduced domain <lb/>stability (Fig. 1D). The site of the p.(Arg367Trp) exchange <lb/>is in the immediate vicinity of a hexapeptide stretch (resi-<lb/>dues 371-377) that is critical for the cytokine activity of <lb/>the EMAP-II domain of TyrRS. [1] Amino acid alignment <lb/>of the C-terminal EMAP-II-like domain of YARS1 and the <lb/>aminoacyl-tRNA synthetase complex interacting multifunc-<lb/>tional protein 1 (AIMP1) shows that their corresponding <lb/>residues Arg367 and Asp478 are conserved in both domains <lb/>(Fig. 1F). <lb/>Homozygous YARS1 c.1099C &gt; T, p.(Arg367Trp) <lb/>variant causes a distinct multisystem disease <lb/>We characterized the clinical features of the ten newly identi-<lb/>fied patients (families 1-4, 6) and two previously published <lb/>patients (family 5) with homozygous p.(Arg367Trp) variants, <lb/>all presenting with moderate ID and multisystem disease <lb/>(Table 1, Fig. 1A-G) [15]. Family 1 originates from Turkey <lb/>and family 5 originates from Iran close to the border to Tur-<lb/>key. Families 2, 3, and 4 stem from three different regions in <lb/>Saudi Arabia. Family 6 originates from Puerto Rico. <lb/>The individuals were born at term. Body measurements <lb/>at birth, including weight, length, and head circumference, <lb/>were at the lower end of the range. The weight at birth <lb/>ranged between -0.8 and -2.8 standard deviations (SD) <lb/>(5/5) (medium -1.8 SD). <lb/>All individuals, of whom data were available, had <lb/>acquired microcephaly (12/12, 100%), a postnatal failure <lb/>to thrive or growth delay (11/12, 92%) and developmental <lb/>delay or intellectual disability (12/12, 100%). Most individu-<lb/>als learned to walk independently (9/12, 75%, average age <lb/>3.3 years, SD 0.7) and all acquired the ability to communi-<lb/>cate using single words (11/12, 92%, average age 3.4 years, <lb/>SD 1.3). At the age of last evaluation, almost half of the <lb/>individuals were able to follow simple demands (5/12, 42%), <lb/>but only one individual spoke simple sentences of three or <lb/>more words (1/12, 8%, 8.5 years). Neurological assessment <lb/>revealed muscular hypotonia (9/12, 75%) including the face <lb/>(6/10, 60%), ataxia (7/10, 70%), and a poor coordination <lb/>(5/8, 63%). None of the patients had a history of epilepsy. <lb/>Seven patients were reported to have abnormal liver find-<lb/>ings including hepatomegaly (7/7, 100%), hyperechogenic <lb/>liver texture on ultrasonography (5/7, 71%), or an episode <lb/>of elevated liver enzymes (1/11, 9%) suggestive of stable <lb/>liver disease with steatosis. Serum albumin was in the lower <lb/>normal reference range (mean ± SD, 3.4 ± 0.5 g/L). Until the <lb/>last investigation (oldest age 15 years), only one patient had <lb/>a history of temporary ascites and no patient showed clinical <lb/>signs of liver failure. All individuals who had a blood analy-<lb/>sis done displayed a chronic microcytic anemia (8/8, 100%, <lb/>mean ± SD, hemoglobin 10.9 ± 0.9 g/dl, MCV 63.9 ± 2.2 fL, <lb/>MCH 19.6 ± 1.4 pg). Almost half of patients had laboratory <lb/>results suggestive of hypothyroidism (4/9, 44%). Sporadic <lb/>findings and features included mild hearing impairment <lb/>(1/12, 8%), gastroesophageal reflux and vomiting (2/12, <lb/>17%), abnormal findings on chest X-ray (2/11), dyspnea <lb/></body>

			<page>1757 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Journal of Molecular Medicine (2021) 99:1755-1768 <lb/></note>

			<page>1 3 <lb/></page>

			<body>(1/12, 8%), recurrent obstructive pulmonary disease (1/12, <lb/>8%), and recurrent infections (1/12, 8%). MRI imaging of <lb/>the head revealed a reduced brain volume, (7/9, 78%), a thin <lb/>corpus callosum (6/9, 67%), and a delay in myelination (6/9, <lb/>67%) (Fig. 2 H + J). Patients displayed facial dysmorphic <lb/>features including a flat philtrum (6/7, Fig. 2 B-G), a open <lb/>mouth appearance (6/7, Fig. 2 B, D, E, F, G), deep set eyes <lb/>(5/7, Fig. 2 B, C, D, G), hanging columella (5/7, Fig. 2B, C, <lb/>D, F, G), a prominent nose tip with relative small nares (3/7, <lb/>Fig. B, C, D), low set (1/7, Fig. 2F), and large ears (4/7 Fig. <lb/>B, C, D), sparse hair (4/7, Fig. 2 E-G), together reminding <lb/>of a progeroid-like appearance (6/6, Fig. 2 B-G). <lb/>In summary, the homozygous missense variant <lb/>p.(Arg367Trp) causes a clinically consistent, multisystem <lb/>disease with mildly delayed motor and severely impaired <lb/>speech development, microcephaly, failure to thrive, short <lb/>statue, muscular hypotonia, ataxia, brain atrophy, microcytic <lb/>anemia, hepatomegaly, hypothyroidism, and facial features <lb/>including a deep set eyes, a flat philtrum, and open mouth <lb/>appearance. Clinical heterogeneity is only observed for <lb/>hypothyroidism (approximately 50% of patients affected) <lb/>and some sporadic findings such as hearing loss or gastroe-<lb/>sophageal reflux. <lb/>YARS1 is one of the established disease genes of CMT. <lb/>Patients and their parents had no peripheral palsy, impair-<lb/>ment of peripheral sensation, autonomic dysfunction, or <lb/>neuropathic pain. In conclusion, no clinical signs of periph-<lb/>eral neuropathy were present. In four patients, peripheral <lb/>nerve conduction studies were performed which showed <lb/>unremarkable amplitudes of sensory action potentials and <lb/>normal nerve conduction velocities. Detailed case reports <lb/>medical histories are reported in the supplementary material. <lb/>Review of individuals from the literature: allelic <lb/>and clinical heterogeneity associated with biallelic <lb/>variations in YARS1 <lb/>In the recent literature, five homozygous or compound het-<lb/>erozygous disease-causing variants in YARS1 other than <lb/>p.(Arg367Trp) have been described (Table 2). <lb/>In 2016, two siblings with compound heterozygous <lb/>likely pathogenic variants c.638C &gt; T, p.(Pro213Leu) and <lb/>c.1573G &gt; A, p.(Gly525Arg) in YARS1 were reported. They <lb/>were affected by mild developmental delay (1/2) or normal <lb/>development (1/2), failure to thrive in the first year of life, <lb/>short statue, microcephaly (1/2), stable liver disease with <lb/>Fig. 1 a Organization of the functional domains of the three domains <lb/>of human TyrRS and biallelic variants reported in the literature. <lb/>TyrRS has three domains: (i) The catalytic N-terminal domain is <lb/>essential for aminoacylation of tRNA. As a monomeric fragment, <lb/>the N-terminal domain has cytokine activity and the ELR motif is <lb/>critical for this activity. (ii) tRNA anti-codon-binding domain. (iii) <lb/>The C-terminal EMAP-II-like domain that was shown to be dispen-<lb/>sable for aminoacylation. The heptapeptide sequence within this <lb/>domain is critical for the cytokine activity. The homozygous vari-<lb/>ants p.(Pro167Thr) and p.(Pro213Leu) reside in the catalytic domain, <lb/>harboring to the critical ELR motif, while most of the other variants <lb/>reside outside this domain. All five heterozygous mutations causing <lb/>Charcot-Marie-Tooth neuropathy reside in the catalytic domain. b <lb/>Structure of the C-terminal domain of TyrRS shown as backbone rep-<lb/>resentation indicating the elements of secondary structure. Arg367 is <lb/>shown in space-filled presentation and colored according to the atom <lb/>types. The heptapeptide sequence stretch critical for the cytokine <lb/>activity (residues 371-377) is shown in blue. c Structural role of <lb/>Arg367 in TyrRS: In the wild-type, Arg367 forms a salt-bridge to <lb/>Asp478 (indicated by green dotted lines). d In the p.(Arg367Trp) <lb/>mutant, the bulky uncharged tryptophan cannot form an electrostatic <lb/>interaction resulting in domain destabilization. c + d Arg367/Asp478 <lb/>are shown in stick presentation. e Multi-species amino acid alignment <lb/>indicates that Arg367 is highly conserved in mammals and down to <lb/>zebrafish (Danio rerio), but not in the western clawed frog (Xenopus <lb/>tropicalis) [23]. f Amino acid alignment of the C-terminal EMAP-<lb/>II-like domain of TyrRS compared to AIMP1. The corresponding <lb/>residues Arg367 and Asp478 are conserved in both domains. TyrRS, <lb/>tyrosine tRNA synthetase; AIMP1, aminoacyl-tRNA synthetase com-<lb/>plex interacting multifunctional protein 1 <lb/></body>

			<page>1758 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Journal of Molecular Medicine (2021) 99:1755-1768 <lb/></note>

			<page>1 3 <lb/></page>

			<body>Table 1 <lb/>Clinical features of 12 individuals homozygous for NM_003680.3(YARS1):c.1099C &gt; T, p.(Arg367Trp). Features with a frequency reported ≥ <lb/>2 times were reported in this table <lb/>NM_003680.3(YARS1):c.1099C &gt; T, p.(Arg367Trp) <lb/>Family 1 <lb/>Family 2 <lb/>Family 3 <lb/>Family 4 <lb/>Family 5 <lb/>Family 6 <lb/>A:II-1 <lb/>B:II-2 <lb/>C:II-2 <lb/>D:II-3 <lb/>E:II-5 <lb/>F:II-3 <lb/>G:II-4 <lb/>H:II-5 <lb/>I:II-1 <lb/>J:II-1 <lb/>K:II-2 <lb/>L:II-1 <lb/>Sex <lb/>M <lb/>M <lb/>F <lb/>F <lb/>F <lb/>F <lb/>M <lb/>M <lb/>M <lb/>M <lb/>M <lb/>M <lb/>Ethnicity <lb/>Turkish <lb/>Arabian <lb/>Arabian <lb/>Arabian <lb/>Iranian <lb/>Puerto-<lb/>Rican <lb/>Age at last exam (years) <lb/>15 <lb/>9 <lb/>5 <lb/>14 <lb/>11 <lb/>7 <lb/>6 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>15 <lb/>13 <lb/>4 <lb/>Body measurements <lb/>Microcephaly <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>12/12 (100%) <lb/>Birth <lb/>(weeks) <lb/>39 <lb/>40 <lb/>39 <lb/>n/r <lb/>n/r <lb/>40 <lb/>40 <lb/>40 <lb/>39 <lb/>38 <lb/>38 <lb/>40 <lb/>-weight at birth (g)/(SD) <lb/>2600/ -2.0 <lb/>2910/ -1.7 3000/-0.8 <lb/>n/r <lb/>n/r <lb/>2/ -2.8 <lb/>n/r <lb/>n/r <lb/>2700/ -1.8 n/r <lb/>n/r <lb/>3285/-0.77 <lb/>-Length at birth (cm)/(SD) 49/-1.26 <lb/>48/ -2.0 <lb/>n/r <lb/>n/r <lb/>n/r <lb/>n/r <lb/>n/r <lb/>n/r <lb/>n/r <lb/>50/ -0.06 <lb/>50/ -0.06 <lb/>49.5/-1.3 <lb/>-OFC at birth <lb/>(cm)/(SD) <lb/>34/ -1.0 <lb/>33/-2.0 <lb/>n/r <lb/>n/r <lb/>n/r <lb/>n/r <lb/>n/r <lb/>n/r <lb/>n/r <lb/>35/ -0.4 <lb/>35/ -0.4 <lb/>33/-2.0 <lb/>Failure <lb/>to thrive <lb/>Age of measurement (y) <lb/>+ 6 3/12 <lb/>+ 7 6/12 <lb/>+ 5 7/12 <lb/>+ <lb/>n/r <lb/>+ 3/12 <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ 4 5/12 <lb/>+ 14 <lb/>+ 13 <lb/>+ 3 6/12 <lb/>11/12 (92%) <lb/>-Weight (kg)/(SD) <lb/>15/ -2.9 <lb/>17.3/-3.1 <lb/>12.6/ -2.7 <lb/>n/r <lb/>n/r <lb/>1.7/ -5.4 <lb/>&lt; 3 rd <lb/>&lt; 3 rd <lb/>12.2/ -3.2 <lb/>n/r <lb/>n/r <lb/>12.3/ -1.8 <lb/>-Length (cm)/(SD) <lb/>108/ -3.3 <lb/>112/ -2.7 <lb/>102/ -3.6 <lb/>n/r <lb/>n/r <lb/>&lt; 3 rd <lb/>&lt; 3 rd <lb/>&lt; 3 rd <lb/>94/ -3.0 <lb/>122/ -5.1 <lb/>120/ -4.6 <lb/>94/ -1.4 <lb/>-OFC (cm)/(SD) <lb/>48/ <lb/>-3.6 <lb/>47/ <lb/>-4.4 <lb/>45/ <lb/>-5.5 <lb/>n/r <lb/>n/r <lb/>&lt; 3 rd <lb/>&lt; 3 rd <lb/>&lt; 3 rd <lb/>45/ -5.1 <lb/>44/ -6.7 <lb/>47/ -4.8 <lb/>47/ -3.1 <lb/>Cognitive development and acquired skills <lb/>Intellectual disability (IQ) <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ (30) <lb/>+ (30) <lb/>+ <lb/>12/12 (100%) <lb/>Developmental delay <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>12/12 (100%) <lb/>Ability to sit alone-age <lb/>2 y <lb/>n/r <lb/>n/r <lb/>n/r <lb/>n/r <lb/>2.5 y <lb/>2 y <lb/>2 <lb/>1 y <lb/>1 y 8 m <lb/>1 y 8 m <lb/>1 y <lb/>8/8 (100%) <lb/>Ability to walk-age <lb/>3 y <lb/>3.5 y <lb/>3 y <lb/>3 y <lb/>2 y <lb/>No (7) <lb/>4 y <lb/>No (3) <lb/>No (4) <lb/>4 y <lb/>4 y <lb/>2.5 y <lb/>9/12 (72%) <lb/>Speech-single words <lb/>3.5 y <lb/>3 y <lb/>4 y <lb/>4 y <lb/>3 y <lb/>6 y <lb/>5 y <lb/>2-3 y <lb/>2 y <lb/></body>

			<front>2 y <lb/>2 y <lb/>No <lb/>11/12 (92%) <lb/>Speech-simple sentences 8.5 y <lb/>No <lb/>No <lb/>No <lb/>No <lb/>No <lb/>No <lb/>No <lb/>No <lb/>No <lb/>No <lb/>No <lb/>1/12 (8%) <lb/>Follows simple demands <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>No <lb/>No <lb/>No <lb/></front>

			<body>No <lb/>No <lb/>No <lb/>No <lb/>5/12 (42%) <lb/>Neurological <lb/>findings <lb/>Muscular hypotonia <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>9/12 (75%) <lb/>Ataxia <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>n/r <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>n/r <lb/>7/10 (70%) <lb/>Poor coordination <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>n/r <lb/>n/r <lb/>n/r <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>n/r <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>5/8 (63%) <lb/>Facial hypotonia <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>+ <lb/>n/r <lb/>n/r <lb/>-<lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>6/10 (60%) <lb/>Seizures <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>0/12 (0%) <lb/>Liver <lb/>Hepatomegaly <lb/>n/r <lb/>+ <lb/>n/r <lb/>n/r <lb/>n/r <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ (mild) <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>n/r <lb/>7/7 (100%) <lb/>Hyperechogenic liver <lb/>texture <lb/>n/r <lb/>+ <lb/>n/r <lb/>n/r <lb/>n/r <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ (mild) <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>n/r <lb/>5/7 (71%) <lb/>Elevated liver enzymes <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>n/r <lb/>n/r <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>One episode n/r <lb/>n/r <lb/>-<lb/>1/8 (13%) <lb/>History of Ascites <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>+ <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>1/12 (9%) <lb/>Liver failure <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>0/12 (0%) <lb/>Abnormal laboratory findings <lb/>Chronic anemia <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>n/r <lb/>n/r <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>n/r <lb/>n/r <lb/>+ <lb/>8/8 (100%) <lb/></body>

			<page>1759 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Journal of Molecular Medicine (2021) 99:1755-1768 <lb/></note>

			<page>1 3 <lb/></page>

			<body>Table 1 <lb/>(continued) <lb/>NM_003680.3(YARS1):c.1099C &gt; T, p.(Arg367Trp) <lb/>Hypothyreoidism <lb/>+ <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>-<lb/>n/r <lb/>n/r <lb/>n/r <lb/>4/9 (44%) <lb/>Growth hormone defi-<lb/>ciency <lb/>+ <lb/>-<lb/>n/r <lb/>n/r <lb/>n/r <lb/>n/r <lb/>n/r <lb/>n/r <lb/>n/r <lb/>n/r <lb/>n/r <lb/>n/r <lb/>1/2 (50%) <lb/>Brain imaging (MRI) <lb/>Age <lb/>12 2/12 <lb/>1 6/12 <lb/>1.5 y <lb/>2 y <lb/>n/r <lb/>1 y/3 y <lb/>2 y <lb/>2 y <lb/>2 y <lb/>n/r <lb/>n/r <lb/>n/r <lb/>9/11 (81%) <lb/>Thin corpus callosum <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>n/r <lb/>n/r <lb/>n/r <lb/>6/9 (67%) <lb/>Reduced brain volume <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>-<lb/>+ <lb/>-<lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>n/r <lb/>n/r <lb/>n/r <lb/>7/9 (78%) <lb/>Delay in myelination <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>n/r <lb/>n/r <lb/>n/r <lb/>6/9 (67%) <lb/>Other findings <lb/>-<lb/>+ (#) <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>+ ($) <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>n/r <lb/>n/r <lb/>-<lb/>2/9 (11%) <lb/>Nerve conduction-sensory potentials <lb/>Decreased velocity <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>n/r <lb/>n/r <lb/>n/r <lb/>n/r <lb/>n/r <lb/>n/r <lb/>n/r <lb/>-<lb/>n/r <lb/>0/4 (0%) <lb/>Decreased amplitude <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>n/r <lb/>n/r <lb/>n/r <lb/>n/r <lb/>n/r <lb/>n/r <lb/>n/r <lb/>-<lb/>n/r <lb/>0/4 (0%) <lb/>Other findings <lb/>Visual impairment <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>n/r <lb/>n/r <lb/>-<lb/>0/11 (0%) <lb/>Retinal degeneration <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>n/r <lb/>n/r <lb/>n/r <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>n/r <lb/>n/r <lb/>-<lb/>0/6 (0%) <lb/>Hearing loss <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>+ <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>n/r <lb/>-<lb/>+ <lb/>-<lb/>2/12 (17%) <lb/>Vomiting <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>+ <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>+ <lb/>2/11 (18%) <lb/>Gastroesophageal reflux <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>+ <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>+ <lb/>2/11 (18%) <lb/>Dyspnea <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>+ <lb/>n/r <lb/>n/r <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>1/10 (10%) <lb/>Chest X-ray <lb/>n/r <lb/>n/r <lb/>Normal <lb/>+ (##) <lb/>n/r <lb/>n/r <lb/>+ (ß) <lb/>n/r <lb/>n/r <lb/>n/r <lb/>Recurrent bronchitides <lb/>+ <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>1/12 (8%) <lb/>pancreatitis <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>+ <lb/>1/12 (8%) <lb/>Cardiovascular/urinary <lb/>abnormalities <lb/>-<lb/>+ (&amp;) <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>+ ( +) <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>2/12 (17%) <lb/>Recurrent infections <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>+ ( §) <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>1/12 (8%) <lb/>Mortality-age (years) <lb/>15 <lb/># <lb/>Arachnoid cyst 6 × 3 × 3 cm <lb/>$ <lb/>periventricular leucomalazia <lb/>&amp; <lb/>hydro-nephrosis of right kidney <lb/>+ <lb/>PDA, muscular ventricular septal defect <lb/>## <lb/>hypoplastic right lung <lb/>ß, perihilar bronchial wall thickening <lb/>MRI, <lb/>magnet resonance imaging <lb/>OFC, <lb/>occipitofrontal circumference <lb/>n/r, <lb/>not reported <lb/>SD, standard deviation <lb/></body>

			<page>1760 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Journal of Molecular Medicine (2021) 99:1755-1768 <lb/></note>

			<page>1 3 <lb/></page>

			<body>steatosis (without inflammation), hypercholesterinemia, <lb/>areflexic muscular hypotonia (1/2), cystic lung disease, and <lb/>non-progressive mild brain atrophy and thinning of corpus <lb/>callosum with cystic changes in periventricular white matter <lb/>[18]. The nerve conduction was not affected and both parents <lb/>had no evidence of neuropathy or neurological disease. <lb/>In 2017, the homozygous variant c.806 T &gt; C, p.(Phe269Ser) <lb/>in YARS1 in one individual was associated with poor weight <lb/>gain (necessitating tube feeding), severe visual impairment <lb/>caused by progressive-rod-cone degeneration (fundus pig-<lb/>mentation), profound hearing impairment, poor balance and <lb/>muscular hypotonia during first years of life, stable liver disease <lb/>with steatosis (later minor fibrotic changes), primary amenor-<lb/>rhea, but normal psychomotor development [14]. MRI images <lb/>revealed a thin corpus callosum. Laboratory analyses showed <lb/>high level of blood platelets related to hyperactive bone marrow. <lb/>In 2019, seven related individuals with a homozygous <lb/>c.499C &gt; A, p.(Pro167Thr) pathogenic variant within the <lb/>catalytic N-terminal domain of YARS1 were reported to be <lb/>affected by a more severe multisystem disorder than previ-<lb/>ously reported [17]. All patients had developmental delay, <lb/>microcephaly, bilateral sensorineural hearing loss, and poor <lb/>growth. Some patients had abnormal ophthalmological find-<lb/>ings including pigmentary degeneration and visual impair-<lb/>ment. They were affected by exocrine pancreatic insuffi-<lb/>ciency and chronic, progressive liver disease with steatosis <lb/>at the early stages, and inflammatory cirrhosis at the later <lb/>stages. MRI images of the head revealed restricted diffu-<lb/>sion among the white matter and abnormal T2-weighted <lb/>hyperintensity with dysmyelination. Autopsy of one of the <lb/>deceased patients showed evidence of chronic neuronal loss <lb/>with vacuoles. Laboratory analyses showed chronic anemia, <lb/>hypalbuminemia, and intermittent proteinuria. Four patients <lb/>died during the first 2 years of life due to progressive liver <lb/>failure. <lb/>In 2019, in a large cohort of patients with microceph-<lb/>aly, the homozygous variant c.789C &gt; A,p.(Phe263Leu) in <lb/>YARS1 was associated with microcephaly, developmental <lb/>delay and primordial dwarfism in one girl [16]. <lb/>In summary, recessively inherited variants in YARS1 <lb/>cause some overlapping clinical features including small <lb/>stature and motor problems (all published variants). There <lb/>are also decisive differences between clinical features associ-<lb/>ated with the different variants. <lb/>The neurological impairment of p.Pro167Thr, p.(Arg367Trp), <lb/>and p.(Phe263Leu) is much more severe when compared <lb/>to p.(Phe269Ser) or the compound heterozygous variants <lb/>p.(Pro213Leu) and p.(Gly525Arg). For almost all variants, some <lb/>liver involvement has been reported, ranging from mild steatosis <lb/>(p.(Pro213Leu)/p.(Gly525Arg); p.(Phe269Ser); p.(Arg367Trp)) <lb/>to cirrhosis and hepatic failure (p.Pro167Thr). Abnormal <lb/>blood cells (anemia or low platelets) are reported in asso-<lb/>ciation with p.(Phe269Ser), p.Pro167Thr, and p.(Arg367Trp). <lb/>Hearing and visual impairment is only consistently observed for <lb/>p.(Phe269Ser) and p.Pro167Thr. The disease severity associated <lb/>with p.(Arg367Trp) (the variant of this study) lies somewhere in <lb/>between with p.Pro167Thr and the severe end and p.(Pro213Leu), <lb/>p.(Gly525Arg), and p.(Phe269Ser) at the milder end of the spec-<lb/>trum. The variants reside in different protein domains. In silico <lb/>analysis with VIPUR algorithm predicts that all biallelic vari-<lb/>ants associated with recessive multisystem disease significantly <lb/>affect the protein structure and stability (score &gt; 0.5, Table 2), <lb/>which leads to a significant disruption of the specific protein <lb/>domain in which they reside [24]. Given that the variants are <lb/>located in different protein domains the functional impact of the <lb/>structural domain destabilization is expected to differ between <lb/>the variants (Fig. 1). The variants p.(Phe269Ser), p.(Pro213Leu), <lb/>p.(Phe263Leu), and p.(Gly525Arg) were absent from gnomAD <lb/>and the p.(Pro167Thr) was detected only twice (in European) <lb/>within at least 141,000 individuals. Compared to the biallelic <lb/>variants reported in the literature, p.(Arg367Trp) was observed <lb/>in the heterozygous state in eleven individuals from gnomAD <lb/>v2.1.1 (1 South Asian and 10 Latino) [26]. <lb/>Discussion <lb/>Since the availability and broad use of exome sequencing, <lb/>the success rate in solving the genetic cause of ID and multi-<lb/>system diseases has significantly increased. Most of the new <lb/>disease genes have been identified as private disease-causing <lb/>variants in single families within larger cohorts [15, 16, 27]. <lb/>For many disease genes, reliable clinical data on the features <lb/>and course of the associated disorders are sparse. For appro-<lb/>priate patient counseling and guidance, the delineation of <lb/>typical clinical signs is needed. <lb/>Aminoacyl-tRNA synthetases link specific amino acids <lb/>with their transfer RNAs and play a key role in protein trans-<lb/>lation. Beyond their canonical role, many ARS1 acquired <lb/>secondary functions by the incorporation of additional <lb/>domains during evolution of more complex eukaryotes and <lb/>play key regulatory roles e.g. in immunomodulation and <lb/>inflammation [28-31]. <lb/>TyrRS couples the amino acid tyrosine to its spe-<lb/>cific tRNA. In this study, we identified and character-<lb/>ized 10 newly diagnosed and two previously reported <lb/>individuals carrying the homozygous missense variant <lb/>NM_003680.3:c.1099C &gt; T, p.(Arg367Trp) in YARS1 and <lb/>summarized all previously published patients from the lit-<lb/>erature, carrying alternative, biallelic variants in YARS. We <lb/>identified a specific multisystem disease affecting not only <lb/>the central nervous system, but also the liver, the hemat-<lb/>opoietic system (anemia), and the endocrine system (hypo-<lb/>thyroidism). The specification of the common, clinical fea-<lb/>tures allows to establish the recommendation of monitoring <lb/>affected individuals with regards to psychomotor, liver, <lb/></body>

			<page>1761 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Journal of Molecular Medicine (2021) 99:1755-1768 <lb/></note>

			<page>1 3 <lb/></page>

			<body>Fig. 2 a Pedigrees of affected individuals with homozygous <lb/>p.(Arg367Trp) in YARS1. Individuals J and K had been reported <lb/>within a large cohort of consanguineous families with ID [15]. Indi-<lb/>vidual L additionally has two unaffected half-siblings (not depicted). <lb/>b-h Facial features of individuals (A + B, F + G + H, I, and L). b Indi-<lb/>vidual A (family 1:II-1) at age of A 11 and 15 years, c Individual B <lb/>(family 1:II-2) at age of 7 and 9 years, d Individual I (family 4:II-1) <lb/>at age of 7 years, e Individual F (Family 3:II-3) at age of 3 years, f <lb/>Individual H (family 3:II-5), g Individual G (family 3:II-4) at age of <lb/>5 years. h Individual L (Family 6:II-41) at age of 3.5 years. Facial <lb/>dysmorphic features including deep set eyes (b, c, d, g, h), sparse hair <lb/>(e-h), a long nose (b-d), a flat nasal bridge (b-d), full cheeks (E -G), <lb/>long columella (c-d, f-g), flat philtrum (b-h), open mouth appear-<lb/>ance (b, d-h), low set (1), and large ears (b-d, h), together resem-<lb/>bling progeroid-like appearance (b-h). i Axial sequences (head MRI) <lb/>of individuals I, G, and F showing wide lateral ventricles as a sign <lb/>of diffuse cerebral volume due to periventricular white matter loss, <lb/>j Sagittal sequences (head MRI) of individuals I (2y), G (2y), and F <lb/>(2y) (from left to right) showing thinning of corpus callosum <lb/></body>

			<page>1762 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Journal of Molecular Medicine (2021) 99:1755-1768 <lb/></note>

			<page>1 3 <lb/></page>

			<body>Table 2 <lb/>Summary of all patients with biallelic variants in YARS1 <lb/>other than p.(Arg367Trp) from the literature. In silico <lb/>analysis with VIPUR algorithm predicts that all biallelic variants associ-<lb/>ated with recessive multisystemic disease significantly impact the protein structure and stability (score &gt; 0.5) of the respective <lb/>TyrRS protein domain <lb/>+ <lb/>Present in &gt; 50%; ± <lb/>present in 5-50%; -<lb/>absent <lb/>* <lb/>compound heterozygous <lb/>A <lb/>Mild <lb/>B <lb/>at age of 7 months after anoxic brain injury <lb/>C <lb/>steatosis <lb/>D <lb/>cirrhosis <lb/>E <lb/>cystic changes <lb/>F <lb/>dysmyelination, diffusion restriction, T2 hyperintensity <lb/>G <lb/>during first 2 years; n/r, <lb/>not reported <lb/>Nowaczyk et al. 2016 <lb/>Tracewska-Siemiatkowska et al., 2017 <lb/>Williams et al., 2019 <lb/>Alkuraya et al., 2019 <lb/>This study <lb/>2 patients <lb/>1 patient <lb/>7 patients <lb/>1 patient <lb/>12 patients <lb/>Gender <lb/>1F/1 M <lb/>F <lb/>5F/2 M <lb/>F <lb/>4F/8 M <lb/>Origin <lb/>Polish <lb/>Swedish <lb/>Amish (USA) <lb/>Saudi Arabian <lb/>Turkish/Iranian/Saudia Arabian/Puerto-Rican <lb/>Variant <lb/>p.(Pro213Leu) p.(Gly525Arg) * <lb/>p.(Phe269Ser) <lb/>p.Pro167Thr <lb/>p.(Phe263Leu) <lb/>p.(Arg367Trp) <lb/>Domain <lb/>N-terminal catalytic domain and <lb/>C-terminal EMAP-II-like domain <lb/>tRNA anti-codon-binding domain <lb/>N-terminal catalytic domain <lb/>tRNA anti-codon-<lb/>binding domain <lb/>C-terminal EMAP-II-like domain <lb/>VIPUR Score <lb/>0.84 <lb/>0.93 <lb/>0.86 <lb/>0.73 <lb/>0.67 <lb/>0.90 <lb/>Pregnancy/birth <lb/>Normal <lb/>No complications <lb/>Normal <lb/>No complications <lb/>3/7: premature <lb/>5/7: placental abnormalities <lb/>4/7: growth restriction <lb/>Primordial dwarfism Body measurements at birth in lower range <lb/>Short statue <lb/>+ <lb/>1/2 <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>7/7 <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>9/9 <lb/>Failure to thrive <lb/>+ <lb/>2/2 <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>7/7 <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>10/12 <lb/>Microcephaly <lb/>+ <lb/>1/2 <lb/>-<lb/>+ <lb/>7/7 <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>12/12 <lb/>Developmental delay <lb/>± <lb/>1/2 A <lb/>-<lb/>+ <lb/>7/7 <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>12/12 <lb/>Muscular hypotonia <lb/>+ <lb/>2/2 <lb/>-<lb/>+ <lb/>7/7 <lb/>n/r <lb/>+ <lb/>9/12 <lb/>Poor coordination <lb/>-<lb/>0/2 <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>7/7 <lb/>n/r <lb/>+ <lb/>5/8 <lb/>Hearing loss <lb/>-<lb/>0/2 <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>7/7 <lb/>n/r <lb/>± <lb/>2/11 <lb/></body>

			<page>1763 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Journal of Molecular Medicine (2021) 99:1755-1768 <lb/></note>

			<page>1 3 <lb/></page>

			<body>hematological, and hormonal symptoms. In addition, the <lb/>identification of total 12 patients with a matching and com-<lb/>mon clinical phenotype confirms the classification of the <lb/>variant p.(Arg367Trp) to be unequivocally pathogenic. <lb/>We originally intended to include patients with multisys-<lb/>tem disorders caused by biallelic variants in YARS1, regard-<lb/>less of the specific variants. Interestingly, our efforts that <lb/>included GeneMatcher and international collaborations, <lb/>only identified additional patients that were homozygous <lb/>for the p.(Arg367Trp) variant. We therefore compared the <lb/>allele frequency of the published variants to the frequency of <lb/>p.(Arg367Trp) in population databases. p.(Arg367Trp) and <lb/>the other variants from the literature have not been identified <lb/>in any of the control individuals from the Iranome or GME <lb/>Variome projects [32, 33]. In gnomAD v2.1.1, the higher <lb/>allele frequency of p.(Arg367Trp) (11 among a total of more <lb/>than 141,000 individuals) compared to variants from the <lb/>previous publication (0-2 alleles among more than 141,000 <lb/>individuals) in the general population probably accounts for <lb/>the higher prevalence of homozygous p.(Arg367Trp) and <lb/>explains why we identified an unexpected and disproportion-<lb/>ate high number of patients with this specific variant [26]. <lb/>Despite predominant reports of heterozygotes in the Latino <lb/>population, we only recruited one patient originating from <lb/>Latin America (Patient L, Puerto Rico). A possible reason <lb/>might be the relatively rare application exome sequencing in <lb/>Latin America, or the predominant random-mating scheme <lb/>in contrast to the prevalent consanguineous mating which <lb/>is common in Middle East and South Asia. Of note, many <lb/>variants causing autosomal recessive disorders in communi-<lb/>ties with high consanguinity rates occur as private disease-<lb/>causing variants in single families. This also seems to be <lb/>the case for the previously published individuals with vari-<lb/>ants that are absent from established control databases. In <lb/>contrast, the variant p.(Arg367Trp) is reported with a much <lb/>higher frequency and, therefore, might be of high and nota-<lb/>ble clinical relevance. Haplotype analysis of our patients <lb/>revealed diverging haplotypes surrounding the YARS1 gene <lb/>region suggesting that p.(Arg367Trp) does not essentially <lb/>trace back to a single founder. <lb/>As a native protein TyrRS comprises three functional <lb/>domains: the catalytic domain, the anticodon-binding <lb/>domain, and the C-terminal domain. TyrRS is only catalyti-<lb/>cally active as a homodimer [34-36]. While the full-length, <lb/>dimeric TyrRS (528 AA) has no known additional cytokine <lb/>activity, proteolytic cleavage and dissociating of monomeric <lb/>TyrRS into the N-terminal TyrRS Mini (composed of the cata-<lb/>lytic and anticodon domain) and a C-terminal EMAP-II-like <lb/>domain (164 AA) activates the secondary functions of these <lb/>domains [1, 2]. <lb/>Many genes involved in protein synthesis have been <lb/>associated with neurodevelopmental disorders [37, 38]. In <lb/>view of the core function of TyrRS in aminoacylation, it is <lb/>tempting to expect that a limited protein synthesis which <lb/>might not meet translational demand causes YARS1-associ-<lb/>ated disorders. Based on our findings, the hypothesis confer-<lb/>ring that a dysbalanced protein homeostasis is the sufficient <lb/>explanation of YARS1-associated disorders must be ques-<lb/>tioned for several reasons. First, the hypothesis of impaired <lb/>protein synthesis lacks to explain the considerable clinical <lb/>variability of autosomal recessive diseases associated with <lb/>YARS1 and also other ARS1-deficiencies. If a reduced or less <lb/>specific enzyme activity was the common cause of disease, <lb/>we would expect a more homogeneous clinical presentation <lb/>of all biallelic YARS1 and other ARS1 pathogenic variants. <lb/>Second, pathogenic variations causing recessive ARS1 defi-<lb/>ciencies generally reside in catalytic or anticodon binding <lb/>domains of ARS1 genes. However, in silico analysis show <lb/>that p.(Arg367Trp) lie outside these catalytically important <lb/>domains, but that they are located in the C-terminal domain <lb/>that accounts for non-canonical, immunomodulatory func-<lb/>tions [18]. <lb/>It was shown that the cleaved N-terminal TyrRS Mini <lb/>retains the aminoacylation activity of native TyrRS, and <lb/>thus, the C-terminal EMAP-II-like domain was shown <lb/>to be dispensable for aminoacylation [1, 39]. Therefore, <lb/>p.(Arg367Trp) that resides in the C-terminal domain prob-<lb/>ably does not affect the aminoacylation activity of TyrRS. <lb/>In silico analyses show that Arg367 is critical for a tight <lb/>electrostatic interaction with the oppositely charged Asp478 <lb/>and that p.(Arg367Trp) reduces the domain stability of the <lb/>C-terminal EMAP-II-like domain which is in close vicinity <lb/>of the critical hexapeptide stretch of this domain (residues <lb/>371-377). As a consequence, the destabilization of the pro-<lb/>tein structure could disrupt the EMAP-II-like cytokine activ-<lb/>ity. EMAP-II is also known as the aminoacyl-tRNA multiple <lb/>synthetase complex (MSC) Interacting Multifunctional Pro-<lb/>tein 1 (AIMP1). The EMAP-II-like domain of YARS1 shares <lb/>51% identity (78% similarity) including Arg367 (Fig. 1F). <lb/>It plays a role in the assembly of the multiple synthetase-<lb/>complex (MSC), and once it is secreted from apoptotic cells <lb/>confers multiple effects on angiogenesis, wound healing, <lb/>glucose metabolism, and neuronal development [40]. Of <lb/>note, Arg367 and Asp478 are not only highly conserved in <lb/>the C-terminal domain of TyrRS, but also its correspond-<lb/>ing residues in the homologue EMAP-II underpinning their <lb/>importance for the protein function (Fig. 1F). Homozygous <lb/>pathogenic variants in AIMP1 have been reported to cause <lb/>moderate to severe intellectual disability suggesting that <lb/>imbalances in EMAP-II-like functions are sufficient to cause <lb/>developmental disorders [41, 42]. <lb/>Apart from its procytokine activity, the C-terminal <lb/>domain functions to sterically block the critical chemotac-<lb/>tic ELR motif in the N-terminal domain by mutual shielding <lb/>[43]. By this mechanism, the C-terminal domain is thought <lb/>to suppress the cytokine activity of TyrRS in the state of a <lb/></body>

			<page>1764 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Journal of Molecular Medicine (2021) 99:1755-1768 <lb/></note>

			<page>1 3 <lb/></page>

			<body>native full-length protein [43]. Thus, destabilization of the <lb/>C-terminal domain could impede the steric block of the ELR <lb/>motif and thus induce a proinflammatory phenotype. The <lb/>finding of hyperechogenic liver cirrhosis in our patients and <lb/>patients from the literature, potentially supports the idea that <lb/>an imbalanced immune response and excessive inflammation <lb/>may play a role in the underlying disease pathophysiology. <lb/>The finding of chronic, microcytic anemia in relation to nor-<lb/>mal ferritin and low reticulocytes could also be explained by <lb/>a chronic inflammatory condition. <lb/>The phenotypic spectrum of the disorder associated with <lb/>p.(Arg367Trp) overlaps, but also differs to a certain extent <lb/>from other reported pathogenic variants in YARS1 from the <lb/>literature. In silico analysis of the protein structure predict a <lb/>significant impact of all previously reported recessive vari-<lb/>ants on the stability of the respective TyrRS protein domain. <lb/>Compared to the homozygous variant p.(Pro167Thr) <lb/>that causes a severe multisystem disorder including the <lb/>liver, the pancreas and the kidneys and a high infant mor-<lb/>tality, p.(Arg367Trp) is associated with a milder clinical <lb/>presentation [17]. In contrast, the compound heterozygous <lb/>variants p.(Pro213Leu)/p.(Gly525Arg) and p.(Phe269Ser) <lb/>were described to compromise the auditory perception, eyes, <lb/>reproductive organs, and liver, while not causing ID [14]. <lb/>These observations suggest that YARS1 displays consider-<lb/>able allelic heterogeneity concerning the disease severity <lb/>and pattern. p.(Pro167Thr) at the severe end of the spectrum <lb/>and p.(Pro213Leu) at the mild end of the spectrum both <lb/>reside in the N-terminal catalytic domain of YARS1, while <lb/>p.(Arg367Trp) with a disease severity in between these both <lb/>domains is located in the C-terminal domain. Given the lim-<lb/>ited number of variants described so far and the phenotypic <lb/>heterogeneity associated with the different domains, it is dif-<lb/>ficult to draw a clear link between the affected domain and <lb/>the disease severity and organs involved. <lb/>The hypothesis that autosomal recessive disorders asso-<lb/>ciated with YARS1 are caused by dysregulated secondary <lb/>functions rather than only by impaired protein synthesis <lb/>is further supported by location of the variations reported <lb/>in patients from the literature outside the TyrRS catalytic <lb/>domain (e.g., p.(Gly525Arg) in the C-terminal domain). <lb/>Until recently, all 19 ARS1 have been associated with <lb/>autosomal recessive diseases [8]. While recessively inher-<lb/>ited ARS1 disorders share some common clinical signs, <lb/>e.g., involvement of the CNS and microcephaly (in all but <lb/>HARS1), there is a striking heterogeneity of the clinical <lb/>manifestation which does not follow a reproducible pattern. <lb/>Liver involvement has been reported for IARS, LARS, and <lb/>MARS while for example skin anomalies have only been <lb/>described for QARS or anatomical heart anomalies have <lb/>only been described for MARS [38, 44-49]. LARS1-and <lb/>MARS1-associated disorders are associated with neurologi-<lb/>cal impairment, MRI abnormalities, liver disease, anemia, <lb/>and endocrine abnormalities and show the greatest clinical <lb/>overlap with the YARS1 p.(Arg367Trp)-associated pheno-<lb/>type delineated here. <lb/>Another example of ARS1-associated disorders, in which <lb/>an impaired protein synthesis as the causative disease mech-<lb/>anism can be questioned is VARS1 causing developmental <lb/>delay with microcephaly [38]. Interestingly, in in vitro <lb/>assays, the authors found a 50% residual aminoacylation <lb/>activity. Because reductions in enzyme activity of approxi-<lb/>mately 50% are often well tolerated, it can be speculated <lb/>that reduced aminoacylation is not the underlying disease <lb/>mechanism, but that dysregulated secondary functions (for <lb/>example, dysregulation of VEGF) might be involved. In <lb/>many ARS1 genes, over 200 &quot;catalytic nulls&quot; natural splice <lb/>variants have been annotated which primarily ablate or dis-<lb/>rupt the catalytic domain but retain the noncatalytic section. <lb/>This observation underpins the diverse, functions of nonen-<lb/>zymatic domains of ARS1 genes [50]. <lb/>CMT is another disease reflecting the significance of sec-<lb/>ondary protein functions of YARS1. Since the discovery of <lb/>pathogenic variants in YARS1 causing CMT type C more <lb/>than 15 years ago, the exact disease mechanism has not <lb/>been understood, yet. All five CMT-causing mutations in <lb/>YARS1 reside in the N-terminal catalytic domain (Fig. 1A). <lb/>Because aminoacylation activity is not a shared property of <lb/>pathogenic variations, it is unlikely that haploinsufficiency <lb/>affecting the aminoacylation enzyme activity is the underly-<lb/>ing mechanism [7, 51]. Currently, gain-of-function patho-<lb/>genic variants in non-catalytical domains or transcriptional <lb/>dysregulation are discussed to be the potential underlying <lb/>disease mechanism [52]. Of note, none of the patients or <lb/>parents reported here is affected by CMT neuropathy. This <lb/>is in line with the absence of neuropathy in patients with <lb/>recessive disorders caused by other ARS1 genes which have <lb/>been implicated with CMT [8]. <lb/>One limitation in the interpretation of the impact <lb/>of YARS1 variants on protein function is that to date <lb/>no structural model of the full-length protein is avail-<lb/>able and that separate structures of mini-TyrRS and <lb/>C-domains are the basis for functional predictions. <lb/>Another limitation is that our assumptions are based on <lb/>clinical findings, in silico analyses, and on recent find-<lb/>ings from functional in vitro studies. Protein dimeriza-<lb/>tion assays and yeast growth complementation assays <lb/>have been performed for YARS1 p.(Pro167Thr) showing <lb/>impaired dimerization and limited yeast growth [17]. <lb/>Functional studies for p.(Arg367Trp) have not been <lb/>performed. As the C-terminal domain was shown to <lb/>be dispensable for aminoacylation, it can be supposed <lb/>that p.(Arg367Trp) residing in the C-terminal domain <lb/>does not affect the enzymatic function of TyrRS; how-<lb/>ever, indirect effects on enzymatic function cannot be <lb/>ruled out [1, 39]. Experimental studies will be required <lb/></body>

			<page>1765 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Journal of Molecular Medicine (2021) 99:1755-1768 <lb/></note>

			<page>1 3 <lb/></page>

			<body>to systematically investigate the impact of all vari-<lb/>ants on enzyme activity and to delineate the disease <lb/>mechanism. <lb/>In conclusion, the characterization of the distinct mul-<lb/>tisystem disease associated with p.(Arg367Trp) and other <lb/>YARS1 biallelic variants will help in the clinical diagnostic-<lb/>workup of undiagnosed patients and will improve counseling <lb/>of affected families. There is decisive clinical heterogeneity <lb/>associated with different variants in YARS1 and also across <lb/>different ARS1-disorders. An advanced understanding of <lb/>secondary functions of ARS1 will pave the way to identify <lb/>new targets for treatment of ARS1-associated multisystem <lb/>disorders and CMT in the future. <lb/></body>

			<div type="annex">Supplementary Information The online version contains supplemen-<lb/>tary material available at https:// doi. org/ 10. 1007/ s00109-021-02124-9. <lb/></div>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgements We thank the patients and their families for taking <lb/>part in this study. This work was partly done within the Zentrum für <lb/>Seltene Erkrankungen of the University Hospital Düsseldorf (ZSED). <lb/>One of the authors of this publication (D.W.) is member of the Euro-<lb/>pean Reference Network on Rare Congenital Malformations and Rare <lb/>Intellectual Disability ERN-ITHACA [EU Framework Partnership <lb/>Agreement ID: 3HP-HP-FPA ERN-01-2016/739516]. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Author contributions Conceptualization: L.A., H.St., A.R., F.S.A., <lb/>D.W.; Methodology: L.A., H.S.A., D.W., Formal analysis and inves-<lb/>tigation: L.A., H.St., H.S., H.-J.L.; Data acquisition: L.A., M. K.-H., <lb/>K.K, H.S.A., B.S.A., M.T., C.K., S.E.; H.N., F.S.A., A.R., S.E., D.W., <lb/>S.E., E.W., J.K. Funding acquisition: A.R., H.N., F.S.A., D.W.; Visuali-<lb/>zation: L.A., H.St., H.S. Writing -original draft: L.A.; H.St., Writing <lb/>-review &amp; editing: H.St., H.S., H.-J.L, F.S.A., D.W. <lb/></div>

			<div type="funding">Funding Open Access funding enabled and organized by Projekt <lb/>DEAL. This work was in part supported by the German Ministry of <lb/>Research and Education (01GS08167 (DW)) and BMBF German Men-<lb/>tal Retardation Network (01GM1520A (AR)), German Mental Retarda-<lb/>tion Network] as part of the National Genome Research Network. SE <lb/>was supported by an MRC strategic award to establish an International <lb/>Centre for Genomic Medicine in Neuromuscular Diseases (ICGNMD) <lb/>MR/S005021/1&apos;. <lb/></div>

			<div type="availability">Data availability Additional clinical data and materials will be indi-<lb/>vidually available upon request. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Declarations <lb/>Ethics approval The study was approved by the institutional ethical <lb/>review boards (King Faisal Specialist Hospital and Research Center; <lb/>Ref. No # 2121053 and 2080006; University Hospital Erlangen Ref. <lb/>No. 253_15B). <lb/>Consent to participate Informed consent was obtained from legal <lb/>guardians. <lb/>Consent for publication Written informed consent for publishing of <lb/>clinical, genetic data and photographs was obtained from the legal <lb/>guardians. <lb/>Conflict of interest The authors declare no competing interests. <lb/>Open Access This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attri-<lb/>bution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adapta-<lb/>tion, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long <lb/>as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, <lb/>provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes <lb/>were made. The images or other third party material in this article are <lb/>included in the article&apos;s Creative Commons licence, unless indicated <lb/>otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in <lb/>the article&apos;s Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not <lb/>permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will <lb/>need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a <lb/>copy of this licence, visit http:// creat iveco mmons. org/ licen ses/ by/4. 0/. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>1. Wakasugi K, Schimmel P (1999) Two distinct cytokines released <lb/>from a human aminoacyl-tRNA synthetase. Sci 284(5411):147-<lb/>151. https:// doi. org/ 10. 1126/ scien ce. 284. 5411. 147 <lb/>2. Wakasugi K, Slike BM, Hood J, Ewalt KL, Cheresh DA, Schimmel <lb/>P (2002) Induction of angiogenesis by a fragment of human tyrosyl-<lb/>tRNA synthetase. J Biol Chem 277(23):20124-20126. https:// doi. <lb/>org/ 10. 1074/ jbc. C2001 26200 <lb/>3. Kanaji T, Vo MN, Kanaji S, Zarpellon A, Shapiro R, Morodomi Y, <lb/>Yuzuriha A, Eto K, Belani R, Do MH et al (2018) Tyrosyl-tRNA syn-<lb/>thetase stimulates thrombopoietin-independent hematopoiesis accel-<lb/>erating recovery from thrombocytopenia. Proc Natl Acad Sci USA <lb/>115(35):E8228-E8235. https:// doi. org/ 10. 1073/ pnas. 18070 00115 <lb/>4. Kao J, Ryan J, Brett G, Chen J, Shen H, Fan YG, Godman G, <lb/>Familletti PC, Wang F, Pan YC et al (1992) Endothelial mono-<lb/>cyte-activating polypeptide II: A novel tumor-derived poly-<lb/>peptide that activates host-response mechanisms. J Biol Chem <lb/>267(28):20239-20247 <lb/>5. Kao J, Fan YG, Haehnel I, Brett J, Greenberg S, Clauss M, Kayton M, <lb/>Houck K, Kisiel W, Seljelid R et al (1994) A peptide derived from <lb/>the amino terminus of endothelial-monocyte-activating polypeptide II <lb/>modulates mononuclear and polymorphonuclear leukocyte functions <lb/>defines an apparently novel cellular interaction site and induces an <lb/>acute inflammatory response. J Biol Chem 269(13):9774-9782 <lb/>6. Wakasugi K, Schimmel P (1999) Highly differentiated motifs <lb/>responsible for two cytokine activities of a split human tRNA <lb/>synthetase. J Biol Chem 274(33):23155-23159. https:// doi. org/ <lb/>10. 1074/ jbc. 274. 33. 23155 <lb/>7. Jordanova A, Irobi J, Thomas FP, Van Dijck P, Meerschaert K, Dewil <lb/>M, Dierick I, Jacobs A, De Vriendt E, Guergueltcheva V et al (2006) <lb/>Disrupted function and axonal distribution of mutant tyrosyl-tRNA <lb/>synthetase in dominant intermediate Charcot-Marie-Tooth neuropa-<lb/>thy. Nat Genet 38(2):197-202. https:// doi. org/ 10. 1038/ ng1727 <lb/>8. Fuchs SA, Schene IF, Kok G, Jansen JM, Nikkels PGJ, van Gassen <lb/>KLI, Terheggen-Lagro SWJ, van der Crabben SN, Hoeks SE, Niers <lb/>LEM et al (2019) Aminoacyl-tRNA synthetase deficiencies in search <lb/>of common themes. Genet Med 21(2):319-330. https:// doi. org/ 10. <lb/>1038/ s41436-018-0048-y <lb/>9. McLaughlin HM, Sakaguchi R, Liu C, Igarashi T, Pehlivan D, Chu <lb/>K, Iyer R, Cruz P, Cherukuri PF, Hansen NF et al (2010) Compound <lb/>heterozygosity for loss-of-function lysyl-tRNA synthetase mutations <lb/>in a patient with peripheral neuropathy. Am J Hum Genet 87(4):560-<lb/>566. https:// doi. org/ 10. 1016/j. ajhg. 2010. 09. 008 <lb/>10. Antonellis A, Ellsworth RE, Sambuughin N, Puls I, Abel A, Lee-<lb/>Lin SQ, Jordanova A, Kremensky I, Christodoulou K, Middleton <lb/>LT et al (2003) Glycyl tRNA synthetase mutations in Charcot-<lb/>Marie-Tooth disease type 2D and distal spinal muscular atrophy <lb/>type V. Am J Hum Genet 72(5):1293-1299. https:// doi. org/ 10. <lb/>1086/ 375039 <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>1766 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Journal of Molecular Medicine (2021) 99:1755-1768 <lb/></note>

			<page>1 3 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>11. Latour P, Thauvin-Robinet C, Baudelet-Mery C, Soichot P, Cusin <lb/>V, Faivre L, Locatelli MC, Mayencon M, Sarcey A, Broussolle E <lb/>et al (2010) A major determinant for binding and aminoacylation <lb/>of tRNA(Ala) in cytoplasmic Alanyl-tRNA synthetase is mutated <lb/>in dominant axonal Charcot-Marie-Tooth disease. Am J Hum <lb/>Genet 86(1):77-82. https:// doi. org/ 10. 1016/j. ajhg. 2009. 12. 005 <lb/>12. Gonzalez M, McLaughlin H, Houlden H, Guo M, Yo-Tsen L, <lb/>Hadjivassilious M, Speziani F, Yang XL, Antonellis A, Reilly <lb/>MM et al (2013) Exome sequencing identifies a significant variant <lb/>in methionyl-tRNA synthetase (MARS) in a family with late-onset <lb/>CMT2. J Neurol Neurosurg Psychiatry 84(11):1247-1249. https:// <lb/>doi. org/ 10. 1136/ jnnp-2013-305049 <lb/>13. Safka Brozkova D, Deconinck T, Griffin LB, Ferbert A, Haberlova <lb/>J, Mazanec R, Lassuthova P, Roth C, Pilunthanakul T, Rautenstrauss <lb/>B et al (2015) Loss of function mutations in HARS cause a spectrum <lb/>of inherited peripheral neuropathies. Brain 138(Pt 8):2161-2172. <lb/>https:// doi. org/ 10. 1093/ brain/ awv158 <lb/>14. Tracewska-Siemiatkowska A, Haer-Wigman L, Bosch DGM, <lb/>Nickerson D, Bamshad MJ, van de Vorst M, Rendtorff ND, Moller <lb/>C, Kjellstrom U, Andreasson S et al (2017) An Expanded Multi-<lb/>Organ Disease Phenotype Associated with Mutations in YARS. <lb/>Genes (Basel) 8(12):381. https:// doi. org/ 10. 3390/ genes 81203 81 <lb/>15. Hu H, Kahrizi K, Musante L, Fattahi Z, Herwig R, Hosseini M, <lb/>Oppitz C, Abedini SS, Suckow V, Larti F et al (2019) Genetics of <lb/>intellectual disability in consanguineous families. Mol Psychiatry <lb/>24(7):1027-1039. https:// doi. org/ 10. 1038/ s41380-017-0012-2 <lb/>16. Shaheen R, Maddirevula S, Ewida N, Alsahli S, Abdel-Salam <lb/>GMH, Zaki MS, Tala SA, Alhashem A, Softah A, Al-Owain M <lb/>et al (2019) Genomic and phenotypic delineation of congenital <lb/>microcephaly. Genet Med 21(3):545-552. https:// doi. org/ 10. 1038/ <lb/>s41436-018-0140-3 <lb/>17. Williams KB, Brigatti KW, Puffenberger EG, Gonzaga-Jauregui <lb/>C, Griffin LB, Martinez ED, Wenger OK, Yoder MA, Kandula <lb/>VVR, Fox MD et al (2019) Homozygosity for a mutation affecting <lb/>the catalytic domain of tyrosyl-tRNA synthetase (YARS) causes <lb/>multisystem disease. Hum Mol Genet 28(4):525-538. https:// doi. <lb/>org/ 10. 1093/ hmg/ ddy344 <lb/>18. Nowaczyk MJ, Huang L, Tarnopolsky M, Schwartzentruber J, <lb/>Majewski J, Bulman DE, Forge Canada Consortium, CRCC, Hartley <lb/>T, Boycott KM (2017) A novel multisystem disease associated with <lb/>recessive mutations in the tyrosyl-tRNA synthetase (YARS) gene. <lb/>Am J Med Genet A 173(1):126-134. https:// doi. org/ 10. 1002/ ajmg.a. <lb/>37973 <lb/>19. Adzhubei IA, Schmidt S, Peshkin L, Ramensky VE, Gerasimova <lb/>A, Bork P, Kondrashov AS, Sunyaev SR (2010) A method and <lb/>server for predicting damaging missense mutations. Nat Methods <lb/>7(4):248-249. https:// doi. org/ 10. 1038/ nmeth 0410-248 <lb/>20. Yang XL, Liu J, Skene RJ, McRee DE, Schimmel P (2003) Crystal <lb/>structure of an EMAP-II-like cytokine released from a human <lb/>tRNA synthetase. Helv Chim Acta 86:1246-1257 <lb/>21. Ittisoponpisan S, Islam SA, Khanna T, Alhuzimi E, David A, <lb/>Sternberg MJE (2019) Can predicted protein 3D Structures pro-<lb/>vide reliable insights into whether missense variants are disease <lb/>associated? J Mol Biol 431(11):2197-2212. https:// doi. org/ 10. <lb/>1016/j. jmb. 2019. 04. 009 <lb/>22. Sayle RA, Milner-White EJ (1995) RASMOL: biomolecular <lb/>graphics for all. Trends Biochem Sci 20(9):374. https:// doi. org/ <lb/>10. 1016/ s0968-0004(00) 89080-5 <lb/>23. UniProt C (2019) UniProt: a worldwide hub of protein knowl-<lb/>edge. Nucleic Acids Res 47(D1):D506-D515. https:// doi. org/ <lb/>10. 1093/ nar/ gky10 49 <lb/>24. Baugh EH, Simmons-Edler R, Muller CL, Alford RF, Volfovsky <lb/>N, Lash AE, Bonneau R (2016) Robust classification of protein <lb/>variation using structural modelling and large-scale data inte-<lb/>gration. Nucleic Acids Res 44(6):2501-2513. https:// doi. org/ <lb/>10. 1093/ nar/ gkw120 <lb/>25. Richards S, Aziz N, Bale S, Bick D, Das S, Gastier-Foster J, <lb/>Grody WW, Hegde M, Lyon E, Spector E et al (2015) Stand-<lb/>ards and guidelines for the interpretation of sequence variants: <lb/>a joint consensus recommendation of the American College <lb/>of Medical Genetics and Genomics and the Association for <lb/>Molecular Pathology. Genet Med 17(5):405-424. https:// doi. <lb/>org/ 10. 1038/ gim. 2015. 30 <lb/>26. Karczewski KJ, Francioli LC, Tiao G, Cummings BB, Alfoldi <lb/>J, Wang Q, Collins RL, Laricchia KM, Ganna A, Birnbaum <lb/>DP et al (2020) The mutational constraint spectrum quantified <lb/>from variation in 141,456 humans. Nature 581(7809):434-443. <lb/>https:// doi. org/ 10. 1038/ s41586-020-2308-7 <lb/>27. Reuter MS, Tawamie H, Buchert R, Hosny Gebril O, Froukh <lb/>T, Thiel C, Uebe S, Ekici AB, Krumbiegel M, Zweier C et al <lb/>(2017) Diagnostic Yield and novel candidate genes by exome <lb/>sequencing in 152 consanguineous families with neurodevelop-<lb/>mental disorders. JAMA Psychiat 74(3):293-299. https:// doi. <lb/>org/ 10. 1001/ jamap sychi atry. 2016. 3798 <lb/>28. Sampath P, Mazumder B, Seshadri V, Gerber CA, Chavatte L, <lb/>Kinter M, Ting SM, Dignam JD, Kim S, Driscoll DM, Fox PL <lb/>(2004) Noncanonical function of glutamyl-prolyl-tRNA syn-<lb/>thetase: gene-specific silencing of translation. Cell 119(2):195-<lb/>208. https:// doi. org/ 10. 1016/j. cell. 2004. 09. 030 <lb/>29. Mukhopadhyay R, Jia J, Arif A, Ray PS, Fox PL (2009) The <lb/>GAIT system: a gatekeeper of inflammatory gene expression. <lb/>Trends Biochem Sci 34(7):324-331. https:// doi. org/ 10. 1016/j. <lb/>tibs. 2009. 03. 004 <lb/>30. Otani A, Slike BM, Dorrell MI, Hood J, Kinder K, Ewalt KL, <lb/>Cheresh D, Schimmel P, Friedlander M (2002) A fragment of <lb/>human TrpRS as a potent antagonist of ocular angiogenesis. <lb/>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA 99(1):178-183. https:// doi. org/ 10. <lb/>1073/ pnas. 01260 1899 <lb/>31. Ewalt KL, Schimmel P (2002) Activation of angiogenic signal-<lb/>ing pathways by two human tRNA synthetases. Biochemistry <lb/>41(45):13344-13349. https:// doi. org/ 10. 1021/ bi020 537k <lb/>32. Scott EM, Halees A, Itan Y, Spencer EG, He Y, Azab MA, <lb/>Gabriel SB, Belkadi A, Boisson B, Abel L et al (2016) Char-<lb/>acterization of Greater Middle Eastern genetic variation for <lb/>enhanced disease gene discovery. Nat Genet 48(9):1071-1076. <lb/>https:// doi. org/ 10. 1038/ ng. 3592 <lb/>33. Fattahi Z, Beheshtian M, Mohseni M, Poustchi H, Sellars E, <lb/>Nezhadi SH, Amini A, Arzhangi S, Jalalvand K, Jamali P et al <lb/>(2019) Iranome: a catalog of genomic variations in the Iranian <lb/>population. Hum Mutat 40(11):1968-1984. https:// doi. org/ 10. <lb/>1002/ humu. 23880 <lb/>34. Ward WH, Fersht AR (1988) Tyrosyl-tRNA synthetase acts as <lb/>an asymmetric dimer in charging tRNA. A rationale for half-of-<lb/>the-sites activity Biochemistry 27(15):5525-5530. https:// doi. <lb/>org/ 10. 1021/ bi004 15a021 <lb/>35. Jones DH, McMillan AJ, Fersht AR, Winter G (1985) Reversible <lb/>dissociation of dimeric tyrosyl-tRNA synthetase by mutagen-<lb/>esis at the subunit interface. Biochemistry 24(21):5852-5857. <lb/>https:// doi. org/ 10. 1021/ bi003 42a024 <lb/>36. Yaremchuk A, Kriklivyi I, Tukalo M, Cusack S (2002) Class I <lb/>tyrosyl-tRNA synthetase has a class II mode of cognate tRNA <lb/>recognition. EMBO J 21(14):3829-3840. https:// doi. org/ 10. <lb/>1093/ emboj/ cdf373 <lb/>37. McLachlan F, Sires AM, Abbott CM (2019) The role of translation <lb/>elongation factor eEF1 subunits in neurodevelopmental disorders. <lb/>Hum Mutat 40(2):131-141. https:// doi. org/ 10. 1002/ humu. 23677 <lb/>38. Siekierska A, Stamberger H, Deconinck T, Oprescu SN, Partoens <lb/>M, Zhang Y, Sourbron J, Adriaenssens E, Mullen P, Wiencek <lb/>P et al (2019) Biallelic VARS variants cause developmental <lb/>encephalopathy with microcephaly that is recapitulated in vars <lb/>knockout zebrafish. Nat Commun 10(1):708. https:// doi. org/ 10. <lb/>1038/ s41467-018-07953-w <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>1767 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Journal of Molecular Medicine (2021) 99:1755-1768 <lb/></note>

			<page>1 3 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>39. Wakasugi K, Quinn CL, Tao N, Schimmel P (1998) Genetic code <lb/>in evolution: switching species-specific aminoacylation with a <lb/>peptide transplant. EMBO J 17(1):297-305. https:// doi. org/ 10. <lb/>1093/ emboj/ 17.1. 297 <lb/>40. Park SG, Choi EC, Kim S (2010) Aminoacyl-tRNA synthetase-<lb/>interacting multifunctional proteins (AIMPs): a triad for cellular <lb/>homeostasis. IUBMB Life 62(4):296-302. https:// doi. org/ 10. <lb/>1002/ iub. 324 <lb/>41. Accogli A, Russell L, Sebire G, Riviere JB, St-Onge J, Addour-<lb/>Boudrahem N, Laporte AD, Rouleau GA, Saint-Martin C, Srour <lb/>M (2019) Pathogenic variants in AIMP1 cause pontocerebellar <lb/>hypoplasia. Neurogenetics 20(2):103-108. https:// doi. org/ 10. <lb/>1007/ s10048-019-00572-7 <lb/>42. Iqbal Z, Puttmann L, Musante L, Razzaq A, Zahoor MY, Hu H, <lb/>Wienker TF, Garshasbi M, Fattahi Z, Gilissen C et al (2016) Mis-<lb/>sense variants in AIMP1 gene are implicated in autosomal reces-<lb/>sive intellectual disability without neurodegeneration. Eur J Hum <lb/>Genet 24(3):392-399. https:// doi. org/ 10. 1038/ ejhg. 2015. 148 <lb/>43. Yang XL, Kapoor M, Otero FJ, Slike BM, Tsuruta H, Frausto R, <lb/>Bates A, Ewalt KL, Cheresh DA, Schimmel P (2007) Gain-of-<lb/>function mutational activation of human tRNA synthetase procy-<lb/>tokine. Chem Biol 14(12):1323-1333. https:// doi. org/ 10. 1016/j. <lb/>chemb iol. 2007. 10. 016 <lb/>44. Orenstein N, Weiss K, Oprescu SN, Shapira R, Kidron D, <lb/>Vanagaite-Basel L, Antonellis A, Muenke M (2017) Bi-allelic <lb/>IARS mutations in a child with intra-uterine growth retardation, <lb/>neonatal cholestasis and mild developmental delay. Clin Genet <lb/>91(6):913-917. https:// doi. org/ 10. 1111/ cge. 12930 <lb/>45. Kopajtich R, Murayama K, Janecke AR, Haack TB, Breuer M, <lb/>Knisely AS, Harting I, Ohashi T, Okazaki Y, Watanabe D et al <lb/>(2016) IARS mutations cause growth retardation with <lb/>prenatal onset intellectual disability muscular hypotonia and <lb/>infantile hepatopathy. Am J Hum Genet 99(2):414-422. https:// <lb/>doi. org/ 10. 1016/j. ajhg. 2016. 05. 027 <lb/>46. Hadchouel A, Wieland T, Griese M, Baruffini E, Lorenz-<lb/>Depiereux B, Enaud L, Graf E, Dubus JC, Halioui-Louhaichi S, <lb/>Coulomb A et al (2015) Biallelic mutations of methionyl-tRNA <lb/>synthetase cause a specific type of pulmonary alveolar proteinosis <lb/>prevalent on Reunion island. Am J Hum Genet 96(5):826-831. <lb/>https:// doi. org/ 10. 1016/j. ajhg. 2015. 03. 010 <lb/>47. Casey JP, Slattery S, Cotter M, Monavari AA, Knerr I, Hughes <lb/>J, Treacy EP, Devaney D, McDermott M, Laffan E et al (2015) <lb/>Clinical and genetic characterisation of infantile liver failure syn-<lb/>drome type 1 due to recessive mutations in LARS. J Inherit Metab <lb/>Dis 38(6):1085-1092. https:// doi. org/ 10. 1007/ s10545-015-9849-1 <lb/>48. Sun Y, Hu G, Luo J, Fang D, Yu Y, Wang X, Chen J, Qiu W <lb/>(2017) Mutations in methionyl-tRNA synthetase gene in a Chi-<lb/>nese family with interstitial lung and liver disease postnatal <lb/>growth failure and anemia. J Hum Genet 62(6):647-651. https:// <lb/>doi. org/ 10. 1038/ jhg. 2017. 10 <lb/>49. van Meel E, Wegner DJ, Cliften P, Willing MC, White FV, Kornfeld <lb/>S, Cole FS (2013) Rare recessive loss-of-function methionyl-tRNA <lb/>synthetase mutations presenting as a multi-organ phenotype. BMC <lb/>Med Genet 14:106. https:// doi. org/ 10. 1186/ 1471-2350-14-106 <lb/>50. Lo WS, Gardiner E, Xu Z, Lau CF, Wang F, Zhou JJ, Mendlein JD, <lb/>Nangle LA, Chiang KP, Yang XL et al (2014) Human tRNA syn-<lb/>thetase catalytic nulls with diverse functions. Science 345(6194):328-<lb/>332. https:// doi. org/ 10. 1126/ scien ce. 12529 43 <lb/>51. Froelich CA, First EA (2011) Dominant intermediate Charcot-<lb/>Marie-Tooth disorder is not due to a catalytic defect in tyrosyl-<lb/>tRNA synthetase. Biochemistry 50(33):7132-7145. https:// doi. <lb/>org/ 10. 1021/ bi200 989h <lb/>52. Bervoets S, Wei N, Erfurth ML, Yusein-Myashkova S, Ermanoska <lb/>B, Mateiu L, Asselbergh B, Blocquel D, Kakad P, Penserga T <lb/>et al (2019) Transcriptional dysregulation by a nucleus-localized <lb/>aminoacyl-tRNA synthetase associated with Charcot-Marie-Tooth <lb/>neuropathy. Nat Commun 10(1):5045. https:// doi. org/ 10. 1038/ <lb/>s41467-019-12909-9 <lb/></listBibl>

			<div type="annex">Publisher&apos;s Note Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to <lb/>jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations. <lb/>Authors and Affiliations <lb/>Luisa Averdunk 1,2 • Heinrich Sticht 3 • Harald Surowy 1 • Hermann-Josef Lüdecke 1 • Margarete Koch-Hogrebe 4 • <lb/>Hessa S. Alsaif 5 • Kimia Kahrizi 6 • Hamad Alzaidan 5 • Bashayer S. Alawam 5 • Mohamed Tohary 5 • Cornelia Kraus 7 • <lb/>Sabine Endele 7 • Erin Wadman 8 • Julie D. Kaplan 8 • Stephanie Efthymiou 9 • Hossein Najmabadi 5 • André Reis 7 • <lb/>Fowzan S. Alkuraya 5 • Dagmar Wieczorek 1 <lb/>1 <lb/>Institute of Human Genetics, Medical Faculty and University <lb/>Hospital Düsseldorf, Heinrich-Heine-University Düsseldorf, <lb/>Universitätsstraße 1, 40225 Düsseldorf, Germany <lb/>2 <lb/>Department of General Pediatrics, Neonatology and Pediatric <lb/>Cardiology, Medical Faculty and University Hospital <lb/>Düsseldorf, Heinrich-Heine-University, Düsseldorf, Germany <lb/>3 <lb/>Division of Bioinformatics, Institute of Biochemistry, Frie <lb/>drich-Alexander-Universität Erlangen-Nürnberg, Erlangen, <lb/>Germany <lb/>4 <lb/>Children&apos;s Hospital Datteln, University Witten Herdecke, <lb/>Datteln, Germany <lb/>5 <lb/>Department of Genetics, King Faisal Specialist Hospital <lb/>and Research Center, Riyadh, Saudi Arabia <lb/></div>

			<front>6 <lb/>Genetics Research Center, University of Social Welfare <lb/>and Rehabilitation Sciences, Tehran, Iran <lb/>7 <lb/>Institute of Human Genetics, University Hospital Erlangen, <lb/>Friedrich-Alexander-Universität Erlangen-Nürnberg, <lb/>Erlangen, Germany <lb/>8 <lb/>Division of Medical Genetics, Department of Pediatrics, <lb/>Nemours Alfred I, DuPont Hospital for Children, <lb/>Wilmington, Delaware, DE, USA <lb/>9 <lb/>Department of Neuromuscular Diseases, UCL Queen <lb/>Square Institute of Neurology and The National Hospital <lb/>for Neurology and Neurosurgery, London, UK <lb/></front>

			<page>1768 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Journal of Molecular Medicine (2021) 99:1755-1768 </note>


	</text>
</tei>