<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>REVIEW ARTICLE <lb/>OPEN <lb/>The signal pathways and treatment of cytokine storm in <lb/>COVID-19 <lb/>Lan Yang 1,2 , Xueru Xie 1,2 , Zikun Tu 1,2 , Jinrong Fu 3 , Damo Xu 4,5 and Yufeng Zhou 1,2 <lb/>The Coronavirus Disease 2019 (COVID-19) pandemic has become a global crisis and is more devastating than any other previous <lb/>infectious disease. It has affected a significant proportion of the global population both physically and mentally, and destroyed <lb/>businesses and societies. Current evidence suggested that immunopathology may be responsible for COVID-19 pathogenesis, <lb/>including lymphopenia, neutrophilia, dysregulation of monocytes and macrophages, reduced or delayed type I interferon (IFN-I) <lb/>response, antibody-dependent enhancement, and especially, cytokine storm (CS). The CS is characterized by hyperproduction of an <lb/>array of pro-inflammatory cytokines and is closely associated with poor prognosis. These excessively secreted pro-inflammatory <lb/>cytokines initiate different inflammatory signaling pathways via their receptors on immune and tissue cells, resulting in complicated <lb/>medical symptoms including fever, capillary leak syndrome, disseminated intravascular coagulation, acute respiratory distress <lb/>syndrome, and multiorgan failure, ultimately leading to death in the most severe cases. Therefore, it is clinically important to <lb/>understand the initiation and signaling pathways of CS to develop more effective treatment strategies for COVID-19. Herein, we <lb/>discuss the latest developments in the immunopathological characteristics of COVID-19 and focus on CS including the current <lb/>research status of the different cytokines involved. We also discuss the induction, function, downstream signaling, and existing and <lb/>potential interventions for targeting these cytokines or related signal pathways. We believe that a comprehensive understanding of <lb/>CS in COVID-19 will help to develop better strategies to effectively control immunopathology in this disease and other infectious <lb/>and inflammatory diseases. <lb/>Signal Transduction and Targeted Therapy (2021) 6:255 <lb/>; https://doi.org/10.1038/s41392-021-00679-0 <lb/></front>

			<body>INTRODUCTION <lb/>Coronavirus Disease 2019 (COVID-19) caused by severe acute <lb/>respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) rapidly spread <lb/>worldwide and was declared a pandemic in early 2020. COVID-19 <lb/>destroyed people&apos;s mental and physical health and staggered <lb/>global economic growth. As of May 18, 2021, 163 million <lb/>infections, including 3.38 million deaths, have been recorded <lb/>(source: World Health Organization). SARS-CoV-2 invades the <lb/>host by virtue of angiotensin-converting enzyme 2 (ACE2) <lb/>receptors broadly distributed on various tissues and immune <lb/>cells. 1-5 The virus can cause a wide range of clinical manifesta-<lb/>tions from mild forms such as fever, cough, and myalgia to <lb/>moderate forms requiring hospitalization (pneumonia and <lb/>localized inflammation) to severe/critical forms with fatal out-<lb/>comes. 6,7 Severe or critical infection often manifests as pneu-<lb/>monia, 8,9 disseminated intravascular coagulation (DIC), acute <lb/>respiratory distress syndrome (ARDS), low blood pressure, and <lb/>multiorgan failure (Fig. 1). 9-11 <lb/>Several lines of evidence have shown that immunopathological <lb/>damage may be responsible for the deterioration of COVID-19. <lb/>Particularly, multiple studies have reported that highly elevated <lb/>levels of pro-inflammatory cytokines are produced during the <lb/>crosstalk between epithelial cells and immune cells in COVID-19, <lb/>which has linked the cytokine storm (CS) with the severe <lb/>complications and poor outcomes in this infection. 12-14 <lb/>CS is a fast-developing, life-threatening, clinical condition in <lb/>which the overproduction of inflammatory cytokines and <lb/>excessive activation of immune cells lead to complicated medical <lb/>syndromes from a persistent fever, nonspecific muscle pain, and <lb/>hypotension, to capillary leak syndrome, DIC, ARDS, hemopha-<lb/>gocytic lymphohistiocytosis (HLH), multiorgan failure, and death if <lb/>treatment is not adequate. 15 Therefore, the timing of diagnosis <lb/>and treatment of CS could be life-saving. The term CS was first <lb/>used in 1993 in graft-versus-host disease, 16 and later, in many <lb/>inflammatory diseases such as autoimmune conditions, organ <lb/>transplantation, cancer chimeric antigen receptor (CAR) T cell <lb/>therapy, and, most recently, in COVID-19. 17-23 However, the <lb/>profile and causative effect of CS in different conditions can <lb/>greatly vary. Thus far, precise diagnosis and treatment guidelines <lb/>for CS in most of the conditions are lacking. Understanding the <lb/>definite alterations and pathogenic roles of individual cytokines <lb/>involved in the COVID-19-related CS (COVID-CS) is hence <lb/>extremely important for the development of precise diagnosis <lb/>and effective treatment. <lb/>Although some aspects of this topic have been partly reviewed <lb/>previously, a comprehensive view of COVID-CS to facilitate its <lb/></body>

			<front>Received: 21 March 2021 Revised: 22 May 2021 Accepted: 12 June 2021 <lb/>1 <lb/>Institute of Pediatrics, Children&apos;s Hospital of Fudan University, National Children&apos;s Medical Center, and the Shanghai Key Laboratory of Medical Epigenetics, International <lb/>Co-laboratory of Medical Epigenetics and Metabolism, Ministry of Science and Technology, Institutes of Biomedical Sciences, Fudan University, Shanghai, China; 2 National <lb/>Health Commission (NHC) Key Laboratory of Neonatal Diseases, Fudan University, Shanghai, China; 3 General Department, Children&apos;s Hospital of Fudan University, Shanghai, <lb/>China; 4 State Key Laboratory of Respiratory Disease for Allergy at Shenzhen University, Shenzhen Key Laboratory of Allergy and Immunology, Shenzhen University School of <lb/>Medicine, Shenzhen, China and 5 Institute of Infection, Immunity and Inflammation, University of Glasgow, Glasgow, UK <lb/>Correspondence: Damo Xu (xdm@szu.edu.cn) or Yufeng Zhou (yfzhou1@fudan.edu.cn) <lb/>www.nature.com/sigtrans <lb/>Signal Transduction and Targeted Therapy <lb/>© The Author(s) 2021, corrected publication 2021 <lb/>1234567890();,: <lb/></front>

			<body>diagnosis and treatment is still lacking with unmet clinical needs. <lb/>Herein, we provide an updated and full scenario of COVID-CS from <lb/>basic research to clinical diagnosis, treatment, and trials. Initially, <lb/>we discuss the currently identified immunopathological features <lb/>of COVID-19, especially the CS; its mechanism of action and <lb/>differences with respect to CS in other disease conditions; and <lb/>individual cytokines involved in the COVID-CS including their <lb/>pathological role, downstream signaling, and existing interven-<lb/>tions. In addition, the challenges and prospects in the diagnosis <lb/>and treatment of COVID-CS are also discussed. <lb/>THE IMMUNOPATHOLOGY OF COVID-19 <lb/>In general, patients with COVID-19 present with an abnormal <lb/>immune landscape, characterized by overactivated inflammatory, <lb/>innate immune response, and impaired protective, adaptive <lb/>immune response. This is primarily responsible for the immuno-<lb/>pathology of severe COVID-19. Thus far, evidence from both <lb/>clinical trials and basic research has revealed several key features <lb/>of immunopathology in severe COVID-19, including lymphopenia, <lb/>antibody-dependent enhancement (ADE), neutrophilia, dysregula-<lb/>tion of monocytes and macrophages, reduced or delayed type I <lb/>interferon (IFN-I) response, and CS (Fig. 2). <lb/>Lymphopenia <lb/>Lymphopenia was commonly found in COVID-19 patients 10,11 <lb/>and is closely correlated with the illness severity. 24,25 Laboratory <lb/>results showed that the counts and percentages of lymphocytes <lb/>including CD4 + T, CD8 + cytotoxic T, 26,27 natural killer (NK), 24 and <lb/>B cells 25 were all reduced in COVID-19 patients. 28-31 Evidence <lb/>from single-cell sequencing, 32 flow cytometry, 33 and nonhuman <lb/>primate models of COVID-19 34 confirmed the involvement of <lb/>lymphopenia to the maximum extent. In addition, T cells <lb/>exhibited exhaustion phenotypes with the expression of higher <lb/>levels of exhaustion markers including programmed cell <lb/>death protein-1 (PD-1) and T cell immunoglobulin and mucin <lb/>domain-3, suggesting that these T cells may have regulatory <lb/>activities. 26,27 Other investigations showed that the PD-1-or NK <lb/>group 2 member A-positive NK cells were also significantly <lb/>increased in the peripheral blood of COVID-19 patients <lb/>compared to healthy controls. 35,36 <lb/>Several mechanisms may contribute to SARS-CoV-2-induced <lb/>depletion and exhaustion of lymphocytes: (1) SARS-CoV-2 may <lb/>directly infect T cells via ACE2 receptor expressed on T cells, 37 <lb/>which results in T cell death; 38,39 (2) several pro-inflammatory or <lb/>anti-inflammatory cytokines can accelerate the depletion and <lb/>exhaustion of T cells with their respective functions. In addition, <lb/>the virus may destroy secondary lymphoid tissues spleen and <lb/>lymph nodes, leading to lymphopenia, which is supported by the <lb/>observations of splenic atrophy, lymph node necrosis, and <lb/>decreased lymphocyte numbers; 24,40-42 (3) a nonhuman primate <lb/>COVID-19 model showed that the impaired anti-viral T cell <lb/>response may be attributed to the increased numbers of <lb/>regulatory T cells (Tregs). 34 However, we cannot exclude the <lb/>possibility that depletion and exhaustion of lymphocytes resulted <lb/>from anti-inflammatory therapies such as the administration of <lb/>glucocorticoids. <lb/>Collectively, lymphopenia may represent a poor outcome of the <lb/>illness. A retrospective, multicenter, emergency clinical trial in a <lb/>Han Chinese population including 14,117 normal controls and 69 <lb/>hospitalized COVID-19 patients (25 severe or critical and 44 mild) <lb/>showed that lymphopenia occurred in almost 100% of the severe/ <lb/>critical cases, and the number of lymphocytes progressively <lb/>decreased with the progression of the disease and deterioration of <lb/>clinical status. The CD4 + and CD8 + T lymphocyte subsets showed <lb/>a marked difference between mild and severe cases. Therefore, <lb/>the authors suggested that analyzing the counts and percentages <lb/>of lymphocytes at admission immediately contributes to improved <lb/>clinical prognosis. 43 <lb/>Antibody-dependent enhancement <lb/>B cells are considered protective in SARS-CoV-2 infection by <lb/>producing neutralizing antibodies against the ACE2 receptor to <lb/>prevent viral entry. 44 However, B cell-produced neutralizing <lb/>antibodies are not necessarily protective, depending on the <lb/>virus element it targets and also the Fc region of the antibody. <lb/>ADE is a phenomenon wherein pre-existing neutralizing anti-<lb/>bodies targeting one serotype of a given virus enhance the <lb/>entry of not only that virus but also another serotype of the virus <lb/>into leukocytes through the interaction between the Fc regions <lb/>of the antibody and Fc receptors or complement receptors on <lb/>such cells. 45-49 The ADE phenomenon has been found in various <lb/>viral infections such as dengue, Flavivirus, SARS-CoV, MERS-CoV, <lb/>and Ebola. 45,48,50-52 <lb/>Recent studies have shown that relatively high levels of B cells <lb/>or antibodies are positively associated with COVID-19 sever-<lb/>ity, 32,53,54 implying the potential involvement of ADE in SARS-CoV-<lb/>2 infection. In addition, a study has reported that the monoclonal <lb/>antibody MW05 targeting SARS-CoV-2 may also induce ADE <lb/>activity by binding to FcγRIIB receptors on the target cells in vitro. <lb/>However, administration of an engineered antibody with Fc region <lb/>mutation in vivo effectively protected animals from SARS-CoV-2 <lb/>infection. 55 This highlights the importance of developing protec-<lb/>tive neutralizing antibodies against SARS-CoV-2. Nevertheless, <lb/>further investigations about ADE in SARS-CoV-2 infection are <lb/>required to facilitate the development of vaccine-or antibody-<lb/>based therapy for COVID-19. <lb/>Neutrophilia <lb/>An increase in neutrophil count in COVID-19 patients is widely <lb/>recognized. It is well known that under normal conditions, <lb/>neutrophils play a protective role against infections by producing <lb/>neutrophil extracellular traps (NETs) to kill extracellular patho-<lb/>gens; 56 however, excessive neutrophil activation can also damage <lb/>the surrounding cells and dissolve connective tissues. 57 <lb/>Fig. 1 A systemic clinical manifestations of COVID-19. SARS-CoV-2 <lb/>infects airway epithelial cells or immune cells via binding to ACE2 <lb/>receptors, causing tissue damage and release of DAMPs, as well as <lb/>production of inflammatory cytokines by epithelial cells and <lb/>immune cells. Then, the crosstalk between epithelial cells and <lb/>immune cells leads to a wide range of clinical manifestations, from <lb/>mild forms (e.g., fever, cough, and myalgia); to moderate forms <lb/>requiring hospitalization (pneumonia and localized inflammation); <lb/>to severe/critical forms with a fatal outcome that are manifested as <lb/>pneumonia, ARDS, DIC, CS, and multiorgan failure. DAMP danger-<lb/>associated molecular pattern, ARDS acute respiratory distress <lb/>syndrome, DIC disseminated intravascular coagulation <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">The signal pathways and treatment of cytokine storm in COVID-19 <lb/>Yang et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Signal Transduction and Targeted Therapy (2021) 6:255 <lb/></note>

			<body>An earlier clinical trial including 138 patients from Wuhan, <lb/>China, showed that neutrophil counts were increased in non-<lb/>survivors compared to survivors and continued to increase until <lb/>death in the non-survivors. 11 Another clinical study that integrated <lb/>transcriptomic, proteomic, and metabolomic platforms showed <lb/>that neutrophil counts were increased in patients with severe, but <lb/>not mild, COVID-19 as compared to healthy controls, and <lb/>molecules associated with NETs were significantly upregulated <lb/>in severe COVID-19 cases. 58 <lb/>The increased neutrophils manifested as both increased <lb/>numbers of mature and immature cells. In a clinical trial that <lb/>integrated single-cell RNA-sequencing with single-cell proteomics <lb/>of blood and peripheral blood mononuclear cells (PBMCs), <lb/>immature neutrophil precursors, and dysfunctional mature <lb/>neutrophils expressing programmed death-ligand 1 appeared in <lb/>severe COVID-19 cases. 59 In addition, a single-cell sequencing <lb/>analysis by Wilk et al. 32 and a flow cytometry analysis by Ronit <lb/>et al. 33 also identified the appearance of neutrophil progenitors at <lb/>various developmental stages in PBMCs or bronchoalveolar lavage <lb/>fluid (BALF) of COVID-19 patients with ARDS. <lb/>Although the mechanism by which the virus promotes <lb/>neutrophil development in COVID-19 is still poorly understood, <lb/>McElvaney et al. 60 found that the levels of pyruvate kinase M2 <lb/>(PKM2), a regulator of glycolysis 61 and coactivator of hypoxia-<lb/>inducible factor-1α, 62 as well as phosphorylated PKM2 were <lb/>higher in the neutrophils of COVID-19 patients in the ICU than in <lb/>those of non-ICU COVID-19 patients. This indicates that neutro-<lb/>phils undergo immunometabolic reprogramming in severe <lb/>COVID-19 cases, which represents a potential intervention target <lb/>for excessive neutrophil generation and activation in severe or <lb/>critical COVID-19. <lb/>Dysregulation of monocytes and macrophages <lb/>Monocytes and macrophages are the major innate immune cells in <lb/>infection and inflammation not just by virtue of their higher <lb/>numbers but also by their functions. A single-cell RNA-sequencing <lb/>analysis showed that classic CD14 + monocytes were significantly <lb/>increased, whereas nonclassical CD16 + monocytes and intermediate <lb/>CD14 + CD16 + monocytes were remarkably reduced in the blood of <lb/>COVID-19 patients with severe symptoms. Classical monocytes can <lb/>differentiate into macrophages in tissue to initiate an inflammatory <lb/>response, whereas nonclassical monocytes were viewed as anti-<lb/>inflammatory as they can maintain vascular homeostasis, 63 which <lb/>may explain the phenotypic shift of circulating monocytes from <lb/>CD16 + to CD14 + . Analysis of the differentiation profiles of BALF and <lb/>circulating monocyte-macrophages from the same patient revealed <lb/>a transition course of blood-toward-BALF. More importantly, multi-<lb/>ple pro-inflammatory cytokines and chemokines were highly <lb/>expressed by the BALF monocyte-macrophages, suggesting that <lb/>the cells are inflamed. 64 Another single-cell sequencing analysis of <lb/>peripheral blood samples also showed that CD16 + monocytes were <lb/>remarkably depleted in COVID-19 patients with ARDS, with a <lb/>phenotypic shift from CD16 + to CD14 + . However, significant <lb/>upregulation of genes encoding pro-inflammatory cytokines or <lb/>chemokines were not found in peripheral monocytes, indicating that <lb/>peripheral monocytes may not be responsible for the progression of <lb/>CS in COVID-19. 32 Moreover, phenotyping leukocyte subpopulations <lb/>in BALF and blood of COVID-19 patients with ARDS showed that the <lb/>expression of activation markers such as CD16, CD64, CD69, and <lb/>HLA-DR was higher in BALF macrophages than in peripheral <lb/>macrophages. 33 Collectively, these existing studies were generally <lb/>consistent and revealed the course of blood-toward-BALF transition <lb/>and the contribution of pulmonary monocyte-macrophages to CS <lb/>Fig. 2 The key immunopathology of severe COVID-19. The immunopathological manifestations of COVID-19 include lymphopenia, <lb/>dysregulation of monocytes and macrophages, neutrophilia, ADE, reduced or delayed IFN-I response, and CS. Lymphopenia is commonly <lb/>observed in severe COVID-19. In addition to decreased counts, lymphocytes often exhibit exhaustion phenotypes with the expression of <lb/>higher levels of exhaustion markers PD-1, Tim-3, or NKG2A. Peripheral monocytes present a phenotype shift from CD16 + to CD14 + , and BALF <lb/>macrophages are increased with a blood-to-BALF transition course. Neutrophil counts are increased with the presence of neutrophil <lb/>precursors in peripheral blood, especially in patients with severe COVID-19. The possible existence of ADE enhances the entry of SARS-CoV-2 <lb/>into cells through interaction between Fc regions and Fc receptors, leading to the aggravation of COVID-19. A CS is characterized by highly <lb/>elevated levels of pro-inflammatory mediators and is a particularly central feature for poor outcomes in patients with severe or critical <lb/>infection. Reduced or delayed IFN-I response impedes viral clearance and induces paradoxical hyperinflammation, thus leading to the <lb/>deterioration of prognosis in COVID-19 patients. BALF bronchoalveolar lavage fluid, ADE antibody-dependent enhancement <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">The signal pathways and treatment of cytokine storm in COVID-19 <lb/>Yang et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Signal Transduction and Targeted Therapy (2021) 6:255 <lb/></note>

			<body>via the release of multiple pro-inflammatory cytokines and <lb/>chemokines during severe COVID-19. <lb/>Interestingly, a two-cohort study showed that activated HLA-<lb/>DR high CD11c high CD14 + monocytes were increased in the PBMCs of <lb/>patients with mild COVID-19, whereas dysfunctional HLA-<lb/>DR low CD163 high (indicative of anti-inflammatory function) CD14 + <lb/>monocytes were observed in severe COVID-19 cases. 59 This merits <lb/>further investigation to understand the underlying mechanism <lb/>and clinical significance. <lb/>Reduced or delayed IFN-I response <lb/>The IFN-I response is the first line of protective response and <lb/>critical to combat viral infections by promoting viral clearance and <lb/>regulating innate and adaptive immune responses. 65 Although the <lb/>detailed mechanism is still unknown when the infection occurs, <lb/>the RNA of SARS-CoV-2 virus may be recognized by innate <lb/>immune cells via pattern recognition receptors (PRRs) including <lb/>toll-like receptor (TLR); retinoic acid-inducible gene-I (RIG-I)-like <lb/>receptors (RLRs)/melanoma differentiation-associated gene 5 <lb/>(MDA5); and NOD-like receptors (NLRs). 66 Subsequently, down-<lb/>stream transcription factors including nuclear factor-κB (NF-κB), <lb/>activator protein-1 (AP-1), and IFN regulatory factor 3/7 (IRF3/7) <lb/>are activated to promote the transcription of pro-inflammatory <lb/>cytokines and IFN-I. The IFN-I can activate the Janus kinase 1 <lb/>(JAK1)/tyrosine kinase 2-signal transducer and activator of <lb/>transcription 1/2 (STAT1/2) pathway, promoting the formation of <lb/>the STAT1/2/IRF9 complex and initiating transcription of IFN-<lb/>stimulated genes (ISGs) (Fig. 3). 66,67 <lb/>However, accumulating evidence has suggested that the <lb/>protective IFN-I response was remarkably reduced in severe <lb/>COVID-19 patients. 26,68,69 At least two mechanisms have been <lb/>proposed to explain the deficient IFN-I response: (1) previous <lb/>studies have suggested that SARS-CoV employs various mechan-<lb/>isms to inhibit IFN response, especially through the components <lb/>of its structural proteins such as M protein, 70 N protein, 71 open-<lb/>reading frame 3a (ORF3a) protein, 72 and ORF6 protein. 73 <lb/>Considering that the structure of SARS-CoV-2 is similar to that of <lb/>SARS-CoV, it can be speculated that SARS-CoV-2 may exert similar <lb/>effects on IFN response. For example, Yang et al. 74 found that the <lb/>NSP1 protein of SARS-CoV-2 can inhibit STAT1 phosphorylation <lb/>and ISG transcription. (2) Decreased plasmacytoid dendritic cells <lb/>(pDCs) may be partly responsible for the deficient IFN-I response. <lb/>Sufficient evidence has suggested that pDC is a prominent <lb/>producer of IFN-I upon viral infection. 75-77 However, existing <lb/>studies showed that counts of pDCs were decreased in the blood <lb/>of COVID-19 patients, especially in severe cases. 26,32 <lb/>Of note, although the levels of systemic IFN-I were low, local <lb/>IFN-I and ISGs were noticeable in the BALF of some critically ill <lb/>patients, 78 which are related to the phenomenon of delayed IFN-I <lb/>response. 69 Evidence has confirmed that a delayed IFN-I response <lb/>not only impedes viral clearance but also induces paradoxical <lb/>hyperinflammation, thereby aggravating the immunopathological <lb/>response. 79,80 Collectively, these studies suggest that IFN-I-based <lb/>therapy for COVID-19 should be applied as early as possible after <lb/>the infection is confirmed. <lb/>Cytokine storm <lb/>In this section, we systemically review and discuss the character-<lb/>istics, possible induction mechanism, pathogenesis, and diagnosis <lb/>of CS in COVID-19. <lb/>Sufficient evidence has revealed the components and character-<lb/>istics of CS in the patients with severe COVID-19, which are <lb/>composed of an array of cytokines including interleukin-1 (IL-1), 2, 6, <lb/>7, 8, 10, 12, 17, 18; tumor necrosis factor-α (TNF-α); IFN-γ; granulocyte <lb/>Fig. 3 The signaling pathways for the production and function of IFN-I after SARS-CoV-2 infection. After infection, the genomic ssRNAs and <lb/>replicative dsRNA intermediates of SARS-CoV-2 are recognized by endosomal toll-like receptors TLR3, 7, 8, and cytosolic RNA sensors, RIG-1/ <lb/>MDA5; next, downstream transcription factors including NF-κB and IRF3/7 are activated to induce the production of pro-inflammatory <lb/>cytokines and IFN-I. IFN-I can activate the JAK1/TYK2-STAT1/2 pathway, promoting the formation of the STAT1/2/IRF9 complex and initiating <lb/>the transcription of ISGs to produce anti-virus mediators, and it can also nonconventionally activate inflammatory pathways such as NF-κB <lb/>and MAPK pathways to induce the expression of pro-inflammatory cytokines and paradoxical hyperinflammation in COVID-19 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">The signal pathways and treatment of cytokine storm in COVID-19 <lb/>Yang et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Signal Transduction and Targeted Therapy (2021) 6:255 <lb/></note>

			<body>colony-stimulating factor (G-CSF); granulocyte-macrophage colony-<lb/>stimulating factor (GM-CSF); and monocyte chemoattractant <lb/>protein-1 (MCP-1). 26,33,60,81-86 Reports of hemophagocytosis and <lb/>clinical benefits from cytokine-targeted therapies in severe COVID-<lb/>19 patients further confirmed the existence and pathogenesis of <lb/>COVID-CS. 87,88 Existing evidence has characterized and distinguished <lb/>COVID-CS from CS in variable conditions such as HLH induced by <lb/>specific viral infections, 89 macrophage activation syndrome (MAS) <lb/>occurring after autoimmune disorders, 90 and cytokine release <lb/>syndrome (CRS) caused by CAR T cell therapy 23 in several aspects. <lb/>First, COVID-CS involves more inflammatory cytokines than other CS <lb/>conditions, thereby providing an explanation for the aggressive <lb/>nature of COVID-19. Second, lymphopenia, although relatively less <lb/>frequent in other CS, was often observed in patients with COVID-<lb/>CS, 88 suggesting that COVID-CS may be mainly attributed to innate <lb/>-rather than adaptive immune cells. Finally, compared with <lb/>bacterial infection-induced CS (e.g., sepsis), the treatment of <lb/>COVID-CS is more challenging, because blocking inflammatory <lb/>cytokine function without effective anti-viral drug support may <lb/>exacerbate the infection. <lb/>The initiation of COVID-CS induction during infection and the <lb/>predominant causative cytokine in COVID-19 immunopathology <lb/>remain largely unknown. Despite the lack of definite pathogen-<lb/>associated molecule pattern (PAMP) of SARS-CoV-2, in analogy <lb/>with SARS-CoV and MERS-CoV, it can be speculated that upon <lb/>cellular entry of SARS-CoV-2 via its ACE2 receptor, viral genomic <lb/>single-stranded RNA or other RNA compositions (double-stranded <lb/>RNA) as PAMPs can be sensed by the related PRRs, including TLRs <lb/>and RLRs in host cells. The downstream transcription factors IRF3/ <lb/>7 and NF-κB are activated following PAMP recognition to induce <lb/>the production of IFN-I and pro-inflammatory cytokines, respec-<lb/>tively. 91-93 However, as mentioned above, the protective IFN-I <lb/>response is quickly and selectively abrogated by SARS-CoV-2 via <lb/>different mechanisms. This is accompanied by an overwhelming <lb/>production of pro-inflammatory cytokines in the context of <lb/>COVID-19, which not only impairs viral clearance but also <lb/>promotes paradoxical hyperinflammation including CS. Therefore, <lb/>from the immunology perspective, COVID-CS may be an <lb/>unfortunate event whereby the intended host immune response <lb/>combating the SARS-CoV-2 has lost control and transformed into <lb/>an inflammatory type. 15 <lb/>In SARS-CoV-2 infection, the virus infects the respiratory <lb/>epithelial tissue and activates local innate immune cells to release <lb/>inflammatory cytokines such as IL-1, IL-6, IL-8, IL-12, TNF-α, and <lb/>other chemokines. These inflammatory cytokines and chemokines <lb/>then recruit more innate immune cells (monocytes, macrophages, <lb/>neutrophils, DCs, and NK cells) and activate adaptive immune cells <lb/>(CD4 + and CD8 + T cells) from the peripheral tissues to produce <lb/>sustained inflammatory cytokines like IL-2, IFN-γ, and TNF-α, which <lb/>induce myelopoiesis and emergency granulopoiesis that further <lb/>aggravate lung and epithelial damage (Fig. 4). In addition, <lb/>overproduction of systemic cytokines, particularly IL-2, IFN-γ, <lb/>GM-CSF, and TNF-α, triggers macrophage activation (i.e., MAS) and <lb/>erythro-phagocytosis (i.e., HLH), resulting in anemia, 94,95 as well as <lb/>causes perturbation of coagulation and vascular hemostasis, <lb/>resulting in capillary leak syndrome, thrombosis, 96 and DIC. These <lb/>events together lead to ARDS, multiorgan failure, and death <lb/>(Fig. 4). 15 Of note, the host immunoregulatory system is usually <lb/>capable of retaining and fine-tuning the protective inflammation <lb/>to an appropriate level. Regulatory cells such as Tregs 97,98 can <lb/>produce regulatory cytokines like IL-10 and tumor growth factor-β <lb/>to antagonize overactivated immune responses. 99,100 However, <lb/>aggressive inflammatory conditions such as CS cannot be calmed <lb/>by the regulatory system&apos;s natural ability. <lb/>Although the immunological and pathological understanding of <lb/>COVID-CS has provided valuable information regarding the <lb/>development of diagnosis and treatment strategies, detailed <lb/>guidelines are still lacking. Developing scoring systems such as <lb/>Fig. 4 The immunopathological mechanisms of COVID-CS. SARS-CoV-2 infects the epithelial cells or immune cells, causing tissue damage and <lb/>release of inflammatory cytokines (e.g., IL-1, IL-6, IL-12, and TNFα) by epithelial cells and immune cells. These inflammatory cytokines then <lb/>recruit innate immune cells (monocytes, macrophages, neutrophils, DCs, and NK cells) and activate adaptive immune cells (CD4 + T cells and <lb/>CD8 + T cells) to induce the occurrence of myelopoiesis and emergency granulopoiesis, as well as the production of sustained and excessive <lb/>circulating cytokines that can further aggravate epithelial damage. In addition, overproduction of systemic cytokines triggers macrophage <lb/>activation (i.e., MAS) and erythro-phagocytosis (i.e., HLH), resulting in anemia and gives rise to perturbation of vascular hemostasis, resulting in <lb/>capillary leak syndrome, thrombosis, and DIC. These events together lead to ARDS, multiorgan failure, and death. HLH hemophagocytic <lb/>lymphohistiocytosis, MAS macrophage activation syndrome, ARDS acute respiratory distress syndrome, DIC disseminated intravascular <lb/>coagulation <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">The signal pathways and treatment of cytokine storm in COVID-19 <lb/>Yang et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Signal Transduction and Targeted Therapy (2021) 6:255 <lb/></note>

			<body>HScore, MS score, HLH-2004, Penn grading scale, and the <lb/>Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events may be <lb/>beneficial to predict COVID-CS or related outcomes. Caricchio <lb/>et al. 101 proposed predictive criteria for COVID-CS diagnosis. These <lb/>criteria comprise three clusters: (1) albumin &lt;2.87 mg/mL, <lb/>lymphocytes &lt;10.2%, neutrophil absolute count &gt;11.4 × 10 3 /mL; <lb/>(2) alanine aminotransferase &gt;60 IU/L, aspartate aminotransferase <lb/>&gt;87 IU/L, D-dimer &gt;4930 ng/mL, lactate dehydrogenase &gt;416 U/L, <lb/>troponin I &gt;1.09 ng/mL; and (3) anion gap &lt;6.8 mmol/L, chloride <lb/>&gt;106 mmol/L, potassium &gt;4.9 mmol/L, and blood urea nitrogen: <lb/>creatinine ratio &gt;29. In addition, ferritin &gt;250 ng/mL and <lb/>C-reactive protein (CRP) &gt;4.6 mg/dL are added for the reassurance <lb/>of ongoing systemic inflammation. In another study, the authors <lb/>proposed that a diagnostic criterion including peripheral blood <lb/>oxygen saturation to the fraction of inspired oxygen (SpO 2 /FiO 2 ), <lb/>CRP, ferritin, cytokines/chemokines, and neutrophil/lymphocyte <lb/>ratio may have a strong diagnostic power for COVID-CS. 102 Mehta <lb/>et al. 13 proposed that prospective screening for hyperinflamma-<lb/>tion using laboratory assays and the HScore should be performed <lb/>in all severely ill COVID-19 patients to identify COVID-CS. Despite <lb/>the requirement for further validation, these criteria indeed <lb/>provide constructive suggestions for the development of officially <lb/>recognized guidelines for COVID-CS. <lb/>COVID-CS is a complicated and dynamic inflammatory process <lb/>caused by a group of cytokines from initiation, immune cell <lb/>hyperactivation, to organ dysfunction. The development of <lb/>precise therapeutic intervention in appropriate time is required <lb/>to effectively control COVID-CS. In principle, the treatment <lb/>strategy is to control ongoing inflammatory response by <lb/>specifically or nonspecifically targeting inflammatory cytokines <lb/>or related signaling pathways and to resume the host <lb/>immunoregulatory system. Herein, we discuss the role of the <lb/>key cytokines and associated signal pathways involved in <lb/>COVID-CS (Fig. 5). <lb/>IL-6/JAK/STAT signaling. A retrospective, multicenter study <lb/>including 150 patients from Wuhan, China showed significantly <lb/>elevated levels of IL-6 in severe COVID-19 cases. 103 A study from <lb/>Germany showed that IL-6 &gt;80 pg/mL in combination with CRP <lb/>&gt;97 mg/L presented a relatively high specificity and sensitivity to <lb/>predict respiratory failure. 104 In addition, other studies have also <lb/>shown the remarkably increased serum levels of IL-6 in patients <lb/>with severe COVID-19. 68,105,106 <lb/>IL-6, first produced by monocytes, macrophages, and DCs, <lb/>serves as a prominent activator of the JAK/STAT3 pathway in the <lb/>context of inflammation. Recent studies have determined that the <lb/>IL-6-JAK-STAT3 axis is closely related to the severity of COVID-<lb/>19, 107,108 and the levels of phosphorylated STAT3 were higher in <lb/>different subsets of leukocytes in COVID-19 patients than in <lb/>healthy controls. 109 IL-6 deploys two signaling pathways-classic <lb/>cis-signaling and trans-signaling-to trigger the activation of <lb/>downstream JAK/STAT3 signaling through the membrane-bound <lb/>(mIL-6R) and soluble form of IL-6R (sIL-6R), respectively. 110 In cis-<lb/>signaling, IL-6 binds to mIL-6Rs that are restrictedly expressed on <lb/>immune cells, forming an IL-6/IL-6R/gp130 complex to activate <lb/>downstream JAK/STAT3, Akt/mTOR, and MAPK signaling. This <lb/>exerts pleiotropic effects on immune cells, which are manifested <lb/>as promoted differentiation of T-helper type 17 (Th17), CD8 + T, <lb/>and B cells; increased migration of neutrophils; and reduced <lb/>development of Tregs. 111,112 These, in turn, induce increased <lb/>secretion of IL-6 and aggravate inflammation. In trans-signaling, <lb/>circulating IL-6 binds to sIL-6Rs to form a complex, then binds with <lb/>the gp130 dimer that is expressed on almost all cell types. The <lb/>resultant activation of the JAK-STAT3 signaling occurs in cells with <lb/>absent expression of mIL-6R, such as endothelial cells and vascular <lb/>smooth muscle cells (VSMCs). The overwhelming activation of the <lb/>IL-6-IL-6R-JAK-STAT3 pathway triggers the secretion of various <lb/>mediators, such as IL-6 itself, IL-8, MCP-1, and vascular endothelial <lb/>growth factor (VEGF), and reduces the expression of E-cadherin <lb/>Fig. 5 Inflammatory signaling cascades activated in COVID-CS. SARS-CoV-2 enters the host cells and is sensed by toll-like receptors (TLRs)3, 7, <lb/>8; RIG-I-like receptor, RIG-I or MDA5; and NOD-like receptor, NLRP3, that can also be directly activated by viral proteins or ROS released by <lb/>apoptotic or inflamed cells. The downstream transcription factors IRF3/7 are activated to induce the production of IFN-I and related <lb/>paradoxical hyperinflammation; NF-κB is activated to induce the production of pro-inflammatory cytokines; and NLRP3 inflammasome is <lb/>activated to induce the production of mature IL-1β and IL-18. Pro-inflammatory cytokines such as IL-6, IL-2, TNF-α, and IFN-γ in turn activate <lb/>the JAK-STAT or NF-κB signaling via binding to their receptors expressed on immune cells to induce more production of pro-inflammatory <lb/>genes, forming a positive feedback to trigger the threshold of CS. Conversely, regulatory cytokines like IL-10 are compensatorily produced to <lb/>antagonize immune hyperactivity <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">The signal pathways and treatment of cytokine storm in COVID-19 <lb/>Yang et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Signal Transduction and Targeted Therapy (2021) 6:255 <lb/></note>

			<body>expressed on endothelial cells. 113 Several studies have shown that <lb/>MCP-1 can facilitate the formation of atherogenesis, 114 production <lb/>of adhesion molecules, 115,116 and proliferation and migration of <lb/>VSMCs, 117 which partly explains the occurrence of cardiovascular <lb/>symptoms observed in COVID-CS. In addition, increased VEGF and <lb/>decreased E-cadherin can lead to vascular permeability and <lb/>leakage and accelerate the presence of hypotension and <lb/>pulmonary dysfunction in COVID-CS. 87 Moreover, IL-6 can <lb/>promote the secretion of various acute-phase proteins such as <lb/>CRP, hepcidin, fibrinogen, thrombopoietin, complement C3, and <lb/>ferritin in hepatocytes. 118,119 Collectively, IL-6 contributes to both <lb/>immune cell hyperactivation and target organ dysfunction in CS. <lb/>Evidence has suggested that the production of IL-6 can be <lb/>induced by angiotensin II in inflamed vessels. The underlying <lb/>mechanism is that angiotensin II binds to angiotensin II type 1 <lb/>(AT1) receptor and then activates JAK/STAT signaling to induce IL-<lb/>6 production. 120,121 Interestingly, existing studies have shown that <lb/>SARS-CoV may promote the expression of angiotensin II by <lb/>downregulating ACE2, 122,123 which potentially leads to the <lb/>possibility that SARS-CoV-2 enhances IL-6 production via the <lb/>angiotensin II/AT1 receptor/JAK/STAT axis, and the positive pro-<lb/>inflammatory feedback of IL-6/JAK/STAT ultimately drives clinical <lb/>signatures of COVID-19, especially COVID-CS. 124 <lb/>IFN-γ/JAK/STAT signaling. IFN-γ, mainly produced by macro-<lb/>phages, T cells, and NK cells, participates in immunological <lb/>processes such as inflammation. It is a dominating driver of <lb/>macrophage, NK, and T cell activation, and exerts a predominant <lb/>effect on protective immunity against bacterial and viral infections <lb/>through the activation of JAK1/JAK2 complex and downstream <lb/>STAT1-IFN-γ-activated site (GAS) cascades. 125-127 <lb/>Evidence has shown that IFN-γ is highly involved in various CS-<lb/>related disorders, 128 as illustrated by its pathological role in <lb/>primary HLH, a syndrome of failure to eliminate pathogens owing <lb/>to impaired NK cell activity. In such cases, despite excessive T cell <lb/>activation and large quantities of IFN-γ production, the increased <lb/>IFN-γ levels fail to combat pathogens and instead cause <lb/>immunopathology because of defective NK activity. 129 Whether <lb/>IFN-γ plays a specific role in COVID-CS is still unknown; however, <lb/>considering its role in promoting immune cell activation, we can <lb/>speculate that it contributes substantially to COVID-CS. <lb/>Numerous studies have reported elevated levels of IFN-γ in <lb/>patients with COVID-19. 9,130,131 Of note, one study showed that <lb/>IFN-γ produced by CD4 + T cells was decreased in patients with <lb/>severe disease compared to those with moderate disease, which <lb/>could be explained by the reduced numbers and functional <lb/>exhaustion of T cells in severe COVID-19, 132 as described-above. <lb/>Therefore, this study suggested that elevated levels of IFN-γ in <lb/>COVID-19 are produced mainly by macrophages, not T cells. <lb/>TNFα/NF-κB signaling. TNFα is a well-known pro-inflammatory <lb/>cytokine and is closely associated with many infectious, auto-<lb/>immune diseases, and cancer, and is primarily produced by <lb/>monocytes, macrophages, and T cells. 133,134 NF-κB plays an <lb/>evolutionarily conserved role in the immune system, 135,136 espe-<lb/>cially in regulating the expression of various vital cytokines involved <lb/>in inflammation. 137 TNFα, as an initial driver of NF-κB activation, can <lb/>activate the NF-κB signaling pathway to induce the expression of <lb/>several pro-inflammatory and antiapoptotic genes through its <lb/>receptor TNFR1 and a series of intermediate adapters. 138-140 In turn, <lb/>NF-κB can induce TNFα expression in the context of inflammation, <lb/>such as lipopolysaccharide (LPS) stimulation. 141 Therefore, TNFα/NF-<lb/>κB signaling may play pathological roles in the stage of initiation <lb/>and immune cell hyperactivation in CS by inducing apoptosis of <lb/>epithelial cells to drive the epithelium-immune cell interplay and <lb/>augmenting systemic inflammation. <lb/>Previous studies have found that excessive TNFα represented a <lb/>poor prognosis in SARS-CoV and MERS cases, 142-145 and inhibition <lb/>of NF-κB improved pulmonary symptoms in SARS-CoV-infected <lb/>mice. 146 However, the role of TNFα in COVID-19 is, so far, still not <lb/>entirely clear. Recent studies have reported elevated serum levels of <lb/>TNFα in severe COVID-19 cases. 9,13,24,81 In addition, a clinical trial <lb/>from Wuhan, China, including 522 patients and 40 healthy controls <lb/>showed that the concentration of TNFα was negatively correlated <lb/>with T cell counts in COVID-19 patients. 27 In contrast, a clinical trial <lb/>from Chongqing, China, including 102 mild and 21 severe cases <lb/>showed that TNFα levels were within the normal values in almost all <lb/>COVID-19 patients (121/123). 147 Thus, further research is urgently <lb/>required to better understand the role of TNFα in COVID-CS. <lb/>Although a recent report suggested that inhibition of the TNFα-NF-<lb/>κB pathway may have protective effects in COVID-19, 124 caution <lb/>should be applied based on two aspects: (1) as mentioned above, <lb/>the roles of TNFα in COVID-CS is still undefined; (2) blocking NF-κB <lb/>nonspecifically may simultaneously impair its protective functions <lb/>in cellular homeostasis, as exemplified by a general suppression on <lb/>innate immunity. 148 <lb/>NLRP3/IL-1β signaling. IL-1β is perhaps the most well-studied <lb/>member of the IL-1 family because of its prominent role in <lb/>autoinflammatory diseases such as gout and chronic inflammatory <lb/>arthritis. 149-151 IL-1β is mainly secreted by macrophages via <lb/>apoptosis and pyroptosis and exerts positive effects on the <lb/>migration of immune cells to inflamed tissues; Th17 cell <lb/>differentiation; expression and release of various cytokines and <lb/>adhesion factors; and NF-κB pathway activation to form a positive <lb/>feedback for its own production. 152,153 Upstream, the NLRP3 <lb/>protein forms a complex with apoptosis-associated speck-like <lb/>protein containing a caspase recruitment domain (ASC) and <lb/>cysteinyl aspartate-specific proteinase-1 (caspase-1), termed the <lb/>NLRP3 inflammasome, to cleave the inactive IL-1β precursor to the <lb/>mature form of IL-1β. 154,155 Considering the positive roles of IL-1β <lb/>in activating initiative and sustained inflammation, 156 it was <lb/>postulated that NLRP3-IL-1β signaling might be involved in <lb/>COVID-CS. <lb/>Multiple indicators from previous evidence have suggested that <lb/>IL-1β may contribute to CS in coronavirus infections. 157-159 Zhang <lb/>et al. 160 reported the elevated levels of multiple cytokines <lb/>including IL-1β in COVID-19 cases with severe symptoms, which <lb/>were also associated with SARS, hypercoagulation, and DIC. <lb/>Consistently, Huang et al. 9 also showed high serum concentrations <lb/>of IL-1β in COVID-19 patients. Moreover, a previous study showed <lb/>that NLRP3 can be directly activated by viral proteins of SARS-CoV <lb/>such as ORF3a and ORF8b, 161,162 which were also found on the <lb/>genome of SARS-CoV-2, 163 suggesting a potentially similar effect <lb/>of direct activation of the NLRP3 by SARS-CoV-2 protein. The <lb/>potential roles of NLRP3 inflammasome in severe COVID-19 have <lb/>been discussed in relevant reviews. 164,165 Reactive oxygen species <lb/>(ROS) was reportedly an initiator of NLRP3 activation. 166-168 Thus, <lb/>it was proposed that excessive production of ROS resulting from <lb/>inflammation infiltration in severe COVID-19 may lead to NLRP3 <lb/>activation and IL-1β precursor cleavage, further aggravating <lb/>inflammation in COVID-CS. <lb/>IL-2/IL-2R/JAK/STAT5 signaling. IL-2 is mainly secreted by CD4 + <lb/>T cells and plays crucial roles in the expansion and differentiation <lb/>of CD4 + T, CD8 + T, NK, and other cells through the IL-<lb/>2R-JAK-STAT5 signaling pathway. 169,170 IL-2 can fine-tune <lb/>immune responses and maintain self-tolerance, 171 and its <lb/>deficiency accounts for the occurrence of autoimmune dis-<lb/>eases. 172 <lb/>Elevated levels of IL-2 have been reported in other types of <lb/>coronavirus infections. 173,174 Recent studies have also shown that <lb/>the concentrations of IL-2 or IL-2R were elevated in COVID-19 <lb/>patients, especially in those with severe illness. 9,13,24,132 However, <lb/>a clinical trial including 54 COVID-19 patients from Beijing, China, <lb/>reported a contradictory result. The authors found that compared <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">The signal pathways and treatment of cytokine storm in COVID-19 <lb/>Yang et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Signal Transduction and Targeted Therapy (2021) 6:255 <lb/></note>

			<body>with severe patients (n = 14), those with a critical illness (n = 6) <lb/>had remarkably reduced plasma levels of IL-2. Accordingly, IL-2Rα <lb/>levels were significantly decreased in the PBMCs of patients with a <lb/>severe and critical illness compared to common patients (n = 34) <lb/>or healthy controls. Furthermore, the levels of JAK1 and STAT5 <lb/>were significantly lower in all three groups than in normal <lb/>controls. Considering the supportive roles of IL-2 in the expansion <lb/>and differentiation of T cells, the authors speculated that the <lb/>presence of lymphopenia especially in severe COVID-19 may be <lb/>attributed to reduced levels of IL-2, IL-2R, JAK1, and STAT5. 175 In <lb/>additionally, CD4 + T cells are the primary source of IL-2, and the <lb/>reduced numbers of lymphocytes during the stage of CS after <lb/>COVID-19 infection can at least partly explain the reduced IL-2 <lb/>level and downregulation of IL-2 signaling. Future investigations <lb/>are required to confirm these findings in more patients. <lb/>IL-7/IL-7R signaling. IL-7/IL-7R signaling is essential for peripheral <lb/>homeostasis and the survival, differentiation, and maintenance of <lb/>T cells including CD4 + T, CD8 + T, naive T, and memory T cells. 176-<lb/>179 It is also indispensable for the development and maintenance <lb/>of innate lymphoid cells (ILCs), formation of lymphoid structures, <lb/>and barrier defense. 180 <lb/>Recent reports have shown elevated levels of IL-7 in COVID-19 <lb/>patients, and these increases were related to disease sever-<lb/>ity. 9,13,147 However, the impact of enhanced levels of IL-7 in <lb/>COVID-19 is largely unknown. Considering the protective role of <lb/>IL-7, we can speculate that the increase of IL-7 may be a feedback <lb/>mechanism in response to the lymphopenia in patients with <lb/>severe/critical COVID-19. <lb/>IL-10 signaling. IL-10 is an important immunoregulatory cytokine <lb/>produced by a variety of immune cells including Th2 cells, Tregs, <lb/>CD8 + T cells, B cells, DCs, macrophages, and NK cells, and signals <lb/>through the IL-10R/JAK/STAT3 pathway. IL-10 exerts anti-<lb/>inflammatory functions by directly limiting the innate immune-<lb/>related functions of macrophages and DCs in an autocrine and <lb/>paracrine manner or indirectly via improving Treg development. In <lb/>addition, IL-10 can activate mast cells and strengthen the <lb/>functions of CD8 + T, B, and NK cells. 181 <lb/>A clinical trial including 102 COVID-19 patients and 45 controls <lb/>from Wuhan, China, showed that the serum IL-10 levels of patients <lb/>with a critical illness (n = 17) were significantly higher than those <lb/>of patients with moderate (n = 42) and severe (n = 43) illness; <lb/>further, the IL-10 levels were positively correlated with the <lb/>concentrations of serum CRP, indicating the potential of IL-10 as <lb/>an indicator of disease severity. 182 Huang et al. 9 also reported the <lb/>significantly high plasma levels of IL-10 in COVID-19 patients <lb/>admitted to the ICU compared to those who were not. In addition, <lb/>a follow-up clinical trial including 71 COVID-19 patients (53 mild <lb/>and 18 severe) from Beijing, China and 18 controls showed that <lb/>the production of IL-10 in the early stage was significantly <lb/>correlated with disease severity. 183 <lb/>It can be speculated that the excessive production of IL-10 is a <lb/>negative feedback mechanism to antagonize the hyperactivity of <lb/>the immune system. However, when faced with an overwhelming <lb/>secretion of inflammatory mediators and activation of pro-<lb/>inflammatory cells in COVID-CS, the fine-tune function of IL-10 is <lb/>rather inadequate. Thus, administration of IL-10 has been <lb/>recommended to treat ARDS in COVID-19. 184 However, a recent <lb/>report showed that IL-10 may be detrimental in the initiation <lb/>phase of SARS-CoV-2 infection by promoting T cell exhaustion. <lb/>The authors proposed that blocking IL-10 with a neutralizing <lb/>antibody in the initiation stage of SARS-CoV-2 infection may be a <lb/>promising therapeutic approach. 185 <lb/>IL-12 signaling. IL-12, mainly produced by DCs, macrophages, <lb/>and B lymphocytes, 186 is a multifunctional immunoregulatory <lb/>factor that can promote proliferation of Th1 and Th17 cells; <lb/>improve the cytotoxicity of NK cells; and induce expression of IFN-<lb/>γ in Th1 cells, NK cells, DCs, and macrophages via a positive <lb/>feedback mechanism. 187,188 Thus, IL-12 plays an aggressive role in <lb/>CS by augmenting the activation of various immune cells. <lb/>Existing studies have reported that viral infections induce the <lb/>production of IL-12 to defend against infections. 189-191 For <lb/>instance, during influenza virus infection, IL-12 is endogenously <lb/>produced to induce the secretion of IFN-γ from Th1 and NK cells, <lb/>thereby inhibiting viral replication. 190 A previous study reported <lb/>elevated plasma levels of IL-12 in patients infected by SARS-<lb/>CoV. 192 However, Huang et al. 9 recently found that the plasma <lb/>levels of IL-12p70 showed no difference between COVID-19 <lb/>patients and healthy adults. Therefore, further research with large-<lb/>sized samples is urgently required to determine the alterations <lb/>and functions of IL-12 in COVID-19, especially COVID-CS. <lb/>IL-17 signaling. IL-17 (primarily IL-17A) is produced by Th17, <lb/>CD8 + T, and group 3 ILC (ILC3) and participates in many pro-<lb/>inflammatory processes and autoimmune diseases. 193-195 Target-<lb/>ing IL-17 is now regarded as a common strategy to reduce the <lb/>burden of several autoimmune diseases such as psoriasis and <lb/>psoriatic arthritis. Nevertheless, the functions of this inflammatory <lb/>cytokine vary, from being protective against infections to having <lb/>detrimental pro-inflammatory effects, depending on the tissue <lb/>type and location (gut, lung, or skin) where it is being expressed <lb/>and its triggering factors. 196 <lb/>Increased levels of IL-17 were previously reported in SARS-CoV-<lb/>or MERS-CoV-infected patients. 197,198 In addition, IL-17 can <lb/>augment lung injury and decrease overall survival through <lb/>recruitment of neutrophils; stimulate the expression of pro-<lb/>inflammatory factors; and induce the expression of G-CSF to <lb/>prevent apoptosis in both ARDS and an LPS-induced acute lung <lb/>injury model. 199,200 Similarly, evidence has suggested that IL-17 <lb/>levels were elevated in COVID-19 patients, especially in those with <lb/>a severe and critical illness. 201 Asrani and Hassan 156 showed that <lb/>IL-17 plays crucial roles in the stages of immune cell hyperactiva-<lb/>tion and target organ dysfunction in COVID-CS by promoting the <lb/>recruitment of neutrophils and producing symptoms such as <lb/>fever, matrix damage, tissue remodeling, and inflammatory <lb/>infiltration. <lb/>Despite multiple evidence suggesting the potential of IL-17 as <lb/>an intervention target for COVID-CS, studies have shown that the <lb/>levels of IL-17 were within normal ranges in 102 and 21 patients <lb/>with mild and severe COVID-19, respectively. 147 Therefore, more <lb/>clinical trials and fundamental research are required for further <lb/>clarification. <lb/>GM-CSF signaling. GM-CSF is produced by endothelial, epithelial, <lb/>hematopoietic, and other cell types. 202 Under physiological <lb/>conditions, low levels of GM-CSF can regulate the homeostasis <lb/>of alveolar macrophages to maintain their antimicrobial func-<lb/>tions. 203,204 Under hyperinflammatory conditions such as CS, GM-<lb/>CSF drives emergency myelopoiesis and recruits myeloid cells to <lb/>the inflammatory sites to perpetuate inflammatory reactions. 205 <lb/>Increased levels of GM-CSF have been observed in SARS, 206 <lb/>ARDS, 207 and CRS. 208 A recent study also reported elevated GM-<lb/>CSF levels in both severe and mild COVID-19. 9 <lb/>Given the role of GM-CSF in maintaining antimicrobial functions <lb/>of alveolar macrophages, administration of GM-CSF to patients <lb/>with early-stage COVID-19 may strengthen the alveolar wall and <lb/>enhance viral clearance. 209 In contrast, the blockade of GM-CSF <lb/>signaling may achieve clinical benefits in COVID-CS. <lb/>CYTOKINE-BASED INTERVENTIONS <lb/>The current treatment for CS is mainly based on traditional anti-<lb/>inflammatory drugs such as the administration of corticosteroids, <lb/>chloroquine, and colchicines. 210,211 Recently, biologics like <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">The signal pathways and treatment of cytokine storm in COVID-19 <lb/>Yang et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Signal Transduction and Targeted Therapy (2021) 6:255 <lb/></note>

			<body>recombinant cytokines; monoclonal antibodies against IL-6, IL-1β, <lb/>TNF-α, and IFN-γ; and signaling pathway inhibitors are also <lb/>available or in the pipeline for production. In this and the next <lb/>section, we aim to discuss the key biologics that are currently or <lb/>potentially applied to treat CS (Fig. 6). <lb/>IFN-I <lb/>Administration of IFN-I has previously been investigated for the <lb/>treatment of SARS-CoV and MERS-CoV. Generally, it was found to <lb/>be relatively effective in vitro and in some animal models, 212 <lb/>although human studies were inconclusive. 213 <lb/>The research team at the University of Texas Medical Branch, <lb/>USA, showed that low concentrations of IFN-α and IFN-β <lb/>effectively reduced virus titer and inhibited viral replication in <lb/>Vero cells in a dose-dependent manner, and they also found that <lb/>SARS-CoV-2 is more sensitive than SARS-CoV to IFN-I in vitro. 214 An <lb/>uncontrolled, exploratory study from Tongji Medical College, <lb/>Wuhan, China, showed that administration of IFN-α2b alone or in <lb/>combination with arbidol remarkably accelerated virus clearance <lb/>as well as the recovery of IL-6 and CRP to normal levels in COVID-<lb/>19 patients. 215 A randomized, multicenter, prospective, phase 2 <lb/>clinical trial conducted at the University of Hong Kong showed <lb/>that compared with the control group (lopinavir/ritonavir), COVID-<lb/>19 patients in the triple group (IFNβ-1b plus lopinavir/ritonavir + <lb/>ribavirin) exhibited significantly alleviated symptoms; shortened <lb/>virus shedding and hospital stay; and improved inflammatory <lb/>conditions (NCT04276688). 216 A prospective study including 2944 <lb/>healthy medical staff in the epidemic areas from Taihe Hospital in <lb/>Shiyan City, Hubei, China, showed that the incidence rate of <lb/>COVID-19 was zero in both the low-risk group (n = 2415) and the <lb/>high-risk group (n = 529) after treatment with recombinant IFN-α <lb/>nose drops for 30 days (NCT04320238), 217 indicating the <lb/>preventive roles of recombinant IFN-α in COVID-19. A trial <lb/>comparing the clinical efficacy of subcutaneous IFN-β1a plus <lb/>lopinavir/ritonavir with lopinavir/ritonavir alone; hydroxychloro-<lb/>quine; and remdesivir in COVID-19 is still ongoing (NCT04315948). <lb/>Collectively, these studies suggested that IFN-I can inhibit SARS-<lb/>CoV-2 infection and potential COVID-CS. <lb/>Another type of interferon-IFN-III-may also have a clinical <lb/>benefit in COVID-19 treatment. Dinnon et al. 218 confirmed the <lb/>anti-viral effect of pegylated IFN-λ1a in both SARS-CoV-2-infected <lb/>human airway epithelial cells and mouse models. Some studies <lb/>have determined that MDA5 plays a leading role in activating IFN-<lb/>I/III response to defend against SARS-CoV-2 in human epithelial <lb/>cells, 219-221 which may open a new avenue for enhancing IFN <lb/>response in COVID-19. In addition, several clinical trials evaluating <lb/>the clinical efficacy of IFN-λ are under investigation (NCT04343976, <lb/>NCT04331899). <lb/>IL-7 <lb/>The supportive role of IL-7 in lymphocyte survival and expansion <lb/>provides clinical implications for the recovery of function of <lb/>lymphocytes in severe/critical COVID-19. <lb/>A case report from Hospices Civils de Lyon, France, showed that <lb/>a period of recombinant human IL-7 (rhIL-7) treatment remarkably <lb/>improved the immune function in a 74-year-old ICU patient with <lb/>severe COVID-19, which manifested as elevated lymphocyte count <lb/>and mHLA-DR expression. In this case, IL-7 was administered quite <lb/>late, on day 24 of admission. Thus, the authors prospectively <lb/>proposed that earlier administration of IL-7 may have indicated <lb/>better clinical outcomes. 222 In a case series from St. Luc University <lb/>Hospital, Brussels, Belgium, the authors showed that patients in <lb/>the IL-7 treatment group seemed to have higher levels of <lb/>lymphocyte counts than those in the control group, without <lb/>aggravated inflammation and pulmonary injury. 223 Unfortunately, <lb/>the absence of detailed phenotypic or functional studies on <lb/>lymphocytes weakens the reliability of these studies. A multi-<lb/>center, double-blind clinical trial in a UK-based cohort is currently <lb/>evaluating whether the administration of CYT107 (a commercial <lb/>product of rhIL-7) can result in clinical improvement of patients <lb/>with severe COVID-19 through immune reconstitution <lb/>(NCT04379076). Clark et al. 224 proposed that administration of <lb/>Fig. 6 The potential inhibitors and therapies to counteract COVID-CS. A variety of inhibitors or drugs have been applied or are under <lb/>consideration to treat COVID-CS, including those targeting a single pro-inflammatory cytokine or its receptor and related signal pathway. In <lb/>addition, several treatments such as intravenous immunoglobulin, corticosteroids, traditional Chinese medicine, and CDK7 inhibitor may have <lb/>the potential to counteract multiple cytokines and pathways involved in COVID-CS. CDK7 cyclin-dependent kinase 7 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">The signal pathways and treatment of cytokine storm in COVID-19 <lb/>Yang et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Signal Transduction and Targeted Therapy (2021) 6:255 <lb/></note>

			<body>IL-7 in combination with dexamethasone may be an optimal <lb/>treatment for severe COVID-19. The underlying mechanism is that <lb/>dexamethasone enhances IL-7 activity by upregulating its receptor <lb/>IL-7Rα, which can also be used to explain the most effective <lb/>properties of dexamethasone in the more severe stage of the <lb/>disease. 225,226 <lb/>These studies indicate that appropriate administration of IL-7 <lb/>alone or in combination with other agents should be considered <lb/>as early as possible for critical COVID-19 patients with severe <lb/>lymphopenia. <lb/>BLOCKADE OF CYTOKINES <lb/>Blockade of IL-6 <lb/>As mentioned above, IL-6 signaling is a leading inducer of <lb/>COVID-CS. Currently, several drugs targeting IL-6 signaling such <lb/>as IL-6 inhibitors (siltuximab, clazakizumab, sirukumab, olokizu-<lb/>mab) and IL-6R inhibitors (tocilizumab, sarilumab, levilimab) are <lb/>available. 227-229 <lb/>A retrospective clinical trial from Anhui, China, including 21 <lb/>COVID-19 patients with severe or critical illness showed that five <lb/>days of tocilizumab therapy immediately improved the clinical <lb/>outcomes in most patients, manifested as decreased oxygen <lb/>requirements, serum CRP concentrations, and hospital stays, as <lb/>well as the rapid recovery of lymphocyte percentage. 230 Another <lb/>multicenter cohort study including 3924 COVID-19 patients in <lb/>the ICU across 68 hospitals in the United States showed that the <lb/>risk of mortality was lower in 433 patients who received <lb/>tocilizumab treatment immediately after ICU admission than in <lb/>those who did not receive early tocilizumab intervention. 231 In <lb/>addition, numerous reports evaluating the administration of <lb/>tocilizumab for severe COVID-19 have also been pub-<lb/>lished, 106,232-247 and a total of 75 clinical trials are currently <lb/>registered in ClinicalTrials. gov. <lb/>An open-label study from Italy including 56 patients with severe <lb/>COVID-19 showed that after 28 days of follow-up, sarilumab <lb/>treatment (n = 28) appeared to promote the recovery of patients <lb/>with mild lung consolidation (&lt;17%) at baseline. 248 Another <lb/>retrospective, single-center, clinical trial from Italy including 15 <lb/>COVID-19 patients showed that sarilumab treatment improved the <lb/>clinical symptoms and reduced serum CRP levels in most patients <lb/>(n = 10). 249 Currently, a total of 17 clinical trials on sarilumab are <lb/>registered in ClinicalTrials.gov for the treatment of COVID-19. <lb/>A randomized, phase 3, clinical trial evaluating the administra-<lb/>tion of levilimab in patients with severe COVID-19 has been <lb/>completed, but the results have not yet been published <lb/>(NCT04397562). <lb/>An observational, controlled cohort study from Italy including <lb/>30 patients requiring ventilator support showed that the 30-day <lb/>mortality was significantly reduced in those receiving siltuximab <lb/>plus optimal supportive care compared with the control patients <lb/>who received only optimal supportive care; ~50% of patients <lb/>receiving siltuximab treatment were finally discharged <lb/>(NCT04322188). 250 Three other clinical trials evaluating the efficacy <lb/>and safety of siltuximab in severe COVID-19 are underway <lb/>(NCT04329650, NCT04330638, NCT04486521). <lb/>In general, published clinical trials showed positive results with <lb/>respect to some common IL-6 or IL-6R antagonists for the <lb/>treatment of COVID-CS. Several clinical trials of other IL-6 or IL-6R <lb/>antagonists including clazakizumab (NCT04381052, NCT04494724, <lb/>NCT04343989, NCT04363502, NCT04348500, NCT04659772); <lb/>sirukumab (NCT04380961); and olokizumab (NCT04380519, <lb/>NCT04452474) have been registered in ClinicalTrials.gov to <lb/>investigate their therapeutic potential in COVID-CS. <lb/>Blockade of IL-1β <lb/>Considering the pathological role of IL-1β signaling in CS, several <lb/>drugs targeting IL-1β signaling, including IL-1β antagonist <lb/>canakinumab and IL-1 receptor antagonist anakinra, may offer <lb/>clinical benefits in the treatment of COVID-19, particularly in CS. <lb/>A retrospective, three-center, clinical trial from France including 22 <lb/>patients with severe/critical COVID-19 showed that after &gt;8 days of <lb/>treatment, patients in the anakinra group (n = 12) presented <lb/>improved clinical conditions as well as decreased mechanical <lb/>ventilation requirements and serum CRP concentrations, as com-<lb/>pared with the control group (n = 10) (INDS, MR4115050520). 251 A <lb/>prospective, cohort study from the Netherlands showed that several <lb/>clinical parameters including temperature; white blood cell count; <lb/>and levels of plasma ferritin, creatinine, procalcitonin, and bilirubin <lb/>were decreased after 28 days of anakinra treatment. 252 Several other <lb/>studies have also investigated the clinical effects of anakinra on <lb/>COVID-19. 253-261 A total of 35 clinical trials are currently registered in <lb/>ClinicalTrials.gov. <lb/>A retrospective study from Italy reported for the first time <lb/>that subcutaneous administration of 300 mg canakinumab <lb/>rapidly reduced systemic inflammation and improved oxygena-<lb/>tion in COVID-19 patients (n = 10) who presented hyperin-<lb/>flammation but did not require mechanical ventilation. 262 <lb/>Another single-center, cohort study from Italy enrolled 34 <lb/>non-ICU patients with mild or severe COVID-19, with 17 <lb/>receiving standard treatment and 17 receiving 300 mg of <lb/>subcutaneous canakinumab. The results showed that canaki-<lb/>numab treatment significantly increased the PaO 2 /FiO 2 ratio <lb/>and reduced inflammatory indices. 263 These two studies <lb/>suggest that canakinumab treatment may have therapeutic <lb/>potentials in non-ICU patients with mild or severe COVID-19. <lb/>Several other reports have also evaluated the administration of <lb/>canakinumab in COVID-19, 264-266 and six clinical trials are <lb/>currently registered in ClinicalTrials.gov (NCT04348448, <lb/>NCT04476706, NCT04362813, NCT04365153, NCT04510493, <lb/>NCT04278404). <lb/>Blockade of IFN-γ <lb/>Emapalumab, a monoclonal antibody targeting IFN-γ, has been <lb/>approved to treat primary HLH, a condition with elevated serum <lb/>levels of IFN-γ. 267 Considering the contribution of IFN-γ to CS as <lb/>mentioned above, emapalumab may be effective in the treatment <lb/>of COVID-CS. <lb/>A randomized, multicenter, clinical trial from Italy was registered <lb/>to investigate the efficacy of emapalumab treatment in combina-<lb/>tion with anakinra to alleviate hyperinflammation and improve <lb/>respiratory conditions (NCT04324021). Unfortunately, this trial is <lb/>now terminated and no further data are currently available. <lb/>Therefore, other randomized, controlled clinical trials are urgently <lb/>required to address these issues. <lb/>Blockade of TNFα <lb/>Recent studies have provided the theoretical and practical bases <lb/>to support TNFα blockade as a potential strategy for excessive <lb/>cytokine release and hyperinflammation in COVID-19. 268-271 <lb/>Etanercept is a soluble TNFα receptor fusion protein that has <lb/>been used to treat toxic epidermal necrolysis (TEN), a condition of <lb/>systemic hyperinflammation. Owing to the similarities in clinical <lb/>manifestations and pathological characteristics between COVID-19 <lb/>and TEN, Chen et al. 268 proposed the temporary use of etanercept <lb/>as a valuable approach to treat severe COVID-19. A case report <lb/>described that a 60-year-old man who received subcutaneous <lb/>etanercept treatment for spondyloarthritis prior to SARS-CoV-2 <lb/>infection presented no signs of respiratory failure and progressive <lb/>deterioration and showed rapid recovery from COVID-19. 269 <lb/>Infliximab is another clinically approved TNFα blocker. A total of <lb/>four clinical trials of infliximab evaluating its therapeutic potential <lb/>in COVID-19 are currently underway (NCT04425538, NCT04734678, <lb/>NCT04593940, NCT04344249). Adalimumab is a monoclonal <lb/>antibody targeting TNFα and is currently undergoing evaluation <lb/>in two clinical trials (ChiCTR2000030089, NCT04705844). <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">The signal pathways and treatment of cytokine storm in COVID-19 <lb/>Yang et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>10 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Signal Transduction and Targeted Therapy (2021) 6:255 <lb/></note>

			<body>Despite these promising results, we cannot exclude the <lb/>possibility of chance, and hence, randomized, controlled, pro-<lb/>spective clinical trials with a large sample size are urgently <lb/>required for further validation. <lb/>Blockade of IL-12/IL-23 <lb/>IL-12/23 inhibitors currently used in the clinic include risankizu-<lb/>mab, guselkumab, tildrakizumab (targeting IL-23p19), and usteki-<lb/>numab (targeting IL-12/IL-23p40) mainly for chronic inflammatory <lb/>and autoimmune diseases such as psoriasis and inflammatory <lb/>bowel disease. 272-276 A recent review proposed IL-12/IL-23 or IL-23 <lb/>inhibitors as potential interventional targets for the ongoing <lb/>COVID-19 pandemic. 277 <lb/>Several case reports have described the clinical efficacy of IL-12/ <lb/>IL-23 inhibitors including ustekinumab, guselkumab, risankizumab, <lb/>and risankizumab in COVID-19 patients with psoriasis. 278-282 The <lb/>reliability of case reports is relatively weak, which is why <lb/>randomized, controlled, prospective clinical trials are so important. <lb/>A multicenter, randomized, clinical trial is ongoing to evaluate <lb/>the efficacy of risankizumab alone or risankizumab in combination <lb/>with remdesivir in COVID-19 (NCT04583956). <lb/>Blockade of IL-17A <lb/>Several review articles have proposed targeting IL-17A signaling as <lb/>an intervening measure for patients with COVID-CS. 196,283-289 <lb/>Case reports from Italy have shown that patients with a history <lb/>of psoriasis and previous treatment with IL-17A antagonists <lb/>including secukinumab and ixekizumab showed relatively mild <lb/>COVID-19 symptoms or were even asymptomatic. 290-292 A retro-<lb/>spective, observational, multicenter clinical trial from Italy contain-<lb/>ing 5206 patients with psoriasis who have been prescribed <lb/>medications including IL-17 inhibitors showed that only four <lb/>patients were hospitalized for COVID-19, and no deaths <lb/>occurred, 293 indicating the protective role of IL-17A inhibitors in <lb/>COVID-CS and ARDS. However, using the general Italian popula-<lb/>tion as the control group reduces the degree of standardization <lb/>and reliability of this trial. The absence of standard clinical or <lb/>experimental diagnosis for COVID-19 is another limitation. In <lb/>addition, other prospective, randomized, clinical trials evaluating <lb/>the administration of ixekizumab (NCT04724629) and secukinu-<lb/>mab (NCT04403243) in COVID-19 are also underway. In addition, <lb/>many researchers have proposed that simultaneously targeting IL-<lb/>17A signaling and synergic IL-6 signaling may offer more clinical <lb/>benefit for COVID-19 patients, particularly for those who <lb/>experience CS. 283,286 <lb/>Blockade of GM-CSF <lb/>Several studies have reported the protective roles of GM-CSF in <lb/>the early stage of infection, 294-296 and numerous clinical trials of <lb/>human recombinant GM-CSF including sargramostim and mol-<lb/>gramostim have been registered for the treatment of COVID-19; <lb/>however, as mentioned above, GM-CSF indeed exerts a patholo-<lb/>gical function in the phase of CS, implying that blocking GM-CSF <lb/>signaling may achieve clinical benefits in COVID-CS. <lb/>Mavrilimumab is a monoclonal antibody against GM-CSF-Rα. 297 <lb/>A prospective cohort study from Italy including 39 patients with <lb/>severe COVID-19 showed that patients in the mavrilimumab group <lb/>(n = 13) showed earlier improvement, lesser progression to <lb/>mechanical ventilation, and faster fever resolution than those in <lb/>the control group (n = 26). 298 In addition, several clinical trials <lb/>evaluating the administration of mavrilimumab in severe COVID-<lb/>19 have been registered (NCT04447469, NCT04463004, <lb/>NCT04492514, NCT04399980, NCT04397497). <lb/>Lenzilumab is a recombinant monoclonal antibody against <lb/>human GM-CSF. A case-cohort study including 39 patients with <lb/>severe COVID-19 from the USA reported that compared to the <lb/>control group (n = 27), patients who received intravenous <lb/>treatment with lenzilumab (n = 12) exhibited significantly rapid <lb/>clinical improvement; reduced progression to ARDS; and <lb/>decreased inflammatory markers and inflammatory myeloid <lb/>cells. 299 In addition, several clinical trials for lenzilumab have <lb/>been registered for the treatment of severe COVID-19 <lb/>(NCT04351152, NCT04583969, NCT04534725). <lb/>These clinical trials showed that blockade of GM-CSF signaling <lb/>indeed improved clinical outcomes in patients with COVID-CS. <lb/>Moreover, several other GM-CSF inhibitors such as gimsilumab, <lb/>otilimab, and TJ003234 are undergoing clinical evaluation as <lb/>potential COVID-19 therapy (NCT04351243, NCT04376684, <lb/>NCT04341116, respectively). <lb/>BLOCKADE OF SIGNALING PATHWAYS <lb/>Blockade of JAK/STAT signaling <lb/>The JAK/STAT pathway lies downstream of various cytokines <lb/>involved in the CS. Thus, several studies have proposed that the <lb/>JAK/STAT signaling inhibition may be a valuable preventive or <lb/>therapeutic option for COVID-CS. 126,300-305 The clinical efficacy of <lb/>various JAK inhibitors (JAKinibs) such as tofacitinib targeting JAK1 <lb/>and JAK3 306,307 as well as baricitinib and ruxolitinib, both targeting <lb/>JAK1 and JAK2, 308-310 are currently under investigation in clinical <lb/>trials in the context of COVID-19. <lb/>Hoang et al. 311 found that baricitinib treatment significantly <lb/>improved the inflammatory condition in SARS-CoV-2-infected <lb/>rhesus macaque, as manifested by reduced inflammatory cell <lb/>infiltration and neutrophil recruitment; limited lung pathology; <lb/>and suppressed expression of pro-inflammatory mediators in lung <lb/>macrophages. Baricitinib has also been evaluated in a series of <lb/>clinical trials. An observational, longitudinal trial including 76 <lb/>COVID-19 patients showed that compared with the control group <lb/>(n = 56), patients in the baricitinib group (n = 20) presented <lb/>remarkably reduced serum levels of IL-6, IL-1β, and TNF-α; <lb/>accelerated recovery of blood T and B cell counts; increased <lb/>production of antibodies against SARS-CoV-2; and progressively <lb/>increased PaO 2 /FiO 2 ratio (NCT04438629). 109 Another observa-<lb/>tional cohort study from Spain showed that baricitinib improved <lb/>lung function in patients with moderate-to-severe COVID-19 <lb/>receiving corticosteroid treatment. 312 Interestingly, existing stu-<lb/>dies showed that besides the acknowledged inhibitory effects on <lb/>CS, baricitinib can also dampen ACE2-mediated SARS-CoV-2 <lb/>endocytosis by inhibiting AP2-associated protein kinase 1 and <lb/>cyclin G-associated kinase, 313,314 which serves as another mechan-<lb/>ism of its action in COVID-19. Moreover, several other reports have <lb/>also been published, 313,315-322 and numerous clinical trials of <lb/>baricitinib are registered at ClinicalTrials.gov to evaluate its clinical <lb/>effects in severe COVID-19. <lb/>Several studies have shown that ruxolitinib may also be <lb/>effective in the treatment of severe/critical COVID-19. 323-326 In a <lb/>prospective, multicenter, single-blind, phase 2 clinical trial <lb/>including 41 COVID-19 patients from Wuhan, China, compared <lb/>with patients in the placebo group (n = 21), those in the <lb/>ruxolitinib group (n = 20) exhibited remarkably reduced levels of <lb/>seven cytokines, as well as a faster rate of clinical improvement <lb/>and lymphocyte-count recovery. 325 In addition, several other <lb/>clinical trials for ruxolitinib evaluation and six clinical trials that <lb/>are evaluating the administration of tofacitinib in COVID-19 <lb/>patients have been registered at ClinicalTrial.gov (NCT04412252, <lb/>NCT04415151, NCT04750317, NCT04469114, NCT04390061, <lb/>NCT04332042). <lb/>Despite these promising clinical data, JAKinibs should be used <lb/>with caution because of their side effects, based on the following <lb/>considerations: (1) nonselective inhibition of the JAK/STAT path-<lb/>way increases the risk of secondary infection such as herpes zoster <lb/>virus reactivation given its general inhibitory effects on multiple <lb/>aspects of physiological actions, including the innate immune <lb/>system. 327,328 In addition, considering the general immunosup-<lb/>pressive nature, some researchers are concerned that continuous <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">The signal pathways and treatment of cytokine storm in COVID-19 <lb/>Yang et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>11 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Signal Transduction and Targeted Therapy (2021) 6:255 <lb/></note>

			<body>treatment with JAKinibs for autoimmune diseases may increase <lb/>the risk of SARS-CoV-2 infections or contribute to poor outcomes <lb/>in COVID-19. Hence, several retrospective clinical trials have been <lb/>conducted to address these concerns; 329-334 (2) critical COVID-19 <lb/>is commonly accompanied by coagulopathy and thrombosis, and <lb/>the Food and Drug Administration has warned that administration <lb/>of some JAKinibs has increased the risk of thrombosis. 335 Thus, <lb/>developing JAKinibs with better specificity could be a future <lb/>direction of research aimed to prevent/reduce CS and improve the <lb/>survival of COVID-19 patients. <lb/>Blockade of NF-κB signaling <lb/>The overwhelming expression of multiple pro-inflammatory <lb/>proteins in COVID-CS has indicated the central roles of pro-<lb/>inflammatory signaling pathways, and in particular, the NF-κB <lb/>pathway. Immunomodulation of NF-κB activation has been <lb/>proven effective in SARS-CoV-infected cells or mice. 146 Thus, <lb/>recent reviews have proposed that the NF-κB pathway represents <lb/>a potential therapeutic target for critical COVID-19 illness. 336-338 <lb/>An in vitro study showed that phillyrin (KD-1), a well-studied <lb/>anti-inflammatory and antioxidative agent, significantly reduced <lb/>the replication of SARS-CoV-2 and expression of pro-inflammatory <lb/>factors in Huh-7 cells via inhibition of the NF-κB signaling <lb/>pathway. 339 Another study showed that a novel pyrazole <lb/>derivative remarkably reduced the expression of IL-6, TNFα, and <lb/>IL-1β in LPS-stimulated RAW267.4 cells by inhibiting NF-κB <lb/>signaling pathway activation. 340 It has been suggested that <lb/>blocking phosphorylation of the inhibitor of NF-κB kinase subunit <lb/>beta, a primary downstream protein of NF-κB signaling, with <lb/>pharmacological inhibitors may be an effective approach for <lb/>COVID-CS treatment. 339 Moreover, Liu Shen capsules, a traditional <lb/>Chinese medicine, were also reported to exert anti-viral and anti-<lb/>inflammatory effects in SARS-CoV-2-infected Huh-7 and Vero E6 <lb/>cells, respectively, by suppressing the NF-κB signaling cascade. 341 <lb/>The effect of several anti-inflammatory or anti-viral drugs on <lb/>COVID-19 such as dexamethasone, 342 hydroxychloroquine, 343 <lb/>macrolide antibiotics, 344,345 and N-acetylcysteine 346,347 are also <lb/>related to NF-κB cascade inhibition. <lb/>Despite the existence of various nonselective agents for NF-κB <lb/>inhibition, developing selective NF-κB inhibitors and a series of <lb/>clinical trials are urgently required to further validate the clinical <lb/>benefits. <lb/>Blockade of NLRP3 signaling <lb/>Several studies have shown that NLRP3 inflammasome is a <lb/>potential therapeutic target for COVID-CS. 164,348,349 <lb/>NLRP3 signaling inhibition may be a potential mechanism of <lb/>action for several anti-inflammatory drugs effective in COVID-19, <lb/>such as colchicine. Studies have shown that colchicine can <lb/>nonselectively inhibit NLRP3 inflammation by inhibiting the activa-<lb/>tion of P2X7 receptor or the interaction between NLRP3 protein and <lb/>ASC. 350,351 In addition, chloroquine 352 and curcumin 353 are also <lb/>capable of inhibiting NLRP3 signaling. Several investigational agents <lb/>capable of inhibiting NLRP3 activation, such as tranilast, 354 <lb/>dapansutrile (OLT1177, selective inhibitor), 354 and thiazolo-alkenyl <lb/>sulfonylurea derivative 7, 355 are also being considered for COVID-CS <lb/>treatment as reviewed by Freeman and Swartz. 164 In addition, some <lb/>nonselective or selective agents against NLRP3 inflammasome <lb/>including melatonin (NCT04409522), OLT1177 (NCT04540120), açai <lb/>palm berry extract (Euterpe oleracea) (NCT04404218), and ZYIL1 <lb/>(selective inhibitor) (NCT04731324) are under investigation. <lb/>INTERVENTIONS TARGETING MULTIPLE CYTOKINES AND <lb/>PATHWAYS <lb/>Intravenous immunoglobulin (IVIg) therapy <lb/>IVIg is a natural immunoglobulin pool with a highly diverse <lb/>antibody network and is administered to superimpose over a <lb/>patient&apos;s imbalanced repertoire caused by infections. 356 It has <lb/>been known for a while that a broad range of natural anti-cytokine <lb/>autoantibodies such as those against IL-1, IL-6, and IFN-γ can be <lb/>detected in the IVIg of healthy individuals. 357-360 Although how <lb/>the autoantibodies are induced is still poorly understood, it has <lb/>been demonstrated that many of the anti-cytokine autoantibodies <lb/>are neutralizing antibodies and may be responsible for the anti-<lb/>inflammatory effect of IVIg in inflammatory and autoimmune <lb/>disorders. <lb/>The potential efficacy of IVIg therapy was reported in SARS <lb/>and the 2009 H1N1 influenza pandemic. 361,362 In a randomized, <lb/>controlled trial including 84 COVID-19 patients, IVIg treatment <lb/>did not demonstrate any therapeutic benefits in severe cases; <lb/>however, a significant positive relationship between the number <lb/>of days from admission to IVIg treatment and the length of <lb/>hospitalization was observed, 363 which indicated the potential <lb/>clinical benefit of IVIg administration during the early stage of <lb/>COVID-19. In contrast, Suzuki et al. 364 reported the potential <lb/>efficacy of IVIg administration along with mechanical ventilation, <lb/>methylprednisolone, favipiravir, ivermectin, and tocilizumab <lb/>therapy in the late phase in an elderly patient with severe <lb/>COVID-19. <lb/>In general, these studies were inconsistent with respect to the <lb/>timing of IVIg administration, i.e., early phase vs. late phase; <lb/>therefore, a larger number of clinical trials are warranted. <lb/>Corticosteroid treatment <lb/>Corticosteroids are one of the most commonly used anti-<lb/>inflammatory drugs in the treatment of many inflammatory <lb/>disorders. They exert immunoregulatory effects by inhibiting the <lb/>expression of multiple pro-inflammatory cytokines and activation of <lb/>various immune cells. At the beginning of 2020, corticosteroid <lb/>treatment in COVID-19 was either contraindicated or not recom-<lb/>mended, 365 because of the statement that no clinical data indicated <lb/>a benefit from corticosteroid treatment. Moreover, it even increased <lb/>the mortality and secondary infection rates in SARS-CoV and MERS-<lb/>CoV. 366 In March 2020, the RECOVERY trials, one of the largest <lb/>randomized, controlled trials for COVID-19 treatments including <lb/>~15% of all hospitalized COVID-19 patients in the UK, were launched. <lb/>The dexamethasone arm enrolled 2104 patients receiving a low-to-<lb/>moderate dexamethasone dose of 6 mg per day for 10 days and the <lb/>control arm comprised 4321 patients receiving standard care. <lb/>Compared to the control group, dexamethasone treatment reduced <lb/>the 28-day mortality by one-third in mechanically ventilated patients <lb/>and by one-fifth in patients receiving oxygen only, but not in patients <lb/>with no need for ventilated support. 367 Therefore, the UK govern-<lb/>ment (https://www.gov.uk/government/news/world-first-coronaviru <lb/>s-treatment-approved-for-nhs-use-by-government/) and the National <lb/>Institutes of Health in the United States (https://www.covid19treat <lb/>mentguidelines.nih.gov/dexamethasone/) have authorized the stan-<lb/>dard use of dexamethasone in hospitalized COVID-19 patients who <lb/>require oxygen. In addition, a meta-analysis of seven clinical trials <lb/>showed that corticosteroid treatment was associated with a lower <lb/>28-day all-cause mortality in critically ill COVID-19 patients. 225 <lb/>Collectively, the clinical benefit of glucocorticoids in COVID-19 <lb/>treatment is based on the selection of the correct dose, correct <lb/>patient, and appropriate timing. Several studies have shown the <lb/>temporal dynamics of viral shedding in SARS-CoV-2. 368-370 After <lb/>the replicative peaks, immunopathological factors may play a <lb/>dominant role in the illness, while active viral replication may play <lb/>a secondary one. Therefore, the viral load may serve as an <lb/>indicator to determine the precise time of glucocorticoid <lb/>treatment. Moreover, in contrast to other agents, dexamethasone <lb/>is readily available worldwide at a low cost, which is beneficial in <lb/>developing countries with limited access to health care. However, <lb/>although corticosteroid improves clinical syndromes in critically ill <lb/>COVID-19 patients, its impact on CS is still unclear and requires <lb/>further investigation. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">The signal pathways and treatment of cytokine storm in COVID-19 <lb/>Yang et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>12 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Signal Transduction and Targeted Therapy (2021) 6:255 <lb/></note>

			<body>Traditional Chinese medicine (TCM) treatment <lb/>Previous studies have reported the therapeutic effects of several <lb/>TCMs such as Lizhong Decoction, 371 Liujunzi Decoction, 372 and <lb/>Huanglian Jiedu Decoction 373 on inflammatory diseases. Recently, <lb/>TCM treatment has also been shown effective for COVID-19 and <lb/>contributed substantially to control the pandemic in China. For <lb/>example, a multicenter, randomized, controlled trial by Nanshan <lb/>Zhong&apos; research team showed that Lianhuaqingwen capsule, a <lb/>repurposed Chinese herb, can ameliorate clinical symptoms and <lb/>shorten the recovery time in COVID-19 patients with no serious <lb/>adverse effects. 374 <lb/>Several TCMs may play an immunosuppressive role to treat CS via <lb/>multiple cytokines or pathways related to the CS. Yang et al. 375 <lb/>showed that Qingfei Paidu Decoction, one of the most well-known <lb/>anti-COVID-19 formulae, can defend against COVID-19 by regulating <lb/>multiple CS-related signaling pathways such as the NF-κB and MAPK <lb/>pathways and cytokines such as TNF-α, IL-1β, and IL-8. In addition, <lb/>Dai et al. 376 conducted a large-scale transcriptional study to evaluate <lb/>the effects of 578 herbs and all 338 reported anti-COVID-19 TCM <lb/>formulae on CS-related signaling, by combining high-throughput <lb/>sequencing-based screening assay with bioinformatics and <lb/>computer-aided drug design. The results showed that some herbs <lb/>might inhibit the IL-6 pathway, some, the TNF-α pathway, and some <lb/>drugs such as Guizhi and Qingfei Paidu Decoction may inhibit both <lb/>pathways. Together, these studies provide scientific evidence for the <lb/>administration of TCMs in COVID-CS. <lb/>Blockade of cyclin-dependent kinase 7 (CDK7) <lb/>It is challenging to block individual cytokines to achieve the desired <lb/>clinical benefit given the complicated crosstalk of cytokine signaling <lb/>during CS. 377 Thus, developing anti-inflammatory strategies with a <lb/>wide-spectrum inhibitory effect is urgently required. <lb/>CDK7 can regulate cell cycle and gene transcription. 378 Previous <lb/>studies have shown that blockade of CDK7 manipulated <lb/>inflammation resolution by remodeling antitumor immunity 378 <lb/>and regulating cytokine secretion. 379 A recent study by Wei <lb/>et al. 380 showed that small-molecule inhibitor, THZ1, mediated the <lb/>blockade of CDK7 and thus mitigated hyperinflammatory states <lb/>and CRS caused by CAR T cell therapy. Mechanistically, when CDK7 <lb/>is blocked by THZ1, various pro-inflammatory genes, especially <lb/>STAT1 and IL1 that are regulated by CDK7/RNA Pol II super-<lb/>enhancers, are preferentially suppressed at the transcriptional <lb/>level. This indicates that blockade of CDK7 may be a promising <lb/>strategy to treat CRS. Considering similar cytokine profiles <lb/>between COVID-CS and CRS, we can hypothesize that the strategy <lb/>may also work in COVID-CS. <lb/>CONCLUSIONS <lb/>Clinical and basic research studies have identified and character-<lb/>ized COVID-CS, which has greatly enhanced our understanding of <lb/>CS and related immunopathology in COVID-19. A full scenario of <lb/>COVID-CS is now emerging, and it appears to be much larger in <lb/>scale and contains more cytokines than the CS recognized in other <lb/>conditions, and is therefore also more damaging. Although it is <lb/>still unclear how the virus turns the protective cytokine profile into <lb/>an inflammatory CS, the cytokines appear to be produced <lb/>predominantly by innate cells because the lymphopenia was <lb/>frequently reported in this condition. While the causative efficacy <lb/>of individual cytokines on the development of certain immuno-<lb/>pathogenic parameters in this condition is yet to be fully <lb/>understood; it is obvious that COVID-CS as a whole is closely <lb/>associated with the major pathogenic changes of COVID-19. To <lb/>treat COVID-CS, several biologic interventions specifically target-<lb/>ing inflammatory cytokines or related signaling pathways have <lb/>been clinically evaluated with promising results and many others <lb/>are in the pipeline. <lb/>In principle, the treatment strategy should be to control <lb/>ongoing inflammatory cytokine production or activity and resume <lb/>the host&apos;s homeostasis. However, we still lack safe and effective <lb/>drugs to control the CS, and clinically, the treatment of CS has <lb/>been proved difficult for several reasons: (1) many medical doctors <lb/>are not aware of the condition and hence, clinical diagnosis and <lb/>treatment guidelines are currently lacking; (2) it is a pharmaceu-<lb/>tical challenge to simultaneously target multiple cytokines. It is <lb/>therefore important to identify and target the key cytokines <lb/>upstream and the cytokine induction network, or directly target <lb/>the predominant cytokine-producing cells such as monocytes and <lb/>macrophages. Alternatively, learning from the host immunoregu-<lb/>latory system and identifying more effective and safer anti-<lb/>inflammatory factor/cytokines with a wide-spectrum inhibitory <lb/>effect may provide a better option for therapeutic intervention; IL-<lb/>37 has been suggested for this purpose; 381-384 (3) it is difficult to <lb/>balance CS and protective immunity in infectious diseases, as the <lb/>appropriate level of inflammatory cytokines is protective against <lb/>infections and inappropriately targeting inflammatory cytokines <lb/>may lead to acquired immunodeficiency and subsequent infec-<lb/>tions; (4) differences among individuals with respect to age, <lb/>immune status, and other comorbidities may result in virtual <lb/>differences in the component and scale of the CS and treatment. <lb/>Therefore, precise treatment is required. Of note, ideally targeting <lb/>predominant cytokines or molecular pathways in a particular CS <lb/>condition should be conducted first and in a timely manner. <lb/>COVID-19 has taught us a critical lesson regarding how to deal <lb/>with natural pathogenic enemies. Knowledge and treatment <lb/>options developed from COVID-CS will be invaluable, not just for <lb/>this disease but also for other CS conditions. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement">ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS <lb/>We thank all medical, social, and scientific efforts to fight against the COVID-19 <lb/>pandemic. This work was supported by grants from the National Key R&amp;D Program of <lb/>China (2016YFC1305102 to Y.Z.); National Natural Science Foundation of China <lb/>(81671561, 81974248 to Y.Z.); the International Joint Laboratory Program of National <lb/>Children&apos;s Medical Center (EK1125180109 to Y.Z.); Program for Outstanding Medical <lb/>Academic Leader (2019LJ19 to Y.Z.); Shanghai Municipal Planning Commission of <lb/>Science and Research Fund (201740065 to Y.Z.). Shanghai Committee of Science and <lb/>Technology (21140902400 to Y.Z.,21ZR1410000, 19ZR1406400 to J.F.); Versus Arthritis <lb/>UK (21327 to D.X.); and Shenzhen Science and Technology Peacock Team Project <lb/>(KQTD20170331145453160). Figure 1 and Figure 4 were produced with the assistance <lb/>of Servier Medical Art (https://smart.servier.com). <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">AUTHOR CONTRIBUTIONS <lb/>L.Y., X.X., Z.T., and J.F. contributed to the collection of references and manuscript <lb/>preparation. D.X. and Y.Z. contributed to the plan and modification of the manuscript. <lb/>ADDITIONAL INFORMATION <lb/>Competing interests: The authors declare no competing interests. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>REFERENCES <lb/>1. Wan, Y. et al. Receptor recognition by the novel coronavirus from Wuhan: an <lb/>analysis based on decade-long structural studies of SARS coronavirus. J. Virol 94, <lb/>e00127-20 (2020). <lb/>2. Hamming, I. et al. Tissue distribution of ACE2 protein, the functional receptor for <lb/>SARS coronavirus. A first step in understanding SARS pathogenesis. J. Pathol. <lb/>203, 631-637 (2004). <lb/>3. Crackower, M. A. et al. Angiotensin-converting enzyme 2 is an essential reg-<lb/>ulator of heart function. Nature 417, 822-828 (2002). <lb/>4. Donoghue, M. et al. A novel angiotensin-converting enzyme-related carbox-<lb/>ypeptidase (ACE2) converts angiotensin I to angiotensin 1-9. Circ. Res. 87, E1-E9 <lb/>(2000). <lb/>5. Tipnis, S. R. et al. A human homolog of angiotensin-converting enzyme. Cloning <lb/>and functional expression as a captopril-insensitive carboxypeptidase. J. Biol. <lb/>Chem. 275, 33238-33243 (2000). <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">The signal pathways and treatment of cytokine storm in COVID-19 <lb/>Yang et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>13 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Signal Transduction and Targeted Therapy (2021) 6:255 <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>6. Siddiqi, H. K. &amp; Mehra, M. R. COVID-19 illness in native and immunosuppressed <lb/>states: a clinical-therapeutic staging proposal. J. Heart Lung Transplant. 39, <lb/>405-407 (2020). <lb/>7. Fu, L. et al. Clinical characteristics of coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) in <lb/>China: a systematic review and meta-analysis. J. Infect. 80, 656-665 (2020). <lb/>8. Zhu, N. et al. A novel coronavirus from patients with pneumonia in China, 2019. <lb/>N. Engl. J. Med. 382, 727-733 (2020). <lb/>9. Huang, C. et al. Clinical features of patients infected with 2019 novel coronavirus <lb/>in Wuhan, China. Lancet 395, 497-506 (2020). <lb/>10. Chen, N. et al. Epidemiological and clinical characteristics of 99 cases of 2019 <lb/>novel coronavirus pneumonia in Wuhan, China: a descriptive study. Lancet 395, <lb/>507-513 (2020). <lb/>11. Wang, D. et al. Clinical characteristics of 138 hospitalized patients with 2019 <lb/>novel coronavirus-infected pneumonia in Wuhan, China. JAMA 323, 1061-1069 <lb/>(2020). <lb/>12. Henderson, L. A. et al. On the alert for cytokine storm: immunopathology in <lb/>COVID-19. Arthritis Rheumatol. 72, 1059-1063 (2020). <lb/>13. Mehta, P. et al. COVID-19: consider cytokine storm syndromes and immuno-<lb/>suppression. Lancet 395, 1033-1034 (2020). <lb/>14. Tufan, A., Avanoglu Guler, A. &amp; Matucci-Cerinic, M. COVID-19, immune system <lb/>response, hyperinflammation and repurposing antirheumatic drugs. Turk. J. <lb/>Med. Sci. 50, 620-632 (2020). <lb/>15. Mangalmurti, N. &amp; Hunter, C. A. Cytokine storms: understanding COVID-19. <lb/>Immunity 53, 19-25 (2020). <lb/>16. Ferrara, J. L., Abhyankar, S. &amp; Gilliland, D. G. Cytokine storm of graft-versus-host <lb/>disease: a critical effector role for interleukin-1. Transplant. Proc. 25, 1216-1217 <lb/>(1993). <lb/>17. Chousterman, B. G., Swirski, F. K. &amp; Weber, G. F. Cytokine storm and sepsis <lb/>disease pathogenesis. Semin. Immunopathol. 39, 517-528 (2017). <lb/>18. Kumar, V. Toll-like receptors in sepsis-associated cytokine storm and their <lb/>endogenous negative regulators as future immunomodulatory targets. Int. <lb/>Immunopharmacol. 89, 107087 (2020). <lb/>19. London, N. R. et al. Targeting Robo4-dependent Slit signaling to survive the <lb/>cytokine storm in sepsis and influenza. Sci. Transl. Med. 2, 23ra19 (2010). <lb/>20. Imus, P. H. et al. Severe cytokine release syndrome after haploidentical per-<lb/>ipheral blood stem cell transplantation. Biol. Blood Marrow Transplant. 25, <lb/>2431-2437 (2019). <lb/>21. Wadia, P. P. &amp; Tambur, A. R. Yin and yang of cytokine regulation in solid organ <lb/>graft rejection and tolerance. Clin. Lab. Med. 28, 469-479, vii-viii (2008). <lb/>22. Davila, M. L. et al. Efficacy and toxicity management of 19-28z CAR T cell therapy <lb/>in B cell acute lymphoblastic leukemia. Sci. Transl. Med. 6, 224ra225 (2014). <lb/>23. Grupp, S. A. et al. Chimeric antigen receptor-modified T cells for acute lymphoid <lb/>leukemia. N. Engl. J. Med. 368, 1509-1518 (2013). <lb/>24. Qin, C. et al. Dysregulation of immune response in patients with coronavirus <lb/>2019 (COVID-19) in Wuhan, China. Clin. Infect. Dis. 71, 762-768 (2020). <lb/>25. Wang, F. et al. Characteristics of peripheral lymphocyte subset alteration in <lb/>COVID-19 pneumonia. J. Infect. Dis. 221, 1762-1769 (2020). <lb/>26. Hadjadj, J. et al. Impaired type I interferon activity and inflammatory responses <lb/>in severe COVID-19 patients. Science 369, 718-724 (2020). <lb/>27. Diao, B. et al. Reduction and functional exhaustion of T cells in patients with <lb/>coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19). Front. Immunol. 11, 827 (2020). <lb/>28. Zhang, J. J. et al. Clinical characteristics of 140 patients infected with SARS-CoV-2 <lb/>in Wuhan, China. Allergy 75, 1730-1741 (2020). <lb/>29. Fang, L., Karakiulakis, G. &amp; Roth, M. Are patients with hypertension and diabetes <lb/>mellitus at increased risk for COVID-19 infection? Lancet Respir. Med. 8, e21 <lb/>(2020). <lb/>30. Wang, K. et al. CD147-spike protein is a novel route for SARS-CoV-2 infection to <lb/>host cells. Signal Transduct. Target Ther. 5, 283 (2020). <lb/>31. Yang, L. et al. COVID-19: immunopathogenesis and Immunotherapeutics. Signal <lb/>Transduct. Target Ther. 5, 128 (2020). <lb/>32. Wilk, A. J. et al. A single-cell atlas of the peripheral immune response in patients <lb/>with severe COVID-19. Nat. Med. 26, 1070-1076 (2020). <lb/>33. Ronit, A. et al. Compartmental immunophenotyping in COVID-19 ARDS: a case <lb/>series. J. Allergy Clin. Immunol. 147, 81-91 (2021). <lb/>34. Zheng, H. et al. Virulence and pathogenesis of SARS-CoV-2 infection in rhesus <lb/>macaques: a nonhuman primate model of COVID-19 progression. PLoS Pathog. <lb/>16, e1008949 (2020). <lb/>35. Li, M. et al. Elevated exhaustion levels of NK and CD8(+) T cells as indicators for <lb/>progression and prognosis of COVID-19 disease. Front. Immunol. 11, 580237 <lb/>(2020). <lb/>36. Zheng, M. et al. Functional exhaustion of antiviral lymphocytes in COVID-19 <lb/>patients. Cell. Mol. Immunol. 17, 533-535 (2020). <lb/>37. Wang, X. et al. Retraction Note to: SARS-CoV-2 infects T lymphocytes through its <lb/>spike protein-mediated membrane fusion. Cell. Mol. Immunol. 17, 894 (2020). <lb/>38. Yue, Y. et al. SARS-coronavirus open reading frame-3a drives multimodal <lb/>necrotic cell death. Cell Death Dis. 9, 904 (2018). <lb/>39. Tan, Y. X. et al. Induction of apoptosis by the severe acute respiratory syndrome <lb/>coronavirus 7a protein is dependent on its interaction with the Bcl-XL protein. J. <lb/>Virol. 81, 6346-6355 (2007). <lb/>40. Tan, L. et al. Lymphopenia predicts disease severity of COVID-19: a descriptive <lb/>and predictive study. Signal Transduct. Target Ther. 5, 33 (2020). <lb/>41. Cao, X. COVID-19: immunopathology and its implications for therapy. Nat. Rev. <lb/>Immunol. 20, 269-270 (2020). <lb/>42. Li, D. et al. Immune dysfunction leads to mortality and organ injury in patients <lb/>with COVID-19 in China: insights from ERS-COVID-19 study. Signal Transduct. <lb/>Target Ther. 5, 62 (2020). <lb/>43. Xu, Y. et al. Clinical characteristics of SARS-CoV-2 pneumonia compared to <lb/>controls in Chinese Han Population. Preprint at medRxiv https://doi.org/10.1101/ <lb/>2020.03.08.20031658 (2020). <lb/>44. Nielsen, S. C. A. et al. Human B cell clonal expansion and convergent antibody <lb/>responses to SARS-CoV-2. Cell Host Microbe 28, 516-525 (2020). e515. <lb/>45. Halstead, S. B. &amp; O&apos;Rourke, E. J. Antibody-enhanced dengue virus infection in <lb/>primate leukocytes. Nature 265, 739-741 (1977). <lb/>46. Halstead, S. B. &amp; O&apos;Rourke, E. J. Dengue viruses and mononuclear phagocytes. I. <lb/>Infection enhancement by non-neutralizing antibody. J. Exp. Med. 146, 201-217 <lb/>(1977). <lb/>47. Halstead, S. B., O&apos;Rourke, E. J. &amp; Allison, A. C. Dengue viruses and mononuclear <lb/>phagocytes. II. Identity of blood and tissue leukocytes supporting in vitro <lb/>infection. J. Exp. Med. 146, 218-229 (1977). <lb/>48. Peiris, J. S. &amp; Porterfield, J. S. Antibody-mediated enhancement of Flavivirus <lb/>replication in macrophage-like cell lines. Nature 282, 509-511 (1979). <lb/>49. Peiris, J. S., Gordon, S., Unkeless, J. C. &amp; Porterfield, J. S. Monoclonal anti-Fc <lb/>receptor IgG blocks antibody enhancement of viral replication in macrophages. <lb/>Nature 289, 189-191 (1981). <lb/>50. Yang, Z. Y. et al. Evasion of antibody neutralization in emerging severe acute <lb/>respiratory syndrome coronaviruses. Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA 102, 797-801 <lb/>(2005). <lb/>51. Wan, Y. et al. Molecular mechanism for antibody-dependent enhancement of <lb/>coronavirus entry. J Virol. 94, e02015-19 (2020). <lb/>52. Kuzmina, N. A. et al. Antibody-dependent enhancement of ebola virus infection <lb/>by human antibodies isolated from survivors. Cell Rep. 24, 1802-1815.e1805 <lb/>(2018). <lb/>53. Zhao, J. et al. Antibody responses to SARS-CoV-2 in patients with novel cor-<lb/>onavirus disease 2019. Clin. Infect. Dis. 71, 2027-2034 (2020). <lb/>54. Zhang, B. et al. Immune phenotyping based on the neutrophil-to-lymphocyte <lb/>ratio and IgG level predicts disease severity and outcome for patients with <lb/>COVID-19. Front. Mol. Biosci. 7, 157 (2020). <lb/>55. Wang, S. et al. Characterization of neutralizing antibody with prophylactic and <lb/>therapeutic efficacy against SARS-CoV-2 in rhesus monkeys. Nat. Commun. 11, <lb/>5752 (2020). <lb/>56. Brinkmann, V. et al. Neutrophil extracellular traps kill bacteria. Science 303, <lb/>1532-1535 (2004). <lb/>57. Weiss, S. J. Tissue destruction by neutrophils. N. Engl. J. Med. 320, 365-376 <lb/>(1989). <lb/>58. Chen, Y. M. et al. Blood molecular markers associated with COVID-19 immu-<lb/>nopathology and multi-organ damage. EMBO J. 39, e105896 (2020). <lb/>59. Schulte-Schrepping, J. et al. Severe COVID-19 is marked by a dysregulated <lb/>myeloid cell compartment. Cell 182, 1419-1440.e1423 (2020). <lb/>60. McElvaney, O. J. et al. Characterization of the inflammatory response to severe <lb/>COVID-19 illness. Am. J. Respir. Crit. Care Med. 202, 812-821 (2020). <lb/>61. Palsson-McDermott, E. M. et al. Pyruvate kinase M2 regulates Hif-1alpha activity <lb/>and IL-1beta induction and is a critical determinant of the Warburg effect in <lb/>LPS-activated macrophages. Cell Metab. 21, 347 (2015). <lb/>62. Luo, W. et al. Pyruvate kinase M2 is a PHD3-stimulated coactivator for hypoxia-<lb/>inducible factor 1. Cell 145, 732-744 (2011). <lb/>63. Narasimhan, P. B., Marcovecchio, P., Hamers, A. A. J. &amp; Hedrick, C. C. Nonclassical <lb/>monocytes in health and disease. Annu. Rev. Immunol. 37, 439-456 (2019). <lb/>64. Xu, G. et al. The differential immune responses to COVID-19 in peripheral and <lb/>lung revealed by single-cell RNA sequencing. Cell Discov. 6, 73 (2020). <lb/>65. Honda, K., Takaoka, A. &amp; Taniguchi, T. Type I interferon [corrected] gene <lb/>induction by the interferon regulatory factor family of transcription factors. <lb/>Immunity 25, 349-360 (2006). <lb/>66. Jensen, S. &amp; Thomsen, A. R. Sensing of RNA viruses: a review of innate immune <lb/>receptors involved in recognizing RNA virus invasion. J. Virol. 86, 2900-2910 <lb/>(2012). <lb/>67. Park, A. &amp; Iwasaki, A. Type I and Type III interferons -induction, signaling, <lb/>evasion, and application to combat COVID-19. Cell Host Microbe 27, 870-878 <lb/>(2020). <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">The signal pathways and treatment of cytokine storm in COVID-19 <lb/>Yang et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>14 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Signal Transduction and Targeted Therapy (2021) 6:255 <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>68. Blanco-Melo, D. et al. Imbalanced host response to SARS-CoV-2 drives devel-<lb/>opment of COVID-19. Cell 181, 1036-1045.e1039 (2020). <lb/>69. Galani, I. E. et al. Untuned antiviral immunity in COVID-19 revealed by temporal <lb/>type I/III interferon patterns and flu comparison. Nat. Immunol. 22, 32-40 (2021). <lb/>70. Siu, K. L. et al. Severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus M protein inhibits <lb/>type I interferon production by impeding the formation of TRAF3.TANK.TBK1/ <lb/>IKKepsilon complex. J. Biol. Chem. 284, 16202-16209 (2009). <lb/>71. Hu, Y. et al. The severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus nucleocapsid <lb/>inhibits Type I interferon production by interfering with TRIM25-mediated RIG-I <lb/>ubiquitination. J. Virol. 91, e02143-16 (2017). <lb/>72. Minakshi, R. et al. The SARS coronavirus 3a protein causes endoplasmic reti-<lb/>culum stress and induces ligand-independent downregulation of the type 1 <lb/>interferon receptor. PLoS ONE 4, e8342 (2009). <lb/>73. Kopecky-Bromberg, S. A. et al. Severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus <lb/>open reading frame (ORF) 3b, ORF 6, and nucleocapsid proteins function as <lb/>interferon antagonists. J. Virol. 81, 548-557 (2007). <lb/>74. Yang, D. et al. Attenuated interferon and proinflammatory response in SARS-<lb/>CoV-2-infected human dendritic cells is associated with viral antagonism of <lb/>STAT1 phosphorylation. J. Infect. Dis. 222, 734-745 (2020). <lb/>75. Webster, B., Assil, S. &amp; Dreux, M. Cell-cell sensing of viral infection by plasma-<lb/>cytoid dendritic cells. J. Virol. 90, 10050-10053 (2016). <lb/>76. Cervantes-Barragan, L. et al. Plasmacytoid dendritic cells control T-cell response <lb/>to chronic viral infection. Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA 109, 3012-3017 (2012). <lb/>77. Honda, K. et al. Spatiotemporal regulation of MyD88-IRF-7 signalling for robust <lb/>type-I interferon induction. Nature 434, 1035-1040 (2005). <lb/>78. Zhou, Z. et al. Heightened innate immune responses in the respiratory tract of <lb/>COVID-19 patients. Cell Host Microbe 27, 883-890.e882 (2020). <lb/>79. Channappanavar, R. et al. Dysregulated Type I interferon and inflammatory <lb/>monocyte-macrophage responses cause lethal pneumonia in SARS-CoV-<lb/>infected mice. Cell Host Microbe 19, 181-193 (2016). <lb/>80. Channappanavar, R. et al. IFN-I response timing relative to virus replication <lb/>determines MERS coronavirus infection outcomes. J. Clin. Invest. 129, 3625-3639 <lb/>(2019). <lb/>81. Lucas, C. et al. Longitudinal analyses reveal immunological misfiring in severe <lb/>COVID-19. Nature 584, 463-469 (2020). <lb/>82. Azkur, A. K. et al. Immune response to SARS-CoV-2 and mechanisms of immu-<lb/>nopathological changes in COVID-19. Allergy 75, 1564-1581 (2020). <lb/>83. Debuc, B. &amp; Smadja, D. M. Is COVID-19 a new hematologic disease? Stem Cell <lb/>Rev. Rep. 17, 4-8 (2020). <lb/>84. Li, X. et al. Molecular immune pathogenesis and diagnosis of COVID-19. J. <lb/>Pharm. Anal. 10, 102-108 (2020). <lb/>85. Nile, S. H. et al. COVID-19: pathogenesis, cytokine storm and therapeutic <lb/>potential of interferons. Cytokine Growth Factor Rev. 53, 66-70 (2020). <lb/>86. Wilson, M. P. &amp; Jack, A. S. Coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) in neurology and <lb/>neurosurgery: a scoping review of the early literature. Clin. Neurol. Neurosurg. <lb/>193, 105866 (2020). <lb/>87. Moore, J. B. &amp; June, C. H. Cytokine release syndrome in severe COVID-19. Science <lb/>368, 473-474 (2020). <lb/>88. Fajgenbaum, D. C. &amp; June, C. H. Cytokine storm. N. Engl. J. Med. 383, 2255-2273 <lb/>(2020). <lb/>89. Esteban, Y. M., de Jong, J. L. O. &amp; Tesher, M. S. An overview of hemophagocytic <lb/>lymphohistiocytosis. Pediatr. Ann. 46, e309-e313 (2017). <lb/>90. Carter, S. J., Tattersall, R. S. &amp; Ramanan, A. V. Macrophage activation syndrome in <lb/>adults: recent advances in pathophysiology, diagnosis and treatment. Rheu-<lb/>matology 58, 5-17 (2019). <lb/>91. Khanmohammadi, S. &amp; Rezaei, N. Role of Toll-like receptors in the pathogenesis <lb/>of COVID-19. J. Med. Virol. 93, 2735-2739 (2021). <lb/>92. Trasino, S. E. A role for retinoids in the treatment of COVID-19? Clin. Exp. <lb/>Pharmacol. Physiol. 47, 1765-1767 (2020). <lb/>93. Onomoto, K., Onoguchi, K. &amp; Yoneyama, M. Regulation of RIG-I-like receptor-<lb/>mediated signaling: interaction between host and viral factors. Cell. Mol. <lb/>Immunol. 18, 539-555 (2021). <lb/>94. Al-Samkari, H. &amp; Berliner, N. Hemophagocytic lymphohistiocytosis. Annu. Rev. <lb/>Pathol. 13, 27-49 (2018). <lb/>95. Suntharalingam, G. et al. Cytokine storm in a phase 1 trial of the anti-CD28 <lb/>monoclonal antibody TGN1412. N. Engl. J. Med. 355, 1018-1028 (2006). <lb/>96. Engelmann, B. &amp; Massberg, S. Thrombosis as an intravascular effector of innate <lb/>immunity. Nat. Rev. Immunol. 13, 34-45 (2013). <lb/>97. Sakaguchi, S. Naturally arising CD4+ regulatory t cells for immunologic self-<lb/>tolerance and negative control of immune responses. Annu. Rev. Immunol. 22, <lb/>531-562 (2004). <lb/>98. Sakaguchi, S. et al. Foxp3+CD25+CD4+ natural regulatory T cells in dominant <lb/>self-tolerance and autoimmune disease. Immunol. Rev. 212, 8-27 (2006). <lb/>99. de Waal Malefyt, R. et al. Interleukin 10 (IL-10) and viral IL-10 strongly reduce <lb/>antigen-specific human T cell proliferation by diminishing the antigen-<lb/>presenting capacity of monocytes via downregulation of class II major histo-<lb/>compatibility complex expression. J. Exp. Med. 174, 915-924 (1991). <lb/>100. Bogdan, C., Vodovotz, Y. &amp; Nathan, C. Macrophage deactivation by interleukin <lb/>10. J. Exp. Med. 174, 1549-1555 (1991). <lb/>101. Caricchio, R. et al. Preliminary predictive criteria for COVID-19 cytokine storm. <lb/>Ann. Rheum. Dis. 80, 88-95 (2021). <lb/>102. Chen, L. Y. C. et al. Confronting the controversy: interleukin-6 and the COVID-19 <lb/>cytokine storm syndrome. Eur. Respir. J. 56, 2003006 (2020). <lb/>103. Ruan, Q. et al. Clinical predictors of mortality due to COVID-19 based on an <lb/>analysis of data of 150 patients from Wuhan, China. Intens. Care Med. 46, <lb/>846-848 (2020). <lb/>104. Herold, T. et al. Elevated levels of IL-6 and CRP predict the need for mechanical <lb/>ventilation in COVID-19. J. Allergy Clin. Immunol. 146, 128-136 (2020). e124. <lb/>105. Laing, A. G. et al. A dynamic COVID-19 immune signature includes associations <lb/>with poor prognosis. Nat. Med. 26, 1623-1635 (2020). <lb/>106. Price, C. C. et al. Tocilizumab treatment for cytokine release syndrome in hos-<lb/>pitalized patients with coronavirus disease 2019: survival and clinical outcomes. <lb/>Chest 158, 1397-1408 (2020). <lb/>107. Giamarellos-Bourboulis, E. J. et al. Complex immune dysregulation in COVID-19 <lb/>patients with severe respiratory failure. Cell Host Microbe 27, 992-1000.e1003 <lb/>(2020). <lb/>108. Hirano, T. &amp; Murakami, M. COVID-19: a new virus, but a familiar receptor and <lb/>cytokine release syndrome. Immunity 52, 731-733 (2020). <lb/>109. Bronte, V. et al. Baricitinib restrains the immune dysregulation in patients with <lb/>severe COVID-19. J. Clin. Invest. 130, 6409-6416 (2020). <lb/>110. Kang, S., Tanaka, T., Narazaki, M. &amp; Kishimoto, T. Targeting interleukin-6 signaling <lb/>in clinic. Immunity 50, 1007-1023 (2019). <lb/>111. Tanaka, T., Narazaki, M. &amp; Kishimoto, T. IL-6 in inflammation, immunity, and <lb/>disease. Cold Spring Harb. Perspect. Biol. 6, a016295 (2014). <lb/>112. Ulich, T. R., del Castillo, J. &amp; Guo, K. Z. In vivo hematologic effects of recombinant <lb/>interleukin-6 on hematopoiesis and circulating numbers of RBCs and WBCs. <lb/>Blood 73, 108-110 (1989). <lb/>113. Tanaka, T., Narazaki, M. &amp; Kishimoto, T. Immunotherapeutic implications of IL-6 <lb/>blockade for cytokine storm. Immunotherapy 8, 959-970 (2016). <lb/>114. Biswas, P. et al. Interleukin-6 induces monocyte chemotactic protein-1 in per-<lb/>ipheral blood mononuclear cells and in the U937 cell line. Blood 91, 258-265 <lb/>(1998). <lb/>115. McLoughlin, R. M. et al. Differential regulation of neutrophil-activating chemo-<lb/>kines by IL-6 and its soluble receptor isoforms. J. Immunol. 172, 5676-5683 <lb/>(2004). <lb/>116. van der Meer, I. M. et al. Inflammatory mediators and cell adhesion molecules as <lb/>indicators of severity of atherosclerosis: the Rotterdam Study. Arterioscler. <lb/>Thromb. Vasc. Biol. 22, 838-842 (2002). <lb/>117. Xiang, S. et al. Inhibitory effects of suppressor of cytokine signaling 3 on <lb/>inflammatory cytokine expression and migration and proliferation of IL-6/IFN-<lb/>gamma-induced vascular smooth muscle cells. J. Huazhong Univ. Sci. Technol. <lb/>Med. Sci. 33, 615-622 (2013). <lb/>118. Schultz, D. R. &amp; Arnold, P. I. Properties of four acute phase proteins: C-reactive <lb/>protein, serum amyloid A protein, alpha 1-acid glycoprotein, and fibrinogen. <lb/>Semin. Arthritis Rheum. 20, 129-147 (1990). <lb/>119. Alonzi, T. et al. Essential role of STAT3 in the control of the acute-phase response <lb/>as revealed by inducible gene inactivation [correction of activation] in the liver. <lb/>Mol. Cell. Biol. 21, 1621-1632 (2001). <lb/>120. Schieffer, B. et al. Role of NAD(P)H oxidase in angiotensin II-induced JAK/STAT <lb/>signaling and cytokine induction. Circ. Res. 87, 1195-1201 (2000). <lb/>121. Marrero, M. B. et al. Direct stimulation of Jak/STAT pathway by the angiotensin II <lb/>AT1 receptor. Nature 375, 247-250 (1995). <lb/>122. Kuba, K. et al. A crucial role of angiotensin converting enzyme 2 (ACE2) in SARS <lb/>coronavirus-induced lung injury. Nat. Med. 11, 875-879 (2005). <lb/>123. Glowacka, I. et al. Differential downregulation of ACE2 by the spike proteins of <lb/>severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus and human coronavirus NL63. J. <lb/>Virol. 84, 1198-1205 (2010). <lb/>124. Catanzaro, M. et al. Immune response in COVID-19: addressing a pharmacolo-<lb/>gical challenge by targeting pathways triggered by SARS-CoV-2. Signal Trans-<lb/>duct. Target Ther. 5, 84 (2020). <lb/>125. Decker, T., Muller, M. &amp; Stockinger, S. The yin and yang of type I interferon <lb/>activity in bacterial infection. Nat. Rev. Immunol. 5, 675-687 (2005). <lb/>126. Luo, W. et al. Targeting JAK-STAT signaling to control cytokine release syndrome <lb/>in COVID-19. Trends Pharm. Sci. 41, 531-543 (2020). <lb/>127. Farrar, M. A. &amp; Schreiber, R. D. The molecular cell biology of interferon-gamma <lb/>and its receptor. Annu. Rev. Immunol. 11, 571-611 (1993). <lb/>128. Tisoncik, J. R. et al. Into the eye of the cytokine storm. Microbiol. Mol. Biol. Rev. <lb/>76, 16-32 (2012). <lb/>129. Bhattacharyya, M. &amp; Ghosh, M. K. Hemophagoctic lymphohistiocytosis-recent <lb/>concept. J. Assoc. Physicians India 56, 453-457 (2008). <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">The signal pathways and treatment of cytokine storm in COVID-19 <lb/>Yang et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>15 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Signal Transduction and Targeted Therapy (2021) 6:255 <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>130. Wang, W. et al. Definition and risks of cytokine release syndrome in 11 critically <lb/>ill COVID-19 patients with pneumonia: analysis of disease characteristics. J. <lb/>Infect. Dis. 222, 1444-1451 (2020). <lb/>131. Chen, C., Zhang, X. R., Ju, Z. Y. &amp; He, W. F. Advances in the research of <lb/>mechanism and related immunotherapy on the cytokine storm induced by <lb/>coronavirus disease 2019. Zhonghua Shao Shang Za Zhi 36, 471-475 (2020). <lb/>132. Chen, G. et al. Clinical and immunological features of severe and moderate <lb/>coronavirus disease 2019. J. Clin. Invest. 130, 2620-2629 (2020). <lb/>133. Pasquereau, S., Kumar, A. &amp; Herbein, G. Targeting TNF and TNF receptor path-<lb/>way in HIV-1 infection: from immune activation to viral reservoirs. Viruses 9, 64 <lb/>(2017). <lb/>134. Filik, H. &amp; Avan, A. A. Electrochemical immunosensors for the detection of <lb/>cytokine tumor necrosis factor alpha: a review. Talanta 211, 120758 (2020). <lb/>135. Gilmore, T. D. &amp; Wolenski, F. S. NF-kappaB: where did it come from and why? <lb/>Immunol. Rev. 246, 14-35 (2012). <lb/>136. Hayden, M. S. &amp; Ghosh, S. NF-kappaB in immunobiology. Cell Res. 21, 223-244 <lb/>(2011). <lb/>137. Acar, L., Atalan, N., Karagedik, E. H. &amp; Ergen, A. Tumour necrosis factor-alpha and <lb/>nuclear factor-kappa B gene variants in sepsis. Balk. Med J. 35, 30-35 (2018). <lb/>138. Aggarwal, B. B. Signalling pathways of the TNF superfamily: a double-edged <lb/>sword. Nat. Rev. Immunol. 3, 745-756 (2003). <lb/>139. Vanden Berghe, T. et al. Regulated necrosis: the expanding network of non-<lb/>apoptotic cell death pathways. Nat. Rev. Mol. Cell Biol. 15, 135-147 (2014). <lb/>140. Dutta, J. et al. Current insights into the regulation of programmed cell death by <lb/>NF-kappaB. Oncogene 25, 6800-6816 (2006). <lb/>141. Shakhov, A. N. et al. Kappa B-type enhancers are involved in lipopolysaccharide-<lb/>mediated transcriptional activation of the tumor necrosis factor alpha gene in <lb/>primary macrophages. J. Exp. Med. 171, 35-47 (1990). <lb/>142. Cheung, C. Y. et al. Cytokine responses in severe acute respiratory syndrome <lb/>coronavirus-infected macrophages in vitro: possible relevance to pathogenesis. <lb/>J. Virol. 79, 7819-7826 (2005). <lb/>143. Law, H. K. et al. Chemokine up-regulation in SARS-coronavirus-infected, <lb/>monocyte-derived human dendritic cells. Blood 106, 2366-2374 (2005). <lb/>144. Chu, H. et al. Middle East respiratory syndrome coronavirus efficiently infects <lb/>human primary T lymphocytes and activates the extrinsic and intrinsic apop-<lb/>tosis pathways. J. Infect. Dis. 213, 904-914 (2016). <lb/>145. Mahallawi, W. H. et al. MERS-CoV infection in humans is associated with a pro-<lb/>inflammatory Th1 and Th17 cytokine profile. Cytokine 104, 8-13 (2018). <lb/>146. DeDiego, M. L. et al. Inhibition of NF-kappaB-mediated inflammation in severe <lb/>acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus-infected mice increases survival. J. Virol. <lb/>88, 913-924 (2014). <lb/>147. Wan, S. et al. Characteristics of lymphocyte subsets and cytokines in peripheral <lb/>blood of 123 hospitalized patients with 2019 novel coronavirus pneumonia <lb/>(NCP). Preprint at medRxiv https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.02.10.20021832 (2020). <lb/>148. Hiscott, J. et al. Manipulation of the nuclear factor-kappaB pathway and the <lb/>innate immune response by viruses. Oncogene 25, 6844-6867 (2006). <lb/>149. Martinon, F. et al. Gout-associated uric acid crystals activate the NALP3 <lb/>inflammasome. Nature 440, 237-241 (2006). <lb/>150. Martin, W. J., Walton, M. &amp; Harper, J. Resident macrophages initiating and <lb/>driving inflammation in a monosodium urate monohydrate crystal-induced <lb/>murine peritoneal model of acute gout. Arthritis Rheum. 60, 281-289 (2009). <lb/>151. Bucala, R., Ritchlin, C., Winchester, R. &amp; Cerami, A. Constitutive production of <lb/>inflammatory and mitogenic cytokines by rheumatoid synovial fibroblasts. J. <lb/>Exp. Med. 173, 569-574 (1991). <lb/>152. Mridha, A. R. et al. NLRP3 inflammasome blockade reduces liver inflammation <lb/>and fibrosis in experimental NASH in mice. J. Hepatol. 66, 1037-1046 (2017). <lb/>153. Ather, J. L. et al. Serum amyloid A activates the NLRP3 inflammasome and <lb/>promotes Th17 allergic asthma in mice. J. Immunol. 187, 64-73 (2011). <lb/>154. Petrilli, V., Dostert, C., Muruve, D. A. &amp; Tschopp, J. The inflammasome: a danger <lb/>sensing complex triggering innate immunity. Curr. Opin. Immunol. 19, 615-622 <lb/>(2007). <lb/>155. Ting, J. P., Willingham, S. B. &amp; Bergstralh, D. T. NLRs at the intersection of cell <lb/>death and immunity. Nat. Rev. Immunol. 8, 372-379 (2008). <lb/>156. Asrani, P. &amp; Hassan, M. I. SARS-CoV-2 mediated lung inflammatory responses in <lb/>host: targeting the cytokine storm for therapeutic interventions. Mol. Cell. Bio-<lb/>chem. 476, 675-687 (2021). <lb/>157. He, L. et al. Expression of elevated levels of pro-inflammatory cytokines in SARS-<lb/>CoV-infected ACE2+ cells in SARS patients: relation to the acute lung injury and <lb/>pathogenesis of SARS. J. Pathol. 210, 288-297 (2006). <lb/>158. Alosaimi, B. et al. MERS-CoV infection is associated with downregulation of <lb/>genes encoding Th1 and Th2 cytokines/chemokines and elevated inflammatory <lb/>innate immune response in the lower respiratory tract. Cytokine 126, 154895 <lb/>(2020). <lb/>159. Lau, S. K. P. et al. Delayed induction of proinflammatory cytokines and sup-<lb/>pression of innate antiviral response by the novel Middle East respiratory <lb/>syndrome coronavirus: implications for pathogenesis and treatment. J. Gen. <lb/>Virol. 94, 2679-2690 (2013). <lb/>160. Zhang, W. et al. The use of anti-inflammatory drugs in the treatment of people <lb/>with severe coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19): the perspectives of clinical <lb/>immunologists from China. Clin. Immunol. 214, 108393 (2020). <lb/>161. Chen, I. Y., Moriyama, M., Chang, M. F. &amp; Ichinohe, T. Severe acute respiratory <lb/>syndrome coronavirus viroporin 3a activates the NLRP3 Inflammasome. Front. <lb/>Microbiol. 10, 50 (2019). <lb/>162. Shi, C. S., Nabar, N. R., Huang, N. N. &amp; Kehrl, J. H. SARS-coronavirus open reading <lb/>frame-8b triggers intracellular stress pathways and activates NLRP3 inflamma-<lb/>somes. Cell Death Discov. 5, 101 (2019). <lb/>163. Mousavizadeh, L. &amp; Ghasemi, S. Genotype and phenotype of COVID-19: their <lb/>roles in pathogenesis. J. Microbiol. Immunol. Infect. 54, 159-163 (2020). <lb/>164. Freeman, T. L. &amp; Swartz, T. H. Targeting the NLRP3 inflammasome in severe <lb/>COVID-19. Front. Immunol. 11, 1518 (2020). <lb/>165. van den Berg, D. F. &amp; Te Velde, A. A. Severe COVID-19: NLRP3 inflammasome <lb/>dysregulated. Front. Immunol. 11, 1580 (2020). <lb/>166. Dostert, C. et al. Innate immune activation through Nalp3 inflammasome sen-<lb/>sing of asbestos and silica. Science 320, 674-677 (2008). <lb/>167. Cassel, S. L. et al. The Nalp3 inflammasome is essential for the development of <lb/>silicosis. Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA 105, 9035-9040 (2008). <lb/>168. Cruz, C. M. et al. ATP activates a reactive oxygen species-dependent oxidative <lb/>stress response and secretion of proinflammatory cytokines in macrophages. J. <lb/>Biol. Chem. 282, 2871-2879 (2007). <lb/>169. Rosenberg, S. A. IL-2: the first effective immunotherapy for human cancer. J. <lb/>Immunol. 192, 5451-5458 (2014). <lb/>170. Fu, X. et al. Enhanced interaction between SEC2 mutant and TCR Vbeta induces <lb/>MHC II-independent activation of T cells via PKCtheta/NF-kappaB and IL-2R/ <lb/>STAT5 signaling pathways. J. Biol. Chem. 293, 19771-19784 (2018). <lb/>171. Yuan, X., Cheng, G. &amp; Malek, T. R. The importance of regulatory T-cell hetero-<lb/>geneity in maintaining self-tolerance. Immunol. Rev. 259, 103-114 (2014). <lb/>172. Abbas, A. K. et al. Revisiting IL-2: biology and therapeutic prospects. Sci. <lb/>Immunol. 3, eaat1482 (2018). <lb/>173. Li, C. K. et al. T cell responses to whole SARS coronavirus in humans. J. Immunol. <lb/>181, 5490-5500 (2008). <lb/>174. Channappanavar, R. et al. Virus-specific memory CD8 T cells provide substantial <lb/>protection from lethal severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus infection. <lb/>J. Virol. 88, 11034-11044 (2014). <lb/>175. Shi, H. et al. The inhibition of IL-2/IL-2R gives rise to CD8(+) T cell and lym-<lb/>phocyte decrease through JAK1-STAT5 in critical patients with COVID-19 <lb/>pneumonia. Cell Death Dis. 11, 429 (2020). <lb/>176. Schluns, K. S., Kieper, W. C., Jameson, S. C. &amp; Lefrancois, L. Interleukin-7 mediates <lb/>the homeostasis of naive and memory CD8 T cells in vivo. Nat. Immunol. 1, <lb/>426-432 (2000). <lb/>177. Tan, J. T. et al. IL-7 is critical for homeostatic proliferation and survival of naive <lb/>T cells. Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA 98, 8732-8737 (2001). <lb/>178. Seddon, B., Tomlinson, P. &amp; Zamoyska, R. Interleukin 7 and T cell receptor signals <lb/>regulate homeostasis of CD4 memory cells. Nat. Immunol. 4, 680-686 (2003). <lb/>179. Fry, T. J. &amp; Mackall, C. L. The many faces of IL-7: from lymphopoiesis to peripheral <lb/>T cell maintenance. J. Immunol. 174, 6571-6576 (2005). <lb/>180. Barata, J. T., Durum, S. K. &amp; Seddon, B. Flip the coin: IL-7 and IL-7R in health and <lb/>disease. Nat. Immunol. 20, 1584-1593 (2019). <lb/>181. Saraiva, M. &amp; O&apos;Garra, A. The regulation of IL-10 production by immune cells. <lb/>Nat. Rev. Immunol. 10, 170-181 (2010). <lb/>182. Han, H. et al. Profiling serum cytokines in COVID-19 patients reveals IL-6 and IL-<lb/>10 are disease severity predictors. Emerg. Microbes Infect. 9, 1123-1130 (2020). <lb/>183. Zhao, Y. et al. Longitudinal COVID-19 profiling associates IL-1RA and IL-10 with <lb/>disease severity and RANTES with mild disease. JCI Insight 5, e139834 (2020). <lb/>184. Hu, W. Use interleukin-10 as the therapeutic agent for COVID-19. OSF Preprint at <lb/>https://doi.org/10.31219/osf.io/arfhb (2020). <lb/>185. Lu, L., Zhang, H., Dauphars, D. J. &amp; He, Y. W. A potential role of interleukin 10 in <lb/>COVID-19 pathogenesis. Trends Immunol. 42, 3-5 (2021). <lb/>186. Ma, X. &amp; Trinchieri, G. Regulation of interleukin-12 production in antigen-<lb/>presenting cells. Adv. Immunol. 79, 55-92 (2001). <lb/>187. Vignali, D. A. &amp; Kuchroo, V. K. IL-12 family cytokines: immunological playmakers. <lb/>Nat. Immunol. 13, 722-728 (2012). <lb/>188. O&apos;Shea, J. J. &amp; Paul, W. E. Regulation of T(H)1 differentiation-controlling the <lb/>controllers. Nat. Immunol. 3, 506-508 (2002). <lb/>189. Ozmen, L., Aguet, M., Trinchieri, G. &amp; Garotta, G. The in vivo antiviral activity of <lb/>interleukin-12 is mediated by gamma interferon. J. Virol. 69, 8147-8150 (1995). <lb/>190. Monteiro, J. M., Harvey, C. &amp; Trinchieri, G. Role of interleukin-12 in primary <lb/>influenza virus infection. J. Virol. 72, 4825-4831 (1998). <lb/>191. Orange, J. S., Wolf, S. F. &amp; Biron, C. A. Effects of IL-12 on the response and <lb/>susceptibility to experimental viral infections. J. Immunol. 152, 1253-1264 <lb/>(1994). <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">The signal pathways and treatment of cytokine storm in COVID-19 <lb/>Yang et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>16 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Signal Transduction and Targeted Therapy (2021) 6:255 <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>192. Wong, C. K. et al. Plasma inflammatory cytokines and chemokines in severe <lb/>acute respiratory syndrome. Clin. Exp. Immunol. 136, 95-103 (2004). <lb/>193. Cua, D. J. &amp; Tato, C. M. Innate IL-17-producing cells: the sentinels of the immune <lb/>system. Nat. Rev. Immunol. 10, 479-489 (2010). <lb/>194. Langrish, C. L. et al. IL-23 drives a pathogenic T cell population that induces <lb/>autoimmune inflammation. J. Exp. Med. 201, 233-240 (2005). <lb/>195. McInnes, I. B. et al. Secukinumab sustains improvement in signs and symptoms <lb/>of psoriatic arthritis: 2 year results from the phase 3 FUTURE 2 study. Rheu-<lb/>matology 56, 1993-2003 (2017). <lb/>196. Pacha, O., Sallman, M. A. &amp; Evans, S. E. COVID-19: a case for inhibiting IL-17? Nat. <lb/>Rev. Immunol. 20, 345-346 (2020). <lb/>197. Josset, L. et al. Cell host response to infection with novel human coronavirus <lb/>EMC predicts potential antivirals and important differences with SARS cor-<lb/>onavirus. mBio 4, e00165-00113 (2013). <lb/>198. Faure, E. et al. Distinct immune response in two MERS-CoV-infected patients: <lb/>can we go from bench to bedside? PLoS ONE 9, e88716 (2014). <lb/>199. Muir, R. et al. Innate lymphoid cells are the predominant source of IL-17A during <lb/>the early pathogenesis of acute respiratory distress syndrome. Am. J. Respir. Crit. <lb/>Care Med. 193, 407-416 (2016). <lb/>200. Li, Q. et al. Blockade of interleukin-17 restrains the development of acute lung <lb/>injury. Scand. J. Immunol. 83, 203-211 (2016). <lb/>201. Liu, Y. et al. 2019-Novel coronavirus (2019-nCoV) infections trigger an exag-<lb/>gerated cytokine response aggravating lung injury. ChinaXiv https://doi.org/ <lb/>10.12074/202002.00018 (2020). <lb/>202. Becher, B., Tugues, S. &amp; Greter, M. GM-CSF: from growth factor to central <lb/>mediator of tissue inflammation. Immunity 45, 963-973 (2016). <lb/>203. Guilliams, M. et al. Alveolar macrophages develop from fetal monocytes that <lb/>differentiate into long-lived cells in the first week of life via GM-CSF. J. Exp. Med. <lb/>210, 1977-1992 (2013). <lb/>204. Trapnell, B. C. et al. Pulmonary alveolar proteinosis. Nat. Rev. Dis. Prim. 5, 16 <lb/>(2019). <lb/>205. Hamilton, J. A. GM-CSF in inflammation. J. Exp. Med. 217, e20190945 (2020). <lb/>206. Reghunathan, R. et al. Expression profile of immune response genes in patients <lb/>with Severe Acute Respiratory Syndrome. BMC Immunol. 6, 2 (2005). <lb/>207. Matute-Bello, G. et al. Neutrophil apoptosis in the acute respiratory distress <lb/>syndrome. Am. J. Respir. Crit. Care Med. 156, 1969-1977 (1997). <lb/>208. Ahmed, O. CAR-T-cell neurotoxicity: hope is on the horizon. Blood 133, <lb/>2114-2116 (2019). <lb/>209. Lang, F. M. et al. GM-CSF-based treatments in COVID-19: reconciling opposing <lb/>therapeutic approaches. Nat. Rev. Immunol. 20, 507-514 (2020). <lb/>210. Liu, Q., Zhou, Y. H. &amp; Yang, Z. Q. The cytokine storm of severe influenza and <lb/>development of immunomodulatory therapy. Cell. Mol. Immunol. 13, 3-10 <lb/>(2016). <lb/>211. Lee, D. W. et al. Current concepts in the diagnosis and management of cytokine <lb/>release syndrome. Blood 124, 188-195 (2014). <lb/>212. Chan, J. F. et al. Treatment with lopinavir/ritonavir or interferon-beta1b <lb/>improves outcome of MERS-CoV infection in a nonhuman primate model of <lb/>common marmoset. J. Infect. Dis. 212, 1904-1913 (2015). <lb/>213. Stockman, L. J., Bellamy, R. &amp; Garner, P. SARS: systematic review of treatment <lb/>effects. PLoS Med. 3, e343 (2006). <lb/>214. Mantlo, E. et al. Antiviral activities of type I interferons to SARS-CoV-2 infection. <lb/>Antivir. Res. 179, 104811 (2020). <lb/>215. Zhou, Q. et al. Interferon-alpha2b treatment for COVID-19. Front. Immunol. 11, <lb/>1061 (2020). <lb/>216. Hung, I. F. et al. Triple combination of interferon beta-1b, lopinavir-ritonavir, and <lb/>ribavirin in the treatment of patients admitted to hospital with COVID-19: an <lb/>open-label, randomised, phase 2 trial. Lancet 395, 1695-1704 (2020). <lb/>217. Meng, Z. et al. The effect of recombinant human interferon alpha nasal drops to <lb/>prevent COVID-19 pneumonia for medical staff in an epidemic area. Curr Top <lb/>Med Chem 21, 920-927 (2021). <lb/>218. Dinnon, K. H. 3rd et al. Publisher Correction: a mouse-adapted model of SARS-<lb/>CoV-2 to test COVID-19 countermeasures. Nature 590, E22 (2021). <lb/>219. Yang, D., Geng, T., Harrison, A. G. &amp; Wang, P. Differential roles of RIG-I-like <lb/>receptors in SARS-CoV-2 infection. Preprint at bioRxiv https://doi.org/10.1101/ <lb/>2021.02.10.430677 (2021). <lb/>220. Yin, X. et al. MDA5 governs the innate immune response to SARS-CoV-2 in lung <lb/>epithelial cells. Cell Rep. 34, 108628 (2021). <lb/>221. Rebendenne, A. et al. SARS-CoV-2 triggers an MDA-5-dependent interferon <lb/>response which is unable to control replication in lung epithelial cells. J. Virol. <lb/>95, e02415-20 (2021). <lb/>222. Monneret, G. et al. Immune monitoring of interleukin-7 compassionate use in a <lb/>critically ill COVID-19 patient. Cell. Mol. Immunol. 17, 1001-1003 (2020). <lb/>223. Laterre, P. F. et al. Association of interleukin 7 immunotherapy with lymphocyte <lb/>counts among patients with severe coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19). JAMA <lb/>Netw. Open. 3, e2016485 (2020). <lb/>224. Clark, I. A. Background to new treatments for COVID-19, including its chronicity, <lb/>through altering elements of the cytokine storm. Rev. Med. Virol. e2210 (2020). <lb/>225. WHOREAfC-TW Group. Association between administration of systemic corti-<lb/>costeroids and mortality among critically ill patients with COVID-19: a meta-<lb/>analysis. JAMA 324, 1330-1341 (2020). <lb/>226. Johnson, R. M. &amp; Vinetz, J. M. Dexamethasone in the management of Covid -19. <lb/>BMJ 370, m2648 (2020). <lb/>227. Lin, P. Targeting interleukin-6 for noninfectious uveitis. Clin. Ophthalmol. 9, <lb/>1697-1702 (2015). <lb/>228. Karkhur, S. et al. Interleukin-6 inhibition in the management of non-infectious <lb/>uveitis and beyond. J. Ophthalmic Inflamm. Infect. 9, 17 (2019). <lb/>229. Kaplon, H. &amp; Reichert, J. M. Antibodies to watch in 2021. mAbs 13, 1860476 <lb/>(2021). <lb/>230. Xu, X. et al. Effective treatment of severe COVID-19 patients with tocilizumab. <lb/>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA 117, 10970-10975 (2020). <lb/>231. Gupta, S. et al. Association between early treatment with tocilizumab and <lb/>mortality among critically ill patients with COVID-19. JAMA Intern. Med. 181, <lb/>41-51 (2021). <lb/>232. Veiga, V. C. et al. Effect of tocilizumab on clinical outcomes at 15 days in patients <lb/>with severe or critical coronavirus disease 2019: randomised controlled trial. BMJ <lb/>372, n84 (2021). <lb/>233. Salama, C. et al. Tocilizumab in patients hospitalized with Covid-19 pneumonia. <lb/>N. Engl. J. Med. 384, 20-30 (2021). <lb/>234. Galvan-Roman, J. M. et al. IL-6 serum levels predict severity and response to <lb/>tocilizumab in COVID-19: an observational study. J. Allergy Clin. Immunol. 147, <lb/>72-80 (2021). e78. <lb/>235. Hermine, O. et al. Effect of tocilizumab vs usual care in adults hospitalized with <lb/>COVID-19 and moderate or severe pneumonia: a randomized clinical trial. JAMA <lb/>Intern. Med. 181, 32-40 (2021). <lb/>236. Salvarani, C. et al. Effect of tocilizumab vs standard care on clinical worsening in <lb/>patients hospitalized with COVID-19 pneumonia: a randomized clinical trial. <lb/>JAMA Intern. Med. 181, 24-31 (2021). <lb/>237. Stone, J. H. et al. Efficacy of tocilizumab in patients hospitalized with Covid-19. <lb/>N. Engl. J. Med. 383, 2333-2344 (2020). <lb/>238. Ramiro, S. et al. Historically controlled comparison of glucocorticoids with or <lb/>without tocilizumab versus supportive care only in patients with COVID-19-<lb/>associated cytokine storm syndrome: results of the CHIC study. Ann. Rheum. Dis. <lb/>79, 1143-1151 (2020). <lb/>239. Roumier, M. et al. Tocilizumab for severe worsening COVID-19 pneumonia: a <lb/>propensity score analysis. J. Clin. Immunol. 41, 303-314 (2021). <lb/>240. Martinez-Sanz, J. et al. Effects of tocilizumab on mortality in hospitalized <lb/>patients with COVID-19: a multicentre cohort study. Clin. Microbiol. Infect. 27, <lb/>238-243 (2021). <lb/>241. Rodriguez-Bano, J. et al. Treatment with tocilizumab or corticosteroids for <lb/>COVID-19 patients with hyperinflammatory state: a multicentre cohort study <lb/>(SAM-COVID-19). Clin. Microbiol. Infect. 27, 244-252 (2021). <lb/>242. Sanz Herrero, F. et al. Methylprednisolone added to tocilizumab reduces mor-<lb/>tality in SARS-CoV-2 pneumonia: an observational study. J. Intern. Med. 289, <lb/>259-263 (2021). <lb/>243. Strohbehn, G. W. et al. COVIDOSE: a phase II clinical trial of low-dose tocilizumab <lb/>in the treatment of noncritical COVID-19 pneumonia. Clin. Pharmacol. Ther. 109, <lb/>688-696 (2021). <lb/>244. Pomponio, G. et al. Tocilizumab in COVID-19 interstitial pneumonia. J. Intern. <lb/>Med. 289, 738-746 (2021). <lb/>245. Perez-Saez, M. J. et al. Use of tocilizumab in kidney transplant recipients with <lb/>COVID-19. Am. J. Transplant. 20, 3182-3190 (2020). <lb/>246. Morillas, J. A. et al. Tocilizumab therapy in 5 solid and composite tissue trans-<lb/>plant recipients with early ARDS due to SARS-CoV-2. Am. J. Transplant. 20, <lb/>3191-3197 (2020). <lb/>247. Menzella, F. et al. Efficacy of tocilizumab in patients with COVID-19 ARDS <lb/>undergoing noninvasive ventilation. Crit. Care 24, 589 (2020). <lb/>248. Della-Torre, E. et al. Interleukin-6 blockade with sarilumab in severe COVID-19 <lb/>pneumonia with systemic hyperinflammation: an open-label cohort study. Ann. <lb/>Rheum. Dis. 79, 1277-1285 (2020). <lb/>249. Montesarchio, V. et al. Outcomes and biomarker analyses among patients with <lb/>COVID-19 treated with interleukin 6 (IL-6) receptor antagonist sarilumab at a <lb/>single institution in Italy. J. Immunother. Cancer 8, e001089 (2020). <lb/>250. Gritti, G. et al. IL-6 signalling pathway inactivation with siltuximab in patients <lb/>with COVID-19 respiratory failure: an observational cohort study. Preprint at <lb/>medRxiv https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.04.01.20048561 (2020). <lb/>251. Cauchois, R. et al. Early IL-1 receptor blockade in severe inflammatory respira-<lb/>tory failure complicating COVID-19. Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA 117, 18951-18953 <lb/>(2020). <lb/>252. Kooistra, E. J. et al. Anakinra treatment in critically ill COVID-19 patients: a <lb/>prospective cohort study. Crit. Care 24, 688 (2020). <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">The signal pathways and treatment of cytokine storm in COVID-19 <lb/>Yang et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>17 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Signal Transduction and Targeted Therapy (2021) 6:255 <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>253. Dimopoulos, G. et al. Favorable Anakinra responses in severe Covid-19 patients <lb/>with secondary hemophagocytic lymphohistiocytosis. Cell Host Microbe 28, <lb/>117-123.e111 (2020). <lb/>254. Huet, T. et al. Anakinra for severe forms of COVID-19: a cohort study. Lancet <lb/>Rheumatol. 2, e393-e400 (2020). <lb/>255. Cavalli, G. et al. Interleukin-1 blockade with high-dose anakinra in patients with <lb/>COVID-19, acute respiratory distress syndrome, and hyperinflammation: a ret-<lb/>rospective cohort study. Lancet Rheumatol. 2, e325-e331 (2020). <lb/>256. Balkhair, A. et al. Anakinra in hospitalized patients with severe COVID-19 <lb/>pneumonia requiring oxygen therapy: results of a prospective, open-label, <lb/>interventional study. Int. J. Infect. Dis. 103, 288-296 (2021). <lb/>257. Bozzi, G. et al. Anakinra combined with methylprednisolone in patients with <lb/>severe COVID-19 pneumonia and hyperinflammation: an observational cohort <lb/>study. J. Allergy Clin. Immunol. 147, 561-566.e564 (2021). <lb/>258. The CORIMUNO-19 Collaborative group. Effect of anakinra versus usual care in <lb/>adults in hospital with COVID-19 and mild-to-moderate pneumonia (COR-<lb/>IMUNO-ANA-1): a randomised controlled trial. Lancet Respir. Med. 9, 295-304 <lb/>(2021). <lb/>259. Iglesias-Julian, E. et al. High dose subcutaneous Anakinra to treat acute <lb/>respiratory distress syndrome secondary to cytokine storm syndrome among <lb/>severely ill COVID-19 patients. J. Autoimmun. 115, 102537 (2020). <lb/>260. Navarro-Millan, I. et al. Use of Anakinra to prevent mechanical ventilation in <lb/>severe COVID-19: a case series. Arthritis Rheumatol. 72, 1990-1997 (2020). <lb/>261. Kyriazopoulou, E. et al. An open label trial of anakinra to prevent respiratory <lb/>failure in COVID-19. Elife 10, e66125 (2021). <lb/>262. Ucciferri, C. et al. Canakinumab in a subgroup of patients with COVID-19. Lancet <lb/>Rheumatol. 2, e457-e458 (2020). <lb/>263. Katia, F. et al. Efficacy of canakinumab in mild or severe COVID-19 pneumonia. <lb/>Immun. Inflamm. Dis 9, 399-405 (2021). <lb/>264. Sheng, C. C. et al. Canakinumab to reduce deterioration of cardiac and <lb/>respiratory function in SARS-CoV-2 associated myocardial injury with heigh-<lb/>tened inflammation (canakinumab in Covid-19 cardiac injury: the three C study). <lb/>Clin. Cardiol. 43, 1055-1063 (2020). <lb/>265. Generali, D. et al. Canakinumab as treatment for COVID-19-related pneumonia: a <lb/>prospective case-control study. Int. J. Infect. Dis. 104, 433-440 (2020). <lb/>266. Landi, L. et al. Blockage of interleukin-1beta with canakinumab in patients with <lb/>Covid-19. Sci. Rep. 10, 21775 (2020). <lb/>267. National Institute of Diabetes and Digestive and Kidney Disease. Emapalumab. <lb/>LiverTox: Clinical and Research Information on Drug-Induced Liver Injury (National <lb/>Institute of Diabetes and Digestive and Kidney Diseases, 2012). <lb/>268. Chen, X. Y., Yan, B. X. &amp; Man, X. Y. TNFalpha inhibitor may be effective for severe <lb/>COVID-19: learning from toxic epidermal necrolysis. Ther. Adv. Respir. Dis. 14, <lb/>1753466620926800 (2020). <lb/>269. Duret, P. M. et al. Recovery from COVID-19 in a patient with spondyloarthritis <lb/>treated with TNF-alpha inhibitor etanercept. Ann. Rheum. Dis. 79, 1251-1252 <lb/>(2020). <lb/>270. Kunisaki, R., Tsukiji, J. &amp; Kudo, M. Potential inhibition of COVID-19-driven <lb/>pneumonia by immunosuppressive therapy and anti-TNFalpha antibodies: a <lb/>case report. J. Crohns Colitis 14,1786-1787 (2020). <lb/>271. Feldmann, M. et al. Trials of anti-tumour necrosis factor therapy for COVID-19 <lb/>are urgently needed. Lancet 395, 1407-1409 (2020). <lb/>272. Bai, F. et al. Short-term efficacy and safety of IL-17, IL-12/23, and IL-23 inhibitors <lb/>brodalumab, secukinumab, ixekizumab, ustekinumab, guselkumab, til-<lb/>drakizumab, and risankizumab for the treatment of moderate to severe plaque <lb/>psoriasis: a systematic review and network meta-analysis of randomized con-<lb/>trolled trials. J. Immunol. Res. 2019, 2546161 (2019). <lb/>273. Armstrong, A. W. &amp; Read, C. Pathophysiology, clinical presentation, and treat-<lb/>ment of psoriasis: a review. JAMA 323, 1945-1960 (2020). <lb/>274. Almradi, A. et al. Clinical trials of IL-12/IL-23 inhibitors in inflammatory bowel <lb/>disease. BioDrugs 34, 713-721 (2020). <lb/>275. Feagan, B. G. et al. Ustekinumab as induction and maintenance therapy for <lb/>Crohn&apos;s disease. N. Engl. J. Med. 375, 1946-1960 (2016). <lb/>276. Moschen, A. R., Tilg, H. &amp; Raine, T. IL-12, IL-23 and IL-17 in IBD: immunobiology <lb/>and therapeutic targeting. Nat. Rev. Gastroenterol. Hepatol. 16, 185-196 (2019). <lb/>277. Sadeghinia, A. &amp; Daneshpazhooh, M. Immunosuppressive drugs for patients <lb/>with psoriasis during the COVID-19 pandemic era. A review. Dermatol. Ther. 34, <lb/>e14498 (2021). <lb/>278. Ward, M. &amp; Gooderham, M. Asymptomatic SARS-CoV2 infection in a patient <lb/>receiving risankizumab, an inhibitor of interleukin 23. JAAD Case Rep. 7, 60-61 <lb/>(2021). <lb/>279. Kiss, N. et al. Coronavirus disease 2019 in a psoriatic patient with concomitant <lb/>chronic obstructive pulmonary disease under treatment with risankizumab. <lb/>Dermatol. Ther. 33, e14186 (2020). <lb/>280. Messina, F., Pampaloni, F. &amp; Piaserico, S. Comment on: recovery from COVID-19 <lb/>in a patient with spondyloarthritis treated with TNF-alpha inhibitor etanercept. <lb/>A report on a patient with COVID-19 with psoriatic arthritis receiving usteki-<lb/>numab. Ann. Rheum. Dis. 80, E79-E79 (2020). <lb/>281. Messina, F. &amp; Piaserico, S. SARS-CoV-2 infection in a psoriatic patient treated <lb/>with IL-23 inhibitor. J. Eur. Acad. Dermatol. Venereol. 34, e254-e255 (2020). <lb/>282. Wang, C. J. &amp; Truong, A. K. COVID-19 infection on IL-23 inhibition. Dermatol. <lb/>Ther. 33, e13893 (2020). <lb/>283. Shibabaw, T. Inflammatory cytokine: IL-17A signaling pathway in patients pre-<lb/>sent with COVID-19 and current treatment strategy. J. Inflamm. Res. 13, 673-680 <lb/>(2020). <lb/>284. Mendoza, V. M. M. Interleukin-17: a potential therapeutic target in COVID-19. J. <lb/>Infect. 81, e136-e138 (2020). <lb/>285. Ayhan, E. et al. Potential role of anti-interleukin-17 in COVID-19 treatment. <lb/>Dermatol. Ther. 33, e13715 (2020). <lb/>286. Casillo, G. M. et al. Could IL-17 represent a new therapeutic target for the <lb/>treatment and/or management of COVID-19-related respiratory syndrome? <lb/>Pharm. Res. 156, 104791 (2020). <lb/>287. Piaserico, S., Meneguzzo, A. &amp; Messina, F. REPLY TO: interleukin-17: a potential <lb/>therapeutic target in COVID-19. J. Infect. 81, e37-e38 (2020). <lb/>288. Cafarotti, S. Severe acute respiratory syndrome-coronavirus-2 infection and <lb/>patients with lung cancer: the potential role of interleukin-17 target therapy. J. <lb/>Thorac. Oncol. 15, e101-e103 (2020). <lb/>289. Wiche Salinas, T. R., Zheng, B., Routy, J. P. &amp; Ancuta, P. Targeting the interleukin-<lb/>17 pathway to prevent acute respiratory distress syndrome associated with <lb/>SARS-CoV-2 infection. Respirology 25, 797-799 (2020). <lb/>290. Conti, A., Lasagni, C., Bigi, L. &amp; Pellacani, G. Evolution of COVID-19 infection in <lb/>four psoriatic patients treated with biological drugs. J. Eur. Acad. Dermatol. <lb/>Venereol. 34, e360-e361 (2020). <lb/>291. Balestri, R., Rech, G. &amp; Girardelli, C. R. SARS-CoV-2 infection in a psoriatic patient <lb/>treated with IL-17 inhibitor. J. Eur. Acad. Dermatol. Venereol. 34, e357-e358 <lb/>(2020). <lb/>292. Carugno, A. et al. Coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) rash in a psoriatic patient <lb/>treated with Secukinumab: Is there a role for interleukin 17? Dermatol. Ther. 33, <lb/>e14011 (2020). <lb/>293. Gisondi, P. et al. The impact of the COVID-19 pandemic on patients with chronic <lb/>plaque psoriasis being treated with biological therapy: the Northern Italy <lb/>experience. Br. J. Dermatol. 183, 373-374 (2020). <lb/>294. Presneill, J. J. et al. A randomized phase II trial of granulocyte-macrophage <lb/>colony-stimulating factor therapy in severe sepsis with respiratory dysfunction. <lb/>Am. J. Respir. Crit. Care Med. 166, 138-143 (2002). <lb/>295. Orozco, H. et al. Molgramostim (GM-CSF) associated with antibiotic treatment in <lb/>nontraumatic abdominal sepsis: a randomized, double-blind, placebo-<lb/>controlled clinical trial. Arch. Surg. 141, 150-153 (2006); discussion 154. <lb/>296. Paine, R. 3rd et al. A randomized trial of recombinant human granulocyte-<lb/>macrophage colony stimulating factor for patients with acute lung injury. Crit. <lb/>Care Med. 40, 90-97 (2012). <lb/>297. Crotti, C. et al. Mavrilimumab: a unique insight and update on the current status <lb/>in the treatment of rheumatoid arthritis. Expert Opin. Investig. Drugs 28, 573-581 <lb/>(2019). <lb/>298. De Luca, G. et al. GM-CSF blockade with mavrilimumab in severe COVID-19 <lb/>pneumonia and systemic hyperinflammation: a single-centre, prospective <lb/>cohort study. Lancet Rheumatol. 2, e465-e473 (2020). <lb/>299. Temesgen, Z. et al. GM-CSF neutralization with lenzilumab in severe COVID-19 <lb/>pneumonia: a case-cohort study. Mayo Clin. Proc. 95, 2382-2394 (2020). <lb/>300. Zhang, X. et al. Baricitinib, a drug with potential effect to prevent SARS-COV-2 <lb/>from entering target cells and control cytokine storm induced by COVID-19. Int. <lb/>Immunopharmacol. 86, 106749 (2020). <lb/>301. Yeleswaram, S. et al. Inhibition of cytokine signaling by ruxolitinib and impli-<lb/>cations for COVID-19 treatment. Clin. Immunol. 218, 108517 (2020). <lb/>302. Seif, F. et al. JAK inhibition as a new treatment strategy for patients with COVID-<lb/>19. Int. Arch. Allergy Immunol. 181, 467-475 (2020). <lb/>303. Pearce, L., Davidson, S. M. &amp; Yellon, D. M. The cytokine storm of COVID-19: a <lb/>spotlight on prevention and protection. Expert Opin. Ther. Targets 24, 723-730 <lb/>(2020). <lb/>304. Satarker, S. et al. JAK-STAT pathway inhibition and their implications in COVID-<lb/>19 therapy. Postgrad. Med. 133, 489-507 (2020). <lb/>305. Calabrese, L. H., Lenfant, T. &amp; Calabrese, C. Cytokine storm release syndrome and <lb/>the prospects for immunotherapy with COVID-19, part 4: the role of JAK inhi-<lb/>bition: posted February 10, 2021. Clevel. Clin. J. Med. (2021). <lb/>306. Flanagan, M. E. et al. Discovery of CP-690,550: a potent and selective Janus <lb/>kinase (JAK) inhibitor for the treatment of autoimmune diseases and organ <lb/>transplant rejection. J. Med. Chem. 53, 8468-8484 (2010). <lb/>307. Danese, S., Grisham, M., Hodge, J. &amp; Telliez, J. B. JAK inhibition using tofaci-<lb/>tinib for inflammatory bowel disease treatment: a hub for multiple inflam-<lb/>matory cytokines. Am. J. Physiol. Gastrointest. Liver Physiol. 310, G155-G162 <lb/>(2016). <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">The signal pathways and treatment of cytokine storm in COVID-19 <lb/>Yang et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>18 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Signal Transduction and Targeted Therapy (2021) 6:255 <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>308. Quintas-Cardama, A. et al. Preclinical characterization of the selective JAK1/2 <lb/>inhibitor INCB018424: therapeutic implications for the treatment of myelopro-<lb/>liferative neoplasms. Blood 115, 3109-3117 (2010). <lb/>309. Verstovsek, S. et al. Safety and efficacy of INCB018424, a JAK1 and JAK2 inhi-<lb/>bitor, in myelofibrosis. N. Engl. J. Med. 363, 1117-1127 (2010). <lb/>310. van Vollenhoven, R. F. Small molecular compounds in development for rheu-<lb/>matoid arthritis. Curr. Opin. Rheumatol. 25, 391-397 (2013). <lb/>311. Hoang, T. N. et al. Baricitinib treatment resolves lower-airway macrophage <lb/>inflammation and neutrophil recruitment in SARS-CoV-2-infected rhesus <lb/>macaques. Cell 184, 460-475.e421 (2021). <lb/>312. Rodriguez-Garcia, J. L. et al. Baricitinib improves respiratory function in patients <lb/>treated with corticosteroids for SARS-CoV-2 pneumonia: an observational cohort <lb/>study. Rheumatology 60, 399-407 (2021). <lb/>313. Moreno-Gonzalez, G. et al. A phase I/II clinical trial to evaluate the efficacy of <lb/>baricitinib to prevent respiratory insufficiency progression in onco-<lb/>hematological patients affected with COVID19: a structured summary of a <lb/>study protocol for a randomised controlled trial. Trials 22, 116 (2021). <lb/>314. Stebbing, J. et al. Mechanism of baricitinib supports artificial intelligence-<lb/>predicted testing in COVID-19 patients. EMBO Mol. Med. 12, e12697 (2020). <lb/>315. Cantini, F. et al. Baricitinib therapy in COVID-19: a pilot study on safety and <lb/>clinical impact. J. Infect. 81, 318-356 (2020). <lb/>316. Kalil, A. C. et al. Baricitinib plus Remdesivir for hospitalized adults with Covid-19. <lb/>N. Engl. J. Med. 384, 795-807 (2020). <lb/>317. Cantini, F. et al. Beneficial impact of Baricitinib in COVID-19 moderate pneu-<lb/>monia; multicentre study. J. Infect. 81, 647-679 (2020). <lb/>318. Titanji, B. K. et al. Use of Baricitinib in patients with moderate and severe COVID-<lb/>19. Clin. Infect. Dis. 72, 1247-1250 (2020). <lb/>319. Cingolani, A. et al. Baricitinib as rescue therapy in a patient with COVID-19 with <lb/>no complete response to sarilumab. Infection 48, 767-771 (2020). <lb/>320. Hasan, M. J., Rabbani, R., Anam, A. M. &amp; Huq, S. M. R. Additional baricitinib <lb/>loading dose improves clinical outcome in COVID-19. Open Med. 16, 41-46 <lb/>(2021). <lb/>321. Sodani, P. et al. Successful recovery from COVID-19 pneumonia after receiving <lb/>baricitinib, tocilizumab, and remdesivir. a case report: review of treatments and <lb/>clinical role of computed tomography analysis. Respir. Med. Case Rep. 31, 101115 <lb/>(2020). <lb/>322. Rosas, J. et al. Experience with the use of Baricitinib and Tocilizumab mono-<lb/>therapy or combined, in patients with interstitial pneumonia secondary to <lb/>coronavirus COVID19: a real-world study. Reumatol. Clin. S1699-258X, 30271-0 <lb/>(2020). <lb/>323. Goker Bagca, B. &amp; Biray Avci, C. The potential of JAK/STAT pathway inhibition by <lb/>ruxolitinib in the treatment of COVID-19. Cytokine Growth Factor Rev. 54, 51-62 <lb/>(2020). <lb/>324. Innes, A. J. et al. Ruxolitinib for tocilizumab-refractory severe COVID-19 infection. <lb/>Br. J. Haematol. 190, e198-e200 (2020). <lb/>325. Cao, Y. et al. Ruxolitinib in treatment of severe coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-<lb/>19): a multicenter, single-blind, randomized controlled trial. J. Allergy Clin. <lb/>Immunol. 146, 137-146.e133 (2020). <lb/>326. Caocci, G. &amp; La Nasa, G. Could ruxolitinib be effective in patients with COVID-19 <lb/>infection at risk of acute respiratory distress syndrome (ARDS)? Ann. Hematol. <lb/>99, 1675-1676 (2020). <lb/>327. Winthrop, K. L. et al. Herpes zoster infection in patients with ulcerative colitis <lb/>receiving Tofacitinib. Inflamm. Bowel Dis. 24, 2258-2265 (2018). <lb/>328. Colombel, J. F. Herpes zoster in patients receiving JAK inhibitors for ulcerative <lb/>colitis: mechanism, epidemiology, management, and prevention. Inflamm. <lb/>Bowel Dis. 24, 2173-2182 (2018). <lb/>329. Askin, O., Ozkoca, D., Uzuncakmak, T. K. &amp; Serdaroglu, S. Uzuncakmak, T. K. &amp; <lb/>Serdaroglu, S. Evaluation of the alopecia areata patients on tofacitinib treatment <lb/>during the COVID-19 pandemic. Dermatol. Ther. 34, e14746 (2021). <lb/>330. Beyzarov, E. et al. Global Safety Database summary of COVID-19-related drug <lb/>utilization-safety surveillance: a sponsor&apos;s perspective. Drug Saf. 44, 95-105 <lb/>(2021). <lb/>331. Agrawal, M. et al. Characteristics and outcomes of IBD patients with COVID-19 <lb/>on Tofacitinib therapy in the SECURE-IBD tegistry. Inflamm. Bowel Dis. 27, <lb/>585-589 (2020). <lb/>332. Favalli, E. G., Biggioggero, M., Maioli, G. &amp; Caporali, R. Baricitinib for COVID-19: a <lb/>suitable treatment? Lancet Infect. Dis. 20, 1012-1013 (2020). <lb/>333. Praveen, D., Puvvada, R. C. &amp; M, V. A. Janus kinase inhibitor baricitinib is not an <lb/>ideal option for management of COVID-19. Int. J. Antimicrob. Agents 55, 105967 <lb/>(2020). <lb/>334. Picchianti Diamanti, A. et al. Cytokine release syndrome in COVID-19 patients, a <lb/>new scenario for an old concern: the fragile balance between infections and <lb/>autoimmunity. Int. J. Mol. Sci. 21, 3330 (2020). <lb/>335. US FDA. FDA Issues Tofacitinib Safety Alert. FDA Approves Boxed Warning About <lb/>Increased Risk of Blood Clots and Death with Higher Dose of Arthritis and <lb/>Ulcerative Colitis Medicine Tofacitinib (US FDA, 2019). <lb/>336. Kircheis, R. et al. NF-kappaB pathway as a potential target for treatment of <lb/>critical stage COVID-19 patients. Front. Immunol. 11, 598444 (2020). <lb/>337. Kandasamy, M. NF-kappaB signalling as a pharmacological target in COVID-19: <lb/>potential roles for IKKbeta inhibitors. Naunyn Schmiedebergs Arch. Pharmacol. <lb/>394, 561-567 (2021). <lb/>338. Hariharan, A. et al. The role and therapeutic potential of NF-kappa-B pathway in <lb/>severe COVID-19 patients. Inflammopharmacology 29, 91-100 (2021). <lb/>339. Ma, Q. et al. Phillyrin (KD-1) exerts anti-viral and anti-inflammatory activities <lb/>against novel coronavirus (SARS-CoV-2) and human coronavirus 229E (HCoV-<lb/>229E) by suppressing the nuclear factor kappa B (NF-kappaB) signaling pathway. <lb/>Phytomedicine 78, 153296 (2020). <lb/>340. Masih, A. et al. Discovery of novel pyrazole derivatives as a potent anti-<lb/>inflammatory agent in RAW264.7 cells via inhibition of NF-kB for possible <lb/>benefit against SARS-CoV-2. J. Biochem. Mol. Toxicol. 35, e22656 (2020). <lb/>341. Ma, Q. et al. Liu Shen capsule shows antiviral and anti-inflammatory abilities <lb/>against novel coronavirus SARS-CoV-2 via suppression of NF-kappaB signaling <lb/>pathway. Pharm. Res. 158, 104850 (2020). <lb/>342. D&apos;Acquisto, F., May, M. J. &amp; Ghosh, S. Inhibition of nuclear factor kappa B (NF-<lb/>B): an emerging theme in anti-inflammatory therapies. Mol. Interv. 2, 22-35 <lb/>(2002). <lb/>343. Liang, N. et al. Immunosuppressive effects of hydroxychloroquine and artemi-<lb/>sinin combination therapy via the nuclear factor-kappaB signaling pathway in <lb/>lupus nephritis mice. Exp. Ther. Med. 15, 2436-2442 (2018). <lb/>344. Cheung, P. S., Si, E. C. &amp; Hosseini, K. Anti-inflammatory activity of azithromycin as <lb/>measured by its NF-kappaB, inhibitory activity. Ocul. Immunol. Inflamm. 18, <lb/>32-37 (2010). <lb/>345. Bleyzac, N., Goutelle, S., Bourguignon, L. &amp; Tod, M. Azithromycin for COVID-19: <lb/>more than just an antimicrobial? Clin. Drug Investig. 40, 683-686 (2020). <lb/>346. Assimakopoulos, S. F. &amp; Marangos, M. N-acetyl-cysteine may prevent COVID-19-<lb/>associated cytokine storm and acute respiratory distress syndrome. Med. <lb/>Hypotheses 140, 109778 (2020). <lb/>347. Oka, S. et al. N-acetylcysteine suppresses TNF-induced NF-kappaB activation <lb/>through inhibition of IkappaB kinases. FEBS Lett. 472, 196-202 (2000). <lb/>348. McCarty, M. F. et al. Nutraceutical strategies for suppressing NLRP3 inflamma-<lb/>some activation: pertinence to the management of COVID-19 and beyond. <lb/>Nutrients 13, 47 (2020). <lb/>349. Shah, A. Novel coronavirus-induced NLRP3 inflammasome activation: a poten-<lb/>tial drug target in the treatment of COVID-19. Front. Immunol. 11, 1021 (2020). <lb/>350. Toldo, S. &amp; Abbate, A. The NLRP3 inflammasome in acute myocardial infarction. <lb/>Nat. Rev. Cardiol. 15, 203-214 (2018). <lb/>351. Marques-da-Silva, C. et al. Colchicine inhibits cationic dye uptake induced by <lb/>ATP in P2X2 and P2X7 receptor-expressing cells: implications for its therapeutic <lb/>action. Br. J. Pharmacol. 163, 912-926 (2011). <lb/>352. Chen, X. et al. The antimalarial chloroquine suppresses LPS-induced NLRP3 <lb/>inflammasome activation and confers protection against murine endotoxic <lb/>shock. Mediat. Inflamm. 2017, 6543237 (2017). <lb/>353. Saeedi-Boroujeni, A., Mahmoudian-Sani, M. R., Bahadoram, M. &amp; Alghasi, A. <lb/>COVID-19: a case for inhibiting NLRP3 inflammasome, suppression of inflam-<lb/>mation with curcumin? Basic Clin. Pharmacol. Toxicol. 128, 37-45 (2021). <lb/>354. Quagliariello, V. et al. SARS-CoV-2 infection: NLRP3 inflammasome as plausible <lb/>target to prevent cardiopulmonary complications? Eur. Rev. Med. Pharmacol. Sci. <lb/>24, 9169-9171 (2020). <lb/>355. Agarwal, S. et al. Identification of a novel orally bioavailable NLRP3 inflamma-<lb/>some inhibitor. Bioorg. Med. Chem. Lett. 30, 127571 (2020). <lb/>356. Kohler, H. &amp; Kaveri, S. How IvIg can mitigate Covid-19 disease: a symmetrical <lb/>immune network model. Monoclon. Antib. Immunodiagn. Immunother. 40, 17-20 <lb/>(2021). <lb/>357. Ross, C. et al. High avidity IFN-neutralizing antibodies in pharmaceutically pre-<lb/>pared human IgG. J. Clin. Invest. 95, 1974-1978 (1995). <lb/>358. Mohan, P. V. et al. Can polyclonal intravenous immunoglobulin limit cytokine <lb/>mediated cerebral damage and chronic lung disease in preterm infants? Arch. <lb/>Dis. Child Fetal Neonatal Ed. 89, F5-F8 (2004). <lb/>359. Dalakas, M. C. Mechanism of action of intravenous immunoglobulin and ther-<lb/>apeutic considerations in the treatment of autoimmune neurologic diseases. <lb/>Neurology 51, S2-S8 (1998). <lb/>360. Watanabe, M. et al. High avidity cytokine autoantibodies in health and disease: <lb/>pathogenesis and mechanisms. Cytokine Growth Factor Rev. 21, 263-273 (2010). <lb/>361. Hung, I. F. N. et al. Hyperimmune IV immunoglobulin treatment: a multicenter <lb/>double-blind randomized controlled trial for patients with severe 2009 influenza <lb/>A(H1N1) infection. Chest 144, 464-473 (2013). <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">The signal pathways and treatment of cytokine storm in COVID-19 <lb/>Yang et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>19 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Signal Transduction and Targeted Therapy (2021) 6:255 <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>362. Chong, P. Y. et al. Analysis of deaths during the severe acute respiratory syn-<lb/>drome (SARS) epidemic in Singapore: challenges in determining a SARS diag-<lb/>nosis. Arch. Pathol. Lab. Med. 128, 195-204 (2004). <lb/>363. Tabarsi, P. et al. Evaluating the effects of intravenous immunoglobulin (IVIg) on <lb/>the management of severe COVID-19 cases: a randomized controlled trial. Int. <lb/>Immunopharmacol. 90, 107205 (2021). <lb/>364. Suzuki, Y. et al. Severe coronavirus disease 2019 that recovered from respiratory <lb/>failure by treatment that included high-dose intravenous immunoglobulin. <lb/>Intern. Med. 60, 457-461 (2021). <lb/>365. Dagens, A. et al. Scope, quality, and inclusivity of clinical guidelines produced <lb/>early in the covid-19 pandemic: rapid review. BMJ 369, m1936 (2020). <lb/>366. Russell, C. D., Millar, J. E. &amp; Baillie, J. K. Clinical evidence does not support <lb/>corticosteroid treatment for 2019-nCoV lung injury. Lancet 395, 473-475 (2020). <lb/>367. Group, R. C. et al. Dexamethasone in hospitalized patients with covid-19. N. Engl. <lb/>J. Med. 384, 693-704 (2021). <lb/>368. He, X. et al. Temporal dynamics in viral shedding and transmissibility of COVID-<lb/>19. Nat. Med. 26, 672-675 (2020). <lb/>369. Wolfel, R. et al. Virological assessment of hospitalized patients with COVID-2019. <lb/>Nature 581, 465-469 (2020). <lb/>370. To, K. K. et al. Temporal profiles of viral load in posterior oropharyngeal saliva <lb/>samples and serum antibody responses during infection by SARS-CoV-2: an <lb/>observational cohort study. Lancet Infect. Dis. 20, 565-574 (2020). <lb/>371. Shen, Y. et al. Protective effects of Lizhong decoction on ulcerative colitis in <lb/>mice by suppressing inflammation and ameliorating gut barrier. J. Ethno-<lb/>pharmacol. 259, 112919 (2020). <lb/>372. Chen, X. et al. Study on efficacy of liujunzi decoction combined with zuojin pills <lb/>in treating acute radioactive duodenitis and their mechanism. Zhongguo Zhong <lb/>Yao Za Zhi 39, 278-284 (2014). <lb/>373. Zhou, J. et al. Anti-inflammatory and regulatory effects of Huanglian Jiedu <lb/>Decoction on lipid homeostasis and the TLR4/MyD88 signaling pathway in LPS-<lb/>induced zebrafish. Front. Physiol. 10, 1241 (2019). <lb/>374. Hu, K. et al. Efficacy and safety of Lianhuaqingwen capsules, a repurposed <lb/>Chinese herb, in patients with coronavirus disease 2019: a multicenter, pro-<lb/>spective, randomized controlled trial. Phytomedicine 85, 153242 (2021). <lb/>375. Yang, R. et al. Chemical composition and pharmacological mechanism of <lb/>Qingfei Paidu Decoction and Ma Xing Shi Gan Decoction against coronavirus <lb/>disease 2019 (COVID-19): In silico and experimental study. Pharm. Res. 157, <lb/>104820 (2020). <lb/>376. Dai, Y. et al. A large-scale transcriptional study reveals inhibition of COVID-19 <lb/>related cytokine storm by traditional Chinese medicines. Sci. Bull. 66, 884-888 <lb/>(2021). <lb/>377. Bonifant, C. L., Jackson, H. J., Brentjens, R. J. &amp; Curran, K. J. Toxicity and man-<lb/>agement in CAR T-cell therapy. Mol. Ther. Oncolytics 3, 16011 (2016). <lb/>378. Zhang, H. et al. CDK7 inhibition potentiates genome instability triggering anti-<lb/>tumor immunity in small cell lung cancer. Cancer Cell 37, 37-54 (2020). e39. <lb/>379. Cartwright, J. A., Lucas, C. D. &amp; Rossi, A. G. Inflammation resolution and the <lb/>induction of granulocyte apoptosis by cyclin-dependent kinase inhibitor drugs. <lb/>Front. Pharmacol. 10, 55 (2019). <lb/>380. Wei, Y. et al. Targeting CDK7 suppresses super enhancer-linked inflammatory <lb/>genes and alleviates CAR T cell-induced cytokine release syndrome. Mol. Cancer <lb/>20, 5 (2021). <lb/>381. Cavalli, G. &amp; Dinarello, C. A. Suppression of inflammation and acquired immunity <lb/>by IL-37. Immunol. Rev. 281, 179-190 (2018). <lb/>382. Dinarello, C. A. The IL-1 family of cytokines and receptors in rheumatic diseases. <lb/>Nat. Rev. Rheumatol. 15, 612-632 (2019). <lb/>383. Nold, M. F. et al. IL-37 is a fundamental inhibitor of innate immunity. Nat. <lb/>Immunol. 11, 1014-1022 (2010). <lb/>384. Banchereau, J., Pascual, V. &amp; O&apos;Garra, A. From IL-2 to IL-37: the expanding <lb/>spectrum of anti-inflammatory cytokines. Nat. Immunol. 13, 925-931 (2012). <lb/></listBibl>

			<front>Open Access This article is licensed under a Creative Commons <lb/>Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, <lb/>adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give <lb/>appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative <lb/>Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party <lb/>material in this article are included in the article&apos;s Creative Commons license, unless <lb/>indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the <lb/>article&apos;s Creative Commons license and your intended use is not permitted by statutory <lb/>regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly <lb/>from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this license, visit http://creativecommons. <lb/>org/licenses/by/4.0/. <lb/>© The Author(s) 2021, corrected publication 2021 <lb/></front>

			<note place="headnote">The signal pathways and treatment of cytokine storm in COVID-19 <lb/>Yang et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>20 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Signal Transduction and Targeted Therapy (2021) 6:255 </note>


	</text>
</tei>