<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>Thieno[2,3-d]pyrimidine-2,4(1H,3H)-dione Derivative Inhibits <lb/>D-Dopachrome Tautomerase Activity and Suppresses the <lb/>Proliferation of Non-Small Cell Lung Cancer Cells <lb/>Zhangping Xiao, Angelina Osipyan, Shanshan Song, Deng Chen, Reinder A. Schut, Ronald van Merkerk, <lb/>Petra E. van der Wouden, Robbert H. Cool, Wim J. Quax, Barbro N. Melgert, Gerrit J. Poelarends, <lb/>and Frank J. Dekker* <lb/>Cite This: J. Med. Chem. 2022, 65, 2059-2077 <lb/>Read Online <lb/>ACCESS <lb/>Metrics &amp; More <lb/>Article Recommendations <lb/>* sı Supporting Information <lb/>ABSTRACT: The homologous cytokines macrophage migration <lb/>inhibitory factor (MIF) and D-dopachrome tautomerase (D-DT or <lb/>MIF2) play key roles in cancers. Molecules binding to the MIF <lb/>tautomerase active site interfere with its biological activity. In <lb/>contrast, the lack of potent MIF2 inhibitors hinders the exploration <lb/>of MIF2 as a drug target. In this work, screening of a focused <lb/>compound collection enabled the identification of a MIF2 <lb/>tautomerase inhibitor R110. Subsequent optimization provided <lb/>inhibitor 5d with an IC 50 of 1.0 μM for MIF2 tautomerase activity <lb/>and a high selectivity over MIF. 5d suppressed the proliferation of <lb/>non-small cell lung cancer cells in two-dimensional (2D) and three-<lb/>dimensional (3D) cell cultures, which can be explained by the <lb/>induction of cell cycle arrest via deactivation of the mitogen-activated protein kinase (MAPK) pathway. Thus, we discovered and <lb/>characterized MIF2 inhibitors (5d) with improved antiproliferative activity in cellular models systems, which indicates the potential <lb/>of targeting MIF2 in cancer treatment. <lb/></front>

			<body>■ INTRODUCTION <lb/>Cancer is one of the major public health challenges and <lb/>contributes to a currently estimated annual death toll of 10 <lb/>million worldwide. 1 Although targeted cancer treatment has <lb/>achieved enormous progress over the last decades, its <lb/>effectiveness is limited by the heterogeneity and acquired <lb/>therapy resistance of cancers. 2 Therefore, it is important to <lb/>explore novel anticancer drug targets and to develop new <lb/>therapeutic agents to target them. This could expand the <lb/>possibilities to employ targeted therapeutic approaches and <lb/>also increase the possibilities to develop combination therapy <lb/>regimens. 3 The macrophage migration inhibitory factor (MIF) <lb/>family proteins are implicated in the development of cancers, <lb/>which is demonstrated by the overexpression of MIF family <lb/>proteins in several cancer types, such as genitourinary cancer, 4 <lb/>melanoma, 5 neuroblastoma, 6 and lung carcinoma. 7 Notably, <lb/>downregulation of MIF family proteins by gene-knockout 8 or <lb/>gene-knockdown 9,10 exhibited reduction of tumor progression <lb/>and induction of antitumor immune responses. Thus, MIF <lb/>family proteins could be promising targets of novel cancer <lb/>therapeutics. <lb/>The most studied member of the MIF family proteins is <lb/>macrophage migration inhibitory factor (MIF), which was <lb/>initially discovered as an inflammatory cytokine. Currently, <lb/>there is accumulating evidence revealing a key role in the <lb/>proliferation of cancer cells. MIF exerts its proliferative effect <lb/>through various mechanisms, for example, binding to the <lb/>cognate receptor cluster of differentiation 74 (CD74). 11,12 <lb/>CD74 binding induces the activation of the MAPK pathway, <lb/>which stabilizes cyclin D1 and consequently regulates cell cycle <lb/>progression to enhance cell proliferation. In addition, <lb/>activation of the MAPK pathway also suppresses p53 activity, <lb/>which results in the inhibition of cell apoptosis. 4 Other binding <lb/>partners of MIF, such as CXCR4 13 and JAB1 also play central <lb/>roles in cancer growth. Several MIF-targeting reagents showed <lb/>substantial potency on the deactivation of MIF-related <lb/>signaling pathway and the inhibition of cancer cell prolifer-<lb/>ation. 14,15 <lb/>D-Dopachrome tautomerase (D-DT or MIF2) is a structural <lb/>and functional homologue but not a backup of MIF. 16 Most <lb/>studies on MIF2 were comparisons with MIF, as MIF2 is a <lb/></body>

			<front>Received: September 10, 2021 <lb/>Published: January 18, 2022 <lb/>Article <lb/>pubs.acs.org/jmc <lb/>© 2022 The Authors. Published by <lb/>American Chemical Society <lb/>2059 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jmedchem.1c01598 <lb/>J. Med. Chem. 2022, 65, 2059-2077 <lb/>Downloaded via 76.98.249.125 on February 25, 2025 at 15:32:44 (UTC). <lb/>See https://pubs.acs.org/sharingguidelines for options on how to legitimately share published articles. <lb/></front>

			<body>relatively recently identified family member of MIF. 17 MIF2 <lb/>and MIF share a high similarity in several aspects. The 3D <lb/>structure shows that the overall folding and subunit topology <lb/>of MIF2 and MIF are almost identical, with two β-α-β motifs <lb/>related by pseudo-2-fold symmetry and similar trimeric β-sheet <lb/>packing (Figure 1A). 18 Both MIF2 and MIF harbor enzyme <lb/>activity and catalyze the keto-enol tautomerization of 4-<lb/>hydroxylphenylpyruvate (4-HPP) in an active site centered <lb/>around proline-1. Moreover, both MIF and MIF2 are ligands <lb/>of CD74 and JAB1 17 that could consequently endow these two <lb/>proteins with a similar effect on cell growth and tumorigenesis. <lb/>Despite their high structure similarity, MIF and MIF2 share <lb/>just 34% percent amino acid sequence identity (Figure 1B). 19 <lb/>These sequence differences may provide differences in <lb/>interaction sites. For instance, the difference of amino acids <lb/>inside the tautomerase active sites causes differences in their <lb/>activity toward the keto-enol tautomerization of 4-HPP. 17 <lb/>Moreover, MIF2 does not bind to MIF receptors CXCR2/4 <lb/>because it lacks a pseudo(E)LR motif, which mediates the <lb/>interactions. 20,21 Thus, understanding the similarities and <lb/>differences between MIF2 and MIF is important for the <lb/>discovery of therapeutics to selectively target these MIF family <lb/>members. <lb/>Considerable efforts have been devoted to the discovery of <lb/>small-molecule inhibitors to target MIF family proteins in <lb/>cancers. For the last two decades, researchers have reported <lb/>dozens of MIF-targeting inhibitors, most of which bind to the <lb/>tautomerase active site of MIF. As the tautomerase active sites <lb/>are located in close proximity to amino acid residues playing <lb/>key roles in binding to the CD74 receptor, 22,23 small-molecule <lb/>binders of the MIF tautomerase site can also interfere with the <lb/>structural or dynamic features of MIF that are essential for <lb/>CD74 binding and MIF-related cell signaling. 24 For instance, <lb/>the most widely investigated MIF inhibitor ISO-1 (Figure 1C) <lb/>not only inhibits MIF tautomerase activity 25 but also shows <lb/>significant suppression of prostate cancer growth in cellular <lb/>and animal models, which can be explained by the attenuation <lb/>of MIF-triggered activation of the MAPK pathway. 26 In a <lb/>recent study, we demonstrated that a 7-hydroxycoumarin <lb/>derivative can interfere with MIF-CD74 interaction through <lb/>binding to the MIF tautomerase active site. 15 Additionally, the <lb/>Jorgensen Lab discovered several promising biaryltriazole-or <lb/>pyrazole-containing MIF inhibitors, which showed inhibitory <lb/>potency at the nanomolar level. 27,28 Moreover, we developed a <lb/>potent MIF-targeted proteolysis targeting chimera (PROTAC) <lb/>to remove the MIF protein from its interaction network, which <lb/>further expanded the toolbox to study MIF functions. 29 <lb/>However, little is known about the effect of MIF2 inhibitors <lb/>on cancer development due to a lack of potent MIF2 inhibitors <lb/>and other effective molecular tools. 4-Iodo-6-phenylpyrimidine <lb/>(4-IPP) is the firstly discovered MIF2 inhibitor, which <lb/>covalently binds to proline-1 of MIF2 to interfere with its <lb/>tautomerase enzyme activity and its biological function. 19 <lb/>However, 4-IPP shows low potency on MIF2 inhibition with <lb/>an IC 50 value larger than 100 μM. In contrast, 4-IPP inhibits <lb/>MIF with micromolar potency and binds covalently to the <lb/>active site proline. As reported in 2019, Bucala and co-workers <lb/>discovered the selective MIF2 inhibitor 4-(3-carboxyphenyl)-<lb/>Figure 1. Tertiary and secondary structures of MIF and MIF2 and some key inhibitors. (A) Similar 3D structures of MIF (PDB code: 3ijj) 31 and <lb/>MIF2 (PDB code: 6c5f) 32 monomers. (B) Comparison of the MIF and MIF2 amino acid sequences. (C) Some representative MIF or MIF2 <lb/>tautomerase inhibitors. ISO-1 is one of the most studied MIF inhibitors. 25 4-IPP is a covalent inhibitor for both MIF and MIF2. 19 4-CPPC is an <lb/>MIF2 inhibitor with an IC 50 value of 27 μM with selectivity for MIF2 over MIF. 30 <lb/>Figure 2. Workflow for the discovery of MIF2 inhibitors. In this study, a MIF2 tautomerase activity assay was established using phenylpyruvate as a <lb/>substrate. This assay was employed to screen several structurally diverse compound collections. A hit compound was discovered and further <lb/>optimized. The most potent MIF2 tautomerase inhibitor was also tested on non-small cell lung cancer cells for its effect on cell proliferation. <lb/></body>

			<front>Journal of Medicinal Chemistry <lb/>pubs.acs.org/jmc <lb/>Article <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jmedchem.1c01598 <lb/>J. Med. Chem. 2022, 65, 2059-2077 <lb/></front>

			<page>2060 <lb/></page>

			<body>2,5-pyridinedicarboxylic acid (4-CPPC) through virtual screen-<lb/>ing, which displays an IC 50 value of 27 μM on MIF2 <lb/>tautomerase activity. 30 More importantly, 4-CPPC can also <lb/>inhibit MIF2-CD74 binding and MIF2-mediated pERK <lb/>activation. To further investigate the biological role of MIF2 <lb/>in cancer and exploit it to develop cancer therapy, more potent <lb/>MIF2 selective inhibitors are needed. <lb/>In this study, we describe the discovery and exploration of a <lb/>potent and selective MIF2 inhibitor 5d with a low micromolar-<lb/>level potency for inhibition of both MIF2 tautomerase activity <lb/>and cancer cell proliferation (Figure 2). First, the tautomerase <lb/>activity assay was optimized for assessing the potency of MIF2 <lb/>inhibitors in competition binding studies and enzyme kinetic <lb/>analysis. Subsequently, several in-house available compound <lb/>collections were screened and a promising hit compound was <lb/>chosen for further optimization. Toward this aim, 33 analogues <lb/>were prepared and tested for their inhibitory potency on MIF2 <lb/>tautomerase activity. The most potent inhibitor 5d was tested <lb/>in two-dimensional (2D) and three-dimensional (3D) cultures <lb/>of non-small cell lung cancer (NSCLC) cell lines. Altogether, <lb/>the development of 5d provides a powerful tool for MIF2-<lb/>oriented research and provides a perspective toward MIF2-<lb/>directed therapeutics. <lb/>■ RESULTS <lb/>Optimization MIF2 Tautomerase Activity Assay. To <lb/>facilitate the effective assessment of binding potency of MIF2 <lb/>inhibitors, a convenient and reliable assay is needed. The most <lb/>widely used assay to evaluate MIF tautomerase activity <lb/>inhibition is the 4-HPP-based tautomerization assay, in <lb/>which the potency on inhibition of MIF-catalyzed 4-HPP <lb/>tautomerization is applied to reflect the binding affinity of the <lb/>tested compound to MIF. 33 This assay was also applied to <lb/>assess MIF2 binding in previous studies. 30 However, the <lb/>catalytic activity of MIF2 on the 4-HPP keto-enol conversion is <lb/>10 times lower compared to MIF (Figure 3A). 17 This renders <lb/>Figure 3. Setup of the phenylpyruvate tautomerization-based MIF2 binding assay. (A) Rate of the MIF-or MIF2-catalyzed 4-HPP tautomerization <lb/>reaction. The rate of the MIF-catalyzed reaction is 10-fold faster than that of the MIF2-catalyzed reaction. 17 (B) Superposition of MIF2 (PDB <lb/>code: 6c5f) 32 and complex (PDB: 6ijj) 31 of MIF and 4-HPP reveals the differences in the tautomerase active site pocket. (C) UV spectra of 1 mM <lb/>phenylpyruvate in its keto-form (gray) or enol-form (blue). (D) The signal in the MIF2 tautomerase activity assay is halved in the presence of 10 <lb/>μM Cu 2+ and can be rescued by 0.5 mM ethylenediamine tetraacetic acid (EDTA). <lb/>Table 1. Enzyme Kinetic Parameters for the Conversion of PP and Its Derivatives by MIF and MIF2 <lb/>enzyme <lb/>parameter <lb/>PP <lb/>4-CPP <lb/>4-HPP <lb/>4-MPP <lb/>MIF <lb/>K M (mM) <lb/>0.76 ± 0.28 <lb/>0.60 ± 0.24 <lb/>0.94 ± 0.14 <lb/>1.3 ± 0.32 <lb/>k cat (s -1 ) # <lb/>14 ± 2.5 <lb/>25 ± 4.1 <lb/>25 ± 1.8 37 <lb/>13 ± 1.7 <lb/>k cat /K M (10 4 M -1 s -1 ) <lb/>1.9 <lb/>4.3 <lb/>2.6 <lb/>0.98 <lb/>MIF2 <lb/>K M (μM) <lb/>2.4 ± 0.56 <lb/>2.17 ± 0.22 <lb/>3.62 ± 0.47 <lb/>6.7 ± 0.78 <lb/>k cat (s -1 ) <lb/>132 ± 17 <lb/>68 ± 3.7 <lb/>13 ± 1.0 <lb/>28 ± 2.3 <lb/>k cat /K M (10 4 M -1 s -1 ) <lb/>5.5 <lb/>3.2 <lb/>0.37 <lb/>0.43 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Journal of Medicinal Chemistry <lb/>pubs.acs.org/jmc <lb/>Article <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jmedchem.1c01598 <lb/>J. Med. Chem. 2022, 65, 2059-2077 <lb/></note>

			<page>2061 <lb/></page>

			<body>4-HPP unsuitable as a substrate in the MIF2 tautomerase <lb/>activity assay because high enzyme concentrations and long <lb/>measurement times are needed. This indicates the need for a <lb/>different substrate. <lb/>The structural features of the tautomerase active site of <lb/>MIF2 were compared to the tautomerase active site of MIF. A <lb/>superimposition of the crystal structure of MIF2 32 on a <lb/>complex 31 of MIF and 4-HPP showed that the proline-1 of <lb/>MIF2 overlaps well with the proline-1 of MIF, which indicates <lb/>that the catalytic centers of MIF2 and MIF occupy the same <lb/>spatial location in the active sites. Nevertheless, MIF2 is not <lb/>able to form the two hydrogen bonds observed between Asn97 <lb/>of MIF and the 4-position hydroxyl group of 4-HPP, as the <lb/>Arg98 locates at the corresponding position of MIF2 (Figure <lb/>3B). Accordingly, we hypothesized that MIF2 could exhibit <lb/>different catalytic activity for keto-enol tautomerization of 4-<lb/>HPP analogues with different substituents at the phenyl 4-<lb/>position. Therefore, we set out to find a more active substrate <lb/>for MIF2 to establish a convenient and sensitive enzymatic <lb/>assay. Three 4-HPP analogues, 4-methoxylphenylpyruvate (4-<lb/>MPP), 4-chlorophenylpyruvate (4-CPP), and phenylpyruvate <lb/>(PP), were synthesized and the catalytic activities of MIF and <lb/>MIF2 toward these &quot;artificial substrates&quot; were tested. The <lb/>measured parameters show that K M values of MIF on <lb/>catalyzing PP, 4-CPP, 4-HPP, and 4-MPP keto-enol con-<lb/>version are 0.76, 0.60, 0.94, and 1.3 mM (Table 1), <lb/>respectively. These values are lower than the corresponding <lb/>values of MIF2. Nevertheless, the catalytic efficiencies for MIF <lb/>and MIF2 on each substrate are diverse. For instance, the <lb/>catalytic efficiency of MIF on 4-HPP is 7 times higher than that <lb/>of MIF2, making 4-HPP a less effective MIF2 substrate. In <lb/>contrast, MIF2 can catalyze the keto-enol conversion of PP <lb/>around 3 times more efficient than MIF, which provides MIF2 <lb/>with the highest catalytic efficiency for PP among this series of <lb/>substrates. Interestingly, PP is a known MIF2 substrate and <lb/>MIF2 was even named as phenylpyruvate tautomerase (PPT <lb/>II) because of this property as early as 1997. 34 Altogether, this <lb/>identifies PP as a substrate for a MIF2 tautomerase assay. <lb/>Next, PP was used to establish the MIF2 tautomerase assay <lb/>in the same way as done for MIF. In this assay format, a MIF2 <lb/>solution in assay buffer was mixed with the compound stock <lb/>solution and an aqueous EDTA solution followed by 10 min <lb/>preincubation. 35 The assay was started by adding a PP solution <lb/>to the inhibitor-enzyme mixture. In the final reaction mixture, <lb/>there were 50 nM MIF2, 0.5 mM PP, 2.5% (v/v) dimethyl <lb/>sulfoxide (DMSO), and variable concentrations of the <lb/>inhibitor. The formation of the reaction product was <lb/>monitored at 300 nm and corrected for the blank in which <lb/>the enzyme was excluded (Figure 3C). The linear regression <lb/>parameters were utilized to determine the inhibitory potency <lb/>or IC 50 using GraphPad Prism. The window coefficient (Z′-<lb/>factor) of this optimized assay was determined as 0.75 in this <lb/>setup, indicating that the quality of this assay is sufficient for <lb/>application in medium-to high-throughput screenings (0.5-<lb/>1). 36 Similar to MIF, we observed that Cu 2+ ions interfere with <lb/>this MIF2 tautomerase activity assay and that including EDTA <lb/>in the assay buffer prevents this (Figure 3D). 35 <lb/>Compounds Screening and Hit Confirmation. The <lb/>MIF2 tautomerase activity assay was employed to screen an in-<lb/>house available compound collection containing 305 distinct <lb/>chemical entities at compound concentrations of 50 μM <lb/>(Figure 4A and Supporting Table 1). The performance of the <lb/>MIF2 activity assay in this screening campaign proved to be <lb/>excellent with an average Z′ factor (a screening window <lb/>coefficient) of 0.87. The hit identification criterion was defined <lb/>as beyond 75% inhibition (Table S1). The inhibitory potency, <lb/>Figure 4. Library screening and hit confirmation. (A) 305 compounds from an in-house library were screened at a single concentration of 50 μM <lb/>for their inhibition on MIF2 tautomerase activity. The inhibition potency of each compound was shown as an average of three measurements. (B) <lb/>Structure of selected hit compound R110 (3a). (C) Fluorescence-based thermal shift assay result from the interaction between R110 and MIF2. <lb/>ΔTm depicts the difference between the apparent melting temperature of MIF2 with or without R110. (D) Lineweaver-Burk plot of MIF2 activity <lb/>in the presence of R110 (3a). Results are shown as mean ± standard deviation (SD) of three experiments. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Journal of Medicinal Chemistry <lb/>pubs.acs.org/jmc <lb/>Article <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jmedchem.1c01598 <lb/>J. Med. Chem. 2022, 65, 2059-2077 <lb/></note>

			<page>2062 <lb/></page>

			<body>potential binding efficiency, and drug-likeness were used to <lb/>select hit compounds for follow-up investigation. R110 (3a) <lb/>exhibited good inhibitory potency against MIF2 tautomeriza-<lb/>tion activity (IC 50 = 15 μM) and good ligand efficiency (LE = <lb/>0.34) (Figure 4B). To verify the binding between R110 (3a) <lb/>and MIF2, the thermal stability assay was performed as an <lb/>orthogonal assay. The apparent melting temperature (ΔTm) of <lb/>MIF2 increased with 2.5 °C in the presence of 100 μM R110 <lb/>(3a) (Figure 4C), which confirms binding of R110 (3a) to <lb/>MIF2. Subsequently, the enzyme kinetics for binding of R110 <lb/>(3a) to MIF2 were investigated. The Lineweaver-Burk plots <lb/>show intersection at the ordinate (y-axis), demonstrating that <lb/>R110 (3a) binds in competition with the substrate phenyl-<lb/>pyruvate to the MIF2 tautomerase active site (Figure 4D). <lb/>Taken together, R110 (3a) is a competitive inhibitor of MIF2 <lb/>tautomerase activity with micromolar potency, indicating that <lb/>R110 (3a) is a promising chemical starting point for the <lb/>development of a more potent MIF2 inhibitor. <lb/>Design and Synthesis. To rationalize the binding <lb/>between R110 (3a) and MIF2, a docking study was performed <lb/>by docking R110 (3a) into the crystal structure of MIF2 (PDB <lb/>code: 6c5f). 32 Modeling was performed using the software <lb/>Discovery Studio 3.0. R110 (3a) was docked into the <lb/>tautomerase active site of the crystal structure of MIF2 and <lb/>energy-minimized (Figure 5). The five highest-scoring poses <lb/>occupy similar positions. The optimal binding pose indicates <lb/>that the chlorophenyl group of R110 (3a) is embedded into <lb/>the hydrophobic active site pocket of MIF2, while the n-butyl <lb/>group is exposed to water. The interactions between R110 <lb/>(3a) and MIF2 are mainly formed through van der Waals <lb/>forces, including the interactions between the chlorophenyl <lb/>group and Phe2, Arg98, Leu102, and Ile107 of MIF2, and the <lb/>interactions between the thiophene and Arg36, Met114 of <lb/>MIF2. A hydrogen bond is formed between R110 (3a) and <lb/>Lys109 of MIF2. This model indicates that there is still some <lb/>unoccupied space around the chlorophenyl fragment and the <lb/>butyl group of R110 (3a). Therefore, we set out to exploit <lb/>these regions in our structure-activity relationship (SAR) with <lb/>the aim to enhance the potency of the MIF2 inhibitor. <lb/>To optimize R110 (3a), phenylthiophene derivatives were <lb/>constructed employing the Gewald three-component reaction <lb/>as a key step using routes as depicted in scheme 1-3. Two <lb/>different methods were employed to prepare compounds 3a-<lb/>k. Compounds 3a-c and 3e-h were obtained using the <lb/>Gewald-reaction employing different aldehydes, cyanoaceta-<lb/>mides, and elementary sulfur as starting materials with yields of <lb/>18-56%. Compounds 3d and 3i-k were synthesized by <lb/>condensation of the corresponding ketones and cyanoaceta-<lb/>mides in the presence of SnCl 4 and Et 3 N to provide the <lb/>corresponding intermediates, which were cyclized with S 8 to <lb/>afford the products with overall yields of 16-42%. The <lb/>resulting 2-aminothiophenes were acylated by different <lb/>acylchlorides to prepare the desired 2-amide-substituted <lb/>thiophene products 4a-c with yields of 44-58%. The 2-<lb/>aminothiophenes were also employed to synthesize thieno[2,3-<lb/>d]pyrimidine-2,4(1H,3H)-diones 5a-e using 1,1′-carbonyldii-<lb/>midazole (CDI) as a coupling reagent with yields of 40-91%. <lb/>The profiles of 5d were further investigated. 5d and 5e show <lb/>different retention times on chiral chromatography and <lb/>opposite optical rotation in optical characterization (Figure <lb/>S3). The results together with the NMR spectra and high-<lb/>resolution mass spectrometry (HRMS) data indicate that 5d <lb/>and 5e are chirally pure enantiomers. The same scaffold in 7a-<lb/>i and 11a-b was synthesized using a different method, in <lb/>which the respective isocyanates were reacted with 2-<lb/>aminothiophenes (6a-g) to the corresponding ureas that <lb/>were cyclized by treatment with MeONa to provide overall <lb/>yields of 20-62%. Compounds 8a-d were constructed by the <lb/>condensation of 2-aminothiophenes with nitriles in 4 N HCl to <lb/>provide the corresponding products in yields of 32-60%. All <lb/>final products were purified with chromatography, and their <lb/>structures were characterized by 1 H and 13 C NMR spectros-<lb/>copy and liquid chromatography high-resolution mass <lb/>spectrometry (LC-HRMS) (Supporting information). The <lb/>purity of all tested compounds is &gt;95% as determined by <lb/>high-performance liquid chromatography (HPLC). <lb/>Structure-Activity Relationships. The inhibitory po-<lb/>tency toward MIF2 tautomerase activity of this focused <lb/>compound collection was evaluated using the MIF2 tautomer-<lb/>ase activity assay to provide IC 50 values as shown in Tables <lb/>2-4. The positive control compound 4-CPPC exhibits an IC 50 <lb/>of 47 ± 7.2 μM, which is in line with the result of 27 μM from <lb/>the literature. 30 Compared with inhibitor 3a (R110) with an <lb/>IC 50 of 15 ± 0.8 μM, the bromo-substituted analogue 3b <lb/>exhibits enhanced potency with an IC 50 value of 7.2 ± 0.6 μM. <lb/>Neither adding a butyl group to the 4-position of thiophene <lb/>(3d) nor elongating the butyl to an octyl (3f) influenced the <lb/>activity of R110 (3a). In contrast, replacement of butyl group <lb/>with phenethyl (3c), (tetrahydrofuran-3-yl)methyl (3e), <lb/>ethoxyethyl (3g), or 4-chlorophenethyl (3h) diminished the <lb/>MIF2 inhibitory potency. Amidation of the 2-amino group <lb/>with different acyls (4a-c) also failed to increase the potency. <lb/>However, the derivatives with a CF 3 group and a naphthalene <lb/>substitution (3i-k) showed increased activity, with an IC 50 of <lb/>2.6 ± 0.2 μM for the most potent compound 3i. <lb/>To investigate the importance of the thiophene core of <lb/>inhibitors, we changed the thiophene to thieno[2,3-d]-<lb/>pyrimidine-2,4(1H,3H)-diones using ring closure strategies to <lb/>bridge the 2-amino and 3-amide functionalities. The activities <lb/>of 5a and 5b, which have aliphatic chains at R 3 position, are <lb/>similar to R110 (3a). By analyzing the SARs of 7a-d, we <lb/>observed that a chlorophenyl group, compared with a phenyl <lb/>group, at the R 2 position and a benzyl group at the R 3 position <lb/>is beneficial for MIF2 inhibitory potency within this series of <lb/>inhibitors. Thus, 7d, which has an IC 50 of 5.1 ± 0.5 μM, was <lb/>employed as a new starting point for further exploring the <lb/>Figure 5. Schematic representation of the binding mode of R110 (3a) <lb/>(thick sticks) with MIF2 (PDB code: 6c5f). 32 The residues of the <lb/>binding pocket are shown as thin sticks. The hydrogen bond formed <lb/>with Lys109 is shown as the red dash line. Discovery Studio was <lb/>employed for docking, and PyMOL was used for graph preparation. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Journal of Medicinal Chemistry <lb/>pubs.acs.org/jmc <lb/>Article <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jmedchem.1c01598 <lb/>J. Med. Chem. 2022, 65, 2059-2077 <lb/></note>

			<page>2063 <lb/></page>

			<body>SARs. First, a CF 3 group installed on the para-position of the <lb/>benzyl group afforded 7e, which shows similar potency to 7d. <lb/>Subsequently, we moved the phenyl or 4-chlorophenyl group <lb/>to the neighboring position to prepare 11a and 11b, which <lb/>both show impaired activity. Therefore, we started again from <lb/>7d to explore the space around the 4′-chlorophenyl group. <lb/>Interestingly, all four patterns of substitutions (7f-i) on the <lb/>phenyl ring provide increased potency. Among them, the 3′-<lb/>CF 3 substitution (7h) results in a 3-fold improvement of <lb/>potency with an IC 50 of 1.7 ± 0.1 μM. By replacing the benzyl <lb/>group of 7h with a (naphthalen-1-yl)methyl group, we <lb/>achieved 5c, which affords another a 2-fold increase of potency <lb/>on MIF2 tautomerase inhibition with an IC 50 of 0.8 ± 0.1 μM. <lb/>However, the solubility of 5c is only 3.3 μg/mL (7.4 μM), <lb/>which would be a limitation for further application in cell-<lb/>based assays. Therefore, we synthesized a pair of methyl-<lb/>Scheme 1. Synthesis of Thiophene Derivatives a <lb/>a <lb/>Reagents and conditions: a. (i) S 8 , TEA, EtOH, reflux; b. (i) SnCl 4 , TEA, THF; (ii) S 8 , EtOH, TEA, reflux; c. Acyl chloride, pyridine, N,N-<lb/>dimethylformamide (DMF), rt; d. CDI, CH 2 Cl 2 . <lb/>Scheme 2. Synthesis of Thiophene Derivatives a <lb/>a <lb/>Reagents and conditions: a. (i) Ammonium acetate, AcOH, toluene, reflux; (ii) S 8 , TEA, EtOH, reflux; b. (i) R-NCO, pyridine, reflux; (ii) 30% <lb/>MeONa, reflux; c. R-CN, HCl, dioxane, reflux. <lb/></body>
			
			<note place="headnote">Journal of Medicinal Chemistry <lb/>pubs.acs.org/jmc <lb/>Article <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jmedchem.1c01598 <lb/>J. Med. Chem. 2022, 65, 2059-2077 <lb/></note>

			<page>2064 <lb/></page>

			<body>branched enantiomers (5d and 5e) to break the planarity of 5c <lb/>and to improve water solubility. 38 Favorably, both 5d and 5e <lb/>have improved solubility in aqueous solution with saturated <lb/>concentrations of 16 μg/mL (36 μM) and 15 μg/mL (33 μM) <lb/>for 5d and 5e, respectively. Moreover, 5d exhibits a <lb/>comparable potency as 5c, while 5e is less active. This <lb/>identified 5d as one of the most potent inhibitors of MIF2 <lb/>tautomerase with a water solubility that is sufficient for further <lb/>studies. <lb/>In addition, a scaffold hopping from thieno[2,3-d]-<lb/>pyrimidine-2,4(1H,3H)-dione (7d) to thieno[2,3-d]-<lb/>pyrimidin-4(1H)-one (8b) led to a decrease in potency with <lb/>an IC 50 of 15 ± 1.4 μM (Table 4). Adding a methoxy group to <lb/>the meta-position of benzyl (8d) increases the inhibitory <lb/>potency of 8b by 3 times to an IC 50 of 4.3 ± 0.4 μM, but <lb/>modifying the benzyl to chloromethyl group (8a) or Cl to F <lb/>(8c) failed to improve the potency of compound 8b. <lb/>Characterization of 5d. We next confirmed that 5d <lb/>inhibits MIF2 through a direct interaction by monitoring MIF2 <lb/>thermal stability using the thermal shift assay. Incubation with <lb/>5d stabilizes MIF2 from heat-induced unfolding and increased <lb/>Scheme 3. Synthesis of Thiophene Derivatives a <lb/>a <lb/>Reagents and conditions: a. Ethyl cyanoacetate, S 8 , TEA, EtOH, <lb/>reflux; b. (i) Ethyl cyanoacetate, acetic acid, toluene, reflux; (ii) S 8 , <lb/>EtOH, reflux; c. CDI, CH 2 Cl 2 . <lb/>Table 2. Potency of MIF2 Tautomerase Inhibition by Thiophene Derivatives Determined Using the MIF2-Catalyzed PP <lb/>Conversion Assay a <lb/>a# (n = 3, values are shown as IC 50 ± SD). <lb/></body>
			
			<note place="headnote">Journal of Medicinal Chemistry <lb/>pubs.acs.org/jmc <lb/>Article <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jmedchem.1c01598 <lb/>J. Med. Chem. 2022, 65, 2059-2077 <lb/></note>

			<page>2065 <lb/></page>

			<body>its melting temperature in a dose-dependent manner over the <lb/>DMSO control (Figure 6A). The melting temperature of MIF2 <lb/>increases by 8.5 °C in the presence of 50 μM 5d, indicating a <lb/>binding between 5d and MIF2. Subsequently, 5d was <lb/>subjected to enzyme kinetic analysis for MIF2 inhibition. <lb/>The Lineweaver-Burk plot shows that the V max is unaffected <lb/>by 5d, while K M increases with the increase of 5d <lb/>concentration (Figure 6B), indicating that 5d binds in <lb/>competition with the tautomerase substrate to the active site. <lb/>Moreover, we also interrogated the selectivity of 5d toward <lb/>MIF2 tautomerase activity by testing its inhibitory potential for <lb/>MIF tautomerase activity. 5d provided less than 50% inhibition <lb/>of MIF tautomerase activity at 50 μM, which indicates a more <lb/>than 50-fold difference in potency (Figure 6C). Taken <lb/>together, 5d is a potent, competitive, and selective binder of <lb/>MIF2. <lb/>Molecular Modeling of the Interaction between 5d <lb/>and MIF2. To gain insight into the structure-activity <lb/>Table 3. Potency of MIF2 Tautomerase Inhibition by Thieno[2,3-d]pyrimidine-2,4(1H,3H)-diones Determined Using MIF2-<lb/>Catalyzed PP Conversion Assay a <lb/>a# (n = 3, values are shown as IC 50 ± SD). <lb/></body>
			
			<note place="headnote">Journal of Medicinal Chemistry <lb/>pubs.acs.org/jmc <lb/>Article <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jmedchem.1c01598 <lb/>J. Med. Chem. 2022, 65, 2059-2077 <lb/></note>

			<page>2066 <lb/></page>

			<body>relationships, a modeling study was done for the binding of <lb/>inhibitor 5d to MIF2. 5d was docked into the tautomerase <lb/>active site of the crystal structure of MIF2 (PDB code: 6c5f), 32 <lb/>and energy was minimized (Figure 7). The five highest-scoring <lb/>poses of 5d occupy similar positions. In this model, the π-π <lb/>stacking between Phe2 and the phenyl group of R110 (3a) is <lb/>preserved for 5d. Furthermore, 5d and Ser50 interact through <lb/>a hydrogen bond, which is also found between R110 (3a) and <lb/>Lys109. Instead, 5d has two π-cation interactions with <lb/>Lys109. Additionally, the CF 3 group of 5d has several <lb/>interactions with MIF2 via Phe2, Arg98, and Leu102. Besides, <lb/>Pro1 and Leu117 are two newly involved interactive residues <lb/>that can contribute to 5d-MIF2 binding. These newly formed <lb/>interactions could explain the increased potency of 5d <lb/>compared with R110 (3a). Taken together, the putative <lb/>binding mode rationalizes the binding of 5d to MIF2 and also <lb/>sheds light on the increased binding affinity of 5d. <lb/>Antiproliferative Activity of 5d. After the identification <lb/>of 5d as a potent MIF2 tautomerase inhibitor, we tested its <lb/>effect on the proliferation of non-small cell lung cancer <lb/>(NSCLC) cells. First, we investigated the toxicity of 5d using a <lb/>cell viability assay (MTS assay). The results (Figure S4) <lb/>indicated that 5d did not show cell viability inhibition up to a <lb/>concentration of 10 μM in A549, H1650, H1299, and <lb/>HCC827 cells upon 24 h of exposure. To evaluate the <lb/>antiproliferative effects of inhibitor 5d, we treated the cells with <lb/>5d in different concentrations for 72 h before quantifying cell <lb/>numbers by measuring the DNA content using a CyQUANT <lb/>assay. The results indicate that 5d inhibited the growth of <lb/>several types of NSCLC cell lines dose-dependently (Figure 8). <lb/>Table 4. Potency of MIF2 Tautomerase Inhibition by <lb/>Thieno[2,3-d]pyrimidin-4(1H)-ones Determined Using <lb/>MIF2-Catalyzed PP Conversion Assay a <lb/>a# (n = 3, values are shown as IC 50 ± SD). <lb/>Figure 6. Characterization of 5d. (A) Fluorescence-based thermal shift assay for the binding of 5d to MIF2. The melting temperature shows a <lb/>concentration-dependent to a higher temperature in the presence of 5d. (B) Lineweaver-Burk plot representation. (C) Incubation of MIF <lb/>with micromolar concentrations of 5d provided less than 50% inhibition compared to the vehicle control. The data shown are the average of <lb/>triplicate samples with SD. (n = 3, *p &lt; 0.05, **p &lt; 0.01 and ***p &lt; 0.001 vs control). <lb/>Figure 7. Schematic representation of the binding mode of 5d (thick <lb/>sticks) with MIF2 (PDB code: 6c5f). 32 The residues of the binding <lb/>pocket are shown as thin sticks. The hydrogen bond formed with <lb/>Ser50 is shown as the red dashed line. The cation-π interactions <lb/>formed with Lys109 are shown as the blue dash line. Discovery Studio <lb/>was employed for docking and PyMOL was used for graph <lb/>preparation. <lb/>Figure 8. Effect of inhibitor 5d on the proliferation of the NSCLC <lb/>cells lines A549, H1650, H1299, and HCC827. The cells were seeded <lb/>at a density of about 1000 cells per well in a 96-well plate. After <lb/>overnight culturing, the cells were treated with various concentrations <lb/>of 5d for 72 h. Afterward, relative cell numbers were determined by <lb/>CyQUANT cell proliferation assays and compared with a DMSO-<lb/>treated control. The data shown are the average of three experiments <lb/>with SD (n = 3). <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Journal of Medicinal Chemistry <lb/>pubs.acs.org/jmc <lb/>Article <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jmedchem.1c01598 <lb/>J. Med. Chem. 2022, 65, 2059-2077 <lb/></note>

			<page>2067 <lb/></page>

			<body>5d showed a visible inhibitory effect at 1 μM and reached <lb/>about 90% inhibition of cell growth at 7.5 μM on A549 cells, <lb/>showing an IC 50 of 3.0 μM. 5d also inhibited the proliferation <lb/>of H1650, H1299, and HCC827 cells with IC 50 values of 5.3, <lb/>7.6, and 5.2 μM, respectively. Taken together, these results <lb/>demonstrate that 5d inhibits the proliferation of several types <lb/>of NSCLC cell lines. <lb/>The inhibitory effect of 5d on the proliferation of NSCLC <lb/>cell lines was further evaluated using a clonogenic assay. The <lb/>results of this colony formation assay showed that 5d potently <lb/>inhibited cell growth of the four NSCLC cell lines tested. We <lb/>observed a dose-dependent reduction in both colony number <lb/>and size in 5d-treated cells compared to vehicle-treated <lb/>controls (Figure 9A). The number of colonies in each well <lb/>was quantified by the absorption of crystal violet. 5d <lb/>suppressed colony formation in a dose-dependent manner by <lb/>around 90% in all four NSCLC cell lines tested at a <lb/>concentration of 10 μM (Figure 9B). These results confirm <lb/>the efficacy of 5d on inhibition of NSCLC cell proliferation. <lb/>To gain insights into the effect of longer-term 5d treatment <lb/>in a more elaborate model, we employed a 3D spheroid tumor <lb/>growth model, which was established using A549 cancer <lb/>cells, 39 with each spheroid containing about 1000 A549 cells. <lb/>After 5-day culturing, different concentrations of 5d were used <lb/>to treat these spheroids with 72 h intervals over 12 days. The <lb/>diameters of spheroid were monitored and compared to day 0 <lb/>of the treatment. Treatment of 5d significantly reduced the size <lb/>of tumor spheroids (Figure 10). With exposure to 1, 2, and 5 <lb/>μM concentrations of 5d for 12 days, the volume of spheroid <lb/>was reduced by 40, 63, and 79%, respectively. These results <lb/>indicate that the MIF2 tautomerase inhibitor 5d effectively <lb/>reduces the growth of A549 cancer cells in a 3D tumor model. <lb/>5d Arrests the Cell Cycle of A549 Cells at the G 0 /G 1 <lb/>Phase. The cell cycle progression of 5d-treated cancer cells <lb/>Figure 9. Treatment with inhibitor 5d inhibits colony formation of NSCLC cell lines. (A) A549 or other NSCLC cell lines were seeded in a 12-well <lb/>plate (1000 cells/well). The cells were preincubated overnight and were then treated with compounds or vehicle (DMSO) for 5 days. Afterward, <lb/>the cells were fixed and stained with 0.5% crystal violet solution. Image of representative wells were scanned and are shown. (B) Stained colonies <lb/>were dissolved in 30% acetic acid and then quantified by measuring the absorbance at 590 nm. The relative colony number is normalized to the <lb/>DMSO-treated control. The data shown are the average of three experiments with SD (n = 3, *p &lt; 0.05, **p &lt; 0.01 and ***p &lt; 0.001 vs control). <lb/>Figure 10. 5d treatment reduces the growth of A549 cancer cells in a spheroid model. A549 cells were seeded in ultralow attachment 96-well U <lb/>bottom plate (1000 cells/well) to generate tumor spheroids (a single spheroid per well). After initiation, the spheroids were treated with 5d at the <lb/>indicated concentrations every 3 days. DMSO was used as a vehicle control. The day of the first treatment was indicated as day 0. (A) <lb/>Representative images were obtained at the indicated intervals using an inverted microscope. Scale bar: 500 μm. (B) Analysis was carried out using <lb/>NIS-Elements AR 3.1 software, and growth curves were obtained relative to the volume of untreated spheroids (day 0) and plotted with GraphPad <lb/>Prism8. Values are displayed as mean ± SD (n = 3 spheroids for each time point, *p &lt; 0.05, **p &lt; 0.01 and ***p &lt; 0.001 vs control). <lb/></body>
			
			<note place="headnote">Journal of Medicinal Chemistry <lb/>pubs.acs.org/jmc <lb/>Article <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jmedchem.1c01598 <lb/>J. Med. Chem. 2022, 65, 2059-2077 <lb/></note>

			<page>2068 <lb/></page>

			<body>was investigated using flow cytometry. A549 cells were exposed <lb/>to different concentrations of 5d for a duration of 2 days before <lb/>analysis. The data show that 5d induced cell cycle arrest at the <lb/>G 0 /G 1 phase dose-dependently (Figure 11). The percentage of <lb/>A549 cells in the G 0 /G 1 phases was 56% for the control group. <lb/>Upon treatment with 5, 7.5, and 10 μM 5d, this percentage <lb/>increased to 58, 63, and 67%, respectively. This result indicates <lb/>that 5d inhibited cell cycle progression, which provided an <lb/>explanation for the observed inhibition of cancer cell growth. <lb/>5d Inhibits ERK Phosphorylation. The effect of 5d <lb/>treatment on MIF2-related signaling pathways was studied by <lb/>assessing MIF2-induced ERK phosphorylation. Towards this <lb/>aim, MIF2 or 5d preincubated MIF2 was employed to <lb/>stimulate A549 cells for 15 min; subsequently, ERK <lb/>phosphorylation of treated cells was analyzed using western <lb/>blot detection. MIF2 treatment stimulated ERK phosphor-<lb/>ylation in A549 cells to about 4.5-fold of the control. <lb/>Treatment with 5d attenuated this stimulation in a dose-<lb/>dependent manner (Figure 12). These data demonstrate that <lb/>5d treatment inhibits ERK phosphorylation in response to <lb/>MIF2-stimulation. <lb/>■ DISCUSSION AND CONCLUSIONS <lb/>The overexpression of MIF family proteins, MIF and MIF2, <lb/>has been implicated in several types of cancer. 40,41 Therefore, <lb/>MIF and MIF2 are promising drug targets for cancer <lb/>treatment. A significant effort has been invested into the <lb/>development of inhibitory strategies to target MIF. 42 Never-<lb/>theless, the drug discovery efforts to target MIF2 are lagging <lb/>behind. Thus, the aim of this study was to develop potent <lb/>small-molecule MIF2 inhibitors that could be applied in cancer <lb/>therapy. <lb/>To discover a potent small-molecule inhibitor to target <lb/>MIF2, we set up a MIF2-targeted drug discovery campaign, <lb/>which includes library screening, hit optimization, and a <lb/>relevant cellular model. Toward this aim, we firstly optimized <lb/>the 4-HPP based enzyme assay. Although MIF2 possesses an <lb/>enzymatic activity on catalyzing the keto-enol tautomerization <lb/>of 4-HPP, its catalytic efficiency is much lower than that of <lb/>MIF. 17 The structural information shows that the differences <lb/>inside the enzyme active sites of MIF and MIF2 not only <lb/>contribute to their unique substrate preference but also <lb/>facilitate the possibility to develop selective inhibitors such as <lb/>ISO-1, which is a representative MIF inhibitor that does not <lb/>inhibit MIF2. 19 Therefore, we set up a MIF2-based <lb/>tautomerization assay using phenylpyruvate as a substrate. <lb/>This PP-based assay was employed to screen an in-house <lb/>library, which afforded several compounds with IC 50 &apos;s in the <lb/>low micromolar range. 3a was selected as the hit for further <lb/>optimization on the basis of its potency and druglike <lb/>properties. <lb/>The putative binding mode of 3a with MIF2 reveals that the <lb/>chlorophenyl group of 3a is embedded in the pocket and the <lb/>butyl group is exposed to water. There is vacancy around the <lb/>Figure 11. Treatment with 5d induces cell cycle arrest in A549 cells. (A) A549 cells were treated with 5d at the indicated concentrations for 48 h. <lb/>Representative cell cycle distributions graphs obtained using propidium iodide staining-based flow cytometry. (B) Bar graph representatives of the <lb/>distribution of cells in each phase of the cell cycle (G 0 /G 1 , S, and G 2 /M phases) were analyzed using FlowJo. Results are displayed as mean ± SD (n <lb/>= 3, t-test analysis was performed between G 2 /M phase of treated groups and control group. *p &lt; 0.05 and **p &lt; 0.01 vs control.). <lb/>Figure 12. Inhibition of MIF2-induced ERK phosphorylation in A549 cells upon treatment with 5d. (A) A549 cells were stimulated with <lb/>recombinant MIF2 with or without 5d preincubation at indicated concentrations for 15 min; the concentrations of pERK and total ERK were <lb/>examined by immunoblots with anti-pERK, anti-ERK using glyceraldehyde 3-phosphate dehydrogenase (GAPDH) as a loading control. A <lb/>representative western blot is shown (n = 2). (B) Relative pERK level was quantified by calculating the pERK:ERK ratio and normalized to the <lb/>control group. Data are displayed as the mean of two experiments. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Journal of Medicinal Chemistry <lb/>pubs.acs.org/jmc <lb/>Article <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jmedchem.1c01598 <lb/>J. Med. Chem. 2022, 65, 2059-2077 <lb/></note>

			<page>2069 <lb/></page>

			<body>chloro and thiophene groups, as well as a water-exposed rim. <lb/>To exploit the unoccupied space in the binding site, a focused <lb/>collection of thiophenes was designed and prepared and MIF2 <lb/>binding was assessed using a PP-tautomerization assay. We <lb/>observed that the potency of 3a analogues can be tuned by <lb/>different substituents in the thiophene 3-position, and a <lb/>(naphthalen-1-yl)methyl group proved to be the favorable <lb/>modification in this series of derivatives. Ring closure of the <lb/>respective 2-aminothiophene precursor afforded the corre-<lb/>sponding thienopyrimidione 5c, which shows an IC 50 of 0.81 <lb/>μM. Thus, inhibitor 5c gained 50-fold in potency compared to <lb/>the previously identified MIF2 inhibitor 4-CPPC that proved <lb/>to have an IC 50 of 47 μM in our assay format. 30 To improve <lb/>the solubility of 5c, we disrupted the planarity of 5c by <lb/>introducing a methyl group to provide 5d, 38 which has <lb/>improved solubility and preserved MIF2 binding potency. <lb/>Notably, 5d exhibits weak inhibition MIF thus demonstrat-<lb/>ing a more than 50-fold selectivity for MIF2 compared to MIF. <lb/>Taken together, we obtained 5d as a selective MIF2 <lb/>tautomerase inhibitor with submicromolar potency and <lb/>optimal solubility, which enable its use in cellular model <lb/>systems. <lb/>The effect of 5d on proliferation was evaluated using cell <lb/>culture assays on several NSCLC cell lines including A549, <lb/>H1299, HCC827, and H1299. 5d showed more than 80% <lb/>inhibition of the proliferation of all four types of tested cancer <lb/>cells at 10 μM in both a DNA content-based assay and a <lb/>clonogenic assay. The effectiveness of 5d was also confirmed <lb/>on a spheroid cell culture assay, which is able to mimic some of <lb/>the main features of solid human tumors, such as their cellular <lb/>layered assembly, hypoxia state, structural organization, and <lb/>nutrient gradients. 43 In this assay, the spheroid volume growth <lb/>was reduced by 63% upon treatment with 2 μM 5d. The data <lb/>demonstrate that 5d treatment provides a strong inhibition of <lb/>cell proliferation, which is in line with the previously reported <lb/>antiproliferation effect of siRNA-mediated MIF2 silencing. 41,44 <lb/>We also noticed, compared with our previous studies on MIF <lb/>tautomerase inhibitors, 15,35 inhibition of MIF2 tautomerase <lb/>activity in this study yielded a more substantial impact on <lb/>cancer cell proliferation. This observation is in line with <lb/>previous results that MIF2-silencing siRNA inhibited cell <lb/>growth more potently than MIF-silencing siRNA. 41 Taken <lb/>together, our results indicate that MIF2 inhibitor 5d inhibits <lb/>the cell proliferation of several model systems, which is in line <lb/>with previous siRNA-based studies on similar model <lb/>systems. 41,44 <lb/>A main feature of the growth of cancer cells is their <lb/>continuous and ordered progression of the cell cycle. 45 <lb/>Treatment of A549 cancer cells with 5d arrested cells in the <lb/>G 0 /G 1 phase, indicating interference of cell cycle progression. <lb/>MIF2 is a growth factor that is involved in the modulation of <lb/>cell cycle progression through the MAPK pathway. 41,46 We <lb/>also observed that 5d treatment attenuates the MAPK <lb/>signaling as we found less MIF2-induced ERK phosphor-<lb/>ylation. The 5d-mediated MAPK pathway deactivation is also <lb/>in line with the effect of siRNA-mediated downregulation of <lb/>MIF2 protein levels. 41 It is also consistent with the inhibition <lb/>of ERK phosphorylation by MIF2 inhibitor 4-CPPC. 30 <lb/>Collectively, these data show that the growth inhibition of <lb/>cancer cell proliferation by 5d treatment can be explained by <lb/>ERK phosphorylation blockade and cell cycle progression <lb/>arrest. <lb/>In conclusion, screening of focused compound collections <lb/>and structure-guided hit optimization enabled the discovery of <lb/>the potent MIF2 inhibitor 5d. This inhibitor has submicro-<lb/>molar potency toward MIF2 tautomerase activity, whereas <lb/>MIF tautomerase activity is not affected. 5d binds in <lb/>competition with the MIF2 tautomerase substrate, and its <lb/>binding was verified by the thermal shift assay in which 5d <lb/>improves the MIF2 thermal stability. Furthermore, we have <lb/>demonstrated that 5d-mediated inhibition of MIF2 activity <lb/>suppresses the growth of NSCLC cells in 2D and 3D cell <lb/>cultures, which can be explained by the inhibition of the <lb/>MAPK signaling and subsequent cell cycle arrest, thus <lb/>validating MIF2 as a target with therapeutic potential for <lb/>NSCLC patients. Taken together, the thienopyrimidione <lb/>reported here represents a novel molecule for the inhibition <lb/>of MIF2 with a clear potential for use in cellular model <lb/>systems. <lb/>■ EXPERIMENTAL SECTION <lb/>General. All of the chemicals and solvents were purchased from <lb/>Sigma-Aldrich, AK Scientific, Fluorochem, or Acros Organics and <lb/>were used without further processing unless stated otherwise. Thin-<lb/>layer chromatography (TLC) of Merck silica gel 60 F 254 plates was <lb/>used for reaction monitoring. Column chromatography was <lb/>conducted using MP Ecochrom silica 32-63 (60 Å). 1 H NMR <lb/>(500 MHz) and 13 C NMR (126 MHz) were recorded on a Bruker <lb/>Avance 500 spectrometer. 1 H and 13 C NMR spectra were reported in <lb/>parts per million (ppm) referenced to deuterated solvents, for <lb/>example, CDCl 3 : δ = 7.26 ppm ( 1 H) and 77.05 ppm ( 13 C) or DMSO-<lb/>d 6 : δ = 2.50 ppm ( 1 H) and 39.52 ppm ( 13 C). To report spin <lb/>multiplicity, the following abbreviations were used: s (singlet), d <lb/>(doublet), dd (doublet of doublets), t (triplet), q (quartet), and m <lb/>(multiplet). Coupling constants were reported in hertz (Hz). Fourier <lb/>transform mass spectrometry (FTMS) and electrospray ionization <lb/>(ESI) on an Applied Biosystems/SCIEX API3000-triple quadrupole <lb/>mass spectrometer were applied for high-resolution mass spectra. <lb/>Purity of the compounds was confirmed to be &gt;95% by C18 HPLC <lb/>analysis. The analogues of 4-HPP were synthesized by following a <lb/>published method. 47 <lb/>2-Amino-N-butyl-5-(4-chlorophenyl)thiophene-3-carboxamide <lb/>(3a). The starting materials 1a-e and 2a-j were either purchased or <lb/>prepared using our previously published methods. 48 To synthesize <lb/>R110 (3a), 2-(4-chlorophenyl)acetaldehyde (1a, 0.32 g, 2.0 mmol) in <lb/>EtOH (5 mL) was added into a solution of N-butyl-2-cyanoacetamide <lb/>(2a, 0.31 g, 2.1 mmol). To the resulting suspension, triethylamine <lb/>(0.30 mL, 2.1 mmol) was added, followed by the addition of S 8 (80 <lb/>mg, 0.60 mmol). Then, the reaction mixture was refluxed overnight. <lb/>After cooled down to room temperature, the mixture was diluted <lb/>using EtOAc (50 mL) and washed with water (2 × 30 mL) and brine <lb/>(2 × 30 mL). The EtOAc layer was collected and dried over MgSO 4 . <lb/>After filtration, the solvent was collected and removed under reduced <lb/>pressure and purification was conducted using flash chromatography, <lb/>with petroleum ether/EtOAc 5:1 (v/v) as eluent. The product (260 <lb/>mg) was obtained as a light brown solid, yield 42%. 1 H NMR (500 <lb/>MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) δ 7.70 (t, J = 5.6 Hz, 1H), 7.64 (s, 1H), 7.50 (s, <lb/>2H), 7.43-7.35 (m, 4H), 3.18 (q, J = 6.9 Hz, 2H), 1.47 (p, J = 7.3 <lb/>Hz, 2H), 1.35-1.29 (m, 2H), 0.90 (t, J = 7.3 Hz, 3H). 13 C NMR <lb/>(126 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) δ 165.15, 161.12, 133.28, 129.92, 128.94, <lb/>125.09, 121.76, 119.86, 108.33, 38.04, 31.58, 19.71, 13.80. HRMS, <lb/>calculated for C 15 H 18 ON 2 ClS [M + H] + : 309.0823, found 309.0824. <lb/>2-Amino-5-(4-bromophenyl)-N-butylthiophene-3-carboxamide <lb/>(3b). 48 2-(4-Bromophenyl)acetaldehyde (0.20 g, 1.0 mmol) and N-<lb/>butyl-2-cyanoacetamide (140 mg, 1.0 mmol) were used to prepare 3b <lb/>following the procedure for the synthesis of 3a, affording compound <lb/>3b (97 mg, yield 28%) as a light yellowish powder. 1 H NMR (500 <lb/>MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) δ 7.71 (t, J = 5.6 Hz, 1H), 7.66 (s, 1H), 7.53 (d, J = <lb/>8.6 Hz, 2H), 7.32 (d, J = 8.6 Hz, 2H), 3.18 (q, J = 6.9 Hz, 2H), 1.47 <lb/>(m, 2H), 1.31 (m, 2H), 0.90 (t, J = 7.3 Hz, 3H). 13 C NMR (126 <lb/></body>
			
			<note place="headnote">Journal of Medicinal Chemistry <lb/>pubs.acs.org/jmc <lb/>Article <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jmedchem.1c01598 <lb/>J. Med. Chem. 2022, 65, 2059-2077 <lb/></note>

			<page>2070 <lb/></page>

			<body>MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) δ 165.6, 161.6, 134.1, 132.3, 125.8, 122.3, 120.3, <lb/>118.7, 108.8, 38.5, 32.0, 20.2, 14.2. HRMS, calculated for <lb/>C 15 H 18 ON 2 BrS [M + H] + : 353,0318, found 353,0318. <lb/>2-Amino-5-(4-chlorophenyl)-N-phenethylthiophene-3-carboxa-<lb/>mide (3c). 2-(4-Chlorophenyl)acetaldehyde (1a, 77 mg, 0.50 mmol) <lb/>and 2-cyano-N-phenethylacetamide (2b, 94 mg, 0.50 mmol) were <lb/>reacted using a procedure similar to the synthesis of 3a, affording <lb/>compound 3c (33 mg, yield 18%) as a light yellowish powder. 1 H <lb/>NMR (500 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) δ 7.88 (t, J = 5.4 Hz, 1H), 7.62 (s, 1H), <lb/>7.52 (s, 2H), 7.41 (d, J = 8.6 Hz, 2H), 7.37 (d, J = 8.7 Hz, 2H), 7.30 <lb/>(t, J = 7.3 Hz, 2H), 7.22 (dd, J = 16.7, 7.0 Hz, 3H), 3.43-3.38 (m, <lb/>2H), 2.81 (t, J = 7.5 Hz, 2H). 13 C NMR (126 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) δ <lb/>165.20, 161.29, 139.65, 133.24, 129.95, 129.00, 128.93, 128.64, <lb/>128.39, 126.09, 125.06, 119.90, 108.21, 40.23, 35.55. MS (ESI): m/z <lb/>357.15 [M + H] + . <lb/>2-Amino-5-phenyl-N-((tetrahydrofuran-3-yl)methyl)thiophene-<lb/>3-carboxamide (3e). 2-Phenylacetaldehyde (1d, 60 mg, 0.50 mmol) <lb/>and 2-cyano-N-((tetrahydrofuran-3-yl)methyl)acetamide (2c, 84 mg, <lb/>0.50 mmol) were reacted using a procedure similar to the synthesis of <lb/>3a, affording compound 3e (52 mg, yield 35%) as a light yellowish <lb/>powder. 1 H NMR (500 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) δ 7.82 (t, J = 5.8 Hz, 1H), <lb/>7.67 (s, 1H), 7.46 (s, 2H), 7.40 (d, J = 8.0 Hz, 2H), 7.34 (t, J = 7.8 <lb/>Hz, 2H), 7.16 (t, J = 7.3 Hz, 1H), 3.93 (p, J = 6.3 Hz, 1H), 3.77 (q, J <lb/>= 7.1, 6.2 Hz, 1H), 3.62 (q, J = 7.4 Hz, 1H), 3.25 (t, J = 5.9 Hz, 2H), <lb/>1.91-1.77 (m, 3H), 1.62-1.52 (m, 1H). 13 C NMR (126 MHz, <lb/>DMSO-d 6 ) δ 165.38, 161.03, 134.30, 128.98, 125.84, 123.58, 121.37, <lb/>120.97, 108.01, 77.35, 67.20, 42.59, 28.66, 25.15. HRMS, calculated <lb/>for C 16 H 19 O 2 N 2 S [M + H] + : 303.1162, found 303.1162. <lb/>2-Amino-N-octyl-5-phenylthiophene-3-carboxamide (3f). 2-Phe-<lb/>nylacetaldehyde (1d, 60 mg, 0.50 mmol) and 2-cyano-N-octylaceta-<lb/>mide (2d, 0.10 g, 0.50 mmol) were reacted using a procedure similar <lb/>to the synthesis of 3a, affording compound 3f (72 mg, yield 44%) as a <lb/>light yellowish powder. 1 H NMR (500 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) δ 7.71 (t, J = <lb/>5.6 Hz, 1H), 7.60 (s, 1H), 7.43 (s, 2H), 7.39 (d, J = 7.3 Hz, 2H), 7.34 <lb/>(t, J = 7.7 Hz, 2H), 7.16 (t, J = 7.7 Hz, 1H), 3.17 (q, J = 6.7 Hz, 2H), <lb/>1.52-1.43 (m, 2H), 1.30-1.23 (m, 10H), 0.85 (t, J = 6.8 Hz, 3H). <lb/>13 <lb/>C NMR (126 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) δ 165.23, 160.77, 134.30, 128.98, <lb/>125.83, 123.63, 121.35, 120.67, 108.25, 38.40, 31.32, 29.47, 28.86, <lb/>28.74, 26.60, 22.15, 14.00. HRMS, calculated for C 19 H 27 N 2 S [M + <lb/>H] + : 331.1839, found 331.1839. <lb/>2-Amino-5-(4-chlorophenyl)-N-(2-ethoxyethyl)thiophene-3-car-<lb/>boxamide (3g). 2-(4-Chlorophenyl)acetaldehyde (1a, 77 mg, 0.50 <lb/>mmol) and 2-cyano-N-(2-ethoxyethyl)acetamide (2e, 80 mg, 0.50 <lb/>mmol) were reacted using a procedure similar to the synthesis of 3a, <lb/>affording compound 3g (88 mg, yield 56%) as a light yellowish <lb/>powder. 1 H NMR (500 MHz, CDCl 3 ) δ 7.34 (d, J = 8.6 Hz, 2H), <lb/>7.29 (d, J = 8.6 Hz, 2H), 6.94 (s, 1H), 6.23 (s, 2H), 6.11 (s, 1H), 3.58 <lb/>(d, J = 2.5 Hz, 4H), 3.55 (q, J = 7.0 Hz, 2H), 1.24 (t, J = 7.0 Hz, 3H). <lb/>13 <lb/>C NMR (126 MHz, CDCl 3 ) δ 165.78, 160.62, 132.68, 132.35, <lb/>129.12, 125.94, 123.98, 118.84, 109.92, 69.45, 66.65, 39.20, 15.32. <lb/>HRMS, calculated for C 15 H 18 ON 2 ClS [M + H] + : 325.0772, found <lb/>325.0773. <lb/>2-Amino-N-(4-chlorophenethyl)-5-(4-chlorophenyl)thiophene-3-<lb/>carboxamide (3h). 48 2-(4-Chlorophenyl)acetaldehyde (1a, 77 mg, <lb/>0.50 mmol) and N-(4-chlorophenethyl)-2-cyanoacetamide (2f, 0.10 g, <lb/>0.50 mmol) were reacted using a procedure similar to the synthesis of <lb/>3a, affording compound 3g (66 mg, yield 34%) as a light yellowish <lb/>powder. 1 H NMR (500 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) δ 7.85 (t, J = 5.6 Hz, 1H), <lb/>7.60 (s, 1H), 7.51 (s, 2H), 7.41 (d, J = 8.8 Hz, 2H), 7.37 (d, J = 9.0 <lb/>Hz, 2H), 7.35 (d, J = 8.4 Hz, 2H), 7.26 (d, J = 8.4 Hz, 2H), 3.40 (q, J <lb/>= 7.1 Hz, 2H), 2.80 (t, J = 7.3 Hz, 2H). 13 C NMR (126 MHz, <lb/>DMSO-d 6 ) δ 165.22, 161.33, 138.72, 133.22, 130.73, 130.57, 129.97, <lb/>129.01, 128.94, 128.28, 125.08, 119.91, 108.13, 40.11, 34.73. MS <lb/>(ESI): m/z 391.10 [M + H] + . <lb/>2-Amino-N,4-dibutyl-5-(4-chlorophenyl)thiophene-3-carboxa-<lb/>mide (3d). 48 1-(4-Chlorophenyl)hexan-2-one (1c, 0.20 g, 1.0 mmol) <lb/>and 2-(4-chlorophenyl)acetaldehyde (1a, 0.15 g, 1.0 mmol) were <lb/>dissolved in dry THF (5 mL). To the stirred solution, SnCl 4 (0.22 <lb/>mL, 2.0 mmol) was added dropwisely. Then, Et 3 N (0.30 mL) was <lb/>added. The reaction mixture was stirred at 40 °C for 16 h, followed by <lb/>the addition of HCl solution (1 N, 25 mL) and extraction with EtOAc <lb/>(3 × 20 mL). The combined organic layers were washed with a <lb/>NaOH solution (1 N, 25 mL) and dried over MgSO 4 . The solid was <lb/>filtrated, and the solvent was removed using evaporation under <lb/>reduced pressure. The resulting mixture was dissolved in EtOH (5 <lb/>mL), and S 8 (32 mg, 0.25 mmol) and Et 3 N (0.2 mL) were added. The <lb/>reaction mixture was refluxed overnight. Then, the mixture was <lb/>diluted with EtOAc (25 mL) and washed with water (2 × 50 mL) and <lb/>brine (2 × 50 mL). The organic layers were dried over MgSO 4 , <lb/>filtrated, and the solvent was removed using evaporation under <lb/>reduced pressure. The product was obtained as a brown solid (151 <lb/>mg, yield 41%) after chromatography using petroleum ether:EtOAc <lb/>30:1 (v/v) as eluent. 1 H NMR (500 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) δ 7.64 (t, J = <lb/>5.6 Hz, 1H), 7.45 (d, J = 8.5 Hz, 2H), 7.28 (d, J = 8.5 Hz, 2H), 6.21 <lb/>(s, 2H), 3.19 (q, J = 6.8 Hz, 2H), 2.66-2.58 (m, 2H), 1.49-1.43 (m, <lb/>2H), 1.33 (dt, J = 14.9, 7.2 Hz, 4H), 1.16 (q, J = 7.3 Hz, 2H), 0.89 (t, <lb/>J = 7.3 Hz, 3H), 0.76 (t, J = 7.3 Hz, 3H). 13 C NMR (126 MHz, <lb/>DMSO-d 6 ) δ 165.47, 155.55, 135.69, 133.52, 131.11, 130.51, 128.70, <lb/>117.17, 113.51, 38.36, 32.22, 31.39, 27.12, 22.10, 19.79, 13.79, 13.65. <lb/>HRMS, calculated for C 19 H 26 ON 2 ClS [M + H] + : 365.1449, found <lb/>365.1449. <lb/>2-Amino-4-methyl-N-(naphthalen-1-ylmethyl)-5-( 3-<lb/>(trifluoromethyl)phenyl)thiophene-3-carboxamide (3i). 1-(3-<lb/>(Trifluoromethyl)phenyl)propan-2-on (1e, 0.30 g, 1.5 mmol) and <lb/>2-cyano-N-(naphthalen-1-ylmethyl)acetamide (2h, 0.30 g, 1.5 mmol) <lb/>were reacted using a procedure similar to the synthesis of 3d, <lb/>affording compound 3i (178 mg, yield 28%) as a brown solid. 1 H <lb/>NMR (500 MHz, CDCl 3 ) δ 8.08 (d, J = 8.3 Hz, 1H), 7.89 (d, J = 8.0 <lb/>Hz, 1H), 7.83 (d, J = 8.1 Hz, 1H), 7.58-7.42 (m, 8H), 6.10 (s, 1H), <lb/>5.07 (d, J = 5.0 Hz, 2H), 2.16 (s, 3H). 13 C NMR (126 MHz, CDCl 3 ) <lb/>δ 166.2, 135.0, 134.1, 133.6, 132.9, 131.5, 131.1, 130.9 (q, J = 32.2 <lb/>Hz), 129.1, 129.0, 128.9, 128.8, 126.8, 126.3 (q, J = 3.6 Hz), 126.2, <lb/>126.1 (q, J = 234.9 Hz), 125.7, 125.6, 123.7 (q, J = 3.7 Hz), 123.5, <lb/>119.8, 112.1, 42.0, 16.2. HRMS, calculated for C 24 H 20 ON 2 F 3 S [M + <lb/>H] + : 441.1243, found 441.1240. <lb/>(R)-2-Amino-4-methyl-N-(1-(naphthalen-1-yl)ethyl)-5-(3-<lb/>(trifluoromethyl)phenyl)thiophene-3-carboxamide (3j). 1-(3-<lb/>(Trifluoromethyl)phenyl)propan-2-on (1e, 0.41 g, 2.0 mmol) and <lb/>(R)-2-cyano-N-(1-(naphthalen-1-yl)ethyl)acetamide (2i, 0.50 g, 2.0 <lb/>mmol) were reacted using a procedure similar to the synthesis of 3d, <lb/>affording compound 3j (146 mg, yield 16%) as a brown solid. 1 H <lb/>NMR (500 MHz, CDCl 3 ) δ 8.18 (d, J = 8.5 Hz, 1H), 7.88 (d, J = 8.1 <lb/>Hz, 1H), 7.81 (d, J = 8.2 Hz, 1H), 7.59-7.43 (m, 8H), 6.19-6.02 (m, <lb/>3H), 2.19 (s, 3H), 1.78 (d, J = 5.9 Hz, 3H). 13 C NMR (126 MHz, <lb/>CDCl 3 ) δ 165.4, 138.6, 135.0, 134.2, 132.9, 131.2, 131.1, 130.9 (q, J = <lb/>20.7 Hz), 129.1, 129.0, 128.9, 128.5, 127.5 (q, J = 306.1 Hz), 126.7, <lb/>126.3, 126.3, 126.0, 125.4, 123.7 (q, J = 4.9 Hz), 123.5, 123.0, 122.7, <lb/>45.0, 21.4, 16.2. HRMS, calculated for C 25 H 22 ON 2 F 3 S [M + H] + : <lb/>455.1399, found 455.1397. <lb/>(S)-2-Amino-4-methyl-N-(1-(naphthalen-1-yl)ethyl)-5-(3-<lb/>(trifluoromethyl)phenyl)thiophene-3-carboxamide (3k). 1-(3-<lb/>(Trifluoromethyl)phenyl)propan-2-on (1e, 0.2 g, 1 mmol) and (S)-<lb/>2-cyano-N-(1-(naphthalen-1-yl)ethyl)acetamide (2i, 0.20 g, 1.0 <lb/>mmol) were reacted using a procedure similar to the synthesis of <lb/>3d, affording compound 3k (0.20 g, yield 42%) as a brown solid. 1 H <lb/>NMR (500 MHz, CDCl 3 ) δ 8.19 (d, J = 8.5 Hz, 1H), 7.88 (d, J = 8.1 <lb/>Hz, 1H), 7.82 (d, J = 8.2 Hz, 1H), 7.63-7.39 (m, 9H), 6.13-6.07 (m, <lb/>2H), 2.19 (s, 3H), 1.81 (m, 3H). 13 C NMR (126 MHz, CDCl 3 ) δ <lb/>165.4, 138.6, 135.0, 134.2, 132.9, 131.1, 130.9, 129.1, 129.1, 128.9, <lb/>128.5, 126.7, 126.3, 126.3, 126.0, 125.5 (q, J = 285.6 Hz), 125.4, <lb/>123.9, 123.7, 123.5, 123.0, 122.7, 45.1, 21.4, 16.2. HRMS, calculated <lb/>for C 25 H 22 ON 2 F 3 S [M + H] + : 455.1399, found 455.1398. <lb/>2-Acetamido-N-butyl-5-phenylthiophene-3-carboxamide (4a). <lb/>To a stirred solution of 2-amino-N-butyl-5-phenylthiophene-3-<lb/>carboxamide (0.30 g, 1.0 mmol) in DMF (4 mL), acyl chloride <lb/>(2.0 mmol) and pyridine (2 mmol) were added. The reaction mixture <lb/>was stirred at room temperature overnight. Subsequently, the reaction <lb/>mixture was diluted with CH 2 Cl 2 (20 mL) and was sequentially <lb/>washed with HCl (1 N, 20 mL), saturated NaHCO 3 (20 mL), water <lb/>(20 mL), and brine (2 × 20 mL). The organic layer was collected and <lb/></body>
			
			<note place="headnote">Journal of Medicinal Chemistry <lb/>pubs.acs.org/jmc <lb/>Article <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jmedchem.1c01598 <lb/>J. Med. Chem. 2022, 65, 2059-2077 <lb/></note>

			<page>2071 <lb/></page>

			<body>dried over MgSO 4 . After filtration, the solvent was removed under <lb/>reduced pressure. The product was obtained as a brown solid (182 <lb/>mg, yield 58%). 1 H NMR (500 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) δ 12.06 (s, 1H), <lb/>8.39 (t, J = 5.5 Hz, 1H), 7.88 (s, 1H), 7.57 (d, J = 7.3 Hz, 2H), 7.42 <lb/>(t, J = 7.8 Hz, 2H), 7.29 (t, J = 7.9 Hz, 1H), 3.28 (q, J = 7.0 Hz, 2H), <lb/>2.22 (s, 3H), 1.53 (p, J = 7.4 Hz, 2H), 1.34 (h, J = 7.3 Hz, 2H), 0.91 <lb/>(t, J = 7.4 Hz, 3H). 13 C NMR (126 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) δ 166.99, <lb/>164.51, 144.58, 133.62, 131.67, 129.31, 127.31, 124.82, 118.78, <lb/>115.85, 38.45, 31.23, 23.22, 19.71, 13.75. HRMS, calculated for <lb/>C 17 H 21 O 2 N 2 S [M + H] + : 317.1318, found 317.1317. <lb/>N-Butyl-2-butyramido-5-phenylthiophene-3-carboxamide <lb/>(4b). 48 4b was prepared by following the similar procedure for the <lb/>synthesis of 4a. Product was obtained as a brown solid (152 mg, yield <lb/>44%). 1 H NMR (500 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) δ 12.2 (s, 1H), 8.4 (t, J = 5.7 <lb/>Hz, 1H), 7.9 (s, 1H), 7.6-7.5 (m, 2H), 7.4 (t, J = 7.7 Hz, 2H), 7.3 <lb/>(td, J = 7.3, 1.1 Hz, 1H), 3.3 (td, J = 7.1, 5.6 Hz, 2H), 2.5 (t, J = 7.3 <lb/>Hz, 2H), 1.6 (h, J = 7.3 Hz, 2H), 1.5 (tt, J = 7.7, 6.5 Hz, 2H), 1.3 (h, J <lb/>= 7.3 Hz, 2H), 0.9 (dt, J = 10.0, 7.3 Hz, 6H) ppm. 13 C NMR (126 <lb/>MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) δ 169.6, 164.6, 144.6, 133.6, 131.7, 129.2, 127.3, <lb/>124.8, 124.6, 118.8, 118.6, 115.9, 38.5, 37.6, 31.2, 19.7, 18.3, 13.7, <lb/>13.5. HRMS, calculated for C 19 H 25 O 2 N 2 S [M + H] + : 345.1631, found <lb/>345.1631. <lb/>N-Butyl-2-heptanamido-5-phenylthiophene-3-carboxamide <lb/>(4c). 4c was prepared by following the similar procedure for the <lb/>synthesis of 4a. Product was obtained as a brown solid (195 mg, yield <lb/>51%). 1 H NMR (500 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) δ 12.15 (s, 1H), 8.39 (t, J = <lb/>5.6 Hz, 1H), 7.88 (s, 1H), 7.57 (d, J = 7.5 Hz, 2H), 7.43 (t, J = 7.8 <lb/>Hz, 2H), 7.29 (t, J = 7.4 Hz, 1H), 2.49-2.45 (m, 2H), 2.18 (t, J = 7.4 <lb/>Hz, 2H), 1.61 (p, J = 7.2 Hz, 2H), 1.53 (p, J = 7.4 Hz, 2H), 1.35 (dt, J <lb/>= 14.8, 7.4 Hz, 2H), 1.27-1.23 (m, 8H), 0.91 (t, J = 7.4 Hz, 3H), <lb/>0.85 (s, 3H). 13 C NMR (126 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) δ 174.98, 170.15, <lb/>165.03, 145.02, 134.09, 132.11, 129.67, 127.74, 125.06, 116.31, 38.90, <lb/>36.15, 34.12, 31.62, 28.94, 25.23, 24.97, 22.53, 20.15, 14.42, 14.19. <lb/>HRMS, calculated for C 23 H 33 O 2 N 2 S [M + H] + : 401.2255, found <lb/>401.2254. <lb/>3-Butyl-6-phenylthieno[2,3-d]pyrimidine-2,4(1H,3H)-dione <lb/>(5a). 48 To a solution of 2-amino-N-butyl-5-phenylthiophene-3-<lb/>carboxamide (0.3g, 1.0 mmol) in DCM (10 mL), 1,1-carbon-<lb/>yldiimidazole (CDI, 0.50 g, 3.1 mmol) was added, and the solution <lb/>was refluxed for 16 h. Subsequently, the solvent was removed under <lb/>reduce pressure and EtOAc (25 mL) was added to dissolve the <lb/>residual mixture. The organic solution was then washed with water <lb/>(25 mL) and brine (25 mL). The EtOAc layer was collected and dried <lb/>over MgSO 4 . After the removal of MgSO 4 by filtration, the solvent <lb/>was removed using evaporation under reduced pressure. The <lb/>purification was done using chromatography with petroleum ether:-<lb/>EtOAc 3:1 (v/v) as an eluent, and a 159 mg light yellow solid was <lb/>obtained as the product. Yield 52%. 1 H NMR (500 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) <lb/>δ 7.66 (d, J = 7.4 Hz, 2H), 7.58 (s, 1H), 7.41 (t, J = 7.7 Hz, 2H), 7.32 <lb/>(t, J = 7.4 Hz, 1H), 3.96-3.73 (m, 2H), 1.53 (p, J = 7.5 Hz, 2H), 1.30 <lb/>(h, J = 7.4 Hz, 2H), 0.90 (t, J = 7.4 Hz, 3H). 13 C NMR (126 MHz, <lb/>DMSO-d 6 ) δ 158.32, 150.26, 149.70, 133.44, 132.60, 129.25, 127.95, <lb/>125.29, 118.10, 115.60, 29.48, 22.39, 19.68, 13.76. HRMS, calculated <lb/>for C 16 H 17 O 2 N 2 [M + H] + : 301.1005, found 301.1006. <lb/>3-Allyl-6-(4-chlorophenyl)thieno[2,3-d]pyrimidine-2,4(1H,3H)-<lb/>dione (5b). N-Allyl-2-amino-5-(4-chlorophenyl)thiophene-3-carbox-<lb/>amide (0.30 g, 1.0 mmol) was reacted with CDI (0.50 g, 3.0 mmol) <lb/>following a similar method for the synthesis of 5a to provide 5b as a <lb/>126 mg light yellow solid. Yield 40%. 1 H NMR (500 MHz, DMSO-<lb/>d 6 ) δ 12.39 (s, 1H), 7.69 (d, J = 8.4 Hz, 2H), 7.65 (s, 1H), 7.46 (d, J <lb/>= 8.4 Hz, 2H), 5.85 (dq, J = 16.0, 5.2 Hz, 1H), 5.14-5.05 (m, 2H), <lb/>4.45 (d, J = 4.5 Hz, 2H). 13 C NMR (126 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) δ 157.93, <lb/>150.19, 149.97, 132.71, 132.33, 132.11, 131.53, 129.14, 126.90, <lb/>118.89, 116.23, 115.55, 41.93. MS (ESI): m/z 319.08 [M + H] + . <lb/>5-Methyl-3-(naphthalen-1-ylmethyl)-6-(3-(trifluoromethyl)-<lb/>phenyl)thieno[2,3-d]pyrimidine-2,4(1H,3H)-dione (5c). 3i (50 mg, <lb/>0.10 mmol) and CDI (50 mg, 0.31 mmol) were reacted using a <lb/>procedure similar to the synthesis of 5a, affording compound 5c (48 <lb/>mg, yield 91%) as a brown solid. 1 H NMR (500 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) δ <lb/>12.56 (s, 1H), 8.22 (d, J = 8.3 Hz, 1H), 7.98 (d, J = 8.0 Hz, 1H), <lb/>7.84-7.72 (m, 5H), 7.64-7.56 (m, 2H), 7.42 (t, J = 7.7 Hz, 1H), <lb/>7.10 (d, J = 7.2 Hz, 1H), 5.53 (s, 2H), 2.44 (s, 3H). 13 C NMR (126 <lb/>MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) δ 159.3, 151.2, 150.2, 133.5, 133.4 (q, J = 15.3 Hz), <lb/>133.2, 132.2, 131.2, 130.4, 130.2, 129.9, 129.6, 128.7, 127.2, 127.1, <lb/>126.4, 125.8, 125.5, 125.1, 123.8 (q, J = 231.0 Hz), 123.0, 122.0, <lb/>113.8, 40.9, 14.1. HRMS, calculated for C 25 H 18 O 2 N 2 F 3 S [M + H] + : <lb/>467.1036, found 467.1034. <lb/>(R)-5-Methyl-3-(1-(naphthalen-1-yl)ethyl)-6-(3-(trifluoromethyl)-<lb/>phenyl)thieno[2,3-d]pyrimidine-2,4(1H,3H)-dione (5d). 3j (0.10 g, <lb/>0.50 mmol) and CDI (0.20 g, 1.2 mmol) were reacted using a <lb/>procedure similar to the synthesis of 5a, affording compound 5d (68 <lb/>mg, yield 64%) as a brown solid. 1 H NMR (500 MHz, CDCl 3 ) δ <lb/>11.27 (s, 1H), 7.98 (dd, J = 10.4, 7.9 Hz, 2H), 7.80 (d, J = 8.3 Hz, <lb/>1H), 7.76 (d, J = 8.2 Hz, 1H), 7.65 (t, J = 3.6 Hz, 2H), 7.62-7.57 (m, <lb/>2H), 7.53-7.49 (m, 1H), 7.46-7.37 (m, 2H), 6.91 (q, J = 7.0 Hz, <lb/>1H), 2.56 (s, 3H), 2.03 (d, J = 7.0 Hz, 3H). 13 C NMR (126 MHz, <lb/>CDCl 3 ) δ 159.5, 152.3, 150.0, 134.7, 133.8, 133.7, 132.9, 132.3, 131.8, <lb/>131.5 (q, J = 32.1 Hz), 129.5, 129.1, 128.4, 127.9, 126.6, 126.4, 126.3 <lb/>(q, J = 3.7 Hz), 126.1 (q, J = 251.2 Hz), 125.3, 125.0, 124.8 (q, J = 3.4 <lb/>Hz), 123.2, 115.3, 47.9, 16.9, 14.7. HRMS, calculated for <lb/>C 26 H 20 O 2 N 2 F 3 S [M + H] + : 481.1192, found 481.1192. <lb/>(S)-5-Methyl-3-(1-(naphthalen-1-yl)ethyl)-6-(3-(trifluoromethyl)-<lb/>phenyl)thieno[2,3-d]pyrimidine-2,4(1H,3H)-dione (5e). 3k (0.10 g, <lb/>0.50 mmol) and CDI (0.20 g, 1.2 mmol) were reacted using a <lb/>procedure similar to the synthesis of 5e, affording compound 5e (82 <lb/>mg, yield 77%) as a light yellow solid. 1 H NMR (500 MHz, CDCl 3 ) δ <lb/>11.13 (s, 1H), 7.97 (m, 2H), 7.81 (d, J = 7.8 Hz, 1H), 7.76 (d, J = 8.2 <lb/>Hz, 1H), 7.64 (d, J = 5.4 Hz, 2H), 7.59 (d, J = 3.5 Hz, 2H), 7.51 (t, J <lb/>= 7.7 Hz, 1H), 7.42 (dt, J = 22.1, 7.4 Hz, 2H), 6.91 (q, J = 6.6 Hz, <lb/>1H), 2.55 (s, 3H), 2.03 (d, J = 6.9 Hz, 3H). 13 C NMR (126 MHz, <lb/>CDCl 3 ) δ 159.5, 152.1, 150.0, 134.8, 133.8, 133.7, 132.9, 132.3, 131.8, <lb/>131.5 (q, J = 32.8 Hz), 129.5, 129.1, 128.4, 127.9, 126.7, 126.3, 126.3, <lb/>126.0 (q, J = 236.1 Hz), 125.4, 125.0, 124.8 (q, J = 3.4), 123.2, 115.3, <lb/>47.9, 16.9, 14.6. HRMS, calculated for C 26 H 20 O 2 N 2 F 3 S [M + H] + : <lb/>481.1192, found 481.1192. <lb/>Ethyl 2-Amino-4-methyl-5-phenylthiophene-3-carboxylate <lb/>(6a). 49 A mixture of phenolacetone (1f, 0.7 mL, 5 mmol), ethyl <lb/>cyanoacetate (0.5 mL, 5 mmol), ammonium acetate (0.1 g, 1 mmol), <lb/>and acetic acid (0.2 mL, 4 mmol) in toluene (5 mL) was heated under <lb/>reflux for 20 h, while water was removed using a molecular sieve. After <lb/>the mixture was cooled to room temperature, the mixture was <lb/>concentrated in vacuo. The residue was diluted with saturated <lb/>NaHCO 3 (20 mL) and extracted with CHCl 3 (3 × 25 mL). The <lb/>extract was washed with brine (25 mL) and dried (MgSO 4 ). After <lb/>evaporation of the solvent in vacuo, the residue was purified by flash <lb/>column chromatography to give an oil-like intermediate, which was <lb/>dissolved in EtOH (9 mL). To the solution were added sulfur powder <lb/>(0.13 g, 4.0 mmol) and triethylamine (0.6 mL, 4 mmol), and the <lb/>resulting mixture was stirred at 100 °C for 2 h. After removal of the <lb/>solvent in vacuo, the residue was diluted with brine and extracted with <lb/>CHCl 3 (3 × 25 mL). The organic layers were collected and washed <lb/>with brine (25 mL) and dried (MgSO 4 ). The solution was <lb/>concentrated in vacuo, and the residue was recrystallized from <lb/>CHCl 3 to afford 6a (1.1 g, 81%) as dark brown crystals. 1 H NMR <lb/>(500 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) δ 7.82 (t, J = 5.8 Hz, 1H), 7.46 (s, 2H), 7.40 <lb/>(d, J = 8.0 Hz, 2H), 7.34 (t, J = 7.8 Hz, 2H), 4.36 (q, J = 7.0 Hz, 3H), <lb/>1.34 (t, J = 7.1 Hz, 3H). <lb/>Ethyl 2-Amino-5-(4-chlorophenyl)-4-methylthiophene-3-carbox-<lb/>ylate (6b). 4-Chlorophenylacetone (1j, 0.7 mL, 5 mmol) and ethyl <lb/>cyanoacetate (0.5 g, 5 mmol) were reacted using a procedure similar <lb/>to the synthesis of 6a, affording compound 6b (0.9 g, yield 61%) as a <lb/>brown solid. 1 H NMR (500 MHz, CDCl 3 ) δ 7.34 (d, J = 8.5 Hz, 2H), <lb/>7.27 (d, J = 7.3 Hz, 2H), 6.12 (s, 2H), 4.35-4.28 (m, 2H), 2.30 (s, <lb/>3H), 1.37 (t, J = 7.1 Hz, 3H). <lb/>Ethyl 2-Amino-5-(3,4-dichlorophenyl)-4-methylthiophene-3-car-<lb/>boxylate (6c). 1-(3,4-Dichlorophenyl)propan-2-one (1k, 0.3 mL, 2 <lb/>mmol) and ethyl cyanoacetate (0.5 g, 5 mmol) were reacted using a <lb/>procedure similar to the synthesis of 6a, affording compound 6c (0.3 <lb/>g, yield 39%) as a brown solid. 1 H NMR (500 MHz, methanol-d 4 ) δ <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Journal of Medicinal Chemistry <lb/>pubs.acs.org/jmc <lb/>Article <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jmedchem.1c01598 <lb/>J. Med. Chem. 2022, 65, 2059-2077 <lb/></note>

			<page>2072 <lb/></page>

			<body>7.54 (s, 1H), 7.29 (d, J = 7.1 Hz, 1H), 7.27 (d, J = 7.1 Hz, 1H), 4.13 <lb/>(q, J = 7.0 Hz, 32), 2.05 (s, 3H), 1.27 (t, J = 7.1 Hz, 3H). <lb/>Ethyl 2-Amino-5-(2,4-dichlorophenyl)-4-methylthiophene-3-car-<lb/>boxylate (6d). 1-(2,4-Dichlorophenyl)propan-2-one (1l, 0.3 mL, 2 <lb/>mmol) and ethyl cyanoacetate (0.3 g, 3 mmol) were reacted using a <lb/>procedure similar to the synthesis of 6a, affording compound 6d (0.3 <lb/>g, yield 49%) as a brown solid. 1 H NMR (500 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) δ <lb/>7.72 (d, J = 2.1 Hz, 1H), 7.49-7.38 (m, 4H), 4.20 (q, J = 7.1 Hz, <lb/>2H), 1.99 (s, 3H), 1.27 (t, J = 7.1 Hz, 3H). <lb/>Ethyl 2-Amino-4-methyl-5-(3-(trifluoromethyl)phenyl)-<lb/>thiophene-3-carboxylate (6e). 1e (0.7 mL, 5 mmol) and ethyl <lb/>cyanoacetate (0.5 g, 5 mmol) were reacted using a procedure similar <lb/>to the synthesis of 6a, affording compound 6e (1.0 g, yield 68%) as a <lb/>brown solid. 1 H NMR (500 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) δ 7.64 (m, 3H), 7.58 <lb/>(s, 1H), 7.55 (s, 2H), 4.22 (q, J = 7.1 Hz, 2H), 2.26 (s, 3H), 1.28 (t, J <lb/>= 7.1 Hz, 3H). <lb/>Ethyl 2-Amino-5-(benzo[d][1,3]dioxol-5-yl)-4-methylthiophene-<lb/>3-carboxylate (6f). 1-(Benzo[d][1,3]dioxol-5-yl)propan-2-one (1m, <lb/>0.3 mL, 2 mmol) and ethyl cyanoacetate (0.5 g, 5 mmol) were reacted <lb/>using a procedure similar to the synthesis of 6a, affording compound <lb/>6b (0.2 g, yield 28%) as a brown solid. 1 H NMR (500 MHz,CDCl 3 ) δ <lb/>7.74 (s, 1H), 7.44 (d, J = 6.8 Hz, 1H), 6.94 (d, J = 6.1 Hz, 1H), 6.84 <lb/>(s, 2H), 6.12 (s, 2H), 4.39 (q, J = 6.8 Hz, 2H), 2.31 (s, 3H), 1.40 (t, J <lb/>= 6.5 Hz, 3H). <lb/>Ethyl 2-Amino-5-(4-fluorophenyl)-4-methylthiophene-3-carbox-<lb/>ylate (6g). 1-(Benzo[d][1,3]dioxol-5-yl)propan-2-one (1m, 0.70 mL, <lb/>5.0 mmol) and ethyl cyanoacetate (0.55 g, 5.0 mmol) were reacted <lb/>using a procedure similar to the synthesis of 6a, affording compound <lb/>6b (0.81 g, yield 59%) as a brown solid. 1 H NMR (500 MHz, <lb/>methanol-d 4 ) δ 7.37-7.31 (m, 2H), 7.14-7.10 (m, 2H), 4.30 (q, J = <lb/>7.1 Hz, 2H), 2.27 (s, 3H), 1.37 (t, J = 7.1 Hz, 3H). <lb/>Synthesis of 7a-i. 5-Methyl-3,6-diphenylthieno[2,3-d]-<lb/>pyrimidine-2,4(1H,3H)-dione (7a). To a stirred solution of 6a (0.3 <lb/>g, 1 mmol) in pyridine (3 mL), phenyl isocyanate (0.21 mL, 1.5 <lb/>mmol) was added and stirred at 45 °C for overnight. The resulting <lb/>mixture was concentrated reduced pressure, and the residue was <lb/>suspended in MeOH (5 mL). To the suspension, 25% sodium <lb/>methoxide (0.6 mL, 3 mmol) was added and the resulting mixture was <lb/>stirred for 6 h at room temperature. Subsequently, the mixture was <lb/>acidified with 1 N HCl (10 ml) at 0 °C and the pH was regulated to 4. <lb/>The organic solvent was evaporated to a volume of about 5 mL, and <lb/>the precipitate was collected. The obtained solid was dissolved in <lb/>methanol and purified with chromatography using DCM:MeOH <lb/>(100:1) as a solvent. The product was obtained as light brown crystals <lb/>(135 mg, yield 40%). 1 H NMR (500 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) δ 12.37 (s, <lb/>1H), 7.51-7.39 (m, 8H), 7.31-7.27 (m, 2H), 2.40 (s, 3H). 13 C NMR <lb/>(126 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) δ 159.44, 150.86, 150.15, 135.79, 132.38, <lb/>129.83, 129.22, 129.07, 128.99, 128.86, 128.71, 127.97, 126.74, <lb/>114.19, 14.15. HRMS, calculated for C 19 H 15 O 2 N 2 S [M + H] + : <lb/>335.0849, found 335.0849. <lb/>3-Benzyl-5-methyl-6-phenylthieno[2,3-d]pyrimidine-2,4(1H,3H)-<lb/>dione (7b). 6a (0.3 g, 1 mmol) and benzyl isocyanate (0.2 mL, 1.5 <lb/>mmol) were reacted using a procedure similar to the synthesis of 7a, <lb/>affording compound 7b (150 mg, yield 43%) as a white solid. 1 H <lb/>NMR (500 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) δ 12.36 (s, 1H), 7.49-7.44 (m, 4H), <lb/>7.39 (t, J = 6.8 Hz, 1H), 7.32-7.30 (m, 4H), 7.25-7.23 (m, 1H), <lb/>5.04 (s, 2H), 2.43 (s, 3H). 13 C NMR (126 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) δ <lb/>159.19, 150.43, 150.20, 137.49, 132.34, 129.65, 129.16, 129.08, <lb/>128.34, 127.97, 127.40, 127.04, 126.86, 113.76, 42.89, 14.15. HRMS, <lb/>calculated for C 20 H 17 O 2 N 2 S [M + H] + : 349.1005, found 349.1004. <lb/>6-(4-Chlorophenyl)-5-methyl-3-phenylthieno[2,3-d]pyrimidine-<lb/>2,4(1H,3H)-dione (7c). 6b (0.3 g, 1 mmol) and phenyl isocyanate (0.2 <lb/>mL, 1.5 mmol) were reacted using a procedure similar to the synthesis <lb/>of 7a, affording compound 7c (93 mg, yield 31%) as a white solid. 1 H <lb/>NMR (500 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) δ 12.40 (s, 1H), 7.54 (d, J = 8.6 Hz, <lb/>2H), 7.51-7.46 (m, 4H), 7.41 (t, J = 7.4 Hz, 1H), 7.29 (d, J = 7.1 Hz, <lb/>2H), 2.40 (s, 3H). 13 C NMR (126 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) δ 159.84, <lb/>151.48, 150.55, 136.19, 133.12, 131.73, 131.40, 131.23, 131.12, <lb/>131.00, 129.65, 129.37, 125.80, 114.64, 14.55. MS (ESI): m/z 369.09 <lb/>[M + H] + . <lb/>3-Benzyl-6-(4-chlorophenyl)-5-methylthieno[2,3-d]pyrimidine-<lb/>2,4(1H,3H)-dione (7d). 6b (0.2 g, 0.7 mmol) and benzyl isocyanate <lb/>(0.2 mL, 1.5 mmol) were reacted using a procedure similar to the <lb/>synthesis of 7a, affording compound 7d (73 mg, yield 34%) as a white <lb/>solid. 1 H NMR (500 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) δ 12.38 (s, 1H), 7.53 (d, J = <lb/>6.1 Hz, 2H), 7.47 (d, J = 7.6 Hz, 2H), 7.31-7.24 (m, 5H), 5.04 (s, <lb/>2H), 2.43 (s, 3H). 13 C NMR (126 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) δ 159.58, <lb/>151.07, 150.60, 137.91, 133.11, 131.70, 131.28, 130.82, 129.50, <lb/>128.79, 127.86, 127.49, 125.92, 114.20, 43.36, 14.56. HRMS, <lb/>calculated for C 20 H 16 O 2 N 2 ClS [M + H] + : 383.0616, found 383.0616. <lb/>6-(4-Chlorophenyl)-5-methyl-3-(4-(trifluoromethyl)benzyl)-<lb/>thieno[2,3-d]pyrimidine-2,4(1H,3H)-dione (7e). 6b (0.2 g, 0.5 <lb/>mmol) and 4-(trifluoromethyl)benzyl isocyanate (0.2 mL, 1.0 <lb/>mmol) were reacted using a procedure similar to the synthesis of <lb/>7a, affording compound 7e (0.1 g, yield 44%) as a white solid. 1 H <lb/>NMR (500 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) δ 12.44 (s, 1H), 7.68 (d, J = 6.8 Hz, <lb/>2H), 7.56-7.44 (m, 6H), 5.12 (s, 2H), 2.42 (s, 3H). 13 C NMR (126 <lb/>MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) δ 159.6, 151.3, 150.6, 142.7, 133.1, 131.7, 131.3, <lb/>131.1 (q, J = 26.4 Hz), 130.8, 129.4, 128.4, 126.0, 125.8, 124.4 (q, J = <lb/>284.0 Hz), 114.2, 43.2, 14.5. HRMS, calculated for C 21 H 15 O 2 N 2 ClF 3 S <lb/>[M + H] + : 451.0489, found 451.0489. <lb/>3-Benzyl-6-(3,4-dichlorophenyl)-5-methylthieno[2,3-d]-<lb/>pyrimidine-2,4(1H,3H)-dione (7f). 6c (0.2 g, 0.5 mmol) and benzyl <lb/>isocyanate (0.2 mL, 1.5 mmol) were reacted using a procedure similar <lb/>to the synthesis of 7a, affording compound 7f (0.1 g, yield 48%) as a <lb/>white solid. 1 H NMR (500 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) δ 12.34 (s, 1H), 7.53 <lb/>(dt, J = 5.9, 2.7 Hz, 2H), 7.27 (t, J = 6.2 Hz, 5H), 6.74 (d, J = 4.5 Hz, <lb/>1H), 5.00 (s, 2H), 4.16 (s, 3H). 13 C NMR (126 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) δ <lb/>158.91, 150.35, 141.33, 137.47, 136.65, 130.71, 130.66, 130.41, <lb/>129.23, 128.66, 128.31, 127.47, 127.07, 120.90, 113.57, 111.82, 42.77, <lb/>33.69. HRMS, calculated for C 20 H 15 O 2 N 2 Cl 2 S [M + H] + : 417.0226, <lb/>found 417.0225. <lb/>3-Benzyl-6-(2,4-dichlorophenyl)-5-methylthieno[2,3-d]-<lb/>pyrimidine-2,4(1H,3H)-dione (7g). 6d (0.2 g, 0.5 mmol) and benzyl <lb/>isocyanate (0.2 mL, 1.5 mmol) were reacted using a procedure similar <lb/>to the synthesis of 7a, affording compound 7g (82 mg, yield 39%) as a <lb/>white solid. 1 H NMR (500 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) δ 12.37 (s, 1H), 7.81 (d, <lb/>J = 2.0 Hz, 1H), 7.56-7.49 (m, 2H), 7.33-7.29 (m, 4H), 7.26-7.23 <lb/>(m, 1H), 5.04 (s, 2H), 2.18 (s, 3H). 13 C NMR (126 MHz, DMSO-<lb/>d 6 ) δ 159.49, 151.85, 150.66, 137.91, 135.49, 135.01, 134.92, 133.15, <lb/>130.05, 129.79, 128.81, 127.91, 127.88, 127.53, 122.38, 113.26, 43.39, <lb/>14.68. HRMS, calculated for C 20 H 15 O 2 N 2 Cl 2 S [M + H] + : 417.0226, <lb/>found 417.0225. <lb/>3-Benzyl-5-methyl-6-(3-(trifluoromethyl)phenyl)thieno[2,3-d]-<lb/>pyrimidine-2,4(1H,3H)-dione (7h). 6e (0.20 g, 0.50 mmol) and <lb/>benzyl isocyanate (0.20 mL, 1.5 mmol) were reacted using a <lb/>procedure similar to the synthesis of 7a, affording compound 7h (130 <lb/>mg, yield 62%) as a white solid. 1 H NMR (500 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) δ <lb/>12.46 (s, 1H), 7.75 (m, 4H), 7.32 (m, 4H), 7.26 (m, 1H), 5.06 (s, <lb/>2H), 2.45 (s, 3H). 13 C NMR (126 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) δ 159.2, 151.0, <lb/>150.2, 137.5, 133.5, 133.2, 131.2, 130.3 (q, J = 30.5 Hz), 129.9, 129.6, <lb/>128.4, 127.4, 127.1, 125.6 (q, J = 272.9 Hz), 125.0, 122.9, 113.7, 42.9, <lb/>14.1. HRMS, calculated for C 21 H 16 O 2 N 2 F 3 S [M + H] + : 417.0879, <lb/>found 417.0879. <lb/>6-(Benzo[d][1,3]dioxol-5-yl)-3-benzyl-5-methylthieno[2,3-d]-<lb/>pyrimidine-2,4(1H,3H)-dione (7i). 6f (0.20 g, 0.50 mmol) and benzyl <lb/>isocyanate (0.2 mL, 1.5 mmol) were reacted using a procedure similar <lb/>to the synthesis of 7a, affording compound 7i (38 mg, yield 20%) as a <lb/>white solid. 1 H NMR (500 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) δ 12.33 (s, 1H), 7.27 <lb/>(dd, J = 19.8, 6.8 Hz, 5H), 7.01 (dd, J = 10.2, 5.7 Hz, 2H), 6.90 (t, J = <lb/>6.3 Hz, 1H), 6.08 (s, 2H), 5.04 (s, 2H), 2.39 (s, 3H). 13 C NMR (126 <lb/>MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) δ 159.61, 150.67, 150.49, 148.16, 147.62, 137.95, <lb/>129.63, 128.80, 127.81, 127.48, 127.19, 126.31, 123.60, 114.03, <lb/>109.95, 109.19, 101.92, 43.31, 14.54. HRMS, calculated for <lb/>C 21 H 17 O 4 N 2 S [M + H] + : 393.0904, found 393.0897. <lb/>2-(Chloromethyl)-6-(4-chlorophenyl)-5-methylthieno[2,3-d]-<lb/>pyrimidin-4(1H)-one (8a). 6b (0.33 g, 1.0 mmol) and 2-<lb/>chloroacetonitrile (0.1 mL, 1.2 mmol) were diluted into HCl (4 N, <lb/>6 mL) in 1,4-dioxane (2 mL) and stirred for 1 h at room temperature. <lb/>Subsequently, the reaction mixture was heated to 100 °C 12 h until <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Journal of Medicinal Chemistry <lb/>pubs.acs.org/jmc <lb/>Article <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jmedchem.1c01598 <lb/>J. Med. Chem. 2022, 65, 2059-2077 <lb/></note>

			<page>2073 <lb/></page>

			<body>precipitation formed. After cooled down to room temperature, the <lb/>reaction mixture was filtered and the precipitate was washed with n-<lb/>hexane. The final product was purified with column chromatography <lb/>with DCM:MeOH 10:1 (v/v). The product was obtained as a 195 mg <lb/>white solid. Yield 60%. 1 H NMR (500 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) δ 12.81 (s, <lb/>1H), 7.55 (m, 4H), 4.57 (s, 2H), 2.53 (s, 3H). 13 C NMR (126 MHz, <lb/>DMSO-d 6 ) δ 162.8, 158.8, 153.1, 133.1, 132.4, 131.5, 131.1, 130.9, <lb/>130.0, 129.1, 128.9, 123.0, 42.5, 14.3. HRMS, calculated for <lb/>C 14 H 11 ON 2 Cl 2 S [M + H] + : 324.9964, found 324.9964. <lb/>2-Benzyl-6-(4-chlorophenyl)-5-methylthieno[2,3-d]pyrimidin-<lb/>4(1H)-one (8b). 6b (0.30 g, 1.0 mmol) was reacted with 2-<lb/>phenylacetonitrile (0.20 g, 1.6 mmol) following similar procedure of <lb/>synthesis of 8a to afford 8b (201 mg, 55%) as a white solid. 1 H NMR <lb/>(500 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) δ 12.6 (s, 1H), 7.6-7.5 (m, 4H), 7.4-7.3 (m, <lb/>4H), 7.3-7.2 (m, 1H), 4.0 (s, 2H), 2.5 (s, 3H) ppm. 13 C NMR (126 <lb/>MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) δ 163.8, 159.1, 157.1, 136.3, 132.9, 131.7, 131.0, <lb/>130.9, 130.8, 130.7, 129.7, 129.1, 128.9, 128.6, 126.9, 121.9 56.9, 26.6 <lb/>ppm. HRMS, calculated for C 20 H 16 ON 2 ClS [M + H] + : 367.0666, <lb/>found 367.0665. <lb/>2-Benzyl-6-(4-fluorophenyl)-5-methylthieno[2,3-d]pyrimidin-<lb/>4(1H)-one (8c). 6g (0.30 g, 1.1 mmol) was reacted with 2-(3-<lb/>methoxyphenyl)acetonitrile (0.21 g, 1.4 mmol) following similar <lb/>procedure of synthesis of 8a to afford 8c (127 mg, 32%) as a white <lb/>solid. 1 H NMR (500 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) δ 12.65 (s, 1H), 7.53 (dd, J = <lb/>8.7, 5.4 Hz, 2H), 7.37-7.29 (m, 6H), 7.25 (t, J = 6.7 Hz, 1H), 3.95 (s, <lb/>2H), 2.49 (s, 3H). 13 C NMR (126 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) δ 164.1, 162.3 <lb/>(d, J = 246.0), 159.7, 157.4, 136.8, 131.9, 131.5, 129.7, 129.6, 129.4, <lb/>129.0, 127.4, 122.3, 116.4 (d, J = 21.4), 40.6, 14.7. HRMS, calculated <lb/>for C 20 H 16 ON 2 FS [M + H] + : 351.0962, found 351.0961. <lb/>6-(4-Chlorophenyl)-2-(3-methoxybenzyl)-5-methylthieno[2,3-d]-<lb/>pyrimidin-4(1H)-one (8d). 6g (0.32 g, 1 mmol) was reacted with 2-<lb/>phenylacetonitrile (0.21 g, 1.6 mmol) following similar procedure of <lb/>synthesis of 8a to afford 8d (203 mg, 53%) as a white solid. 1 H NMR <lb/>(500 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) δ 12.6 (s, 1H), 7.6-7.4 (m, 4H), 7.2 (t, J = <lb/>7.8 Hz, 1H), 7.0-6.9 (m, 1H), 6.9 (d, J = 7.8 Hz, 1H), 6.8 (ddd, J = <lb/>8.4, 2.7, 1.0 Hz, 1H), 3.9 (s, 2H), 3.7 (s, 3H), 2.5 (s, 3H) ppm. 13 C <lb/>NMR (126 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) δ 163.8, 159.3, 159.1, 156.9, 137.7, <lb/>132.8, 131.7, 131.0, 130.8, 130.7, 129.7, 129.6, 129.0, 128.8, 121.9, <lb/>121.0, 114.8, 112.2, 55.1, 54.9, 14.2. HRMS, calculated for <lb/>C 21 H 18 O 2 N 2 ClS [M + H] + : 397.0772, found 397.0770. <lb/>Synthesis of 10a was performed by following a reported method 50 <lb/>(ethyl 2-amino-4-phenylthiophene-3-carboxylate, 10a). An equimolar <lb/>mixture of powdered sulfur (160 mg, 5.0 mmol) and morpholine <lb/>(0.50 mL) was stirred until total dissolution of the sulfur. Then, ethyl <lb/>cyanoacetate (0.60 mL, 5.0 mmol) and acetophenone (0.60 mL, 5 <lb/>mmol) were added to the reaction mixture, which was stirred at room <lb/>temperature for 18 h. After completion of the reaction, as monitored <lb/>by TLC, the crude product was chromatographed on silica with <lb/>CH 2 Cl 2 to afford a white solid, yield 34%. <lb/>Ethyl 2-Amino-4-(4-chlorophenyl)thiophene-3-carboxylate <lb/>(10b). 10b was synthesized by following the same method as the <lb/>preparation of 6a using 1-(4-chlorophenyl)ethan-1-one (5 mmol) as a <lb/>starting material. A white powder (250 mg) was obtained as the <lb/>product with a yield of 18%. <lb/>3-Benzyl-5-phenylthieno[2,3-d]pyrimidine-2,4(1H,3H)-dione <lb/>(11a). 11a was prepared similarly to 7a with a yield of 67%. 1 H NMR <lb/>(500 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) δ 12.43 (s, 1H), 7.44 (d, J = 6.4 Hz, 2H), 7.35 <lb/>(q, J = 8.2, 7.3 Hz, 3H), 7.27 (d, J = 6.5 Hz, 4H), 7.21 (t, J = 6.4 Hz, <lb/>1H), 7.04 (s, 1H), 5.00 (s, 2H). 13 C NMR (126 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) δ <lb/>158.14, 152.69, 150.33, 138.92, 137.51, 134.95, 129.28, 128.32, <lb/>127.55, 127.47, 127.40, 127.01, 114.74, 111.16, 43.06. HRMS, <lb/>calculated for C 19 H 15 O 2 N 2 S [M + H] + : 335.0849, found 335.0848. <lb/>3-Benzyl-5-(4-chlorophenyl)thieno[2,3-d]pyrimidine-2,4(1H,3H)-<lb/>dione (11b). 11b was prepared similarly to 7a with a yield of 56%. 1 H <lb/>NMR (500 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) δ 12.42 (s, 1H), 7.46 (d, J = 8.4 Hz, <lb/>2H), 7.42 (d, J = 8.6 Hz, 2H), 7.31-7.19 (m, 5H), 7.08 (s, 1H), 5.00 <lb/>(s, 2H). 13 C NMR (126 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) δ 158.13, 152.72, 150.22, <lb/>137.43, 137.39, 133.68, 132.26, 130.94, 128.24, 127.45, 127.35, <lb/>126.94, 121.99, 115.13, 43.03. HRMS, calculated for C 19 H 14 O 2 N 2 ClS <lb/>[M + H] + : 369.0459, found 369.0459. <lb/>Preparation of Recombinant Human MIF2. The detailed <lb/>procedures to produce recombinant human MIF2 were reported in <lb/>our previous publications. 46 Gene sequences of the human MIF2 gene <lb/>(Invitrogen) were adapted to bacterial expression. After subcloning <lb/>into a pET20b(+) expression vector, IPTG-induced expression was <lb/>performed in E.coli strain BL21(DE3). MIF2 protein was over-<lb/>produced overnight, and harvested cells were resuspended and <lb/>sonicated. The soluble fraction was purified using a Q sepharose <lb/>column (GE Healthcare) with a gradient of NaCl. The fractions <lb/>containing MIF2 were brought to 1.7 M ammonium sulfate and <lb/>loaded on a phenyl sepharose column (GE Healthcare) and eluted <lb/>with a gradient to 0 M ammonium sulfate in a 20 mM sodium <lb/>phosphate buffer, pH 8.0. Finally, the proteins were purified by size <lb/>exclusion chromatography on a Superdex75 column (GE Healthcare) <lb/>in 20 mM sodium phosphate buffer, pH 8.0, with an elution volume <lb/>characteristic for trimeric MIF2. The collected protein was <lb/>concentrated using a VivaSpin centrifugation column with a <lb/>molecular-weight cutoff at 5000 Da (Sartorius Stedim Biotech <lb/>GmbH). Purified proteins were aliquoted, snap-frozen in liquid <lb/>nitrogen, and stored at -80 °C. The purity of the obtained protein <lb/>was tested by sodium dodecyl sulfate polyacrylamide gel electro-<lb/>phoresis (SDS-PAGE) and coomassie staining. <lb/>Tautomerase Assay. The MIF tautomerase activity and enzyme <lb/>kinetics were measured by a previously described protocol. 35 The <lb/>methods to study MIF2 enzyme activity were adapted from protocols <lb/>to study MIF. Briefly, 10 μL of EDTA (20 mM) solution in <lb/>demiwater was added into 180 μL of MIF2 solution (100 nM) in <lb/>boric acid buffer (435 mM, pH 6.2), followed by the addition of 10 <lb/>μL of the desired compound in DMSO or vehicle. This mixture was <lb/>homogenized and preincubated at room temperature for 10 min. <lb/>Subsequently, 50 μL of this enzyme-inhibitor mixture was mixed <lb/>with 50 μL of phenylpyruvate solution (1 mM) in ammonium acetate <lb/>buffer (50 mM, pH 6.0). The increase of UV absorbance at 300 nm <lb/>over time represents MIF2 tautomerase activity. MIF2 tautomerase <lb/>activity in the group containing blank DMSO dilution was set to <lb/>100%. Noncatalyzed conversion of the PP without the MIF presence <lb/>was set to 0%. Data from the first 3 min were linear and used to <lb/>calculate the conversion velocities. GraphPad Prism was employed for <lb/>the calculation. <lb/>Cell Culture. Four different human lung cancer cell lines including <lb/>A549 (ATCC-CCL-185), H1650 (ATCC-CRL-5883), H1299 <lb/>(ATCC-CRL-5803), and HCC827 (ATCC-CRL-2868) were cul-<lb/>tured in RPMI-1640 Medium (GibcoTM #61870-010) containing <lb/>10% (v/v) fetal bovine serum (FBS) and 100 U/mL penicillin/ <lb/>streptomycin (GibcoTM#10378016) at 37 °C with 5% CO 2 in <lb/>humidified air. <lb/>Cell Proliferation Assay. Cell proliferation was measured with <lb/>the CyQUANT Direct Cell Proliferation Assay Kit (Thermo Fisher, <lb/>#C35011) by following the protocol. Cells were cultured in 96-well <lb/>plates at a density of 1000 cells/well and treated with different <lb/>concentrations of 5d (0.25-10 μM) for 72 h. The cells were <lb/>incubated with a detection reagent (100 μL) for 60 min at 37 °C with <lb/>5% CO 2 . The fluorescence of each well was read at 485/535 nm by a <lb/>plate reader (BioTek). <lb/>Clonogenic Assay. Cells were seeded in 12-well plates (1000 cells <lb/>per well in 2 mL of the same medium used for cell proliferation assay) <lb/>and incubated overnight. Corresponding inhibitors were added to the <lb/>cell culture medium, and the cells were exposed to the treatment for 5 <lb/>days. Subsequently, the medium was carefully removed and the cells <lb/>were washed with PBS before they were fixed with 4% (v/v) <lb/>paraformaldehyde for 20 min at room temperature. After removal of <lb/>the fixation reagent, the cells were stained with 0.5% (w/v) crystal <lb/>violet in the dark for 20 min. After washing, the image of stained <lb/>cancer cell colonies in each well was photographed. To quantify the <lb/>staining, 10% acetic acid was utilized to dissolve the colonies. The <lb/>absorbance at a wavelength of 590 nm was measured to represent the <lb/>relative cell number by comparing with the DMSO-treated group. <lb/>Tumor Spheroid Assay. A549 cells (1000 cells/well) were <lb/>seeded onto a 96-well U bottom ultralow attachment plate (Corning). <lb/>After 2 days of incubation without disturbance, the spheroid was <lb/></body>
			
			<note place="headnote">Journal of Medicinal Chemistry <lb/>pubs.acs.org/jmc <lb/>Article <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jmedchem.1c01598 <lb/>J. Med. Chem. 2022, 65, 2059-2077 <lb/></note>

			<page>2074 <lb/></page>

			<body>treated with indicated compound every 3 days. Images were captured, <lb/>and the diameter of each tumor spheroid was measured on the <lb/>indicated days post-treatment using an inverted microscope (Nikon <lb/>Eclipse Ti) connected with NIS-Elements software. The data were <lb/>analyzed and plotted with GraphPad Prism8. <lb/>ERK Phosphorylation Study. 15 A549 cells were seeded into each <lb/>well of a six-well plate in a density of 3 × 10 5 cells per well with 2 mL <lb/>of RPMI-1640 medium containing 0.5% (v/v) FBS (Costar Europe, <lb/>Badhoevedorp, The Netherlands), and 1% (v/v) penicillin/ <lb/>streptomycin solution (Corning). After overnight culturing, the cells <lb/>were stimulated with MIF2 (100 ng/mL in FBS-free medium) or a <lb/>mixture of MIF2 and different concentrations of 5d for 15 min. <lb/>Subsequently, the cells were washed with cold PBS and lysed using <lb/>RIPA buffer containing PhosSTOP and protease inhibitor (PI) <lb/>cocktail (Roche, Mannheim, Germany). After determination of the <lb/>protein concentration of each sample using the BCA Protein Assay <lb/>Kit (Pierce, Rockford IL), 20 μg protein was loaded onto and <lb/>separated by a precast 10% NuPAGE Bis-Tris gel (Invitrogen). The <lb/>proteins in the gel were then transferred to a poly(vinylidene <lb/>difluoride) (PVDF) membrane. After blocking with 5% (w/v) of <lb/>skimmed milk for 1 h at room temperature and incubation with the <lb/>appropriate primary antibody (pERK, #9101, Cell Signaling, 1:1000; <lb/>ERK, #9102, Cell Signaling, 1:1000; GAPDH, #97166, Cell Signaling, <lb/>1:10 000) overnight at 4 °C, the membrane was treated with HRP-<lb/>conjugated secondary antibodies and the protein bands were <lb/>visualized with enhanced chemiluminescence (ECL) solution (GE <lb/>Healthcare)and quantified with ImageJ software based on grayscale. <lb/>Flow Cytometry. For cell cycle analysis, A549 cells were seeded <lb/>in six-well plates at a density of 1 × 10 5 per well. The next day, the <lb/>cells were treated with 5d or vehicle for 48 h. After the treatment, the <lb/>cells were washed with PBS (3×) and then harvested after <lb/>trypsinization. After centrifugation at 300g, the cells were incubated <lb/>with a solution containing 20 μg/mL propidium iodide (PI) (Sigma, <lb/>P4864) and 0.1% (v/v) Triton-X100 (Sigma, T8787) for 15 min at <lb/>room temperature. Fluorescence was detected by a Cytoflex flow <lb/>cytometer (Beckman Coulter, Woerden, the Netherlands) immedi-<lb/>ately. A total of 30 000 cells were collected for each sample. Data were <lb/>analyzed using FlowJo software (Tree Start, Ashland). <lb/></body>
			
			<div type="annex">■ ASSOCIATED CONTENT <lb/>* sı Supporting Information <lb/>The Supporting Information is available free of charge at <lb/>https://pubs.acs.org/doi/10.1021/acs.jmedchem.1c01598. <lb/>Additional figures and schemes; HPLC assessment of <lb/>purity and solubility for target compounds; tautomerase <lb/>activity inhibition IC 50 curves; molecular modeling <lb/>details; and analytical data ( 1 H NMR, 13 C NMR, <lb/>HRMS) (PDF) <lb/>Molecular formula strings (CSV) <lb/>■ AUTHOR INFORMATION <lb/>Corresponding Author <lb/>Frank J. Dekker -Chemical and Pharmaceutical Biology, <lb/>Groningen Research Institute of Pharmacy (GRIP), <lb/>University of Groningen, 9713 AV Groningen, The <lb/>Netherlands; orcid.org/0000-0001-7217-9300; <lb/>Phone: +31-5-3638030; Email: f.j.dekker@rug.nl; <lb/>Fax: +31-5-3637953 <lb/>Authors <lb/>Zhangping Xiao -Chemical and Pharmaceutical Biology, <lb/>Groningen Research Institute of Pharmacy (GRIP), <lb/>University of Groningen, 9713 AV Groningen, The <lb/>Netherlands; orcid.org/0000-0003-0557-9843 <lb/>Angelina Osipyan -Chemical and Pharmaceutical Biology, <lb/>Groningen Research Institute of Pharmacy (GRIP), <lb/>University of Groningen, 9713 AV Groningen, The <lb/>Netherlands <lb/>Shanshan Song -Chemical and Pharmaceutical Biology, <lb/>Groningen Research Institute of Pharmacy (GRIP), <lb/>University of Groningen, 9713 AV Groningen, The <lb/>Netherlands; Molecular Pharmacology, Groningen Research <lb/>Institute of Pharmacy (GRIP), University of Groningen, 9713 <lb/>AV Groningen, The Netherlands <lb/>Deng Chen -Chemical and Pharmaceutical Biology, <lb/>Groningen Research Institute of Pharmacy (GRIP), <lb/>University of Groningen, 9713 AV Groningen, The <lb/>Netherlands <lb/>Reinder A. Schut -Chemical and Pharmaceutical Biology, <lb/>Groningen Research Institute of Pharmacy (GRIP), <lb/>University of Groningen, 9713 AV Groningen, The <lb/>Netherlands <lb/>Ronald van Merkerk -Chemical and Pharmaceutical Biology, <lb/>Groningen Research Institute of Pharmacy (GRIP), <lb/>University of Groningen, 9713 AV Groningen, The <lb/>Netherlands <lb/>Petra E. van der Wouden -Chemical and Pharmaceutical <lb/>Biology, Groningen Research Institute of Pharmacy (GRIP), <lb/>University of Groningen, 9713 AV Groningen, The <lb/>Netherlands <lb/>Robbert H. Cool -Chemical and Pharmaceutical Biology, <lb/>Groningen Research Institute of Pharmacy (GRIP), <lb/>University of Groningen, 9713 AV Groningen, The <lb/>Netherlands <lb/>Wim J. Quax -Chemical and Pharmaceutical Biology, <lb/>Groningen Research Institute of Pharmacy (GRIP), <lb/>University of Groningen, 9713 AV Groningen, The <lb/>Netherlands; orcid.org/0000-0002-5162-9947 <lb/>Barbro N. Melgert -Molecular Pharmacology, Groningen <lb/>Research Institute of Pharmacy (GRIP), University of <lb/>Groningen, 9713 AV Groningen, The Netherlands; University <lb/>Medical Center Groningen, Groningen Research Institute of <lb/>Asthma and COPD, University of Groningen, 9713 GZ <lb/>Groningen, The Netherlands <lb/>Gerrit J. Poelarends -Chemical and Pharmaceutical Biology, <lb/>Groningen Research Institute of Pharmacy (GRIP), <lb/>University of Groningen, 9713 AV Groningen, The <lb/>Netherlands; orcid.org/0000-0002-6917-6368 <lb/>Complete contact information is available at: <lb/>https://pubs.acs.org/10.1021/acs.jmedchem.1c01598 <lb/>Author Contributions <lb/>All authors have given approval to the final version of the <lb/>manuscript. <lb/>Funding <lb/>Z.X. and D.C. are funded by China Scholarship Council (grant <lb/>nos.: 201706010341 for Z.X., 201907720019 for D.C.). A.O. <lb/>was supported by funding from Marie Skłodowska-Curie <lb/>Action (CoFund project 754425). S.S. was funded by Royalties <lb/>Prof. Dr. H.W. Frijlink Scholarship from University of <lb/>Groningen. <lb/>Notes <lb/>The authors declare no competing financial interest. <lb/></div>
			
			<div type="acknowledgment">■ ACKNOWLEDGMENTS <lb/>The authors acknowledge Prof. Matthew R. Groves and Chao <lb/>Wang from the Drug Design group, Groningen Research <lb/></div>

			<note place="headnote">Journal of Medicinal Chemistry <lb/>pubs.acs.org/jmc <lb/>Article <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jmedchem.1c01598 <lb/>J. Med. Chem. 2022, 65, 2059-2077 <lb/></note>

			<page>2075 <lb/></page>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Institute of Pharmacy, University of Groningen, for advices and <lb/>help on the thermal shift assay. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">■ ABBREVIATIONS USED <lb/>4-CPP, 4-chlorophenylpyruvate; 4-HPP, 4-hydroxylphenylpyr-<lb/>uvate; 4-MPP, 4-methoxylphenylpyruvate; CD74, cluster of <lb/>differentiation 74; CXCR4, chemokine receptor 4; D-DT, D-<lb/>dopachrome tautomerase; DMF, N,N-dimethylformamide; <lb/>DMSO, dimethyl sulfoxide; EDCI, 1-ethyl-3-(3-dimethylami-<lb/>nopropyl) carbodiimide hydrochloride; EDTA, ethylenedi-<lb/>amine tetraacetic acid; ELISA, enzyme-linked immunosorbent <lb/>assay; FID, fluorescent indicator displacement; HOBt, <lb/>hydroxybenzotriazole; HTS, high-throughput screening; <lb/>JAB1, c-Jun activation domain-binding protein-1; MAPK, <lb/>mitogen-activated protein kinase; MIF, macrophage migration <lb/>inhibitory factor; PP, phenylpyruvate; SAR, structure-activity <lb/>relationship <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>■ REFERENCES <lb/>(1) Bray, F.; Ferlay, J.; Soerjomataram, I.; Siegel, R. L.; Torre, L. A.; <lb/>Jemal, A. Global cancer statistics 2018: GLOBOCAN estimates of <lb/>incidence and mortality worldwide for 36 cancers in 185 countries. <lb/>Ca-Cancer J. Clin. 2018, 68, 394-424. <lb/>(2) Dagogo-Jack, I.; Shaw, A. T. Tumour heterogeneity and <lb/>resistance to cancer therapies. Nat. Rev. Clin. Oncol. 2018, 15, 81-94. <lb/>(3) Hahn, W. C.; Bader, J. S.; Braun, T. P.; Califano, A.; Clemons, P. <lb/>A.; Druker, B. J.; Ewald, A. J.; Fu, H.; Jagu, S.; Kemp, C. J.; Kim, W.; <lb/>Kuo, C. J.; Mcmanus, M.; Mills, G. B.; Mo, X.; Sahni, N.; Schreiber, S. <lb/>L.; Talamas, J. A.; Tamayo, P.; Tyner, J. W.; Wagner, B. K.; Weiss, W. <lb/>A.; Gerhard, D. S.; et al. An expanded universe of cancer targets. Cell <lb/>2021, 184, 1142-1155. <lb/>(4) Penticuff, J. C.; Woolbright, B. L.; Sielecki, T. M.; Weir, S. J.; <lb/>Taylor, J. A. MIF family proteins in genitourinary cancer: tumorigenic <lb/>roles and therapeutic potential. Nat. Rev. Urol. 2019, 16, 318-328. <lb/>(5) Soumoy, L.; Kindt, N.; Ghanem, G.; Saussez, S.; Journe, F. Role <lb/>of macrophage migration inhibitory factor (Mif) in melanoma. <lb/>Cancers 2019, 11, 529. <lb/>(6) Cavalli, E.; Ciurleo, R.; Petralia, M. C.; Fagone, P.; Bella, R.; <lb/>Mangano, K.; Nicoletti, F.; Bramanti, P.; Basile, M. S. Emerging role <lb/>of the macrophage migration inhibitory factor family of cytokines in <lb/>neuroblastoma. Pathogenic effectors and novel therapeutic targets? <lb/>Molecules 2020, 25, 1194. <lb/>(7) Coleman, A. M.; Rendon, B. E.; Zhao, M.; Qian, M.-W.; Bucala, <lb/>R.; Xin, D.; Mitchell, R. A. Cooperative regulation of non-small cell <lb/>lung carcinoma angiogenic potential by macrophage migration <lb/>inhibitory factor and its homolog, D-dopachrome tautomerase. J. <lb/>Immunol. 2008, 181, 2330-2337. <lb/>(8) Charan, M.; Das, S.; Mishra, S.; Chatterjee, N.; Varikuti, S.; Kaul, <lb/>K.; Misri, S.; Ahirwar, D. K.; Satoskar, A. R.; Ganju, R. K. Macrophage <lb/>migration inhibitory factor inhibition as a novel therapeutic approach <lb/>against triple-negative breast cancer. Cell Death Dis. 2020, 11, 774. <lb/>(9) Zhang, M.; Yan, L.; Kim, J. A. Modulating mammary tumor <lb/>growth, metastasis and immunosuppression by siRNA-induced MIF <lb/>reduction in tumor microenvironment. Cancer Gene Ther. 2015, 22, <lb/>463-474. <lb/>(10) Oliveira, C. S.; de Bock, C. E.; Molloy, T. J.; Sadeqzadeh, E.; <lb/>Geng, X. Y.; Hersey, P.; Zhang, X. D.; Thorne, R. F. Macrophage <lb/>migration inhibitory factor engages PI3K/Akt signalling and is a <lb/>prognostic factor in metastatic melanoma. BMC Cancer 2014, 14, 630. <lb/>(11) Leng, L.; Metz, C. N.; Fang, Y.; Xu, J.; Donnelly, S.; Baugh, J.; <lb/>Delohery, T.; Chen, Y.; Mitchell, R. A.; Bucala, R. MIF signal <lb/>transduction initiated by binding to CD74. J. Exp. Med. 2003, 197, <lb/>1467-1476. <lb/>(12) Shi, X.; Leng, L.; Wang, T.; Wang, W.; Du, X.; Li, J.; <lb/>McDonald, C.; Chen, Z.; Murphy, J. W.; Lolis, E.; Noble, P.; <lb/>Knudson, W.; Bucala, R. CD44 is the signaling component of the <lb/>macrophage migration inhibitory factor-CD74 receptor complex. <lb/>Immunity 2006, 25, 595-606. <lb/>(13) Jäger, B.; Klatt, D.; Plappert, L.; Golpon, H.; Lienenklaus, S.; <lb/>Barbosa, P. D.; Schambach, A.; Prasse, A. CXCR4/MIF axis amplifies <lb/>tumor growth and epithelial-mesenchymal interaction in non-small <lb/>cell lung cancer. Cell. Signalling 2020, 73, No. 109672. <lb/>(14) Mahalingam, D.; Patel, M.; Sachdev, J.; Hart, L.; Halama, N.; <lb/>Ramanathan, R.; Sarantopoulos, J.; Liu, X.; Yazji, S.; Jäger, D.; Adib, <lb/>D.; Kerschbaumer, R.; Yoon, M.; Manzur, G.; Starodub, A.; Sivarajan, <lb/>K.; Wertheim, M.; Thambi, P.; Jones, M.; Goel, S.; Nemunaitis, J.; <lb/>Tsimberidou, A. Safety and efficacy analysis of imalumab, an anti-<lb/>oxidized macrophage migration inhibitory factor (oxMIF) antibody, <lb/>alone or in combination with 5-fluorouracil/leucovorin (5-FU/LV) or <lb/>panitumumab, in patients with metastatic colorectal cancer (mCRC). <lb/>Ann. Oncol. 2016, 27, ii105. <lb/>(15) Xiao, Z.; Chen, D.; Song, S.; Van Der Vlag, R.; Van Der <lb/>Wouden, P. E.; Van Merkerk, R.; Cool, R. H.; Hirsch, A. K. H.; <lb/>Melgert, B. N.; Quax, W. J.; Poelarends, G. J.; Dekker, F. J. 7-<lb/>Hydroxycoumarins are affinity-based fluorescent probes for com-<lb/>petitive binding studies of macrophage migration inhibitory factor. J. <lb/>Med. Chem. 2020, 63, 11920-11933. <lb/>(16) Illescas, O.; Pacheco-Fernández, T.; Laclette, J. P.; Rodriguez, <lb/>T.; Rodriguez-Sosa, M. Immune modulation by the macrophage <lb/>migration inhibitory factor (MIF) family: D-dopachrome tautomerase <lb/>(DDT) is not (always) a backup system. Cytokine 2020, 133, 155121. <lb/>(17) Merk, M.; Zierow, S.; Leng, L.; Das, R.; Du, X.; Schulte, W.; <lb/>Fan, J.; Lue, H.; Chen, Y.; Xiong, H.; Chagnon, F.; Bernhagen, J.; <lb/>Lolis, E.; Mor, G.; Lesur, O.; Bucala, R. The D-dopachrome <lb/>tautomerase (DDT) gene product is a cytokine and functional <lb/>homolog of macrophage migration inhibitory factor (MIF). Proc. Natl. <lb/>Acad. Sci. U.S.A. 2011, 108, E577-E585. <lb/>(18) Sugimoto, H.; Taniguchi, M.; Nakagawa, A. I.; et al. Crystal <lb/>structure of human D-dopachrome tautomerase, a homologue of <lb/>macrophage migration inhibitory factor, at 1.54 Å resolution. <lb/>Biochemistry 1999, 38, 3268-3279. <lb/>(19) Rajasekaran, D.; Zierow, S.; Syed, M.; Bucala, R.; Bhandari, V.; <lb/>Lolis, E. J. Targeting distinct tautomerase sites of D-DT and MIF with <lb/>a single molecule for inhibition of neutrophil lung recruitment. FASEB <lb/>J. 2014, 28, 4961-4971. <lb/>(20) Bernhagen, J.; Krohn, R.; Lue, H.; Gregory, J. L.; Zernecke, A.; <lb/>Koenen, R. R.; Dewor, M.; Georgiev, I.; Schober, A.; Leng, L.; <lb/>Kooistra, T.; Fingerle-Rowson, G.; Ghezzi, P.; Kleemann, R.; McColl, <lb/>S. R.; Bucala, R.; Hickey, M. J.; Weber, C. MIF is a noncognate ligand <lb/>of CXC chemokine receptors in inflammatory and atherogenic cell <lb/>recruitment. Nat. Med. 2007, 13, 587-596. <lb/>(21) Weber, C.; Kraemer, S.; Drechsler, M.; Lue, H.; Koenen, R. R.; <lb/>Kapurniotu, A.; Zernecke, A.; Bernhagen, J. Structural determinants of <lb/>MIF functions in CXCR2-mediated inflammatory and atherogenic <lb/>leukocyte recruitment. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A. 2008, 105, 16278-<lb/>16283. <lb/>(22) Pantouris, G.; Syed, M. A.; Fan, C.; Rajasekaran, D.; Cho, T. Y.; <lb/>Rosenberg, E. M.; Bucala, R.; Bhandari, V.; Lolis, E. J. An analysis of <lb/>MIF structural features that control functional activation of CD74. <lb/>Chem. Biol. 2015, 22, 1197-1205. <lb/>(23) Pantouris, G.; Khurana, L.; Ma, A.; Skeens, E.; Reiss, K.; <lb/>Batista, V. S.; Lisi, G. P.; Lolis, E. J. Regulation of MIF enzymatic <lb/>activity by an allosteric site at the central solvent channel. Cell Chem. <lb/>Biol. 2020, 27, 740-750. <lb/>(24) Bloom, J.; Sun, S.; Al-Abed, Y. MIF, a controversial cytokine: a <lb/>review of structural features, challenges, and opportunities for drug <lb/>development. Expert Opin. Ther. Targets 2016, 20, 1463-1475. <lb/>(25) Al-Abed, Y.; VanPatten, S. MIF as a disease target: ISO-1 as a <lb/>proof-of-concept therapeutic. Future Med. Chem. 2011, 3, 45-63. <lb/>(26) Meyer-Siegler, K. L.; Iczkowski, K. A.; Leng, L.; Bucala, R.; <lb/>Vera, P. L. Inhibition of macrophage migration inhibitory factor or its <lb/>receptor (CD74) attenuates growth and invasion of DU-145 prostate <lb/>cancer cells. J. Immunol. 2006, 177, 8730-8739. <lb/>(27) Dziedzic, P.; Cisneros, J. A.; Robertson, M. J.; Hare, A. A.; <lb/>Danford, N. E.; Baxter, R. H. G.; Jorgensen, W. L. Design, synthesis, <lb/>Journal of Medicinal Chemistry <lb/>pubs.acs.org/jmc <lb/>Article <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jmedchem.1c01598 <lb/>J. Med. Chem. 2022, 65, 2059-2077 <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>2076 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>and protein crystallography of biaryltriazoles as potent tautomerase <lb/>inhibitors of macrophage migration inhibitory factor. J. Am. Chem. <lb/>Soc. 2015, 137, 2996-3003. <lb/>(28) Trivedi-Parmar, V.; Robertson, M. J.; Cisneros, J. A.; Krimmer, <lb/>S. G.; Jorgensen, W. L. Optimization of pyrazoles as phenol surrogates <lb/>to yield potent inhibitors of macrophage migration inhibitory factor. <lb/>ChemMedChem 2018, 13, 1092-1097. <lb/>(29) Xiao, Z.; Song, S.; Chen, D.; Merkerk, R.; Wouden, P. E.; Cool, <lb/>R. H.; Quax, W. J.; Poelarends, G. J.; Melgert, B. N.; Dekker, F. J. <lb/>Proteolysis targeting chimera (PROTAC) for macrophage migration <lb/>inhibitory factor (MIF) has anti-proliferative activity in lung cancer <lb/>cells. Angew. Chem., Int. Ed. 2021, 60, 17514-17521. <lb/>(30) Tilstam, P. V.; Pantouris, G.; Corman, M.; Andreoli, M.; <lb/>Mahboubi, K.; Davis, G.; Du, X.; Leng, L.; Lolis, E.; Bucala, R. A <lb/>selective small-molecule inhibitor of macrophage migration inhibitory <lb/>factor-2 (MIF-2), a MIF cytokine superfamily member, inhibits MIF-<lb/>2 biological activity. J. Biol. Chem. 2019, 294, 18522-18531. <lb/>(31) Cho, Y.; Crichlow, G. V.; Vermeire, J. J.; Leng, L.; Du, X.; <lb/>Hodsdon, M. E.; Bucala, R.; Cappello, M.; Gross, M.; Gaeta, F.; <lb/>Johnson, K.; Lolis, E. J. Allosteric inhibition of macrophage migration <lb/>inhibitory factor revealed by ibudilast. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A. <lb/>2010, 107, 11313-11318. <lb/>(32) Pantouris, G.; Bucala, R.; Lolis, E. J. Structural plasticity in the <lb/>C-terminal region of macrophage migration inhibitory factor-2 is <lb/>associated with an induced fit mechanism for a selective inhibitor. <lb/>Biochemistry 2018, 57, 3599-3605. <lb/>(33) Ouertatani-Sakouhi, H.; Liu, M.; El-Turk, F.; Cuny, G. D.; <lb/>Glicksman, M. A.; Lashuel, H. Kinetic-based high-throughput <lb/>screening assay to discover novel classes of macrophage migration <lb/>inhibitory factor inhibitors. J. Biomol. Screening 2010, 15, 347-358. <lb/>(34) Rosengren, E.; Åman, P.; Thelin, S.; Hansson, C.; Ahlfors, S.; <lb/>Björk, P.; Jacobsson, L.; Rorsman, H. The macrophage migration <lb/>inhibitory factor MIF is a phenylpyruvate tautomerase. FEBS Lett. <lb/>1997, 417, 85-88. <lb/>(35) Xiao, Z.; Fokkens, M.; Chen, D.; Kok, T.; Proietti, G.; van <lb/>Merkerk, R.; Poelarends, G. J.; Dekker, F. J. Structure-activity <lb/>relationships for binding of 4-substituted triazole-phenols to macro-<lb/>phage migration inhibitory factor (MIF). Eur. J. Med. Chem. 2020, <lb/>186, 111849-111862. <lb/>(36) Zhang, J.-H.; Chung, T. D. Y.; Oldenburg, K. R. A simple <lb/>statistical parameter for use in evaluation and validation of high <lb/>throughput screening assays. J. Biomol. Screening 1999, 4, 67-73. <lb/>(37) Lubetsky, J. B.; Swope, M.; Dealwis, C.; Blake, P.; Lolis, E. Pro-<lb/>1 of macrophage migration inhibitory factor functions as a catalytic <lb/>base in the phenylpyruvate tautomerase activity. Biochemistry 1999, <lb/>38, 7346-7354. <lb/>(38) Ishikawa, M.; Hashimoto, Y. Improvement in aqueous <lb/>solubility in small molecule drug discovery programs by disruption <lb/>of molecular planarity and symmetry. J. Med. Chem. 2011, 54, 1539-<lb/>1554. <lb/>(39) Feng, W.; Teo, X. Y.; Novera, W.; Ramanujulu, P. M.; Liang, <lb/>D.; Huang, D.; Moore, P. K.; Deng, L. W.; Dymock, B. W. Discovery <lb/>of new H2S releasing phosphordithioates and 2,3-dihydro-2-phenyl-2-<lb/>sulfanylenebenzo[d][1,3,2]oxazaphospholes with improved antiproli-<lb/>ferative activity. J. Med. Chem. 2015, 58, 6456-6480. <lb/>(40) Guo, D.; Guo, J.; Yao, J.; Jiang, K.; Hu, J.; Wang, B.; Liu, H.; <lb/>Lin, L.; Sun, W.; Jiang, X. D-dopachrome tautomerase is over-<lb/>expressed in pancreatic ductal adenocarcinoma and acts cooperatively <lb/>with macrophage migration inhibitory factor to promote cancer <lb/>growth. Int. J. Cancer 2016, 139, 2056-2067. <lb/>(41) Pasupuleti, V.; Du, W.; Gupta, Y.; Yeh, I. J.; Montano, M.; <lb/>Magi-Galuzzi, C.; Welford, S. M. Dysregulated D-dopachrome <lb/>tautomerase, a hypoxiainducible factor-dependent gene, cooperates <lb/>with macrophage migration inhibitory factor in renal tumorigenesis. J. <lb/>Biol. Chem. 2014, 289, 3713-3723. <lb/>(42) Trivedi-Parmar, V. C.; Jorgensen, W. L. Advances and insights <lb/>for small molecule inhibition of macrophage migration inhibitory <lb/>factor. J. Med. Chem. 2018, 61, 8104-8119. <lb/>(43) Vinci, M.; Gowan, S.; Boxall, F.; Patterson, L.; Zimmermann, <lb/>M.; Court, W.; Lomas, C.; Mendiola, M.; Hardisson, D.; Eccles, S. A. <lb/>Advances in establishment and analysis of three-dimensional tumor <lb/>spheroid-based functional assays for target validation and drug <lb/>evaluation. BMC Biol. 2012, 10, No. 29. <lb/>(44) Kobold, S.; Merk, M.; Hofer, L.; Peters, P.; Bucala, R.; Endres, <lb/>S. The macrophage migration inhibitory factor (MIF)-homologue D-<lb/>dopachrome tautomerase is a therapeutic target in a murine <lb/>melanoma model. Oncotarget 2014, 5, 103-107. <lb/>(45) Williams, G. H.; Stoeber, K. The cell cycle and cancer. J. Pathol. <lb/>2012, 226, 352-364. <lb/>(46) Song, S.; Liu, B.; Habibie, H.; van den Bor, J.; Smit, M. J.; <lb/>Gosens, R.; Wu, X.; Brandsma, C.-A.; Cool, R. H.; Haisma, H. J.; <lb/>Poelarends, G. J.; Melgert, B. N. D-dopachrome tautomerase <lb/>contributes to lung epithelial repair via atypical chemokine receptor <lb/>3-dependent Akt signaling. EBioMedicine 2021, 68, No. 103412. <lb/>(47) Zhang, S.; Li, G.; Liu, H.; Wang, Y.; Cao, Y.; Zhao, G.; Tang, Z. <lb/>Bio-inspired enantioselective full transamination using readily <lb/>available cyclodextrin. RSC Adv. 2017, 7, 4203-4208. <lb/>(48) Eleftheriadis, N.; Poelman, H.; Leus, N. G. J.; Honrath, B.; <lb/>Neochoritis, C. G.; Dolga, A.; Dömling, A.; Dekker, F. J. Design of a <lb/>novel thiophene inhibitor of 15-lipoxygenase-1 with both anti-<lb/>inflammatory and neuroprotective properties. Eur. J. Med. Chem. <lb/>2016, 122, 786-801. <lb/>(49) Sasaki, S.; Cho, N.; Nara, Y.; Harada, M.; Endo, S.; Suzuki, N.; <lb/>Furuya, S.; Fujino, M. Discovery of a thieno[2,3-d]pyrimidine-2,4-<lb/>dione bearing a p-methoxyureidophenyl moiety at the 6-position: A <lb/>highly potent and orally bioavailable non-peptide antagonist for the <lb/>human luteinizing hormone-releasing hormone receptor. J. Med. <lb/>Chem. 2003, 46, 113-124. <lb/>(50) Fyfe, T. J.; Zarzycka, B.; Lim, H. D.; Kellam, B.; Mistry, S. N.; <lb/>Katrich, V.; Scammells, P. J.; Lane, J. R.; Capuano, B. A thieno[2,3-<lb/>d]pyrimidine scaffold is a novel negative allosteric modulator of the <lb/>dopamine D2 receptor. J. Med. Chem. 2019, 62, 174-206. <lb/>Journal of Medicinal Chemistry <lb/>pubs.acs.org/jmc <lb/>Article <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jmedchem.1c01598 <lb/>J. Med. Chem. 2022, 65, 2059-2077 <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>2077 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">Recommended by ACS <lb/>Discovery of a Novel, Potent, Orally Active, and Safe <lb/>Inhibitor Targeting Human Mitochondrial RNA Polymerase <lb/>Xinnan Li, Hong Yao, et al. <lb/>MARCH 30, 2023 <lb/>JOURNAL OF MEDICINAL CHEMISTRY <lb/>READ <lb/>Exploration of Janus Kinase (JAK) and Histone Deacetylase <lb/>(HDAC) Bispecific Inhibitors Based on the Moiety of <lb/>Fedratinib for Treatment of Both Hematologic Malignanci... <lb/>Qianqian Qiu, Hai Qian, et al. <lb/>APRIL 14, 2023 <lb/>JOURNAL OF MEDICINAL CHEMISTRY <lb/>READ <lb/>Discovery of Macrocycle-Based HPK1 Inhibitors for T-Cell-<lb/>Based Immunotherapy <lb/>Ming-Shu Wang, Guang-Fu Yang, et al. <lb/>DECEMBER 21, 2022 <lb/>JOURNAL OF MEDICINAL CHEMISTRY <lb/>READ <lb/>Discovery of Potent and Highly Selective Interleukin-2-<lb/>Inducible T-Cell Kinase Degraders with In Vivo Activity <lb/>Danli Zhou, Zhengying Pan, et al. <lb/>MARCH 23, 2023 <lb/>JOURNAL OF MEDICINAL CHEMISTRY <lb/>READ <lb/>Get More Suggestions &gt; </div>


	</text>
</tei>