<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>R E S E A R C H A R T I C L E <lb/>Membrane-acting biomimetic peptoids against visceral <lb/>leishmaniasis <lb/>Vivek Kumar 1 , Jennifer S. Lin 2 , Natalia Molchanova 3 , John A. Fortkort 2 , Carolin Reckmann 4 , <lb/>Stefan Br€ ase 4 , H avard Jenssen 5 , Annelise E. Barron 2 and Archana Chugh 1 <lb/>1 Kusuma School of Biological Sciences, Indian Institute of Technology Delhi, India <lb/>2 Department of Bioengineering, Stanford University, Schools of Medicine and of Engineering, CA, USA <lb/>3 The Molecular Foundry, Lawrence Berkeley National Laboratory, CA, USA <lb/>4 Institute of Biological and Chemical Systems -Functional Molecular Systems (IBCS-FMS), Karlsruhe Institute of Technology (KIT), <lb/>Germany <lb/>5 Department of Science and Environment, Roskilde University, Denmark <lb/>Keywords <lb/>antimicrobial; antiparasitic; leishmania; <lb/>peptide mimetic; peptoid <lb/>Correspondence <lb/>Annelise E. Barron, Department of <lb/>Bioengineering, Stanford University, Schools <lb/>of Medicine and of Engineering, Stanford, <lb/>CA 94305, USA <lb/>E-mail: aebarron@stanford.edu Archana <lb/>Chugh, Kusuma School of Biological <lb/>Sciences, Indian Institute of Technology <lb/>Delhi, New Delhi 110016, India <lb/>E-mail: achugh@bioschool.iitd.ac.in <lb/>(Received 16 August 2022, revised 8 <lb/>December 2022, accepted 20 January 2023) <lb/>doi:10.1002/2211-5463.13562 <lb/></front>

			<body>Visceral leishmaniasis (VL) is among the most neglected tropical diseases <lb/>in the world. Drug cell permeability is essential for killing the intracellular <lb/>residing parasites responsible for VL, making cell-permeating peptides a <lb/>logical choice to address VL. Unfortunately, the limited biological stability <lb/>of peptides restricts their usage. Sequence-specific oligo-N-substituted gly-<lb/>cines (&apos;peptoids&apos;) are a class of peptide mimics that offers an excellent alter-<lb/>native to peptides in terms of ease of synthesis and good biostability. We <lb/>tested peptoids against the parasite Leishmania donovani in both forms, <lb/>that is, intracellular amastigotes and promastigotes. N-alkyl hydrophobic <lb/>chain addition (lipidation) and bromination of oligopeptoids yielded <lb/>compounds with good antileishmanial activity against both forms, showing <lb/>the promise of these antiparasitic peptoids as potential drug candidates to <lb/>treat VL. <lb/>Visceral leishmaniasis (VL) is a neglected tropical dis-<lb/>ease that predominantly affects the poorest populations <lb/>on Earth. According to WHO, VL accounts for <lb/>50 000-90 000 infections annually worldwide. However, <lb/>the total number of VL infections is likely much larger, <lb/>as it is estimated that just 25-45% of infections are <lb/>reported to WHO (https://www.who.int/news-room/ <lb/>fact-sheets/detail/leishmaniasis). According to WHO&apos;s <lb/>2019 data, 90% of this disease is spread across only 10 <lb/>countries of Southeast Asia, East Africa, and Brazil. <lb/>Left untreated, death can result within 2 years of infec-<lb/>tion, during which time the patient also serves as <lb/>reservoir for further spread of the disease [1]. VL is cur-<lb/>rently the deadliest parasitic disease aside from malaria <lb/>[2]. It has been reported that both government and pri-<lb/>vate institutions are showing less interest in tackling VL <lb/>due to a decrease in the reported number of new infec-<lb/>tions [3]. However, this lack of interest is shortsighted, <lb/>because it overlooks the full impact of this disease. This <lb/>includes the increase of post-kala-azar dermal leishma-<lb/>niasis (PKDL) and the co-occurrence of VL with <lb/>malaria [4] /HIV [5] and other similar pathological dis-<lb/>eases that have further complicated the elimination pro-<lb/>gram. PKDL, which occurs in VL-cured patients after <lb/></body>

			<front>Abbreviations <lb/>LD, Leishmania donovani; LDH, lactate dehydrogenase; LPG, lipophosphoglycan; MTT, 3-(4,5-dimethylthiazol-2-yl)-2,5-diphenyl-tetrazolium <lb/>bromide; ROS, reactive oxygen species; PKDL, post-kala-azar dermal leishmaniasis; VL, visceral leishmaniasis. <lb/>519 <lb/>FEBS Open Bio 13 (2023) 519-531 Ó 2023 The Authors. FEBS Open Bio published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of <lb/>Federation of European Biochemical Societies. <lb/>This is an open access article under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits use, <lb/>distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. <lb/></front>

			<body>6-24 months [6], acts as a reservoir for further infection <lb/>and is responsible for the spread of the disease to <lb/>nonendemic areas [7]. Climate change, war, and terror-<lb/>ism are also leading to a mass migration of disease-<lb/>infected people. These mass migrations may increase <lb/>the spread of the disease drastically and may further <lb/>delay reaching the disease elimination target of reducing <lb/>cases to less than 1 in 10,000 in the population [8]. <lb/>Above all, the emergence of COVID in India and other <lb/>VL-affected countries may augment the spread and <lb/>emergence of this disease [9]. It is thus highly likely that <lb/>elimination of the disease will become more challenging <lb/>if appropriate novel strategies are not developed for its <lb/>effective management in a timely manner. <lb/>Achievement of the disease elimination target is cur-<lb/>rently facing several hurdles. These include inherently <lb/>long treatment regimens, high cost of available drugs, <lb/>emergence of resistance to existing drugs, the failure of <lb/>vaccines against VL in phase II and III clinical trials, <lb/>and a current absence of alternative drugs for VL treat-<lb/>ment [10,11]. The condition is further exacerbated by <lb/>an increase in demand for existing VL drugs as a result <lb/>of their use in other indications. In particular, the <lb/>COVID pandemic has resulted in an increase in the use <lb/>of Amphotericin B/AmBisome for post-COVID infec-<lb/>tions such as mucormycosis and a repurposing of <lb/>AmBisome to Remdesivir for COVID treatment [3]. <lb/>Thus, in order to reach sustainable development goal <lb/>3.3 for the year 2030 (elimination of VL) [8], there is an <lb/>urgent need to develop a drug that is low cost, less sus-<lb/>ceptible to the emergence of resistance, and also effec-<lb/>tive against Leishmania donovani, the causal organism <lb/>of VL. Consequently, potential drug candidates for the <lb/>treatment of VL should have suitable permeability, <lb/>making cell-penetrating peptides good candidates for <lb/>this application [12]. Cell-penetrating peptides have an <lb/>inherent ability to cross the cellular membrane and <lb/>carry diverse macromolecules [13,14], but their intracel-<lb/>lular stability and bioavailability remains a concern <lb/>[15]. Therefore, this need may be addressed through the <lb/>development of peptide-based or peptoid-based thera-<lb/>peutics, which are known for their protease resistance <lb/>and enhanced bioavailability [16]. <lb/>Due to the intracellular nature of L. donovani, <lb/>peptide-based or peptoid-based drugs should be tested <lb/>against both promastigote and amastigote forms of the <lb/>parasite [17]. In order to kill intramacrophagic amasti-<lb/>gotes, potential drug candidates will typically need to <lb/>cross the macrophagic membrane. The best-suited candi-<lb/>dates for this purpose are small nonhydrophobic cell-<lb/>permeating drug molecules, or cell-penetrating peptides <lb/>and their mimetics. While multiple peptide-based thera-<lb/>peutic molecules have shown efficacy against <lb/>L. donovani [18], a class of peptide mimetics known as <lb/>peptoids could offer a better alternative for the develop-<lb/>ment of an anti-VL drug. Peptoids differ from peptides <lb/>as side chains are attached to the amide nitrogen, while <lb/>in peptides, side chain attachment occurs at the a-<lb/>carbon. As a result of this structural difference, peptoids <lb/>often exhibit decreased susceptibility to proteolytic <lb/>degradation and better stability, functional versatility, <lb/>and bioavailability than their peptide counterparts <lb/>[16,19]. Peptoids have shown activity against various <lb/>pathogens, including viruses, bacteria, fungus, and para-<lb/>sites [20-27]. However, most of the parasite studies have <lb/>been carried out against either L. amazonensis promasti-<lb/>gotes [25,28] or L. mexicana axenic amastigotes [29]. To <lb/>the best of our knowledge, the present study is the first <lb/>report to successfully assess the effect of peptoids <lb/>against L. donovani in both forms (intracellular amasti-<lb/>gotes and promastigotes). The effect of hydrophobic <lb/>chain addition and bromination of peptoids on the anti-<lb/>VL activity against both forms of leishmaniasis is also <lb/>shown. This study thus establishes peptoids as promising <lb/>components of a potential new antileishmanial strategy. <lb/>Materials and methods <lb/>Leishmania donovani and cell lines <lb/>The Bob strain of L. donovani (promastigotes) was the gener-<lb/>ous gift of Prof. Amitabh Mukhopadhyay (Kusuma School <lb/>of Biological Sciences, IIT Delhi, New Delhi, India). Bob <lb/>cells were cultured in M199 complete media (Sigma-Aldrich, <lb/>St. Louis, MO, USA), supplemented with 50 lgÁmL À1 genta-<lb/>mycin, and sodium bicarbonate, at 25 °C. Promastigote <lb/>forms of L. donovani were subcultured every 3-4 days with <lb/>complete media. Murine macrophage RAW 264.7 cells were <lb/>procured from National Centre for Cell Science, Pune, India <lb/>and were cultured in DMEM (Gibco, Thermo Fisher Scienti-<lb/>fic, Waltham, MA, USA) supplemented with 10% FBS <lb/>(Gibco, Thermo Fisher Scientific) at 37 °C and 5% CO 2 . <lb/>Peptoid design and synthesis <lb/>For an in-depth discussion of the design of the TM peptoid <lb/>library please see [20]. &quot;TM&quot; stands for &quot;Tasha Molcha-<lb/>nova&quot;, which is the name of the organic chemist who <lb/>synthesized and purified these peptoids. <lb/>In vivo inhibition assay <lb/>Promastigotes of bob L. donovani were harvested in the log <lb/>phase, and parasite inhibition was determined through 3-<lb/>(4,5-dimethylthiazol-2-yl)-2,5-diphenyl-tetrazolium bromide <lb/>(MTT) methods using twofold dilution techniques [30]. <lb/>Briefly, promastigote density of 2 9 10 6 cells was taken, <lb/></body>

			<page>520 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">FEBS Open Bio 13 (2023) 519-531 Ó 2023 The Authors. FEBS Open Bio published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of <lb/>Federation of European Biochemical Societies. <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">Membrane-acting peptoids against leishmaniasis <lb/>V. Kumar et al. <lb/></note>

			<body>and different peptoid dilutions were added (0.187-3 lM) in <lb/>a total volume of 100 lL. Percentage parasite viability was <lb/>evaluated at 4 h at 25 °C using MTT (Sigma-Aldrich). <lb/>Parasite viability rate (%) = [OD of test sample/OD of <lb/>untreated sample] 9 100. <lb/>To evaluate the inhibitory effect of different peptoids on <lb/>intracellular amastigotes, RAW 264.7 cells were infected <lb/>with logarithmic phase promastigotes [30]. Briefly, RAW <lb/>264.7 cells (10 5 cells/well) were seeded in 24-well plates with <lb/>round sterile coverslips and allowed to adhere to the cover-<lb/>slip for 24 h at 37 °C at 5% CO 2 DMEM media supple-<lb/>mented with 10% FBS. Adherent macrophages were <lb/>infected with L. donovani promastigotes at 1 : 10 (macro-<lb/>phage: promastigotes) for 6 h. Co-infected cells were <lb/>washed with PBS three times and incubated for a further <lb/>24 h for infection establishment. After 24 h, media were <lb/>removed and again washed with FBS-free DMEM followed <lb/>by peptoid treatment. Ten lM of different peptoids were <lb/>added to the co-infected cells and incubated for 4 h at <lb/>37 °C at 5% CO 2 . After 4 h, peptoid-treated co-infected <lb/>cells were washed with PBS, fixed with 100% methanol, <lb/>and stained with diluted Giemsa stain (1 : 10) (HiMedia, <lb/>Mumbai, India). The parasite clearance status of peptoids <lb/>was determined by counting the number of the parasites <lb/>using the Leica LAS core microscope system by counting <lb/>100 cells per coverslip. <lb/>Scanning electron microscopy <lb/>Sample preparation for scanning electron microscopy was <lb/>performed following this protocol [30]. Briefly, different <lb/>peptoid-treated (1-3 lM for 4 h) promastigote cells of bob <lb/>L. donovani were fixed with 2-3% glutaraldehyde followed <lb/>by gradual dehydration, air-drying, and coating with 1% <lb/>OsO 4 and observed under scanning electron microscopy <lb/>(Zeiss EVO 18 Special) at 20 kX magnifications. <lb/>Quantification of lactate dehydrogenase release <lb/>Promastigote cell viability was quantified in terms of LDH <lb/>release following a published protocol [30]. Briefly, promas-<lb/>tigote cells of L. donovani were treated with varying con-<lb/>centrations (1-5 lM) of peptoids for 4 h in PBS at 25 °C; <lb/>the reaction volume was 200 lL. LDH assay was per-<lb/>formed using the LDH-cytotoxicity assay kit according to <lb/>the manufacturer&apos;s instructions (BioVision, Waltham, MA, <lb/>USA). <lb/>Quantification of reactive oxygen species <lb/>Reactive oxygen species (ROS) generated upon peptoid <lb/>treatment (5 lM for 30 min) were quantified using a fluores-<lb/>cent dye cell-permeant 2 0 ,7 0 -dichlorodihydrofluorescein diace-<lb/>tate (H 2 DCFDA) (Invitrogen, Thermo Fisher Scientific, <lb/>Waltham, MA, USA) following a published protocol [30]. <lb/>Fluorescence was measured using a fluorescence plate reader <lb/>(Biotek Synergy H1) at Ex/Em of 495/529 nm. Data gener-<lb/>ated were converted into a logarithmic scale. <lb/>Cytotoxicity assessment <lb/>The cytotoxicity of different peptoids against RAW 264.7 <lb/>cells was assessed by the MTT method following a pub-<lb/>lished protocol [30]. Briefly, murine macrophages were <lb/>seeded in a 96-well plate using DMEM supplemented with <lb/>10% FBS maintained at 37 °C and 5% CO 2 for 24 h. <lb/>Next, different concentrations of peptoids (5-80 lM) were <lb/>added and incubated for 24 h followed by the addition of <lb/>MTT for 2 h and solubilization of formazene crystals with <lb/>DMSO addition. Percentage cell viability was calculated <lb/>relative to the peptoid untreated sample. <lb/>Statistical analysis <lb/>All experiments were carried out in triplicate and repeated <lb/>at least three times independently (biological replicates), <lb/>and the figures shown are representative of these experi-<lb/>ments. IC 50 was calculated using GRAPHPAD PRISM 6.0 soft-<lb/>ware. The data were analyzed using Student&apos;s t-test for <lb/>comparison of two groups, and data values were expressed <lb/>as mean AE standard deviation (SD). Significant differences <lb/>were determined and designated with asterisks as follows: <lb/>*P &lt; 0.05; **P &lt; 0.01; ***P &lt; 0.001; and ****P &lt; 0.0001. <lb/>Results <lb/>In the present study, the antivisceral leishmaniasis <lb/>activity of different peptoids was assessed. The effect <lb/>on peptoid activity of bromination at one or more <lb/>phenyl ring side chains and of the presence of a lipid <lb/>chain of different lengths was also determined. <lb/>In vitro antileishmanial activity <lb/>Leishmania donovani promastigotes were treated with a <lb/>subset of the peptoid library reported previously [20] <lb/>(TM 1, TM2, TM 3, TM 4, TM 5, TM 7, TM 9, and <lb/>TM 10) with a range of concentrations (0.187-3.0 lM) <lb/>for 4 h, followed by determination of parasite viability <lb/>by MTT assay. All peptoids showed a range of inhibi-<lb/>tory effects on promastigotes. Viability of promasti-<lb/>gotes decreased with increasing concentration of <lb/>peptoid in comparison with untreated cells (Fig. 1, <lb/>Table S1). At 3 lM, peptoids TM1, TM 2, TM 4, TM <lb/>5, and TM 7 reduced promastigotes viability by 50% <lb/>or more. Triton X 100 at 10% concentration was used <lb/>as a positive control. <lb/></body>

			<page>521 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">FEBS Open Bio 13 (2023) 519-531 Ó 2023 The Authors. FEBS Open Bio published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of <lb/>Federation of European Biochemical Societies. <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">V. Kumar et al. <lb/>Membrane-acting peptoids against leishmaniasis <lb/></note>

			<body>Intracellular amastigotes were also treated with a <lb/>subset of the peptoid library (TM 1, TM2, TM 3, TM <lb/>4, TM 5, TM 7, TM 9, and TM 10) at 10 lM concen-<lb/>tration for 24 h followed by microscopy. Giemsa stain-<lb/>ing results indicated a reduction in number and size of <lb/>amastigotes in samples treated with peptoid TM 1, <lb/>TM 7, TM 9, and TM 10 compared with the control <lb/>(untreated sample; Fig. 2). Based on the inhibitory <lb/>effect of different peptoids on promastigotes, IC 50 <lb/>values of these peptoids were calculated (Table 1). <lb/>Effects of peptoid treatment on L. donovani <lb/>plasma membrane ultrastructure <lb/>The tested peptoids induced significant morphological <lb/>changes in L. donovani promastigote cells, including <lb/>membrane weathering followed by shrinking, bursting, <lb/>and aggregation of LD bodies (Fig. 3). These effects <lb/>were observed to become more pronounced with <lb/>increasing peptoid concentrations. Among all peptoids <lb/>at 1 lM, TM 1, TM 9, and TM 10 exhibited visibly <lb/>detectable effects, while at 3 lM, the morphological <lb/>distortion of the LD body was observed for all <lb/>peptoid-treated samples (Fig. 3). The membrane <lb/>damage further results in leakage of cytoplasmic con-<lb/>tent, leading to cellular constriction and bursting of <lb/>the cell body. <lb/>Assessment of the L. donovani promastigote <lb/>plasma membrane upon peptoid treatment <lb/>Considering the apparent membrane-attacking nature <lb/>of these peptoids, the plasma membrane integrity of <lb/>promastigotes was assessed by determining the release <lb/>of lactate dehydrogenase enzyme (LDH) in the media. <lb/>L. donovani cell viability was represented compared <lb/>with untreated cells as the negative control vs Triton <lb/>X 100 treated cells as the positive control. At 3 lM, <lb/>almost all peptoids showed more than 60% cytotoxi-<lb/>city, increasing to 80% or more at 5 lM. At lower con-<lb/>centrations, peptoids TM 3 and TM 4 showed less <lb/>than 40% cytotoxicity (Fig. 4). <lb/>Fig. 1. Antileishmanial activity of peptoids against Leishmania donovani promastigotes. Early-logarithmic-phase promastigotes of L. donovani <lb/>bob strain were treated with different peptoids at different concentrations (0-3 lM) for 4 h. Negative control was considered 100% of cell <lb/>viability (untreated) and positive control (Triton X treated). Cellular viability was assessed by MTT assay, and the IC 50 values were calculated <lb/>using GRAPHPAD PRISM 6.0. Error bars represent SD N = 3 and n = 3. <lb/></body>

			<page>522 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">FEBS Open Bio 13 (2023) 519-531 Ó 2023 The Authors. FEBS Open Bio published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of <lb/>Federation of European Biochemical Societies. <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">Membrane-acting peptoids against leishmaniasis <lb/>V. Kumar et al. <lb/></note>

			<body>Assessment of intracellular ROS generation <lb/>Reactive oxygen species generation upon peptoid treat-<lb/>ment of promastigotes of L. donovani was determined <lb/>by fluorescent dye (H 2 DCFDA). The purpose of this <lb/>experiment was to investigate whether these peptoids <lb/>have an intracellular target. However, no significant <lb/>increase in ROS generation was observed in any of the <lb/>peptoid-treated samples (Fig. 5). <lb/>Effect of peptoids on murine macrophage cells <lb/>Cytotoxicity of different peptoids at a range of (5-<lb/>80 lM) was determined on RAW 264.7 cells using an <lb/>MTT assay. At the working concentration of 10 lM, <lb/>peptoids TM 1 and TM 2 caused ~40% reduction in <lb/>host cell viability and 50% viability reduction in the <lb/>case of TM 4-and TM 5-treated macrophagic cells, <lb/>while peptoids TM 3, TM 7, TM 9, and TM 10 exhib-<lb/>ited no significant reduction in cell viability. At 20 lM <lb/>and above, drastic reduction in host cell viability was <lb/>observed. Still, at 20 lM, peptoid TM 2-treated cells <lb/>showed more than 50% viability, and TM 3, TM 7, <lb/>and TM 9 showed no toxicity against RAW 264.7 cells <lb/>(Fig. 6, Table S2). <lb/>Discussion <lb/>In this study, we report the effect of peptoids against <lb/>Leishmania donovani, a causative species of VL. Pep-<lb/>toids were found to be active against both the <lb/>Fig. 2. Giemsa staining of intracellular amastigotes in macrophage 264.7 cells after treatment with different peptoids at 10 lM <lb/>concentrations. Untreated amastigotes (A), sample treated with TM 1 (B), TM 2 (C), TM 3 (D), TM 4 (E), TM 5 (F), TM 7 (G), TM 9 (H), and <lb/>TM 10 (I). Red arrow points to the amastigotes form of Leishmania donovani parasite. Scale bar represents 10 lM. <lb/></body>

			<page>523 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">FEBS Open Bio 13 (2023) 519-531 Ó 2023 The Authors. FEBS Open Bio published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of <lb/>Federation of European Biochemical Societies. <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">V. Kumar et al. <lb/>Membrane-acting peptoids against leishmaniasis <lb/></note>

			<body>Table 1. Chemical and biological data of different peptoids used for the treatment of leishmanial parasite. <lb/>+: Average, <lb/>++: Good, <lb/>+++: Better, <lb/>++++: Best. <lb/>*: Good, <lb/>**: Better, <lb/>***: Best. <lb/>Peptoids Structure <lb/>Sequences <lb/>Length <lb/>(mer) <lb/>Promastigote IC <lb/>50 (lM) <lb/>SEM of <lb/>promastigote <lb/>Effect on intracellular <lb/>amastigotes <lb/>TM1 <lb/>H-(NLys-Nspe-Nspe) <lb/>4 -NH <lb/>2 <lb/>12 <lb/>1.56 <lb/>++ <lb/>*** <lb/>TM2 <lb/>H-(NLys-Nspe-Nspe(p-Br)) <lb/>2 -NH <lb/>2 <lb/>6 <lb/>1.40 <lb/>++++ <lb/>* <lb/>TM3 <lb/>H-NLys-Nspe-Nspe-NLys-Nspe-Nspe(p-Br) -NH <lb/>2 <lb/>6 <lb/>4.60 <lb/>+ <lb/>* <lb/>TM4 <lb/>H-(NLys-Nspe(p-Br)-Nspe(p-Br)) <lb/>2 -NH <lb/>2 <lb/>6 <lb/>1.38 <lb/>++ <lb/>* <lb/>TM5 <lb/>H-Ntridec-NLys-Nspe-Nspe-NLys-NH <lb/>2 <lb/>5 <lb/>2.35 <lb/>+ <lb/>524 <lb/></body>
			
			<note place="footnote">FEBS Open Bio 13 (2023) 519-531 Ó 2023 The Authors. FEBS Open Bio published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of <lb/>Federation of European Biochemical Societies. <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">Membrane-acting peptoids against leishmaniasis <lb/>V. Kumar et al. <lb/></note>

			<body>Table 1. (Continued). <lb/>Peptoids Structure <lb/>Sequences <lb/>Length <lb/>(mer) <lb/>Promastigote IC <lb/>50 (lM) <lb/>SEM of <lb/>promastigote <lb/>Effect on intracellular <lb/>amastigotes <lb/>TM7 <lb/>H-(NLys-Nspe-Nspe) <lb/>2 -NH <lb/>2 <lb/>6 <lb/>3.03 <lb/>+++ <lb/>** <lb/>TM9 <lb/>H-Ndec-(NLys-Nspe(p-Br)) <lb/>2 -NH <lb/>2 <lb/>7 <lb/>2.58 <lb/>++++ <lb/>*** <lb/>TM10 <lb/>H-Ntridec-(NLys-Nspe(p-Br)) <lb/>2 -NH <lb/>2 <lb/>7 <lb/>1.54 <lb/>++++ <lb/>*** <lb/></body>

			<page>525 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">FEBS Open Bio 13 (2023) 519-531 Ó 2023 The Authors. FEBS Open Bio published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of <lb/>Federation of European Biochemical Societies. <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">V. Kumar et al. <lb/>Membrane-acting peptoids against leishmaniasis <lb/></note>

			<body>promastigotes and intracellular amastigotes form of <lb/>the parasite. Peptoids (other than TM 3) were found <lb/>to be effective against L. donovani promastigote. <lb/>Further, TM 2, TM 9, and TM 10 were found to be <lb/>more effective among all peptoids tested (Figs 1 and <lb/>2). In particular, TM 9 and TM 10 emerged as the <lb/>best peptoids against both promastigote and amasti-<lb/>gote forms of the parasite (Table 1) while exerting no <lb/>significant toxicity at a working concentration of <lb/>10 lM. These results suggest that out of all the peptoid <lb/>design combinations that were tested, substitution of <lb/>two bromine in the para position of two of the four <lb/>phenyl rings appears to have increased the antileishma-<lb/>nial activity without significantly increasing host cell <lb/>toxicity. At the same time, a decrease or increase in <lb/>the degree of bromination (i.e., bromine substitution <lb/>in one or all four of the phenyl rings) was found to <lb/>have a deleterious effect on both antileishmanial activ-<lb/>ity and host cell toxicity (Table 1). It was also found <lb/>that the addition of two bromine atoms along with the <lb/>lipidation Ndec (i.e., C10 tail; TM 9) or Ntridec (i.e., <lb/>C13 tail; TM 10) further improved the antileishmanial <lb/>activity against both promastigote and amastigotes <lb/>forms of the parasite with no significant increase in <lb/>cytotoxicity. However, Ntridec alone (no bromine <lb/>addition) as in the case of TM 5 decreases antileishma-<lb/>nial activity and increases the host cell toxicity. Thus, <lb/>for antileishmaniasis activity and host cell cytotoxicity, <lb/>two bromine atoms along with an N-alkyl hydropho-<lb/>bic tail within the peptoid structure are optimal. The <lb/>most novel aspect of this study is that these peptoids <lb/>exhibit antileishmanial activity after only 4 h of incu-<lb/>bation, whereas the inhibitory action is normally <lb/>observed between 48 and 72 h. In light of this, the <lb/>antileishmanial activity of peptoid is significantly <lb/>superior to that of existing similar peptoid and peptide <lb/>mimetics. In terms of resistance development, the <lb/>shorter treatment time has advantages over other <lb/>developed peptoids. <lb/>Based on the literature, halogenation of antimicro-<lb/>bial peptides or peptoids enhances their antimicrobial <lb/>efficacy by several fold without altering their hemolytic <lb/>Fig. 3. Ultrastructure of Leishmania donovani promastigotes upon treatment with a subset of peptoid library TM 1-10. Treatment time was <lb/>4 h. The left column shows typically untreated control promastigotes at different concentrations, followed in columns to the right by <lb/>treatment with different TM peptoids, respectively, at three different concentrations. Scale bar represents 1 lM. <lb/></body>

			<page>526 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">FEBS Open Bio 13 (2023) 519-531 Ó 2023 The Authors. FEBS Open Bio published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of <lb/>Federation of European Biochemical Societies. <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">Membrane-acting peptoids against leishmaniasis <lb/>V. Kumar et al. <lb/></note>

			<body>and cytotoxic properties [29,31] and we observed a <lb/>similar result in our study. Among halogens, addition <lb/>of bromine to the side chain had the greatest effect in <lb/>augmenting the antimicrobial efficacy of both peptides <lb/>and peptoids [32]. Therefore, we focused on bromine <lb/>substitution in our study. Previously, [29] investigated <lb/>halogenated peptoid analogs for the antileishmanial <lb/>activity against axenic amastigotes and promastigotes <lb/>of L. mexicana. Although the peptoids with shorter <lb/>length (9mer) lost their inhibitory activity against <lb/>L. mexicana, the chloro substitution in the para posi-<lb/>tion of the phenyl ring of peptoid retained its activity <lb/>against axenic amastigotes but only at longer chain <lb/>length &gt; 9mer. In similar fashion, at 48 h of incuba-<lb/>tion, shorter peptoids containing fluorine substituted <lb/>at the para or meta position also lost their inhibitory <lb/>effect against axenic amastigotes but retained some <lb/>activity for the 12mer length. Interestingly, in our <lb/>Fig. 4. Percentage cytotoxicity of peptoids <lb/>toward Leishmania donovani <lb/>promastigotes as assessed in LDH release <lb/>assay. Promastigote cells were treated <lb/>with different concentrations of peptoids <lb/>at 4 h. Percentage cytotoxicity was <lb/>calculated as a measure of LDH release. <lb/>Error bars represent SD N = 3 and n = 3. <lb/>Fig. 5. Peptoid induced ROS generation in <lb/>Leishmania donovani promastigotes. No <lb/>significant increase in ROS production <lb/>compared with positive control (treated <lb/>with H 2 O 2 ). Y axis is represented in the <lb/>logarithmic scale. Error bars represent SD <lb/>N = 3 and n = 3. <lb/></body>

			<page>527 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">FEBS Open Bio 13 (2023) 519-531 Ó 2023 The Authors. FEBS Open Bio published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of <lb/>Federation of European Biochemical Societies. <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">V. Kumar et al. <lb/>Membrane-acting peptoids against leishmaniasis <lb/></note>

			<body>study, we see efficacy against Leishmania donovani with <lb/>bromine-substituted peptoids that are 6 or 7mer in <lb/>length. This may be due to the use of bromine instead <lb/>of chlorine or fluorine for halogen substitution. <lb/>The antimicrobial activity of these peptoids has been <lb/>investigated against several other organisms including <lb/>bacteria [33] and viruses [20]. It is reported that these <lb/>peptoids have both membrane-attacking and intracel-<lb/>lular modes of action [21]. In the present study, using <lb/>scanning electron microscopy, it was observed that in <lb/>L. donovani, these peptoids start attaching to the para-<lb/>sitic membrane, where they cause membrane instability <lb/>(surface weathering) followed by the formation of <lb/>pore-like structures. This leads to morphological defor-<lb/>mation and death (Fig. 3). However, parasitic death <lb/>cannot be inferred from a mere change in surface mor-<lb/>phology. Thus, the parasite killing of the peptoids was <lb/>validated using an MTT assay and LDH release <lb/>assays. LDH is released only when the cell membrane <lb/>is compromised. It was observed that for each peptoid, <lb/>the release of LDH starts at a treatment of 1 lM con-<lb/>centration and increases with increasing peptoid con-<lb/>centration (3 lM; Fig. 4). <lb/>Further increases in peptoid concentration increase <lb/>the LDH release (Fig. 4), suggesting that increases in <lb/>peptoid concentration will follow the same trend as <lb/>the MTT result for L. donovani promastigotes. Apart <lb/>from the cellular membrane, these peptoids could also <lb/>have intracellular targets. In the case with prokaryotes, <lb/>ribosome aggregation was observed [21]. Since VL-<lb/>causing parasites are eukaryotic [34], ribosomal <lb/>aggregation-based killing cannot be the mode of action <lb/>of these peptoids. Other than ribosomes, mitochondria <lb/>are the primary organelle affected by drug treatment. <lb/>Mitochondrial damage leads to the instantaneous <lb/>release of ROS [35]. In this report, the absence of a <lb/>significant increase in ROS (Fig. 5) is the third indica-<lb/>tion that these peptoids have only a membrane disrup-<lb/>tion mechanism of antileishmaniasis. The two other <lb/>indications were MTT assay and LDH release assays. <lb/>Fig. 6. Percentage of living RAW 264.7 cells after incubation with different concentrations of peptoids. RAW 264.7 macrophage cells were <lb/>incubated with peptoid for 24 h. Untreated cells (no peptoid treatment) showed 100% viable. The working concentration of 10 lM of <lb/>peptoids caused only 50% or lower cytotoxicity in RAW 264.7 cells. Cell viability was determined by MTT assay, and data based on three <lb/>experiments are represented by mean AE SD. <lb/></body>

			<page>528 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">FEBS Open Bio 13 (2023) 519-531 Ó 2023 The Authors. FEBS Open Bio published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of <lb/>Federation of European Biochemical Societies. <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">Membrane-acting peptoids against leishmaniasis <lb/>V. Kumar et al. <lb/></note>

			<body>However, other cellular targets need to be evaluated. <lb/>In the present study, the L. donovani membrane <lb/>appears to be an important site of action for the pep-<lb/>toids investigated. In the literature, these peptoids are <lb/>known to have a high binding affinity toward lipopo-<lb/>lysaccharide [36]. At the working concentration (i.e., at <lb/>10 lM), TM 3, TM 7, TM 9, and TM 10 act preferen-<lb/>tially on the promastigote membrane, which is com-<lb/>posed of polysaccharide lipophosphoglycan (LPG), but <lb/>do not act on the host cell membrane whose outer sur-<lb/>face carries phosphatidylcholine and sphingomyelin. It <lb/>is also reported that leishmanial cell membranes com-<lb/>prise ergosterol, while mammalian cell membranes <lb/>instead comprise cholesterol [37,38]. Thus, it may be <lb/>speculated that LPG or ergosterol could be the site of <lb/>action in promastigotes while TM 1, TM 2, TM 4, <lb/>and TM 5 may have another site of action that needs <lb/>to be explored. With intracellular amastigotes, pep-<lb/>toids TM 7, TM 9, and TM 10 significantly reduced <lb/>their count. Considering their membrane-acting nature, <lb/>these peptoids may have glycoinositolphospholipids as <lb/>a target, which are specifically present in the amasti-<lb/>gote membrane. Since TM 1 reduces the amastigote <lb/>count and simultaneously and reduces the cellular via-<lb/>bility by 40%, this peptoid may have a nonglycoinosi-<lb/>tolphospholipids target. <lb/>In previous studies, hydrophobic side chains and <lb/>halogenations improved the antimicrobial activity and <lb/>reduced the host cytotoxicity of peptoids [32,39]. Con-<lb/>sidering the antileishmanial effect of TM 9 and TM <lb/>10, it can be summarized that lipidation with Ndec <lb/>and Ntridec does indeed help peptoid TM 9 and TM <lb/>10 in parasite membrane attachment, while bromina-<lb/>tion augments antileishmanial activity. Further study <lb/>of other peptoid combinations is warranted for a <lb/>clearer picture of the optimal role of bromination for <lb/>this application. <lb/>Conclusions <lb/>In this study, we have shown that a particular class of <lb/>peptide mimetics (peptoids) reduces the viability of <lb/>L. donovani. To the best of our knowledge, this is the <lb/>first study demonstrating the activity of peptoids <lb/>against the L. donovani species of VL. The effect of <lb/>bromination on antileishmanial activity, in terms of <lb/>both number and position, has also been distinctly <lb/>observed. At the same time, it has also been shown <lb/>that the addition of a hydrophobic lipid tail (Ndec and <lb/>Ntridec) improves the peptoid attachment to the para-<lb/>site cell membrane. The peptoids in the present study <lb/>have been shown to be effective against both promasti-<lb/>gote and intracellular amastigote forms of L. donovani <lb/>and thus could serve as the basis of a potential anti-<lb/>VL strategy. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgments <lb/>VK is thankful to Council of Scientific and Industrial <lb/>Research, New Delhi, for Senior Research Fellowship. <lb/>The authors are grateful to Prof. Amitabha Mukho-<lb/>padhyay, Kusuma School of Biological Sciences, <lb/>Indian Institute of Technology Delhi, India, for provid-<lb/>ing Leishmania (Bob) strain. The authors are also <lb/>thankful to CRF IIT Delhi for scanning electron <lb/>microscope facility. AEB acknowledges support from <lb/>the U.S. Public Health Services (NIH Pioneer Award <lb/>from the National Institute on Aging Grant # 1DP1 <lb/>OD029517-01). AEB, JSL, and NM acknowledge <lb/>Michael Connolly at the Molecular Foundry (Lawr-<lb/>ence Berkeley National Laboratory, Berkeley, CA) for <lb/>his support and mentorship. Work at the Molecular <lb/>Foundry was supported by the Office of Science, Office <lb/>of Basic Energy Sciences, of the U.S. Department of <lb/>Energy under Contract No. DE-AC02-05CH11231. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Conflict of interest <lb/>The authors declare no conflict of interest. <lb/>Author contributions <lb/>VK, AEB, and AC conceptualized the project. VK <lb/>performed the experiments and interpreted the data <lb/>under the supervision of AC, JSL, NM, HJ, and AEB <lb/>designed the peptoids. NM and CR synthesized the <lb/>peptoids. SB mentored CR, VK wrote the manuscript. <lb/>JSL, NM, and JAF contributed detailed information <lb/>on peptoids. All authors edited the article. <lb/></div>

			<div type="availability">Data accessibility <lb/>The data that support the findings of this study may <lb/>be accessed as supplementary information or can be <lb/>made available from the corresponding author on rea-<lb/>sonable request. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>1 Le Rutte EA, Zijlstra EE and de Vlas SJ (2019) Post <lb/>kala-azar dermal leishmaniasis as a reservoir for visceral <lb/>leishmaniasis transmission. Trends Parasitol 35, 590-<lb/>592. <lb/>2 Wamai RG, Kahn J, McGloin J and Ziaggi G (2020) <lb/>Visceral leishmaniasis: a global overview. J Glob Health <lb/>Sci 2, 1-22. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>529 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">FEBS Open Bio 13 (2023) 519-531 Ó 2023 The Authors. FEBS Open Bio published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of <lb/>Federation of European Biochemical Societies. <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">V. Kumar et al. <lb/>Membrane-acting peptoids against leishmaniasis <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>3 Dahl EH, Hamdan HM, Mabrouk L, Matendechero <lb/>SH, Mengistie TB, Elhag MS, Lado M, Adera C, Atia <lb/>AA, Potet J et al. (2021) Control of visceral <lb/>leishmaniasis in East Africa: fragile progress, new <lb/>threats. BMJ Glob Health 6, e006835. <lb/>4 Ferede G, DIro E, Getie S, Getnet G, Takele Y, <lb/>Amsalu A and Wondimeneh Y (2017) Visceral <lb/>leishmaniasis-malaria coinfection and their associated <lb/>factors in patients attending Metema hospital, <lb/>Northwest Ethiopia: suggestion for integrated vector <lb/>management. Malar Res Treat 2017, 6816913. <lb/>5 Lindoso JAL, Moreira CHV, Cunha MA and Queiroz <lb/>IT (2018) Visceral leishmaniasis and HIV coinfection: <lb/>current perspectives. HIV AIDS 10, 193-201. <lb/>6 Zijlstra EE, Musa AM, Khalil EAG, El Hassan IM and <lb/>El-Hassan AM (2003) Post-kala-azar dermal <lb/>leishmaniasis. Lancet Infect Dis 3, 87-98. <lb/>7 Burza S, Croft SL and Boelaert M (2018) <lb/>Leishmaniasis. Lancet 392, 951-970. <lb/>8 WHO (2021) Ending the neglect to attain the SDGs-a <lb/>roadmap for NTD diseases 2021-2030. World Health <lb/>Organization, Geneva. <lb/>9 Le Rutte EA, Coffeng LE, Munoz J and De Vlas SJ <lb/>(2021) Modelling the impact of COVID-19-related <lb/>programme interruptions on visceral leishmaniasis in <lb/>India. Trans R Soc Trop Med Hyg 115, 229-235. <lb/>10 Ponte-Sucre A, Gamarro F, Dujardin JC, Barrett MP, <lb/>L opez-V elez R, Garc ıa-Hern andez R, Pountain AW, <lb/>Mwenechanya R and Papadopoulou B (2017) <lb/>Drug resistance and treatment failure in leishmaniasis: a <lb/>21st century challenge. PLoS Negl Trop Dis 11, 1-24. <lb/>11 Noemı M and Laniado-laborı R (2009) Amphotericin B: <lb/>side effects and toxicity. Rev Iberoam Micol 26, 223-227. <lb/>12 Lynn MA, Kindrachuk J, Marr AK, Jenssen H, Pant e <lb/>N, Elliott MR, Napper S, Hancock RE and McMaster <lb/>WR (2011) Effect of BMAP-28 antimicrobial peptides <lb/>on leishmania major promastigote and amastigote <lb/>growth: role of leishmanolysin in parasite survival. <lb/>PLoS Negl Trop Dis 5, e1141. <lb/>13 Jana A, Narula P, Chugh A and Kulshreshtha R (2019) <lb/>Efficient delivery of anti-miR-210 using Tachyplesin, a <lb/>cell penetrating peptide, for glioblastoma treatment. Int <lb/>J Pharm 572, 118789. <lb/>14 Kumar V and Chugh A (2022) Cell-penetrating peptide <lb/>for targeted macromolecule delivery into plant <lb/>chloroplasts. Appl Microbiol Biotechnol 106, 5249-5259. <lb/>15 Ruseska I and Zimmer A (2020) Internalization <lb/>mechanisms of cell-penetrating peptides. Beilstein J <lb/>Nanotechnol 11, 101-123. <lb/>16 Park M, Wetzler M, Jardetzky TS and Barron AE <lb/>(2013) A readily applicable strategy to convert peptides <lb/>to peptoid-based therapeutics. PLoS One 8, 1-7. <lb/>17 Sunter J and Gull K (2017) Shape, form, function and <lb/>leishmania pathogenicity: from textbook descriptions to <lb/>biological understanding. Open Biol 7, 170165. <lb/>18 Cobb SL and Denny PW (2010) Antimicrobial <lb/>peptides for leishmaniasis. Curr Opin Investig Drugs <lb/>11, 868-875. <lb/>19 Zuckermann RN, Kerr JM, Kent SBH and Moosf WH <lb/>(1992) Efficient method for the preparation of peptoids <lb/>[oligo(N-substituted glycines)] by submonomer solid-<lb/>phase synthesis. J Am Chem Soc 114, 10646-10647. <lb/>20 Diamond G, Molchanova N, Herlan C, Fortkort JA, <lb/>Lin JS, Figgins E, Bopp N, Ryan L, Chung D, Adcock <lb/>R et al. (2021) Potent antiviral activity against HSV-1 <lb/>and SARS-CoV-2 by antimicrobial peptoids. <lb/>Pharmaceuticals 14, 304. <lb/>21 Chongsiriwatana NP, Lin JS, Kapoor R, Wetzler M, <lb/>Rea JAC, Didwania MK, Contag CH and Barron AE <lb/>(2017) Intracellular biomass flocculation as a key <lb/>mechanism of rapid bacterial killing by cationic, <lb/>amphipathic antimicrobial peptides and peptoids. Sci <lb/>Rep 7, 16718. <lb/>22 Corson AE, Armstrong SA, Wright ME, McClelland <lb/>EE and Bicker KL (2016) Discovery and <lb/>characterization of a peptoid with antifungal activity <lb/>against Cryptococcus neoformans. ACS Med Chem Lett <lb/>7, 1139-1144. <lb/>23 Diedrich D (2018) One-pot, multi-component synthesis <lb/>and structure-activity relationships of peptoid-based <lb/>histone deacetylase (HDAC) inhibitors targeting <lb/>malaria parasites. Eur J Med Chem 158, 801-813. <lb/>24 Mackwitz MKW (2019) Structure-activity and <lb/>structure-toxicity relationships of novel peptoid-based <lb/>histone deacetylase inhibitors with dual-stage <lb/>antiplasmodial activity. Chem Med Chem 14, 912-926. <lb/>25 Previdi D (2019) Synthesis and antileishmanial activity <lb/>of some functional peptoids. J Braz Chem Soc 30, <lb/>1334-1340. <lb/>26 Bicker KL and Cobb SL (2020) Recent advances in the <lb/>development of anti-infective peptoids. Chem Commun <lb/>56, 11158-11168. <lb/>27 Nielsen JE, Alford MA, Yung DBY, Molchanova N, <lb/>Fortkort JA, Lin JS, Diamond G, Hancock REW, <lb/>Jenssen H, Pletzer D et al. (2022) Self-assembly of <lb/>antimicrobial peptoids impacts their biological effects <lb/>on ESKAPE bacterial pathogens. ACS Infect Dis 8, <lb/>533-545. <lb/>28 Eggimann GA, Bolt HL, Denny PW and Cobb SL <lb/>(2015) Investigating the anti-leishmanial effects of linear <lb/>peptoids. ChemMedChem 10, 233-237. <lb/>29 Bolt HL, Eggimann GA, Denny PW and Cobb SL <lb/>(2016) Enlarging the chemical space of anti-<lb/>leishmanials: a structure-activity relationship study of <lb/>peptoids against: leishmania mexicana, a causative <lb/>agent of cutaneous leishmaniasis. Medchemcomm 7, <lb/>799-805. <lb/>30 Kumar V and Chugh A (2021) Peptide-mediated <lb/>leishmaniasis management strategy: Tachyplesin <lb/>emerges as an effective anti-leishmanial peptide against <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>530 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">FEBS Open Bio 13 (2023) 519-531 Ó 2023 The Authors. FEBS Open Bio published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of <lb/>Federation of European Biochemical Societies. <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">Membrane-acting peptoids against leishmaniasis <lb/>V. Kumar et al. <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>leishmania donovani. Biochim Biophys Acta 1863, <lb/>183629. <lb/>31 Jia F, Zhang Y, Wang J, Peng J, Zhao P, Zhang L, <lb/>Yao H, Ni J and Wang K (2019) The effect of <lb/>halogenation on the antimicrobial activity, antibiofilm <lb/>activity, cytotoxicity and proteolytic stability of the <lb/>antimicrobial peptide Jelleine-I. Peptides 112, 56-66. <lb/>32 Molchanova N, Nielsen JE, Sørensen KB, Prabhala <lb/>BK, Hansen PR, Lund R, Barron AE and Jenssen H <lb/>(2020) Halogenation as a tool to tune antimicrobial <lb/>activity of peptoids. Sci Rep 10, 14805. <lb/>33 Kapoor R, Eimerman PR, Hardy JW, Cirillo JD, Contag <lb/>CH and Barron AE (2011) Efficacy of antimicrobial <lb/>peptoids against mycobacterium tuberculosis. Antimicrob <lb/>Agents Chemother 55, 3058-3062. <lb/>34 Kazemi B (2011) Genomic organization of leishmania <lb/>species. Iran J Parasitol 6, 1-18. <lb/>35 Kathuria M, Bhattacharjee A, Sashidhara KV, Singh <lb/>SP and Mitra K (2014) Induction of mitochondrial <lb/>dysfunction and oxidative stress in leishmania donovani <lb/>by orally active clerodane diterpene. Antimicrob Agents <lb/>Chemother 58, 5916-5928. <lb/>36 Czyzewski AM, Jenssen H, Fjell CD, Waldbrook M, <lb/>Chongsiriwatana NP, Yuen E, Hancock REW and <lb/>Barron AE (2016) In vivo, in vitro, and in silico <lb/>characterization of peptoids as antimicrobial agents. <lb/>PLoS One 11, e0135961. <lb/>37 Marr A and McGwire BMW (2012) Modes of action of <lb/>Leishmanicidal antimicrobial peptides. Future Microbiol <lb/>7, 1047-1059. <lb/>38 Torrent M, Pulido D, Rivas L and Andreu D (2012) <lb/>Antimicrobial peptide action on parasites. Curr Drug <lb/>Targets 13, 1138-1147. <lb/>39 Lee J, Kang D, Choi J, Huang W, Wadman M, Barron <lb/>AE and Seo J (2018) Effect of side chain <lb/>hydrophobicity and cationic charge on antimicrobial <lb/>activity and cytotoxicity of helical peptoids. Bioorg Med <lb/>Chem Lett 28, 170-173. <lb/></listBibl>

			<div type="annex">Supporting information <lb/>Additional supporting information may be found <lb/>online in the Supporting Information section at the end <lb/>of the article. <lb/>Table S1. Antileishmanial activity of peptoids against <lb/>Leishmania donovani promastigotes. <lb/>Table S2. Host cell (RAW 264.7) Viability data. <lb/></div>

			<page>531 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">FEBS Open Bio 13 (2023) 519-531 Ó 2023 The Authors. FEBS Open Bio published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of <lb/>Federation of European Biochemical Societies. <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">V. Kumar et al. <lb/>Membrane-acting peptoids against leishmaniasis </note>


	</text>
</tei>