<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>Bioorg. Med. Chem. 111 (2024) 117841 <lb/>Available online 18 July 2024 <lb/>0968-0896/© 2024 The Authors. Published by Elsevier Ltd. This is an open access article under the CC BY license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/). <lb/>3-Tetrazolyl-β-carboline derivatives as potential neuroprotective agents <lb/>João L.P. Ribeiro a , Inês Costa b, c , Renata Silva b, c , Susana M.M. Lopes a , Lucília Saraiva d , Teresa <lb/>M.V.D. Pinho e Melo a, * <lb/>a University of Coimbra, Coimbra Chemistry Centre-Institute of Molecular Sciences, and Department of Chemistry, 3004-535 Coimbra, Portugal <lb/>b UCIBIO -Applied Molecular Biosciences Unit, Laboratory of Toxicology, Department of Biological Sciences, Faculty of Pharmacy, Porto University, Porto, Portugal <lb/>c Associate Laboratory i4HB -Institute for Health and Bioeconomy, Faculty of Pharmacy, Porto University, Porto, Portugal <lb/>d LAQV/REQUIMTE, Laboratory of Microbiology, Department of Biological Sciences, Faculty of Pharmacy, University of Porto, Rua Jorge Viterbo Ferreira, 228, 4050-<lb/>313 Porto, Portugal <lb/>A R T I C L E I N F O <lb/>Keywords: <lb/>β-Carbolines <lb/>Tetrazoles <lb/>Hetero-Diels-Alder <lb/>Neuroprotective Agents <lb/>Parkinson&apos;s Disease <lb/>A B S T R A C T <lb/>3-Tetrazolyl-β-carbolines were prepared by the Pictet-Spengler approach using a tryptophan analogue as building <lb/>block, in which the carboxylic acid was replaced by the bioisosteric tetrazole group. Knowing that β-carbolines <lb/>are often associated with psychopharmacological effects, the study of the 3-tetrazolyl-β-carbolines as potential <lb/>neuroprotective agents against Parkinson&apos;s disease was investigated. The evaluation of neuroprotective effects <lb/>against 1-methyl-4-phenylpyridin-1-ium (MPP + )-induced cytotoxicity allowed to identify compounds with <lb/>relevant neuroprotective activity. One derivative, 3-(1-benzyl-1H-tetrazol-5-yl)-1-(p-dimethylaminophenyl)-<lb/>β-carboline, stood out for its low cytotoxicity and excellent performance, preventing cell death induced by this <lb/>neurotoxin. The most promising compounds were also evaluated for their neuroprotective properties against iron <lb/>(III)-induced cytotoxicity. However, only one 3-tetrazolyl-β-carboline derivative slightly reduced iron-induced <lb/>cytotoxicity. Overall, the neuroprotective properties of 3-tetrazolyl-β-carbolines have been demonstrated and <lb/>this finding may contribute to the development of new therapies for Parkinson&apos;s disease. <lb/></front>

			<body>1. Introduction <lb/>β-Carbolines constitute a category of both natural and synthetic <lb/>compounds comprised by an indole-based structure featuring a 9H-<lb/>pyrido[3,4-b]indole scaffold. They exhibit diverse biological activ-<lb/>ities, 1,2 including anti-HIV, 3 antimalarial, 4 and anticancer properties, 5-9 <lb/>among others. 10-13 <lb/>In recent years, numerous synthetic methods have been used to <lb/>prepare new β-carboline derivatives, but the formation of tetrahydro-<lb/>β-carboline intermediates through the Pictet-Spengler reaction, fol-<lb/>lowed by their oxidation, has been the method of choice. 14,15 In our <lb/>research group, we have extensively studied the reactivity of nitro-<lb/>soalkenes toward heterocycles, 16 and explored its potential application <lb/>in the synthesis of new tryptamines. Nitrosoalkenes are generated in situ <lb/>by treating α-bromooximes with sodium carbonate and participate in <lb/>hetero-Diels-Alder reactions with indoles. The 1,2-oxazine cycloadducts <lb/>undergo ring-opening affording 3-alkylated indoles incorporating an <lb/>oxime moiety. The open-chain oxime is then reduced to yield the desired <lb/>tryptamines. 6,7,17-19 In this context, tryptophan analogues, in which the <lb/>carboxylic acid was replaced by the bioisosteric tetrazole group, were <lb/>synthesised and used as building block for the synthesis of novel 3-tet-<lb/>razolyl-β-carbolines. 6,7 <lb/>The synthesized derivatives were tested for their activity against a <lb/>wide range of cancer cell lines. β-Carboline 1, showed high selectivity <lb/>for cancer cells, with IC 50 values below 8 μM against pancreatic <lb/>adenocarcinoma (PAN-1), melanoma (A375), hepatocarcinoma <lb/>(HEPG2) and breast adenocarcinoma (MCF-7) cell lines. The fluorine-<lb/>containing 3-tetrazolyl-β-carboline 2 proved to be active against glio-<lb/>blastoma (U251), breast adenocarcinoma (MCF-7), renal adenocarci-<lb/>noma (786-0), ovarian carcinoma (OVAR-3) and leukaemia (K-562) <lb/>tumour cell lines with GI 50 values below 2 μM (Figure 1). 6,7 <lb/>Within their wide range of documented biological activities, both <lb/>synthetic and natural β-carbolines are often associated with psycho-<lb/>pharmacological effects. 10,11 <lb/>Parkinson&apos;s disease is a neurodegenerative disorder characterized by <lb/>the disruption of the dopaminergic pathway, resulting in movement <lb/>disorders, postural instability, tremors, and muscular rigidness. This <lb/>condition is progressive, with symptoms worsening over time, which <lb/></body>

			<front>* Corresponding author. <lb/>E-mail address: tmelo@ci.uc.pt (T.M.V.D. Pinho e Melo). <lb/>Contents lists available at ScienceDirect <lb/>Bioorganic &amp; Medicinal Chemistry <lb/>journal homepage: www.elsevier.com/locate/bmc <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.bmc.2024.117841 <lb/>Received 12 April 2024; Received in revised form 11 July 2024; Accepted 15 July 2024 <lb/></front>

			<note place="headnote">Bioorganic &amp; Medicinal Chemistry 111 (2024) 117841 <lb/></note>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<body>greatly reduces the patient&apos;s life expectancy and quality of life. Par-<lb/>kinson&apos;s disease is currently incurable, with the treatments available <lb/>aiming only at symptom relief and managing the patient&apos;s quality of life. <lb/>Furthermore, some individuals have a higher genetic susceptibility to <lb/>developing the disease, in which case several prophylactic measures can <lb/>be taken to prevent and/or slow the progression of the disease. 20 <lb/>Several studies have been reported on the pharmacological activity <lb/>of β-carboline derivatives against neuropsychiatric disorders, namely <lb/>depression, 21-23 Alzheimer&apos;s disease, 24-26 epilepsy, 27,28 and Parkinson&apos;s <lb/>disease. 29-31 <lb/>In view of the known activity of β-carboline derivatives against <lb/>neuropsychiatric diseases, we decided to study 3-tetrazolyl-β-carbolines <lb/>as potential neuroprotective agents against Parkinson&apos;s disease, using <lb/>differentiated SH-SY5Y cells as in vitro model. <lb/>2. Results and discussion <lb/>2.1. Chemistry <lb/>Initially, the tryptophan analogue 5 was prepared according to pre-<lb/>viously described procedures. 6,18 The synthesis of the open chain oxime <lb/>4 was achieved by bromination of acetyltetrazole 3, followed by oxi-<lb/>mation, and finally hetero-Diels-Alder reaction of the in situ generated <lb/>nitrosoalkene with indole and subsequent 1,2-oxazine ring-opening. 18 <lb/>Reduction of the oxime moiety of compound 4 with Zn in formic acid <lb/>afforded the target tryptamine 5. 6 The Pictet-Spengler reaction of amino <lb/>tetrazole 5 with aromatic aldehydes (m-nitrobenzaldehyde, o-chlor-<lb/>obenzaldehyde and p-dimethylaminobenzaldehyde), in the presence of <lb/>trifluoroacetic acid (TFA), gave tetrahydro-β-carbolines 6 in yields <lb/>ranging from 34% to 84% (Scheme 1). The tetrahydro-β-carbolines 6a-b <lb/>were isolated as mixtures of cis/trans isomers, while trans-6c was iso-<lb/>lated as single isomer. The oxidation of tetrahydro-β-carbolines 6 was <lb/>carried out with sulphur in refluxing dimethylformamide for 24 h, <lb/>affording β-carbolines 7a-c in good yields (56-63%). The β-carbolines <lb/>were purified by recrystallization in methanol, which contributed to the <lb/>overall efficiency of the synthetic procedure. <lb/>2.2. Biological studies <lb/>2.2.1. Evaluation of compounds&apos; cytotoxicity <lb/>The cytotoxicity of the compounds under study towards differenti-<lb/>ated SH-SY5Y cells was evaluated, 24 h after exposure, by the neutral <lb/>red (NR) uptake and resazurin (REZ) reduction assays. As shown in <lb/>Figure 2, compounds 1 and 2 proved to be the most cytotoxic among the <lb/>tested compounds, with significant cytotoxic effects being detected for <lb/>concentrations equal to or higher than 10 μM. In fact, in the case of <lb/>compound 1, NR uptake significantly decreased to 85.6, 81.3 and <lb/>65.9%, 24 h after exposure to 10, 25 and 50 μM, respectively, compared <lb/>to control (untreated cells). In the REZ reduction assay similar results <lb/>were observed, although the cytotoxic effects were only significant for <lb/>the two highest concentrations (REZ reduction significantly decreased to <lb/>74.0 and 59.3%, 24 h after exposure to 25 and 50 μM). For compound 2, <lb/>the results of the two cytotoxicity assays were also highly concordant. <lb/>Indeed, in the NR uptake assay, the lysosomal accumulation of NR <lb/>significantly decreased to 83.6, 70.5 and 56.1%, 24 h after exposure to <lb/>10, 25 and 50 μM, while REZ reduction significantly decreased to 80.0, <lb/>62.2 and 48.5%, 24 h after exposure to the same concentrations. For <lb/>compound 7a, no significant cytotoxic effects were detected 24 h after <lb/>exposure to any of the tested concentrations, as evaluated by the NR <lb/>uptake assay. However, a minor but significant decrease in REZ reduc-<lb/>tion was observed upon exposure to the highest tested concentration <lb/>(REZ reduction significantly decreased to 92.6%, 24 h after exposure to <lb/>50 μM of compound 7a, when compared to control cells). Concerning <lb/>compound 7b, although no significant effects were detected in the REZ <lb/>reduction assay, a significant decrease in NR uptake was observed for <lb/>the two highest concentrations tested (NR uptake significantly <lb/>decreased to 84.0 and 81.7% 24 h after exposure to 25 and 50 μM of <lb/>compound 7b, respectively). Finally, for compound 7c, similarly to <lb/>compound 7b, despite the lack of significant effects detected by the REZ <lb/>reduction assay, the NR uptake significantly decreased 24 h after <lb/>exposure to the highest tested concentration (NR uptake significantly <lb/>decreased to 80.5%, 24 h after exposure to 50 μM of compound 7c). <lb/>Overall, compounds 7a, 7b and 7c can be considered non-cytotoxic <lb/>Figure 1. Structure of 3-tetrazolyl-β-carbolines with promising anti-<lb/>cancer activity. <lb/>Scheme 1. Synthesis of novel 3-tetrazolyl-β-carbolines. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">J.L.P. Ribeiro et al. <lb/>Bioorganic &amp; Medicinal Chemistry 111 (2024) 117841 <lb/></note>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<body>Figure 2. Cytotoxicity of the compounds towards differentiated SH-SY5Y cells, evaluated by the neutral red uptake (A) and resazurin reduction (B) assays, 24 h after <lb/>exposure. Results are presented as mean + SD from 5 independent experiments, performed in triplicate. Statistical comparisons were performed using the One-way <lb/>ANOVA followed by the Dunnett&apos;s multiple comparisons test [***p &lt; 0.001; ****p &lt; 0.0001 vs. control cells]. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">J.L.P. Ribeiro et al. <lb/>Bioorganic &amp; Medicinal Chemistry 111 (2024) 117841 <lb/></note>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<body>at concentrations up to 10 μM, whereas for compounds 1 and 2 the <lb/>highest concentration considered non-cytotoxic is 5 μM. These concen-<lb/>trations were thus selected for the assessment of the compounds&apos; neu-<lb/>roprotective effects. <lb/>The ability of the compounds to induce reactive oxygen species <lb/>(ROS) overproduction was also evaluated 24 h after exposure. However, <lb/>as shown in Figure 3, a small but significant increase in ROS intracellular <lb/>levels was only observed 24 h after exposure to the highest concentra-<lb/>tion of compound 2 (2′,7′-dichlorofluorescein, DCF, fluorescence <lb/>increased to 108.2%, 24 h after exposure to 50 μM of 2, when compared <lb/>to control cells). <lb/>2.2.2. Evaluation of the neuroprotective effects of compounds <lb/>Neuroprotective effects against MPP + -induced cytotoxicity. <lb/>1-Methyl-4-phenyl-1,2,3,6-tetrahydropyridine (MPTP) is a meperi-<lb/>dine analogue, produced as a by-product in the process of synthesizing <lb/>1-methyl-4-phenyl-propionoxzy-piperidine. Once inside the body, due <lb/>to its lipophilicity, it crosses the blood-brain-barrier (BBB) into the <lb/>central nervous system (CNS), where the MAO-B enzyme, secreted by <lb/>glial cells, converts MPTP into a metabolite, 1-methyl-4-phenyl-2,3-<lb/>dihydropyridine (MPDP + ), and subsequently to the final toxic metabo-<lb/>lite, 1-methyl-4-phenylpyridin-1-ium (MPP + ). MPTP itself is not toxic in <lb/>the brain, and it requires the process of biotransformation to form the <lb/>toxic metabolite. 32-37 MPP + can exert its toxicity on the mitochondria, <lb/>where it inhibits the cellular respiration through the blockage of the <lb/>electron transport enzyme NADH-ubiquinone oxidoreductase (complex <lb/>I), inhibiting the electron transport and thus leading to an energy failure <lb/>with ATP depletion, and to an increase in the formation of free radi-<lb/>cals. 38,39 The specific MPP + -induced dopaminergic cytotoxicity has <lb/>been commonly used to investigate the potential of new neuroprotective <lb/>agents, being this neurotoxin largely used, in vitro and in vivo, to mimic <lb/>Parkinson&apos;s disease. 40 The neuroprotective effects of compounds against <lb/>Figure 3. Intracellular levels of reactive oxygen species (ROS), evaluated in differentiated SH-SY5Y cells, 24 h after exposure to the compounds, using the DCFH-DA <lb/>probe. Results are presented as mean + SD from at least 4 independent experiments, performed in triplicate. Statistical comparisons were performed using the One-<lb/>way ANOVA followed by the Dunnett&apos;s multiple comparisons test [****p &lt; 0.0001 vs. control cells]. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">J.L.P. Ribeiro et al. <lb/>Bioorganic &amp; Medicinal Chemistry 111 (2024) 117841 <lb/></note>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<body>MPP + -induced cytotoxicity were assessed, by the NR uptake assay, 24 h <lb/>after exposure of differentiated SH-SY5Y cells to the chemical aggressor <lb/>(up to 1000 μM) in the presence or absence of non-cytotoxic concen-<lb/>trations of the compounds under study (1, 2.5, 5 and 10 μM). All com-<lb/>pounds were tested at 1, 2.5 and 5 μM, and additionally 7a, 7b and 7c <lb/>were also tested at 10 μM given the lack of cytotoxic effects at this <lb/>concentration. As observed in Figure 4, although for 7a no significant <lb/>effects were observed, and for 7b a small but significant reduction of <lb/>MPP + -induced cytotoxicity was detected, particularly for the highest <lb/>concentration, for compounds 1, 2 and 7c a significant decrease in the <lb/>cytotoxicity of the chemical aggressor was observed. For compound 1, <lb/>NR uptake significantly increased to 91.4, 92,1 and 93.5% 24 h after <lb/>exposure to 500 μM MPP + in the presence of 1, 2.5 and 5 μM of com-<lb/>pound 1, respectively, when compared to 83.3% observed for 500 μM <lb/>MPP + alone. Similar results were obtained 24 h after exposure to the <lb/>highest concentration of the neurotoxin, with NR uptake significantly <lb/>increasing to 87.1, 84.6 and 89.1% 24 h after exposure to 1000 μM <lb/>MPP + in the presence of 1, 2.5 and 5 μM of compound 1, respectively, <lb/>when compared to 75.8% observed for 1000 μM MPP + alone. Regarding <lb/>compound 2, when exposed to 500 μM MPP + , the neuroprotective ef-<lb/>fects were only observed for the 2.5 μM concentration (NR uptake <lb/>significantly increased to 91.4% 24 h after exposure to 500 μM MPP + in <lb/>the presence of 2.5 μM of compound 2, when compared to 83.9% <lb/>observed for 500 μM MPP + alone). However, when the highest con-<lb/>centration of the chemical aggressor was used, a significant reduction in <lb/>MPP + -induced cytotoxicity was observed in the presence of compound <lb/>2, for all the concentrations tested (NR uptake significantly increased to <lb/>84.8, 83.4 and 83.2% 24 h after exposure to 1000 μM MPP + in the <lb/>presence of 1, 2.5 and 5 μM of compound 2, respectively, when <lb/>compared to 76.2% observed for 1000 μM MPP + alone). For both <lb/>Figure 4. Neuroprotective effects of compounds against MPP + -induced cytotoxicity evaluated in differentiated SH-SY5Y cells 24 h after exposure to the aggressor in <lb/>the presence or absence of compounds. Results are presented as mean + SD from at least 4 independent experiments, performed in triplicate. Statistical comparisons <lb/>were performed using the Two-way ANOVA followed by the Tukey&apos;s multiple comparisons test [ ## p &lt; 0.01; ### p &lt; 0.001; #### p &lt; 0.0001 vs. in the absence of <lb/>MPP + ; *p &lt; 0.05; **p &lt; 0.01; ****p &lt; 0.0001, for comparisons between treatments [MPP + alone, MPP + + Compound (1, 2.5, 5 or 10 μM)], at each MPP + <lb/>concentration]. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">J.L.P. Ribeiro et al. <lb/>Bioorganic &amp; Medicinal Chemistry 111 (2024) 117841 <lb/></note>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<body>compounds 1 and 2, the observed neuroprotection was not dependent <lb/>on the concentration of compound tested. Finally, compound 7c <lb/>demonstrated the highest protective effect, at least at 1 and 2.5 μM <lb/>concentrations, against the cytotoxicity induced by the MPP + neuro-<lb/>toxin, with a significant reduction in MPP + -induced cell death, being an <lb/>effect observed at all concentrations of the chemical aggressor. Note-<lb/>worthy, the observed neuroprotective effects were more significant for <lb/>the lowest concentration tested of 7c (1 μM) (Figure 4). Indeed, NR <lb/>significantly increased to 97.8, 92.3 and 85.8% 24 h after exposure to <lb/>500 μM MPP + in the presence of 1, 2.5 and 5 μM of compound 7c, <lb/>respectively, when compared to 81.1% observed for 500 μM MPP + <lb/>alone. Notably, no significant effects in NR uptake were detected be-<lb/>tween differentiated SH-SY5Y cells exposed to 500 μM MPP + in the <lb/>presence of 1 μM of compound 7c and control cell (without MPP + ), <lb/>which highlights the remarkable 7c-mediated protection against MPP + -<lb/>induced cytotoxicity, completely preventing the cell death induced by <lb/>the aggressor. When the chemical aggressor was tested at the highest <lb/>concentration, NR significantly increased to 90.3 and 83.6% 24 h after <lb/>exposure to 1000 μM MPP + in the presence of 1 and 2.5 μM of compound <lb/>7c, respectively, when compared to 75.0% observed for 1000 μM MPP + <lb/>alone. <lb/>The existence of a more pronounced neuroprotective effect of com-<lb/>pound 7c against MPP + -induced cytotoxicity at lower concentrations, <lb/>potentially including its ability to restore mitochondrial function and <lb/>enhance energy metabolism, may be due to the existence of an optimal <lb/>concentration range to ensure selective targeting of relevant cell sig-<lb/>nalling pathways, avoidance of off-target effects, and maintenance of <lb/>redox balance and cellular homeostasis. Furthermore, it is widely <lb/>recognized that mitochondrial function and energy metabolism are <lb/>tightly regulated processes within cells. Therefore, lower concentrations <lb/>Figure 5. Neuroprotective effects of compounds against Iron (III)-induced cytotoxicity evaluated in differentiated SH-SY5Y cells 24 h after exposure to the aggressor <lb/>in the presence or absence of compounds. Results are presented as mean + SD from at least 5 independent experiments, performed in triplicate. Statistical com-<lb/>parisons were performed using the Two-way ANOVA followed by the Tukey&apos;s multiple comparisons test [ ### p &lt; 0.001; #### p &lt; 0.0001 vs. in the absence of Iron <lb/>(III); *p &lt; 0.05, for comparisons between treatments [Iron (III) alone, Iron (III) + Compound (1, 2.5, 5 or 10 μM)], at each Iron (III) concentration]. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">J.L.P. Ribeiro et al. <lb/>Bioorganic &amp; Medicinal Chemistry 111 (2024) 117841 <lb/></note>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<body>of compound 7c may be more effective in maintaining the delicate <lb/>balance and homeostasis of these cellular processes, whereas higher <lb/>concentrations could disrupt this balance. <lb/>Overall, these studies led us to the identification of compounds with <lb/>relevant neuroprotective activity against cell death induced by a <lb/>neurotoxin that is selective for dopaminergic neurons, and which is <lb/>frequently used, in vitro and in vivo, to identify new disease-modifying <lb/>drugs with therapeutic potential in Parkinson&apos;s disease. <lb/>Neuroprotective effects against Iron (III)-induced cytotoxicity. <lb/>Iron is a trace element and one of the most abundant metals in the <lb/>human body. Iron homeostasis is achieved through the balance between <lb/>its absorption, use, storage, and excretion. Dysfunction of the iron levels <lb/>and neurodegenerative diseases are closely related. 41 Indeed, dysregu-<lb/>lation of iron metabolism can lead to an imbalance in the normal iron <lb/>redox status and in the levels of Fe 2+ , which can participate in the <lb/>Fenton reaction leading to a cycle between the two redox states, and to <lb/>the generation of •OH. 42 Furthermore, the increased production of ROS <lb/>leads to lipid peroxidation and ferroptosis, which was already reported <lb/>to be present in distinct neurodegenerative diseases. 41 In the present <lb/>study, the neuroprotective effects of compounds against iron (III)-<lb/>induced cytotoxicity were assessed, by the NR uptake assay, 24 h after <lb/>exposure of differentiated SH-SY5Y cells to the chemical aggressor (up to <lb/>1000 μM) in the presence or absence of non-cytotoxic concentrations of <lb/>the compounds under study (1, 2.5, 5 and 10 μM). Only the most <lb/>promising compounds identified as neuroprotective against MPP + -<lb/>induced cell death were selected, namely 1, 2 and 7c. All compounds <lb/>were tested at 1, 2.5 and 5 μM, except 7c which was also tested at 10 μM <lb/>given the lack of cytotoxic effects at this concentration. However, as <lb/>observed in Figure 5, only compound 1 slightly but significantly reduced <lb/>iron-induced cytotoxicity, being this neuroprotective effect observed <lb/>only for the lowest concentration of the aggressor and in the presence of <lb/>the lowest concentration of compound 1. Indeed, NR uptake signifi-<lb/>cantly increased to 87.6% 24 h after exposure to 500 μM iron (III) in the <lb/>presence of 1 μM of compound 1, when compared to 81.4% after <lb/>exposure to iron (III) alone. Although for 7c no significant differences <lb/>were detected upon exposure to iron (III), in the case of compound 2, at <lb/>2.5 or 5 μM, the cytotoxicity induced by the highest iron (III) concen-<lb/>tration was slightly but significantly increased. <lb/>Overall, and according to the obtained results, the developed 3-tet-<lb/>razolyl-β-carbolines demonstrated promising neuroprotective effects, <lb/>counteracting the cytotoxic effects induced by chemical stressors that <lb/>mimic pathophysiological hallmarks of Parkinson&apos;s disease. It is widely <lb/>accepted that MPP + induces cytotoxicity through mechanisms involving <lb/>oxidative stress, mitochondrial dysfunction, and apoptosis. Specifically, <lb/>MPP + inhibits complex I of the mitochondrial electron transport chain, <lb/>leading to increased ROS production and a decline in ATP synthesis, <lb/>ultimately resulting in cell death. 38,39 <lb/>Iron accumulation is another hallmark of distinct neurodegenerative <lb/>disease and in particular of Parkinson&apos;s disease pathology, specifically in <lb/>the substantia nigra. Iron overload can lead to oxidative stress and cell <lb/>death through mechanisms like ferroptosis, a form of regulated cell <lb/>death characterized by iron-dependent lipid peroxidation. Several <lb/>hallmarks of ferroptosis were already identified in distinct neurode-<lb/>generative diseases including Parkinson&apos;s disease. 41 <lb/>However, it should be highlighted that the developed 3-tetrazolyl-<lb/>β-carbolines demonstrated a higher potential in protecting neuronal <lb/>cells against MPP + -induced cytotoxicity, when compared to the neuro-<lb/>protective effects observed against iron-induced cytotoxicity. This sug-<lb/>gests that the studied 3-tetrazolyl-β-carboline derivatives may have <lb/>more potent and specific mechanisms to effectively counteract MPP + -<lb/>induced mitochondrial dysfunction and oxidative stress (e.g. restoring <lb/>mitochondrial function, reducing oxidative damage, or promoting cell <lb/>survival pathways) compared to iron-mediated toxicity. <lb/>3. Conclusion <lb/>The synthesis of 3-tetrazolyl-β-carbolines and their activity as neu-<lb/>roprotective agents against Parkinson&apos;s disease has been reported. The <lb/>synthetic strategy involves the synthesis of a tryptophan analogue via <lb/>hetero-Diels-Alder reaction of a nitrosoalkene, 1-benzyl-5-(1-nitro-<lb/>sovinyl)-1H-tetrazole, and indole used as building block in the Pictet-<lb/>Spengler reaction with aromatic aldehydes followed by an oxidative <lb/>step. <lb/>The 3-tetrazolyl-β-carbolines were evaluated for their cytotoxicity <lb/>against differentiated SH-SY5Y cells, with multiple neuronal character-<lb/>istics, through two different methodologies (neutral red uptake and <lb/>resazurin reduction assays) allowing to conclude that for three of the <lb/>studied compounds concentrations up to 10 μM are non-cytotoxic <lb/>whereas for two derivatives the highest concentration considered non-<lb/>cytotoxic is 5 μM. <lb/>The evaluation of compounds&apos; neuroprotective effects included the <lb/>study of the neuroprotective activity against MPP + -induced cell death, a <lb/>neurotoxin used to mimic Parkinson&apos;s disease. When differentiated SH-<lb/>SY5Y cells were exposed to MPP + in the presence of the compounds <lb/>under investigation, three of the 3-tetrazolyl-β-carbolines showed a <lb/>significant reduction in the cytotoxicity of the chemical aggressor. The <lb/>most promising compound, 3-(1-benzyl-1H-tetrazol-5-yl)-1-(p-dime-<lb/>thylaminophenyl)-β-carboline, led to a marked reduction in MPP + -<lb/>induced cytotoxicity, completely preventing the cell death induced by <lb/>the aggressor, even at a concentration 500 times lower than that of the <lb/>aggressor. <lb/>The compounds with the most promising neuroprotective activity <lb/>against MPP + -induced cell death were also evaluated for their neuro-<lb/>protective effect against iron (III)-induced cytotoxicity. However, only <lb/>one 3-tetrazolyl-β-carboline derivative slightly reduced iron-induced <lb/>cytotoxicity, although this neuroprotective effect was only observed at <lb/>the lowest concentration of the aggressor and in the presence of the <lb/>lowest concentration of this compound. <lb/>Overall, our results clearly highlight the neuroprotective potential of <lb/>new 3-tetrazolyl-β-carbolines. However, while three of the 3-tetrazolyl-<lb/>β-carbolines significantly reduced MPP + -induced cytotoxicity in SH-<lb/>SY5Y cells, only one of the developed compounds showed a slight <lb/>reduction in iron-induced toxicity. This suggests that the studied 3-tet-<lb/>razolyl-β-carbolines may have more potent and specific mechanisms to <lb/>effectively counteract MPP + -induced mitochondrial dysfunction and <lb/>oxidative stress (e.g. restoring mitochondrial function, reducing oxida-<lb/>tive damage, or promoting cell survival pathways) compared to iron-<lb/>mediated toxicity. Knowing that MPP + is a neurotoxin that selectively <lb/>targets and damages dopaminergic neurons, our work thus provides <lb/>evidence that 3-tetrazolyl-β-carbolines can be considered as potential <lb/>neuroprotective agents against Parkinson&apos;s disease, which is likely to <lb/>inspire the development of new Parkinson&apos;s disease therapies. There-<lb/>fore, further targeted research will be employed in the future to fully <lb/>elucidate the precise mechanism(s) underlying the observed 3-tetra-<lb/>zolyl-β-carbolines-mediated neuroprotection. <lb/>4. Experimental section <lb/>4.1. Chemistry <lb/>4.1.1. General information <lb/>Nuclear Magnetic Resonance (NMR) spectra were recorded on a <lb/>Bruker Avance III instrument operating at 400 MHz ( 1 H) or 100 MHz <lb/>( 13 C). Chemical shifts are expressed in parts per million with tetrame-<lb/>thylsilane (TMS) as internal standard, while coupling constants (J) are <lb/>expressed in Hz. Infrared spectra (IR) were recorded in a Fourier <lb/>Transform spectrometer coupled with a diamond Attenuated Total <lb/>Reflectance (ATR) sampling accessory. High-resolution mass spectra <lb/>(HRMS) were obtained on a TOF VG Autospect M spectrometer with <lb/>electrospray ionization (ESI). Melting points were determined in open <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">J.L.P. Ribeiro et al. <lb/>Bioorganic &amp; Medicinal Chemistry 111 (2024) 117841 <lb/></note>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<body>glass capillaries. Thin Layer Chromatography (TLC) was performed <lb/>using precoated silica gel plates. Flash chromatography was performed <lb/>using silica gel 60 as a stationary phase. Tryptamine 5 and 3-tetrazolyl-<lb/>β-carbolines 1 and 2 were prepared as described in the literature. 6 <lb/>4.1.2. General procedure for the synthesis of tetrahydro-β-carbolines 6 <lb/>Trifluoroacetic acid (2 equiv) was added to a solution of amine 5 (1 <lb/>equiv) and the appropriate aldehyde (1 equiv) in dry dichloromethane <lb/>(23 mL/mmol). The reaction mixture was stirred at room temperature, <lb/>and monitored by TLC until all the amine was consumed. Upon <lb/>completion, the reaction mixture was concentrated under reduced <lb/>pressure, the residue dissolved in ethyl acetate (10 mL) and neutralized <lb/>with an aqueous solution of Na 2 CO 3 10%. The resulting solution was <lb/>extracted with ethyl acetate (3 x 25 mL), dried over anhydrous Na 2 SO 4 <lb/>and the solvent evaporated off. The products were purified by recrys-<lb/>tallization in MeOH and obtained as a mixture of cis/trans isomers, un-<lb/>less otherwise stated. <lb/>4.1.2.1. 3-(1-Benzyl-1H-tetrazol-5-yl)-1-(m-nitrophenyl)-2,3,4,9-tetrahy-<lb/>dro-β-carboline (6a). Obtained from the reaction of amine 5 <lb/>(0.20 mmol, 65 mg) with m-nitrobenzaldehyde (0.20 mmol, 34 mg) as <lb/>described in the general procedure (reaction time: 28 h), as a mixture of <lb/>cis/trans isomers [61 mg, 84%, (40:60)]. Major component (trans-6a): IR <lb/>(ATR) ν: 742, 796, 1012, 1323, 1344, 1496, 1521, 3264 cm -1 . 1 H NMR <lb/>(Acetone-d 6 ) δ: 3.27 (dd, J = 15.0, 4.6 Hz, 1H), 3.42-3.48 (m, 1H), 4.39 <lb/>(ddd, J = 14.0, 10.0, 4.6 Hz, 1H), 5.50 (d, J = 15.2 Hz, 1H), 5.57 (d, <lb/>J = 5.2 Hz, 1H), 5.58 (d, J = 15.2 Hz, 1H), 6.83-6.86 (m, 1H), 7.03-7.43 <lb/>(m, 8H), 7.52-7.60 (m, 1H), 7.65-7.69 (m, 1H), 7.74-7.76 (m, 1H), <lb/>8.10-8.11 (m, 1H), 8.18-8.23 (m, 1H), 10.04 (s, 1H). HRMS (ESI-TOF) <lb/>m/z for C 25 H 21 N 7 O 2 Na [M+Na + ] calcd. 474.1649, found 474.1648. <lb/>4.1.2.2. 3-(1-Benzyl-1H-tetrazol-5-yl)-1-(o-chlorophenyl)-2,3,4,9-tetra-<lb/>hydro-β-carboline (6b). Obtained from the reaction of amine 5 <lb/>(0.16 mmol, 50 mg) with o-chlorobenzaldehyde (0.16 mmol, 26 μL) as <lb/>described in the general procedure (reaction time: 40 h), as a mixture of <lb/>cis/trans isomers [52 mg, 70%, (50:50)]. Trans-6b: IR (ATR) ν: 749, 802, <lb/>1016, 1319, 1494, 3179 cm -1 . 1 H NMR (DMSO-d 6 ) δ: 3.09-3.26 (m, <lb/>2H), 4.21 (ddd, J = 14.8, 10.0, 4.4 Hz, 1H), 5.44 (d, J = 15.0 Hz, 1H), <lb/>5.54 (d, J = 15.0 Hz, 1H), 5.62 (d, J = 5.2 Hz, 1H), 6.70-6.73 (m, 2H), <lb/>6.97-7.41 (m, 10H), 7.53-7.60 (m, 2H), 10.86 (s, 1H). HRMS (ESI-TOF) <lb/>m/z for C 25 H 21 N 6 ClNa [M+Na + ] calcd. 463.1408, found 463.1406. <lb/>4.1.2.3. 3-(1-Benzyl-1H-tetrazol-5-yl)-1-(p-dimethylaminophenyl)-<lb/>2,3,4,9-tetrahydro-β-carboline (6c). Obtained from the reaction of amine <lb/>5 (0.16 mmol, 50 mg) with p-dimethylaminobenzaldehyde (0.16 mmol, <lb/>34 mg), as described in the general procedure (reaction time: 40 h), as <lb/>the trans-6c isomer [25 mg, 34%]. IR (ATR) ν: 745, 819, 1017, 1319, <lb/>1495, 1521, 3277 cm -1 . 1 H NMR (DMSO-d 6 ) δ: 2.87 (s, 6H), 3.12 (dd, <lb/>J = 15.4, 4.4 Hz, 1H), 3.63 (dd, J = 11.2, 4.4 Hz, 1H), 4.20 (ddd, <lb/>J = 15.4, 11.2, 4.4 Hz, 1H), 5.17 (d, J = 4.8 Hz, 1H), 5.41 (d, <lb/>J = 14.8 Hz, 1H), 5.57 (d, J = 14.8 Hz, 1H), 6.72-6.76 (m, 4H), <lb/>6.97-7.08 (m, 4H), 7.16-7.20 (m, 2H), 7.23-7.29 (m, 2H), 7.49 (d, <lb/>J = 7.6 Hz, 1H), 10.81 (s, 1H). 13 C NMR (DMSO-d 6 ) δ: 25.0, 40.3, 42.5, <lb/>48.6, 49.8, 54.0, 107.8, 111.1, 112.3, 117.7, 118.4, 120.9, 126.7, 127.9, <lb/>128.2, 128.6, 129.5, 129.8, 134.5, 136.0, 150.1, 155.9. HRMS (ESI-TOF) <lb/>m/z for C 27 H 28 N 7 [M-H + ] calcd. 450.2401, found 450.2399. <lb/>4.1.3. General procedure for the synthesis of β-carbolines 7 <lb/>Sulphur powder (3 equiv) was added to a solution of the appropriate <lb/>tetrahydro-β-carboline 6 (1 equiv) in dimethylformamide (31 mL/ <lb/>mmol). The reaction mixture was stirred under reflux for 24 h. After this <lb/>time, the solvent was evaporated off. The product was precipitated by <lb/>addition of diethyl ether, filtered, and dried under vacuum to give the <lb/>products in a pure form, unless otherwise stated. <lb/>4.1.3.1. 3-(1-Benzyl-1H-tetrazol-5-yl)-1-(m-nitrophenyl)-β-carboline <lb/>(7a). Obtained from tetrahydro-β-carboline 6a (0.16 mmol, 70 mg), as <lb/>described in the general procedure, as an off-white solid (43 mg, 62%). <lb/>mp 275.3-277.2 • C (from diethyl ether). IR (ATR) ν: 668, 729, 852, <lb/>1079, 1343, 1437, 1457 cm -1 . 1 H NMR (DMSO-d 6 ) δ: 6.32 (s, 2H), <lb/>7.18-7.21 (m, 2H), 7.25-7.27 (m, 3H), 7.38 (ddd, J = 8.0, 6.8, 1.2 Hz, <lb/>1H), 7.64-7.72 (m, 2H), 7.88 (t, J = 8.0 Hz, 1H), 8.31 (dt, J = 8.4, <lb/>1.2 Hz, 1H), 8.40 (ddd, J = 8.0, 2.0, 0.8 Hz, 1H), 8.51 (d, J = 8.0 Hz, <lb/>1H), 8.72 (t, J = 2.0 Hz, 1H), 9.18 (s, 1H), 12.14 (s, 1H). 13 C NMR <lb/>(DMSO-d 6 ) δ: 51.8, 112.7, 116.3, 120.7, 120.8, 122.5, 123.2, 123.7, <lb/>127.1, 127.9, 128.6, 129.4, 130.5, 130.6, 133.0, 133.8, 135.0, 135.6, <lb/>138.6, 139.8, 141.7, 148.2, 152.7. HRMS (ESI-TOF) m/z for <lb/>C 25 H 17 N 7 O 2 Na [M+Na + ] calcd. 470.1336, found 470.1330. <lb/>4.1.3.2. 3-(1-Benzyl-1H-tetrazol-5-yl)-1-(o-chlorophenyl)-β-carboline <lb/>(7b). Obtained from tetrahydro-β-carboline 6b (0.14 mmol, 60 mg), as <lb/>described in the general procedure, as a white solid (38 mg, 63%). mp <lb/>234.4-236.0 • C (from diethyl ether). IR (ATR) ν: 722, 799, 867, 1096, <lb/>1436, 1451 cm -1 . 1 H NMR (Acetone-d 6 ) δ: 6.29 (s, 2H), 7.19-7.22 (m, <lb/>3H), 7.24-7.26 (m, 2H), 7.39 (ddd, J = 8.0, 6.4, 2.0 Hz, 1H), 7.57-7.65 <lb/>(m, 4H), 7.67-7.70 (m, 2H), 8.48 (dd, J = 8.0, 1.2 Hz, 1H), 9.12 (s, 1H), <lb/>10.93 (br s, 1H). 13 C NMR (Acetone-d 6 ) δ: 53.0, 113.2, 116.6, 121.6, <lb/>122.4, 123.1, 128.4, 128.8, 129.0, 129.4, 130.2, 130.9, 131.6, 132.8, <lb/>133.9, 134.5, 135.9, 136.9, 137.3, 142.2, 142.6, 153.6. HRMS (ESI-TOF) <lb/>m/z for C 25 H 18 N 6 Cl [M+H + ] calcd. 437.1276, found 437.1269. <lb/>4.1.3.3. 3-(1-Benzyl-1H-tetrazol-5-yl)-1-(p-dimethylaminophenyl)-β-car-<lb/>boline (7c). Obtained from tetrahydro-β-carboline 6c (0.09 mmol, <lb/>40 mg), as described in the general procedure, as a white solid (24 mg, <lb/>56%). mp 259.1-261.2 • C (from diethyl ether). IR (ATR) ν: 693, 723, <lb/>846, 1091, 1363, 1429, 1444 cm -1 . 1 H NMR (DMSO-d 6 ) δ: 3.06 (s, 6H), <lb/>6.49 (s, 2H), 6.88-6.92 (m, 2H), 7.25-7.31 (m, 5H), 7.37 (ddd, J = 8.0, <lb/>6.8, 0.8 Hz, 1H), 7.61 (ddd, J = 8.4, 7.2, 1.2 Hz, 1H), 7.74 (d, J = 8.4 Hz, <lb/>1H), 7.90-7.94 (m, 2H), 8.43 (d, J = 8.0 Hz, 1H), 8.96 (s, 1H), 11.09 (br <lb/>s, 1H). 13 C NMR (DMSO-d 6 ) δ: 34.4, 51.7, 112.3, 112.9, 114.2, 120.3, <lb/>120.6, 121.0, 122.1, 122.5, 127.4, 127.9, 128.0, 128.8, 129.3, 129.5, <lb/>132.7, 133.1, 135.9, 141.5, 150.8, 152.9. HRMS (ESI-TOF) m/z for <lb/>C 27 H 24 N 7 [M+H + ] calcd. 446.2088, found 446.2077. <lb/>4.2. Biological studies <lb/>4.2.1. Materials <lb/>The human neuroblastoma SH-SY5Y cell line was obtained from the <lb/>American Type Culture Collection (ATCC; Manassas, VA, USA). Anti-<lb/>biotic mixture (10 000 U/mL penicillin, 10 000 μg/mL streptomycin), <lb/>non-essential amino acids (NEAA) and Hanks&apos; balanced salt solution <lb/>(HBSS) with or without calcium and magnesium [HBSS (+/+) or HBSS <lb/>(-/-), respectively] were obtained from PanBiotech (Germany). Heat <lb/>inactivated fetal bovine serum (FBS) was obtained from Gibco (United <lb/>Kingdom). Dulbecco&apos;s modified Eagle&apos;s medium with high glucose and <lb/>sodium bicarbonate, as well as trypsin-ethylenediamine tetraacetic acid <lb/>(EDTA) solution (0.25% trypsin/1 mM EDTA), phorbol 12-myristate 13-<lb/>acetate (TPA), neutral red (NR) solution, resazurin (REZ), 1-methyl-4-<lb/>phenylpyridinium (MPP + ), iron (III) chloride (FeCl 3 ), nitrilotriacetic <lb/>acid disodium salt (Na 2 NTA), nitrilotriacetic acid trisodium salt <lb/>(Na 3 NTA), 2′,7′-dichlorofluorescin diacetate (DCFH-DA), tert-Butyl hy-<lb/>droperoxide (t-BHP) and retinoic acid (RA) were obtained from Sigma-<lb/>Aldrich (Germany). Dimethyl sulfoxide (DMSO) was obtained from <lb/>Merck (Darmstadt, Germany). All the sterile plastic material that was <lb/>used was acquired from Corning Costar (Glendale, AZ, USA). The puri-<lb/>fied water that was used in all the experiments was obtained from a <lb/>Direct-Q® Ultrapure Water Systems, Merck Millipore (Darmstadt, Ger-<lb/>many). All the reagents used were of analytical grade or of the highest <lb/>grade available. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">J.L.P. Ribeiro et al. <lb/>Bioorganic &amp; Medicinal Chemistry 111 (2024) 117841 <lb/></note>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<body>4.2.2. Methods <lb/>SH-SY5Y cells -cell culture and differentiation <lb/>The SH-SY5Y neuroblastoma cell line can be manipulated using <lb/>several protocols of terminal neural differentiation, which enable the <lb/>cells to acquire multiple neuronal characteristics, including the devel-<lb/>opment of neurite-like processes, the establishment of functional syn-<lb/>apses, heightened electrical excitability of the cell membrane, and the <lb/>induction of neuron-specific enzymes, neurotransmitters, and neuro-<lb/>transmitter receptors. 43 In our study, the differentiation of SH-SY5Y cells <lb/>was induced by supplementing the cell culture medium with retinoic <lb/>acid (RA) and 12-O-tetradecanoylphorbol-13-acetate (TPA), following a <lb/>well-established protocol. 44 This approach led to a robust differentiation <lb/>of SH-SY5Y cells into a dopaminergic phenotype, as evidenced by a <lb/>significant increase in the expression of dopamine transporter (DAT) and <lb/>tyrosine hydroxylase (TH). 44 <lb/>The cells were regularly grown in 25 cm 2 cell culture flasks, in <lb/>Dulbecco&apos;s Modified Eagle&apos;s Medium containing 4.5 g per liter of <lb/>glucose, supplemented with 10% fetal bovine serum (FBS), 1% anti-<lb/>biotic mixture (100 U/mL penicillin and 100 μg/mL streptomycin), and <lb/>1% MEM non-essential amino acids. The cells were maintained in a <lb/>controlled environment with 5% CO 2 and 95% O 2 at a temperature of <lb/>37 • C to ensure optimal cell growth. When cell confluence reached <lb/>80-90%, cultures were passed weekly by trypsinization (0.25% trypsin/ <lb/>1 mM EDTA). For all experiments, the cells were seeded in sterile 96-<lb/>well plates at a density of 25,000 cells/cm 2 . To promote cell differen-<lb/>tiation, the cells were seeded in complete cell culture medium con-<lb/>taining RA at a final concentration of 10 μM. After three days, TPA was <lb/>added to each well at a final concentration of 80 nM to further enhance <lb/>cell differentiation. Six days after seeding, the cells were used in the <lb/>experiments. The cells used in all the experiments were taken between <lb/>the 20th and 28th passages. <lb/>Evaluation of the Compounds&apos; Cytotoxicity. <lb/>The cytotoxicity of developed compounds towards differentiated SH-<lb/>SY5Y cells was firstly assessed, by using the resazurin (REZ) reduction <lb/>and neutral red uptake assays, 24 h after exposure, aiming to select non <lb/>cytotoxic concentrations to be used in the evaluation of their potential <lb/>neuroprotective effects. For that purpose, six days after seeding, differ-<lb/>entiated SH-SY5Y cells were exposed to several concentrations of the <lb/>compounds under study, in concentrations ranging from 0 to 50 μM, for <lb/>24 h, at 37 • C and in a 5% CO 2 -95% O 2 air atmosphere. Triton™ X-100 <lb/>(1%) was used as positive control. <lb/>Resazurin reduction assay. <lb/>The resazurin (REZ) reduction assay finds widespread utility across a <lb/>variety of applications, encompassing investigations into cell viability, <lb/>cell proliferation, and cytotoxicity. This redox dye serves as an indicator <lb/>of the active metabolism within cell cultures and relies on the intracel-<lb/>lular conversion of resazurin into resorufin by metabolically active cells. <lb/>Initially, the resazurin solution presents itself as a blue-colored solution <lb/>with minimal intrinsic fluorescence. As resazurin permeates through cell <lb/>membranes, it is metabolically reduced by viable cells producing the <lb/>fluorescent, pink-coloured counterpart, resorufin, which is likewise able <lb/>to traverse cell membranes. The amount of formed resorufin is thus an <lb/>indicative of the number of metabolically viable cells in culture. 32,33 <lb/>After exposure of differentiated SH-SY5Y cells to the compounds for <lb/>24 h, the cell culture medium was removed and the cells were incubated <lb/>with REZ (10 μg/mL, prepared in fresh cell culture medium), at 37 • C, in <lb/>a humidified 5% CO 2 -95% O 2 air atmosphere, for 90 min. The fluo-<lb/>rescence was read afterwards in a multiwell plate reader (PowerWaveX <lb/>BioTek Instruments, Vermont, US), using excitation and emission <lb/>wavelengths of 560 nm and 590 nm, respectively. The percentage of REZ <lb/>reduction relative to that of the control cells (DMSO) was used as the <lb/>cytotoxicity measure. Five independent experiments were performed, in <lb/>triplicate. <lb/>NR uptake assay. <lb/>The NR uptake assay is a cytotoxicity and viability assay that relies <lb/>on the capacity of living cells to bind and incorporate the NR dye within <lb/>their lysosomes. This method is notably straightforward and swift, <lb/>yielding dependable outcomes for quantifying the number of viable cells <lb/>in a culture. The amount of NR dye incorporated by the cells thus serves <lb/>as an indicator of their lysosomal activity, offering a means to distin-<lb/>guish between viable, impaired, or deceased cells. 34,35 <lb/>After exposure of differentiated SH-SY5Y cells to the compounds for <lb/>24 h, the cell culture medium was removed and the cells incubated with <lb/>NR (50 μg/mL, prepared in fresh cell culture medium), at 37 • C, in a <lb/>humidified 5% CO 2 -95% O 2 air atmosphere, for 90 min. After this <lb/>incubation period, the cell culture medium was removed, the cells <lb/>washed with HBSS (+/+) and the dye absorbed only by viable cells <lb/>extracted with ethyl alcohol absolute/distilled water (1:1) with 5% <lb/>acetic acid. The absorbance was then measured at 540 nm in a multiwell <lb/>plate reader (PowerWaveX BioTek Instruments, Vermont, US). The <lb/>percentage of NR uptake relative to that of the control cells (DMSO) was <lb/>used as the cytotoxicity measure. Five independent experiments were <lb/>performed, in triplicate. <lb/>Quantification of ROS intracellular levels. <lb/>The potential of the compounds under study to increase the intra-<lb/>cellular levels of reactive oxygen species (ROS), and consequently to <lb/>induce oxidative stress, was also assessed 24 h after exposure using the <lb/>cell permeant probe 2′-7′dichlorofluorescin diacetate (DCFH-DA)]. Upon <lb/>entering the cells, DCFH-DA is cleaved cellular esterases generating <lb/>DCFH. Subsequent oxidation of DCFH by ROS results in the production <lb/>of the fluorescent 2′,7′-dichlorofluorescein (DCF). Consequently, the <lb/>intensity of DCF fluorescence serves as an indicator of the intracellular <lb/>ROS levels, where a higher fluorescence intensity corresponds to <lb/>elevated ROS levels. 36 <lb/>SH-SY5Y cells were seeded into 96-well plates and submitted to <lb/>dopaminergic differentiation as previously described. Six days after <lb/>seeding, differentiated SH-SY5Y cells were pre-incubated with DCFH-DA <lb/>(10 µM), for 1 h, at 37 • C, in a humidified 5% CO2 -95% air atmosphere. <lb/>Then, the cell culture was removed, and the cells exposed to the com-<lb/>pounds under study (0---50 µM) for 24 h. Tert-butyl hydroperoxide (t-<lb/>BHP, 100 µM, 24 h) was used as a positive control of ROS over-<lb/>production. After exposure, ROS intracellular levels were assessed by <lb/>measuring DCF fluorescence, in a multiwell plate reader (PowerWaveX <lb/>BioTekInstruments, Vermont, USA), using an excitation wavelength of <lb/>485 nm and an emission wavelength of 590 nm. Results were expressed <lb/>as percentage of control cells (untreated cells). <lb/>Evaluation of the Compounds&apos; Neuroprotective Effects. <lb/>The potential neuroprotective effects of the developed compounds <lb/>were assessed in differentiated SH-SY5Y cells against different chemical <lb/>aggressors, such as 1-methyl-4-phenylpyridinium (MPP + , the active <lb/>metabolite of MPTP, a dopaminergic neurotoxin that produces features <lb/>of Parkinson&apos;s disease in humans), and iron (III) [in the form of an iron <lb/>(III)-nitrilotriacetic acid (NTA) complex (FeNTA), to simulate iron <lb/>overload]. <lb/>Protective Effects against MPP + -Induced Cytotoxicity. <lb/>To evaluate the potential protective effect of the compounds against <lb/>MPP + -induced cytotoxicity, SH-SY5Y cells were seeded (at a density of <lb/>25,000 cells/cm 2 ) into 96-well plates and submitted to dopaminergic <lb/>differentiation, as previously described. Six days after seeding, a fresh <lb/>stock solution of MPP + was prepared in HBSS (+/+), which was diluted <lb/>afterwards in fresh cell culture medium to the desired concentrations <lb/>and used immediately. Differentiated SH-SY5Y cells were then pre-<lb/>exposed to the compounds under study (1, 2.5, 5 and 10 μM) prepared <lb/>in fresh cell culture medium. After 30 min of pre-incubation, MPP + (500 <lb/>and 1000 μM) was added, and the cells further incubated, at 37 • C, in a <lb/>humidified 5% CO 2 -95% air atmosphere, for 24 h. After the incubation <lb/>period, cell viability was evaluated using the NR uptake assay, as pre-<lb/>viously described. At least five independent experiments were per-<lb/>formed, in triplicate. <lb/>Protective Effects against Iron (III)-Induced Cytotoxicity. <lb/>The potential protective effect of the compounds against iron (III)-<lb/>induced cytotoxicity were assessed upon exposure of differentiated SH-<lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">J.L.P. Ribeiro et al. <lb/>Bioorganic &amp; Medicinal Chemistry 111 (2024) 117841 <lb/></note>

			<page>10 <lb/></page>

			<body>SY5Y cells to ferric nitrilotriacetate (FeNTA). FeNTA results from the <lb/>solubilization of iron (III) in nitrilotriacetic acid, providing an iron (III)-<lb/>NTA complex that facilitates iron entrance into the cells. Also, this <lb/>complex prevents the hydrolysis of iron (III) at physiological pH and has <lb/>been widely used as an iron supply for numerous biological studies. 37 <lb/>Firstly, a NTA (250 mM, pH 7.4) solution was prepared by combining a <lb/>Na 2 NTA solution (100 mM) and a Na 3 NTA solution (100 mM) until <lb/>pH = 7 was reached. Thereafter, iron (III) chloride was weighed to the <lb/>NTA solution, to obtain a 50 mM FeNTA stock solution. In each exper-<lb/>iment, a new FeNTA stock solution was freshly prepared, kept protected <lb/>from light and stabilized for 15 min before being used to ensure the <lb/>complete formation of the ferric oxidation form before addition to the <lb/>cell cultures, and then diluted in fresh cell culture medium to obtain the <lb/>desired concentrations. <lb/>Briefly, SH-SY5Y cells were seeded at a density of 25,000 cells/cm 2 <lb/>and submitted to dopaminergic differentiation, as previously described. <lb/>Six days after seeding, differentiated SH-SY5Y cells were pre-exposed to <lb/>the compounds under study (1, 2.5, 5 and 10 μM), prepared in fresh cell <lb/>culture medium. After 30 min of pre-incubation, FeNTA (500 and <lb/>1000 μM) was added, and the cells were further incubated, at 37 • C, in a <lb/>humidified 5% CO 2 -95% air atmosphere, for 24 h. After the incubation <lb/>period, cell viability was evaluated using the NR uptake assay, as pre-<lb/>viously described. At least five independent experiments were per-<lb/>formed, in triplicate. <lb/>Statistical Analysis. <lb/>The statistical analysis was performed using GraphPad Prism 9 for <lb/>Windows (GraphPad Software, USA). The normality of the data distri-<lb/>bution was assessed using the Kolmogorov-Smirnov, D&apos;Agostino &amp; <lb/>Pearson omnibus, and Shapiro-Wilk normality tests. In the evaluation of <lb/>compounds cytotoxicity, One-way ANOVA was used to perform the <lb/>statistical comparisons, followed by the Dunnett&apos;s multiple comparisons <lb/>test. In the evaluation of the compound&apos;s neuroprotective effects, two-<lb/>way ANOVA was used to compare means of different groups, followed <lb/>by the Tukey&apos;s multiple comparisons test. In all cases, p values smaller <lb/>than 0.05 were considered significant. <lb/>CRediT authorship contribution statement <lb/>João L.P. Ribeiro: Writing -original draft, Investigation, Formal <lb/>analysis. Inês Costa: Writing -original draft, Investigation. Renata <lb/>Silva: Writing -review &amp; editing, Supervision, Formal analysis. Susana <lb/>M.M. Lopes: Writing -review &amp; editing, Supervision, Formal analysis. <lb/>Lucília Saraiva: Writing -review &amp; editing, Supervision, Formal <lb/>analysis, Conceptualization. Teresa M.V.D. Pinho e Melo: Writing -<lb/>review &amp; editing, Supervision, Formal analysis, Conceptualization. <lb/>Declaration of competing interest <lb/>The authors declare that they have no known competing financial <lb/>interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence <lb/>the work reported in this paper. <lb/></body>

			<div type="availability">Data availability <lb/>Data will be made available on request. <lb/></div>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgements <lb/>The Coimbra Chemistry Centre-Institute of Molecular Sciences <lb/>(CQC-IMS) and LAQV/REQUIMTE are supported by Portuguese Foun-<lb/>dation for Science and Technology (FCT) through projects UIDB/00313/ <lb/>2020 (http://doi.org/10.54499/UIDB/00313/2020), UIDP/00313/ <lb/>2020 (http://doi.org/10.54499/UIDP/00313/2020), UIDP/50006/ <lb/>2020 (http://doi.org/10.54499/UIDP/50006/2020) and UIDB/50006/ <lb/>2020 (http://doi.org/10.54499/UIDB/50006/2020) (National Funds), <lb/>and the IMS (LA/P/0056/2020, http://doi.org/10.54499/LA/P/0056/ <lb/>2020) and LAQV/REQUIMTE (LA/P/0008/2020, http://doi.org/ <lb/>10.54499/LA/P/0008/2020) special complementary funds. The authors <lb/>João L. P. Ribeiro (PD/BD/143160/2019, MedChemTrain programme) <lb/>and Susana M. M. Lopes (DL57/2016/CP1370/CT0057, http://doi.org/ <lb/>10.54499/DL57/2016/CP1370/CT0057) also thank FCT for their indi-<lb/>vidual support. Laboratory of Toxicology, Department of Biological <lb/>Sciences of Faculty of Pharmacy of University od Porto, was funded by <lb/>national funds from FCT -Fundação para a Ciência e a Tecnologia, I.P., <lb/>in the scope of the project UIDP/04378/2020 and UIDB/04378/2020 of <lb/>the Research Unit on Applied Molecular Biosciences -UCIBIO and the <lb/>project LA/P/0140/2020 of the Associate Laboratory Institute for <lb/>Health and Bioeconomy -i4HB. The authors acknowledge the UC-NMR <lb/>facility for obtaining the NMR data (https://www.uc.pt/uc-nmr/). <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Appendix A. Supplementary material <lb/>Supplementary data to this article can be found online at https://doi. <lb/>org/10.1016/j.bmc.2024.117841. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>1. Zulkifli SZ, Pungot NH, Saaidin AS, Jani NA, Mohammat MF. Synthesis and diverse <lb/>biological activities of substituted indole β-carbolines: a review. Nat Prod Res. 2023: <lb/>1-14. https://doi.org/10.1080/14786419.2023.2261141. <lb/>2. Abinaya R, Srinath S, Soundarya S, Sridhar R, Balasubramanian KK, Baskar B. <lb/>Recent developments on synthesis strategies, SAR studies and biological activities of <lb/>β-carboline derivatives -an update. J Mol Struct. 2022;1261, 132750. https://doi. <lb/>org/10.1016/j.molstruc.2022.132750. <lb/>3. Ashok P, Lu C-L, Chander S, Zheng Y-T, Murugesan S. Design, synthesis, and <lb/>biological evaluation of 1-(thiophen-2-yl)-9H-pyrido[3,4-b]indole derivatives as <lb/>Anti-HIV-1 agents. Chem Biol Drug Des. 2015;85:722-728. https://doi.org/10.1111/ <lb/>cbdd.12456. <lb/>4. Kushwaha P, Kumar V, Saha B. Current development of β-carboline derived <lb/>potential antimalarial scaffolds. Eur J Med Chem. 2023;252, 115247. https://doi. <lb/>org/10.1016/j.ejmech.2023.115247. <lb/>5. Pontes O, Oliveira-Pinto S, Baltazar F, Costa M. Renal cell carcinoma therapy: <lb/>current and new drug candidates. Drug Discov Today. 2022;27:304-314. https://doi. <lb/>org/10.1016/j.drudis.2021.07.009. <lb/>6. Panice MR, Lopes SMM, Figueiredo MC, et al. New 3-tetrazolyl-β-carbolines and <lb/>β-carboline-3-carboxylates with anti-cancer activity. Eur J Med Chem. 2019;179: <lb/>123-132. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ejmech.2019.05.085. <lb/>7. Ribeiro JL, Loureiro JB, Lopes SM, Saraiva L, Pinho e Melo TM. 3-(1,2,3-Triazol-4-<lb/>yl)-β-carbolines and 3-(1H-Tetrazol-5-yl)-β-carbolines: synthesis and evaluation as <lb/>anticancer agents. Pharmaceuticals. 2022;15:1510. https://doi.org/10.3390/ <lb/>ph15121510. <lb/>8. Aaghaz S, Sharma K, Jain R, Kamal A. β-Carbolines as potential anticancer agents. <lb/>Eur J Med Chem. 2021;216, 113321. https://doi.org/10.1016/j. <lb/>ejmech.2021.113321. <lb/>9. Tshikhudo PP, Mabhaudhi T, Koorbanally NA, et al. Anticancer potential of <lb/>β-carboline alkaloids: an updated mechanistic overview. Chem Biodivers. 2024;21: <lb/>e202301263. <lb/>10. Beato A, Gori A, Boucherle B, Peuchmaur M, Haudecoeur R. β-Carboline as a <lb/>privileged scaffold for multitarget strategies in Alzheimer&apos;s disease therapy. J Med <lb/>Chem. 2021;64:1392-1422. https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jmedchem.0c01887. <lb/>11. Ayipo YO, Mordi MN, Mustapha M, Damodaran T. Neuropharmacological potentials <lb/>of β-carboline alkaloids for neuropsychiatric disorders. Eur J Pharmacol. 2021;893, <lb/>173837. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ejphar.2020.173837. <lb/>12. Louis ED, Michalec M, Jiang W, Factor-Litvak P, Zheng W. Elevated blood harmane <lb/>(1-methyl-9H-pyrido[3,4-b]indole) concentrations in Parkinson&apos;s disease. <lb/>Neurotoxicology. 2014;40:52-56. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.neuro.2013.11.005. <lb/>13. Piechowska P, Zawirska-Wojtasiak R, Mildner-Szkudlarz S. Bioactive β-carbolines in <lb/>food: a review. Nutrients. 2019;11:814. https://doi.org/10.3390/nu11040814. <lb/>14. Szabó T, Volk B, Milen M. Recent advances in the synthesis of β-carboline alkaloids. <lb/>Molecules. 2021;26:663. https://doi.org/10.3390/molecules26030663. <lb/>15. Mousa MO, Adly ME, Mahmoud AM, El-Nassan HB. The progress in pictet-spengler <lb/>β-carboline synthesis under green conditions. ChemistrySelect. 2024;9:e202303149. <lb/>16. Lopes SM, Cardoso AL, Lemos A, Pinho e Melo TM. Recent advances in the chemistry <lb/>of conjugated nitrosoalkenes and azoalkenes. Chem Rev. 2018;118:11324-11352. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.chemrev.8b00375. <lb/>17. Lopes SM, Lemos A, e Melo TMP. A hetero-Diels-Alder approach to functionalized <lb/>1H-tetrazoles: synthesis of tetrazolyl-1,2-oxazines, -oximes and 5-(1-aminoalkyl)-<lb/>1H-tetrazoles. Tetrahedron Lett. 2010;51:6756-6759. https://doi.org/10.1016/j. <lb/>tetlet.2010.10.095. <lb/>18. Lopes SM, Palacios F, Lemos A, e Melo TMP. Diels-Alder reactions of 3-(1H-tetrazol-<lb/>5-yl)-nitrosoalkenes: synthesis of functionalized 5-(substituted)-1H-tetrazoles. <lb/>Tetrahedron. 2011;67:8902-8909. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.tet.2011.09.051. <lb/>19. Lopes SM, Nunes SC, Caratão CC, Pais AA, Pinho e Melo TM. Reactivity of 1-aryl-<lb/>nitrosoethylenes towards indole derivatives. Monatsh Chem. 2016;147:1565-1573. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1007/s00706-016-1763-1. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">J.L.P. Ribeiro et al. <lb/>Bioorganic &amp; Medicinal Chemistry 111 (2024) 117841 <lb/></note>

			<page>11 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>20. Aaseth J, Dusek P, Roos PM. Prevention of progression in Parkinson&apos;s disease. <lb/>Biometals. 2018;31:737-747. https://doi.org/10.1007/s10534-018-0131-5. <lb/>21. Liu W-Z, Huang B-W, You W-J, et al. Harmine enhances GABAergic transmission <lb/>onto basoamygdala projection neurons in mice. Brain Res Bull. 2018;137:294-300. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.brainresbull.2018.01.004. <lb/>22. Ebrahimi-Ghiri M, Nasehi M, Zarrindast M-R. Anxiolytic and antidepressant effects <lb/>of ACPA and harmaline co-treatment. Behav Brain Res. 2019;364:296-302. https:// <lb/>doi.org/10.1016/j.bbr.2019.02.034. <lb/>23. Morales-García JA, de la Fuente Revenga M, Alonso-Gil S, et al. The alkaloids of <lb/>Banisteriopsis caapi, the plant source of the Amazonian hallucinogen Ayahuasca, <lb/>stimulate adult neurogenesis in vitro. Sci Rep. 2017;7:5309. https://doi.org/ <lb/>10.1038/s41598-017-05407-9. <lb/>24. Mohamad Arshad AS, Chear NJY, Ezzat MO, et al. Synthesis, characterization and <lb/>crystal structure of new tetrahydro-β-carboline as acetylcholinesterase inhibitor. <lb/>J Mol Struct. 2020;1200, 127070. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.molstruc.2019.127070. <lb/>25. Guo E, Hu Y, Du T, et al. Effects of Picrasma quassioides and its active constituents <lb/>on Alzheimer&apos;s disease in vitro and in vivo. Bioorg Chem. 2019;92, 103258. https:// <lb/>doi.org/10.1016/j.bioorg.2019.103258. <lb/>26. Zhao Y, Ye F, Xu J, et al. Design, synthesis and evaluation of novel bivalent <lb/>β-carboline derivatives as multifunctional agents for the treatment of Alzheimer&apos;s <lb/>disease. Bioorg Med Chem. 2018;26:3812-3824. https://doi.org/10.1016/j. <lb/>bmc.2018.06.018. <lb/>27. Aricioglu F, Yillar O, Korcegez E, Berkman K. Effect of harmane on the convulsive <lb/>threshold in epilepsy models in mice. Ann N Y Acad Sci. 2003;1009:190-195. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1196/annals.1304.023. <lb/>28. Kasteleijn-Nolst Trenité DGA, Groenwold RHH, Schmidt B, Löscher W. Single dose <lb/>efficacy evaluation of two partial benzodiazepine receptor agonists in photosensitive <lb/>epilepsy patients: A placebo-controlled pilot study. Epilepsy Res. 2016;122:30-36. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.eplepsyres.2016.02.003. <lb/>29. Wernicke C, Hellmann J, Zięba B, et al. 9-Methyl-β-carboline has restorative effects <lb/>in an animal model of Parkinson&apos;s disease. Pharmacol Rep. 2010;62:35-53. https:// <lb/>doi.org/10.1016/S1734-1140(10)70241-3. <lb/>30. Samoylenko V, Rahman MM, Tekwani BL, et al. Banisteriopsis caapi, a unique <lb/>combination of MAO inhibitory and antioxidative constituents for the activities <lb/>relevant to neurodegenerative disorders and Parkinson&apos;s disease. J Ethnopharmacol. <lb/>2010;127:357-367. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jep.2009.10.030. <lb/>31. Zawirska-Wojtasiak R, Fedoruk-Wyszomirska A, Piechowska P, et al. β-carbolines in <lb/>experiments on laboratory animals. Int J Mol Sci. 2020;21:5245. https://doi.org/ <lb/>10.3390/ijms21155245. <lb/>32. O&apos;Brien J, Wilson I, Orton T, Pognan F. Investigation of the Alamar Blue (resazurin) <lb/>fluorescent dye for the assessment of mammalian cell cytotoxicity. Eur J Biochem. <lb/>2000;267:5421-5426. https://doi.org/10.1046/j.1432-1327.2000.01606.x. <lb/>33. Präbst K, Engelhardt H, Ringgeler S, Hübner H. Basic colorimetric proliferation <lb/>assays: MTT, WST, and resazurin. Methods Mol Biol. 2017;1601:1-17. https://doi. <lb/>org/10.1007/978-1-4939-6960-9_1. <lb/>34. Repetto G, del Peso A, Zurita JL. Neutral red uptake assay for the estimation of cell <lb/>viability/cytotoxicity. Nat Protoc. 2008;3:1125-1131. https://doi.org/10.1038/ <lb/>nprot.2008.75. <lb/>35. Zuang V. The neutral red release assay: a review. Altern Lab Anim. 2001;29:575-599. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1177/026119290102900513. <lb/>36. I. Costa, In vitro study of Innovative Antiparkinsonian agents: evaluation of their <lb/>toxicological profile and neuroprotective potential. 2023, Faculty of Pharmacy of <lb/>University of Porto. <lb/>37. Jiang D, Li X, Williams R, et al. Ternary complexes of iron, amyloid-beta, and <lb/>nitrilotriacetic acid: binding affinities, redox properties, and relevance to iron-<lb/>induced oxidative stress in Alzheimer&apos;s disease. Biochemistry. 2009;48:7939-7947. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1021/bi900907a. <lb/>38. Mustapha M, Mat Taib CN. MPTP-induced mouse model of Parkinson&apos;s disease: a <lb/>promising direction of therapeutic strategies. Bosn J Basic Med Sci. 2021;21: <lb/>422-433. https://doi.org/10.17305/bjbms.2020.5181. <lb/>39. Schmidt N, Ferger B. Neurochemical findings in the MPTP model of Parkinson&apos;s <lb/>disease. J Neural Transm. 2001;108:1263-1282. https://doi.org/10.1007/ <lb/>s007020100004. <lb/>40. Yan J, Ma H, Lai X, et al. Artemisinin attenuated oxidative stress and apoptosis by <lb/>inhibiting autophagy in MPP + -treated SH-SY5Y cells. J. Biol. Res.-Thessalon. 2021; <lb/>28:6. https://doi.org/10.1186/s40709-021-00137-6. <lb/>41. Costa I, Barbosa DJ, Benfeito S, et al. Molecular mechanisms of ferroptosis and their <lb/>involvement in brain diseases. Pharmacol Ther. 2023;244, 108373. https://doi.org/ <lb/>10.1016/j.pharmthera.2023.108373. <lb/>42. Weinreb O, Mandel S, Youdim MBH, Amit T. Targeting dysregulation of brain iron <lb/>homeostasis in Parkinson&apos;s disease by iron chelators. Free Radic Biol Med. 2013;62: <lb/>52-64. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.freeradbiomed.2013.01.017. <lb/>43. Kovalevich J, Langford D. Considerations for the use of SH-SY5Y neuroblastoma <lb/>cells in neurobiology. Methods Mol Biol. 2013;1078:9-21. https://doi.org/10.1007/ <lb/>978-1-62703-640-5_2. <lb/>44. Barbosa DJ, Capela JP, Silva R, et al. The mixture of &quot;ecstasy&quot; and its metabolites is <lb/>toxic to human SH-SY5Y differentiated cells at in vivo relevant concentrations. Arch <lb/>Toxicol. 2014;88:455-473. https://doi.org/10.1007/s00204-013-1120-7. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">J.L.P. Ribeiro et al. </note>


	</text>
</tei>